<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1
			<lb />
			Plaintiff carries on business, interalia, as manufacturers,
			<lb />
			importers and suppliers of Bulk Material Handling Equipments and
			<lb />
			Transmission Equipments. Plaintiff settled the suit with defendant nos.1 to 7
			<lb />
			and pursuant to an order dated 30-1-2013, has withdrawn the suit against
			<lb />
			defendant nos.1 to 7. There is nothing on record against defendant no.8 and
			<lb />
			I do not see they having even entered appearance. Anyway plaintiff, after
			<lb />
			30-1-2013, has and is pursuing the suit only against defendant no.9, who
			<lb />
			henceforth is referred to as defendant. Defendant, who was original
			<lb />
			defendant no.9, is an Insurance Company, who had covered a consignment
			<lb />
			which plaintiff was importing. Defendants originally were :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i) defendant no.1 -motor vessel-Rickmers Dubai (vessel that
			<lb />
			carried the cargo),
			<lb />
			(ii) defendant no.2 -Bibi Shipping (that owned/chartered
			<lb />
			defendant no.1 vessel),
			<lb />
			(iii) defendant no.3 -Rickmers Linie GmBH &amp; CIE KG Hamburg
			<lb />
			(carrier that issued the Master Bill of Lading),
			<lb />
			(iv) defendant no.4 -United Liner Agencies of India Pvt Ltd.
			<lb />
			(Agent of defendant no.3 in India),
			<lb />
			Meera Jadhav
			<lb />
			(v) defendant no.5 -Henderson Line Limited (carrier that
			<lb />
			issued the house bill of lading in Antwerpen),
			<lb />
			(vi) defendant no.6 -Excel GmBH (agent of defendant no.5 in
			<lb />
			Antwerpen),
			<lb />
			(vii) defendant no.7 -DHL Lemuir Logistics Pvt Ltd. (Agent of
			<lb />
			defendant no.5 in India),
			<lb />
			(viii) defendant no.8 -Turbowinds NV (the seller of the
			<lb />
			consignment),
			<lb />
			(ix) defendant no.9 -United India Insurance Company Limited
			<lb />
			(Cargo Insurers)
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			Plaintiff had, on or about 30-04-2004, placed a purchase order
			<lb />
			on Turbowinds NV, who was original defendant no.8, for purchase of four
			<lb />
			sets (1 set = 3 nos.) of blade type 23.3 P for Model T-600-48DS Wind
			<lb />
			Operated Electricity Generator. These are more commonly known as Wind
			<lb />
			Mill Blades. The payment term was C &amp; F Nhava Sheva or Chennai or any
			<lb />
			other port as may be advised. The total purchase price was Euro 2,80,000.
			<lb />
			The shipment, which is the subject matter of insurance claim in this suit is
			<lb />
			one set, i.e., 3 nos. windmill blades (the said consignment). The equipment
			<lb />
			was to be packed by shipper, i.e., Turbowinds -original defendant no.8, in
			<lb />
			suitable wooden / water proof / seaworthy strong packing, for protection
			<lb />
			and to prevent damage to or deterioration of the cargo under the normal
			<lb />
			transport condition including sea and rain water. The insurance cover in
			<lb />
			respect of the transit of the said consignment was from warehouse of
			<lb />
			Turbowinds to plaintiff&apos;s factory at V V Nagar, Gujarat. To cover the risk
			<lb />
			associated with transit of the said consignment, and plaintiff had been
			<lb />
			importing many other consignments, plaintiff had taken from defendant an
			<lb />
			open cover policy bearing 180100400008 dated 17-06-2004 (Exhibit P-6).
			<lb />
			The period covered was from 12.36 Hrs. on 17-6-2004 to midnight on 16-6-
			<lb />
			2005.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3
			<lb />
			Plaintiff by letter / declaration dated 6-10-2004 (Exhibit P-8) to
			<lb />
			defendant, informed defendant that the said consignment would be shipped
			<lb />
			on board, &quot;the vessel Rickmers Dubai&quot;, which was original defendant no.1,
			<lb />
			from Antwerp to port of Mumbai/Nhava Sheva Seaport. In the declaration,
			<lb />
			plaintiff had also made it clear to defendant, that the bill of lading number
			<lb />
			and date will be intimated later on. The cargo value declared (CIF + 10%)
			<lb />
			was Rs.64,56,157/-. Based on the declaration made, defendant issued a
			<lb />
			Marine Insurance Certificate (Exhibit P-9), under which the sum insured was
			<lb />
			Rs.64,56,157/-. Basis of valuation was &quot;CIF + 10% extra&quot; and the period of
			<lb />
			risk covered was from &quot;journey anywhere from the world/Antwerpen
			<lb />
			Seaport&quot; to &quot;journey upto V. V. Nagar via Mumbai/Nhava Sheva Seaport&quot;
			<lb />
			and the mode of transit was &quot;vessel/road/rail&quot;. The risk covered included
			<lb />
			(ICC) (A) including war and SRCC (Strike Riots and Civil Commotion). ICC
			<lb />
			(A) means Institute Cargo Clauses (A). What is relevant for the matter at
			<lb />
			hand, is only &quot;ICC (A)&quot; cover. It is an all risk cover except for certain
			<lb />
			exceptions provided in clause 4 to 7 given of ICC(A). As per Marine Open
			<lb />
			Cover (Exhibit P-6) issued, it provided -&quot;Special condition : open cover
			<lb />
			shipping particulars : To be declared to the company immediately upon
			<lb />
			receipt of shipping documents&quot;. Company is defendant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4
			<lb />
			On or about 12-10-2004, plaintiff was informed by an email
			<lb />
			from original defendant nos.6/7, who were the agent of the carrier
			<lb />
			(defendant no.5) under the house bill of lading (HBL) issued to Turbowinds
			<lb />
			(original defendant no.8-sellers), that they had received a message from
			<lb />
			original defendant no.3 stating, during the voyage of original defendant
			<lb />
			no.1 vessel, two blades out of the said consignment of three blades, which
			<lb />
			were stacked on board original defendant no.1 vessel had fallen into the sea
			<lb />
			and one was lying on board damaged. Plaintiff, in turn, by its letter dated
			<lb />
			12-10-2004 (Exhibit P-22) immediately informed defendant about the loss
			<lb />
			and requested defendant to treat that as a formal claim. Plaintiff also
			<lb />
			requested defendant to arrange for survey of the damage / loss of
			<lb />
			consignment at Genoa, Italy, where original defendant no.1 vessel was due
			<lb />
			to arrive on the same day.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5
			<lb />
			Before we go further, it will be necessary to briefly state the
			<lb />
			course of voyage that was adopted to send the said consignment to India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6
			<lb />
			Turbo Winds (seller), original defendant no.8 had entrusted the
			<lb />
			said consignment to original defendant no.6, who had issued House Bill of
			<lb />
			Lading no.002596 dated 4-10-2004 (HBL) (Exhibit P-18). Original
			<lb />
			defendant no.7 was agent in India of original defendant no.6, who was to be
			<lb />
			contacted for delivery. The shipper shown in this HBL was Turbowinds,
			<lb />
			consignee shown was &quot;To order&quot; and notify party was &quot;Bank of Baroda&quot;.
			<lb />
			Original defendant no.6 was the agent in Germany of Henderson Line
			<lb />
			Limited (carrier) who is original defendant no.5. Original defendant no.5
			<lb />
			instead of carrying the said consignment by itself, entrusted the said
			<lb />
			consignment to Rickmers Linie, i.e., original defendant no.3. Rickmers
			<lb />
			Linie, original defendant no.3, issued a Master Bill of Lading no.BOMCV018
			<lb />
			dated 2-10-2004 (MBL) (Exhibit P-21) showing original defendant no.6 as
			<lb />
			the shipper and original defendant no.7 as the consignee. It is clear from
			<lb />
			this MBL that plaintiff was nowhere concerned either as shipper or
			<lb />
			consignee or at all. Even Turbowinds -seller (original defendant no.8) is
			<lb />
			not concerned with this MBL. As per the MBL, the contract of carriage was
			<lb />
			between original defendant no.3 as carrier and original defendant no.6 as
			<lb />
			shipper. If the goods had arrived at Mumbai, what would have happened is,
			<lb />
			plaintiff would have collected the HBL from Bank of India, who would have
			<lb />
			received the documents in view of the conditions in L.C. issued by Bank of
			<lb />
			India, surrendered the HBL to original defendant no.7 as agent of original
			<lb />
			defendant no.5 in Mumbai, and original defendant no.5 in the meanwhile
			<lb />
			would have collected the delivery order for the said consignment from
			<lb />
			original defendant no.4, the agent of original defendant no.3 -Rickmers
			<lb />
			Linie. The delivery order would then be submitted to the port who would
			<lb />
			have handed over the said consignment to plaintiff. Therefore, the contract
			<lb />
			of carriage, which plaintiff will have and which plaintiff would have
			<lb />
			received from Bank of Baroda (LC issuing Bank) would be the HBL (Exhibit
			<lb />
			P-18) and not the MBL (Exhibit P-21). The shipping details mentioned in
			<lb />
			the HBL is what plaintiff is required to declare as per the special condition
			<lb />
			given in Exhibit P-6, that &quot;shipping particulars were to be declared to
			<lb />
			defendants immediately upon receipt of shipping documents&quot;. Which vessel
			<lb />
			or bill of lading details, are not material for the declaration to be made by
			<lb />
			plaintiff and for issuance of Marine Insurance Certificate by defendant
			<lb />
			because under the open cover plaintiff was to give these details only
			<lb />
			&apos;immediately upon receipt of shipping documents&apos;. Shipping documents
			<lb />
			would take its own time and it was also acceptable to defendant because
			<lb />
			defendant accepted the declaration (Exhibit P-8) with the endorsement &quot;bill
			<lb />
			of lading date will be intimated later on&quot; and issued the Marine Insurance
			<lb />
			Certificate (Exhibit P-9), stating &quot;RR/LR/BL/AWB. To Be DECLARED dated
			<lb />
			____&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9/39
			<lb />
			adms-2-06.doc
			<lb />
			For ease of reference and better understanding, Exhibit P-6,
			<lb />
			Exhibit P-8 and Exhibit P-9 and first page of ICC (A) are scanned and
			<lb />
			reproduced:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			EXHIBIT P-6
			<lb />
			11/39
			<lb />
			adms-2-06.doc
			<lb />
			EXHIBIT P-9
			<lb />
			13/39
			<lb />
			adms-2-06.doc
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			After plaintiff intimated defendant about the damage / loss of
			<lb />
			the said consignment vide its letter dated 12-10-2004 (Exhibit P-22),
			<lb />
			defendant immediately engaged services of one Gastaldi International SRL,
			<lb />
			Cargo Surveyors (Gastaldi) to enquire and inspect the remaining blade and
			<lb />
			submit a report. Gastaldi, by a fax dated 18-10-2004 (Exhibit P-42),
			<lb />
			informed defendant that a box of considerable dimensions, i.e., the said
			<lb />
			consignment, was shipped on board, on weather deck. The usual stamp
			<lb />
			&quot;Carried on deck without liability for loss or damage howsoever caused&quot;,
			<lb />
			was endorsed on the bills of lading (signed by agents) (MBL), while no
			<lb />
			remarks were inserted on Mate&apos;s Receipt signed by Master. Bill of lading
			<lb />
			(MBL) was issued without remarks in respect of the condition in the box
			<lb />
			and, therefore, it must be considered shipped in good order and condition.
			<lb />
			Gastaldi, it appears, gave the cause of damage and also reported on the
			<lb />
			extent of damage to one Wind Mill Blade. Gastaldi also submitted various
			<lb />
			documents to defendant, with a copy to plaintiff and for the first time
			<lb />
			plaintiff also came to know about the said consignment having been shipped
			<lb />
			on deck and not under the deck and a MBL having been issued.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8
			<lb />
			Plaintiff, in view of the damage caused to the said consignment,
			<lb />
			lodged this suit, in which, defendant was originally defendant no.9.
			<lb />
			Defendant was sued because defendant did not pay plaintiff&apos;s claim for loss
			<lb />
			of cargo under the insurance policy. Other defendants have been described
			<lb />
			earlier.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9
			<lb />
			After the trial began, plaintiff settled the claim with defendant
			<lb />
			nos.1 to 7 and received a sum of Rs.34 lakhs. Defendant nos.1 to 7 settled
			<lb />
			the claim without admitting liability but under package limitation.
			<lb />
			Defendant nos.1 and 2 together paid Rs.5,00,400/-. Defendant nos.3 and 4
			<lb />
			together paid Rs.11,48,910/-and defendant nos.5, 6 and 7 together paid
			<lb />
			Rs.17,50,690/-. We need not go into any further details on this.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10
			<lb />
			Before arriving at the settlement (Exhibit P-2/2), plaintiff gave
			<lb />
			notice to defendant about the proposed settlement offer from defendant
			<lb />
			nos.1 to 7 and in response, advocate for defendant stated that plaintiff
			<lb />
			cannot settle only with defendant nos.1 to 7 and if plaintiff was settling with
			<lb />
			defendant nos.1 to 7 and withdrawing the suit, plaintiff should withdraw
			<lb />
			the suit against defendant also and not just against defendant nos.1 to 7
			<lb />
			(Exhibit 2/3). Plaintiff by its letter dated (Exhibit P-2/4) once again
			<lb />
			informed defendant that they were ready to settle the suit with defendant
			<lb />
			also, upon defendant paying Rs.60 lakhs without assigning rights of
			<lb />
			subrogation in full and final settlement of all claims against defendant, or, in
			<lb />
			the alternative, defendant may pay a sum of Rs.91.24 lakhs with plaintiff
			<lb />
			assigning the rights of subrogation in full and final settlement. Plaintiff
			<lb />
			made it clear that, if defendant does not agree, then plaintiff will go ahead
			<lb />
			to settle the matter with defendant nos.1 to 7. I have to note that the only
			<lb />
			witness of defendant has given rather strange answers to these
			<lb />
			correspondence. We shall deal with that later.
			<lb />
			11
			<lb />
			In view of defendant not agreeing to settle, plaintiff accepted a
			<lb />
			sum of Rs.34 lakhs and is claiming for the balance from defendant with
			<lb />
			interest plus cost.
			<lb />
			12
			<lb />
			Defendant nos.1 to 7 had filed defence and also started cross-
			<lb />
			examining plaintiff&apos;s witness, but at that stage, settlement was entered into.
			<lb />
			Therefore, we need not consider the defence raised by defendant nos.1 to 7.
			<lb />
			Plaintiff is pursuing this suit only against defendant.
			<lb />
			The defence of defendant can be summarised, from the written
			<lb />
			statement as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(a) the claim raised in the plaint is not and cannot be covered
			<lb />
			under the Marine Insurance Policy because, plaintiff was, under the Marine
			<lb />
			Insurance Act 1963, duty bound and liable to disclose to defendant, before
			<lb />
			the contract was concluded, every material circumstances which is known to
			<lb />
			plaintiff and plaintiff is deemed to know every circumstances, which in the
			<lb />
			ordinary course of business ought to be known to plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(b) Plaintiff was aware that the said consignment was shipped
			<lb />
			on deck and plaintiff has suppressed that material fact at the time of
			<lb />
			declaring the said consignment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(c) The loss and/or damage, if any, is caused due to the
			<lb />
			Meera Jadhav
			<lb />
			negligence and/or tortuous, mischievous and felonious acts on the part of
			<lb />
			defendant nos.1 to 8 and/or their servants, agents or employees. Such loss,
			<lb />
			if any, was payable by defendant nos. 1 to 8 and, therefore, defendant
			<lb />
			cannot be made liable to pay the same.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(d) Plaintiff by its fax dated 6-10-2004 (Exhibit P-6) and 16-10-
			<lb />
			2004 (Exhibit P-7) submitted wrong details regarding particulars of
			<lb />
			dispatch.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(e) Plaintiff has invalidated the insurance policy as plaintiff has
			<lb />
			suppressed material facts from defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(f) Plaintiff misguided and negotiated with their bankers by
			<lb />
			submitting the HBL numbers and the date of MBL and plaintiff is faulted for
			<lb />
			the unauthorised deck stowage of the said consignment.
			<lb />
			None of the case put forth by defendant has been proved by
			<lb />
			defendant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13
			<lb />
			24 issues were framed on 24-11-2006, which read as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;1) Whether this Hon&apos;ble Court has jurisdiction to entertain, try
			<lb />
			and dispose off the present suit ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2) Whether the plaintiffs have any right, title, interest or locus
			<lb />
			to file and maintain the present suit ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3) Whether the plaintiffs have a cause of action against
			<lb />
			defendant nos.1 to 7 or any of them ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4) Whether there is privity of contract between the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			and defendant nos.1 to 7 or any of them ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5) Whether in the absence of any privity of contract between
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs and defendant nos.1 to 7 the plaintiffs have any
			<lb />
			right in rem against defendant no.1 and/or a right in personam
			<lb />
			against defendant nos.2 to 7 or any of them ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6) Whether Indian Law is applicable in respect of the suit
			<lb />
			transaction as alleged by the plaintiffs ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7) Whether the suit is liable to be dismissed for paying
			<lb />
			insufficient court fees ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8) Whether the suit be barred by the law of limitation ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9) Whether the plaintiffs are bound by the clause and terms of
			<lb />
			the bill of lading at Exh.G to the plaint including the clause
			<lb />
			&apos;carried on deck without liability for loss or damage howsoever
			<lb />
			cause&apos; contained on the face of the Bill of Lading ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10) Whether the plaintiffs were aware and/or deemed to be
			<lb />
			aware that the suit consignment was being carried on the deck
			<lb />
			of the vessel ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11) Whether the defendant no.4 at the material time the agent
			<lb />
			of defendant no.3 ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12) If the answer to issue above is in the affirmative, whether
			<lb />
			defendant no.4 as an agent of defendant no.3 is liable to be the
			<lb />
			plaintiff in view of section 230 of the Contract Act 1872 ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13) Whether the suit is liable to be dismissed against defendant
			<lb />
			no.7 as agent of a disclosed principal i.e. defendant no.6 ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14) Whether the defendant nos.5 to 7 or any of them had taken
			<lb />
			charge of the said consignment only as a freight forwarder ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15) Whether the defendant nos.5 to 7 or any of them are
			<lb />
			entitled to limit liability as contended by them in paragraph 5 of
			<lb />
			their written statement ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16) Whether the defendant nos.5 to 7 are disentitled from
			<lb />
			relying upon the numerous exceptions under the bill of lading
			<lb />
			and in law ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17) Whether the defendant nos.5 or 6 were required to obtain
			<lb />
			express permission / consent of the defendant no.8 to stow the
			<lb />
			consignment on the deck of the vessel as alleged in paragraph
			<lb />
			33(f) of the plaint ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18) Whether the loss was caused due to an Act of God and/or
			<lb />
			Peril of the Sea ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19) Whether the lashing / stowage of the plaintiffs consignment
			<lb />
			was insufficient ? And whether the same was causative of the
			<lb />
			loss ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20) Whether defendant no.8 is liable for the loss as contended
			<lb />
			in paragraph 36 of the plaint ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21) Whether the loss is covered under the insurance Policy
			<lb />
			issued by the defendant no.9 ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22) Whether the defendant no.9 proves that the plaintiffs have
			<lb />
			committed a breach of sections 19 and 20 of the Marine
			<lb />
			Insurance Act 1963 ?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			23) Whether the defendant no.9 is liable to indemnify the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs for the loss caused to the aforesaid consignment ?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			24) Whether the plaintiffs prove that they have suffered any loss
			<lb />
			or damage amounting to Rs.67,83,177/-or any other amount
			<lb />
			and whether the plaintiffs are entitled to an order and decree as
			<lb />
			prayed for in the plaint together with interest and if so at what
			<lb />
			rate and for what period ?&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			14
			<lb />
			Only issue nos.10, 21, 22, 23 and 24 which have been
			<lb />
			highlighted above, are relevant to what remains in the suit Plaintiff led
			<lb />
			evidence of two witnesses. Defendant led evidence of only one witness.
			<lb />
			Total of 69 documents from plaintiff have been marked and total of
			<lb />
			13 documents from defendant have been marked. Issue no.24 can be
			<lb />
			answered at the out set, because it is not disputed by defendant that the
			<lb />
			cargo suffered a loss because defendant&apos;s own surveyors have, vide their
			<lb />
			survey report (Exhibit P-53), certified the loss. We will, however, deal with
			<lb />
			the quantum later. All other issues are interlinked and can be dealt with
			<lb />
			together.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15
			<lb />
			Let us see what is the risk that is covered under the open policy.
			<lb />
			As noted above, the policy incorporates ICC(A), which is commonly called
			<lb />
			an all risk policy. Clauses 1 to 4 of ICC (A) deal with the risk covered under
			<lb />
			the policy. In the present case we are only concerned with clause (1) and it
			<lb />
			reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;1) This insurance covers all risks of loss of or damages to the subject-
			<lb />
			matter insured except as provided in clauses 4, 5, 6 and 7 below.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Therefore, every possible situation is covered except those
			<lb />
			provided under clauses 4 to 7 of ICC (A). Only clause 4 is relevant for this
			<lb />
			matter and we need not look into the other clauses 5 to 7. Clause 4 reads as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;4) In no case shall this insurance cover
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.1) loss damage or expense attributable to willful misconduct of the
			<lb />
			Assured
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.2) ordinary leakage, ordinary loss in weight or volume, or ordinary
			<lb />
			wear and tear of the subject-matter insured.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.3) loss damage or expense caused by insufficiency or unsuitability
			<lb />
			of packing or preparation of the subject-matter insured (for the
			<lb />
			purpose of this Clause 4.3 &quot;packing&quot; shall be deemed to include
			<lb />
			stowage in a container or liftvan but only when such stowage is
			<lb />
			carried out prior to attachment of this insurance or by the Assured or
			<lb />
			their servants).
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.4) loss damage or expense caused by inherent vice or nature of the
			<lb />
			subject-matter inusred.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.5) loss damage or expense proximately caused by delay, even
			<lb />
			though the delay be caused by a risk insured against (except
			<lb />
			expenses payable under Clause 2 above)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.6) loss damage or expense arising from insolvency or financial
			<lb />
			default of the owners managers charterers or operators of the vessel
			<lb />
			4.7) loss damage or expense arising from the use of any weapon of
			<lb />
			war employing atomic or nuclear fission and/or fusion or other like
			<lb />
			reaction or radioactive force or matter.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			Mr. Narichania submitted, and rightly so, when it is an all risk
			<lb />
			cover, every risk under the sun is covered, except which are excluded.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16
			<lb />
			Though not pleaded, across the bar, Ms. Diwedi submitted that
			<lb />
			exclusion clause 4.3 will be applicable, i.e., &quot;loss damage or expense caused
			<lb />
			by insufficiency or unsuitability of packing or preparation of the subject-
			<lb />
			matter insured ……..&quot;. Defendant, in its written statement has not stated
			<lb />
			that the loss covered was due to risk, which has been excluded expressly
			<lb />
			under clause 4.3. Even the survey report (Exhibit P-53) issued by
			<lb />
			defendant&apos;s surveyor does not indicate that the loss or damage occurred due
			<lb />
			to insufficiency or unsuitability of packing or preparation of subject matter
			<lb />
			insured.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17
			<lb />
			Now let us also consider what is meant by an open cover policy,
			<lb />
			because the nature of the cover provided is critical to appreciate the role
			<lb />
			which time to time declarations were intended to play in an open cover.
			<lb />
			The main thrust of defence as noted earlier, is non disclosure/mis-disclosure
			<lb />
			under the declarations to be made as per the open cover policy issued.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18
			<lb />
			In paragraph 21 of the Judgment of the Court of Appeal in the
			<lb />
			matter of Glencore International A.G. Vs. (The &quot;Beursgracht&quot;) 1 , the Court
			<lb />
			has dealt with open cover and it reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. I think the nature of the cover provided is critical to any
			<lb />
			consideration of the role which declarations were intended to play in
			<lb />
			this open cover. The words &quot;open cover&quot; are not determinative,
			<lb />
			although interestingly R. H. Brown&apos;s Dictionary of Marine Insurance
			<lb />
			Terms describes an open cover as:
			<lb />
			A form of long-term insurance contract whereby the insurer
			<lb />
			guarantees to accept risks when they are put forward by the assured
			<lb />
			1 (2002) Vol-1 574
			<lb />
			Meera Jadhav
			<lb />
			as they arise during the period of the contract. The assured agrees to
			<lb />
			declare every item that falls within the scope of the cover and does
			<lb />
			not have the option to place such risks elsewhere should he consider
			<lb />
			it advantageous so to do. Thus the open cover is an obligatory
			<lb />
			contract binding both parties to its terms.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19
			<lb />
			What is an open cover is also defined in M. N. Srinivasan&apos;s -
			<lb />
			Principles of Insurance Law, by Dr. Avtar Singh, published by Wadhwa and
			<lb />
			Company, Seventh Edition 2002, page 139 and the same reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;This is a contract to insure cargo that may be shipped by a merchant
			<lb />
			during a period usually 12 months at rates fixed in the beginning itself,
			<lb />
			irrespective of the total value of the goods that may be sent, the only
			<lb />
			limit fixed is of the goods that may be sent in any one vessel. As and
			<lb />
			when each shipment goes, a separate policy is issued to satisfy the
			<lb />
			requirement of S.24. The open cover thus corresponds to an original
			<lb />
			slip for a series of policies for each shipment sent during the period.
			<lb />
			This is more popular than the floating policy as the merchant here gets
			<lb />
			the advantage of a long term agreement for his insurance needs at
			<lb />
			fixed rates without limit of sum assured. He has only to declare the
			<lb />
			particulars of each shipment during the period and cover is assured.
			<lb />
			Even if a declaration is missed or loss occurs before advice is given to
			<lb />
			the insurer the insured is given protection of the insurance. The open
			<lb />
			cover is not reduced by the value of the shipment sent as in a floating
			<lb />
			policy.&quot; (emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Therefore, even if the declaration is missed or loss occurs before
			<lb />
			advice is given to insurer, the insured is given protection of the insurance. It
			<lb />
			is for this reason, defendant was perfectly happy when in the declaration
			<lb />
			made on 6-10-2004 (Exhibit P-8), plaintiff stated &quot;bill of lading date will be
			<lb />
			intimated later on and the Marine Insurance Certificate (Exhibit P-9) also
			<lb />
			states&quot; to be declared, dated ______&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			20
			<lb />
			It is defendant&apos;s case that plaintiff did not disclose a material
			<lb />
			fact before the insurance contract was concluded and that material fact was
			<lb />
			that the said consignment was carried on deck. First of all, the contract was
			<lb />
			concluded when the open policy cover for the period 12.36 Hrs on 17-6-
			<lb />
			2004 to midnight of 16-6-2005 was issued. It is not defendant&apos;s case that
			<lb />
			the contract was concluded when defendant issued the Marine Insurance
			<lb />
			Certificate (Exhibit P-9). At the same time, even if, we say that every time
			<lb />
			the declaration was made, there was a responsibility on the insurer, i.e.,
			<lb />
			plaintiff, to declare correctly (and that is not defendant&apos;s case) still, I say
			<lb />
			there is no fault on the part of plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21
			<lb />
			Section 19 and Section 20 of the Marine Insurance Act 1963,
			<lb />
			read as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			19. Insurance is unberrimae fidei:-A contract of marine insurance is a
			<lb />
			contract based upon the utmost good faith, and if the utmost good
			<lb />
			faith be not observed by either party, the contract may be avoided by
			<lb />
			the other party.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			20. Disclosure by assured:-(1) subject to the provisions of this
			<lb />
			section, the assured must disclosed to the insurer, before the contract
			<lb />
			is concluded, every material circumstance which, is known to the
			<lb />
			assured, and the assured is deemed to know every circumstance
			<lb />
			which, in the ordinary course of business, ought to be known to him.
			<lb />
			If the assured fails to make such disclosure, the insurer may avoid the
			<lb />
			contract.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) Every circumstance is material which would influence the
			<lb />
			judgment of a prudent insurer in fixing the premium, or determining
			<lb />
			whether he will take the risk.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(3) In the absence of inquiry the following circumstances need not be
			<lb />
			disclosed, namely:-(a) any circumstance which diminishes the risk.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) any circumstance which is known or presumed to be known to the
			<lb />
			insurer. The insurer is presumed to know matters of common
			<lb />
			notoriety or knowledge, and matters which an insurer in the ordinary
			<lb />
			course of his business as such ought to know;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) any circumstance as to which information is waived by the
			<lb />
			insurer;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d) any circumstance as to which it is superfluous to disclose by
			<lb />
			reason of any express or implied warranty.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(4) Whether any particular circumstance, which is not disclosed, be
			<lb />
			material or not is, in each case, a question of fact.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(5) The term &quot;circumstance&quot; includes any communication made to, or
			<lb />
			information received by, the assured.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			22
			<lb />
			Under Section 19, it is very clear that the contract of marine
			<lb />
			insurance is a contract based upon the utmost good faith, and if the utmost
			<lb />
			good faith be not observed by either party, the contract may be avoided by
			<lb />
			the other party. Therefore, good faith has to be maintained by either party,
			<lb />
			i.e., not only by assured but also the insurer. What is relevant to this case is
			<lb />
			Section 20, under which, the assured (plaintiff) must disclose to the insurer
			<lb />
			(defendant), before the contract is concluded, every material circumstance
			<lb />
			which is known to the assured, and the assured is deemed to know every
			<lb />
			circumstance which, in the ordinary course of business, ought to be known
			<lb />
			to him. If the assured fails to make such disclosure, the insurer may avoid
			<lb />
			the contract. Every circumstance is material which would influence the
			<lb />
			judgment of a prudent insurer in fixing the premium or determining
			<lb />
			whether he will take the risk. What fact is material would depend on facts
			<lb />
			and circumstances of each case. If the insurer-defendant is rejecting the
			<lb />
			claim on the basis of non-disclosure of a material fact or avoiding the
			<lb />
			contract on the basis of non-disclosure of a material fact by plaintiff, the
			<lb />
			onus is on the defendant to prove :-a) that the information regarding
			<lb />
			loading of the said consignment on the deck was a material fact; b) if it had
			<lb />
			been disclosed despite issuing an open cover, defendant would have still
			<lb />
			refused to cover or cancelled the cover to the said consignment or atleast
			<lb />
			increased the premium payable; and c) that material fact was known to
			<lb />
			assured, i.e., plaintiff before the contract was concluded to wit, before the
			<lb />
			issuance of the open cover (Exhibit P-6) or before the declaration (Exhibit P-
			<lb />
			8) was made. I have to say that defendant has miserably failed in all these
			<lb />
			three counts.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23
			<lb />
			While dealing with an all risk policy, King&apos;s Bench Division of
			<lb />
			England in London and Provincial Leather Processes Ltd. Vs. Hudson 2 has
			<lb />
			held that for a loss to be recoverable under an all-risks policy there must
			<lb />
			only be a casualty, something accidental or fortuitous. The court held that
			<lb />
			an all risk policy insures against all and every risk whatsoever, however
			<lb />
			arising. Before a claim can attach on a policy of insurance there must be a
			<lb />
			loss of an accidental or fortuitous character, there must be in some form or
			<lb />
			another a casualty. The court held that it is accidental and fortuitous in the
			<lb />
			sense that the assured is deprived by some unexpected acts of his property
			<lb />
			in the goods or his possession of the goods. An assured would have suffered
			<lb />
			a loss in the sense that they cannot get their goods.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24
			<lb />
			In paragraph 23-80 in Arnould Law of Marine Insurance And
			<lb />
			2 1939 KB 724
			<lb />
			Meera Jadhav
			<lb />
			Average, 19 th Edition, printed by Sweet &amp; Maxwell, an all risks cover is
			<lb />
			explained as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;All risks&quot; policies are not subject to any ejusdem generis limitation.
			<lb />
			Goods insured against all risks are in effect, and subject to the express
			<lb />
			exclusions in the policy, covered against loss or damage from any
			<lb />
			external cause. A policy against all risks does not absolve the assured
			<lb />
			from the need to prove that he has suffered loss from an insured peril;
			<lb />
			he must, as it is sometimes expressed, prove a casualty; but the class
			<lb />
			of insured perils is so wide that he may be able to do this by necessary
			<lb />
			inference. If the goods are shipped sound and arrive damaged, and
			<lb />
			the damage is of such a kind as to raise a presumption of some
			<lb />
			external cause, there is prima facie evidence of loss by an insured
			<lb />
			peril and the burden is on the underwriter to prove that the loss in
			<lb />
			fact occurred in some way for which he is not liable.
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			25
			<lb />
			Therefore, in all risks policies, the class of insured perils is so
			<lb />
			wide that the assured will be able to prove the casualty by necessary
			<lb />
			inference. If the goods are shipped sound and arrive damaged, and the
			<lb />
			damage is of such a kind as to raise a presumption of some external cause,
			<lb />
			there is prima facie evidence of loss by an insured peril and the burden is on
			<lb />
			the underwriter to prove that the loss in fact occurred in some way for
			<lb />
			which he is not liable. I have already stated that the only point raised by
			<lb />
			counsel for defendant that too orally was that risk was not covered because
			<lb />
			it fell under clause 4.3 in the exclusions of ICC (A) and I have negated it.
			<lb />
			The fact that there has been a casualty and that there has been prima facie
			<lb />
			evidence of loss by an insured peril has been proved, because admittedly
			<lb />
			even the surveyor Gastaldi appointed by defendant has confirmed the loss of
			<lb />
			the said consignment (Exhibit P-42) and (Exhibit P-53).
			<lb />
			Meera Jadhav
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26/39
			<lb />
			adms-2-06.doc
			<lb />
			26
			<lb />
			Has defendant discharged the burden to prove that the loss in
			<lb />
			fact occurred in some way for which he is not liable?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27
			<lb />
			Ms Diwedi submitted that it is plaintiff&apos;s own case that
			<lb />
			defendant no.3 illegally and without authority carried the said consignment
			<lb />
			on deck and, therefore, the loss is not payable. Open cover policy or Marine
			<lb />
			Insurance Certificate issued or ICC(A), which is included and is part of the
			<lb />
			insurance cover, does not ban or bar carriage of goods on deck or excludes
			<lb />
			loss due to goods being carried on deck. Moreover, it is precisely the reason
			<lb />
			why insurance cover is taken to cover for loss due to such misdemeanors /
			<lb />
			misadventures by third party or act of God etc. The only witness, who gave
			<lb />
			evidence on behalf of defendant no.9, in answer to question nos.14 and 15
			<lb />
			of his cross-examination stated he did not even know what &quot;on deck
			<lb />
			stowage&quot; means and what &quot;under deck stowage&quot; means. In the affidavit in
			<lb />
			examination in chief, defendant&apos;s witness states that MBL was a qualified
			<lb />
			bill of lading. When he was asked what according to him was the meaning
			<lb />
			of the term &quot;qualified bill of lading&quot;, his answer is beyond comprehension.
			<lb />
			Question no.33 and answer thereto read as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Q.33. What is the meaning of the term &quot;qualified bill of lading&quot; ?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ans. A qualified bill of lading a bill of lading. Most of ships which are
			<lb />
			seaworthy belong to the London Underwriter Classification. No ship
			<lb />
			comes out of London, without classification.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			He was shown a MBL and was asked, was that a qualified bill of
			<lb />
			lading or not clean bill of lading and his answer was &quot;I cannot say&quot;.
			<lb />
			Question no.40 and the answer thereto reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;(Witness is shown Bill of Lading No.BOMCVO18 dated 2 nd October
			<lb />
			2004. This document is not exhibited but is annexed at Exhibit G to
			<lb />
			the plaint. It is also disclosed at Sr. No.17 to the plaintiff&apos;s
			<lb />
			compilation of documents)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Q.40. Is this a qualified bill of lading or not a clean bill of lading&quot; ?
			<lb />
			Ans. I cannot say.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			28
			<lb />
			The other defence of defendant was non disclosure of material
			<lb />
			fact and the material fact was that the said consignment was loaded on
			<lb />
			deck, which plaintiff failed to disclose. The onus to prove that it was a
			<lb />
			material fact and it was not disclosed, though plaintiff was aware, was on
			<lb />
			defendant. The only place where the bill of lading contains endorsement of
			<lb />
			stowage on deck, was the MBL. In response to question no.48 in his cross-
			<lb />
			examination defendant&apos;s witness states that he was not aware as to whether
			<lb />
			at the time of applying for insurance coverage, plaintiff was aware of and
			<lb />
			had in its possession the MBL. Question No.48 and answer thereto read as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Q.48. Do yo know whether at the time of applying the insurance
			<lb />
			coverage, the plaintiff was aware of and had in its possession bill of
			<lb />
			lading No.BOMCVO18 dated 2 nd October 2004 ?&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ans. No, I am not aware&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			29
			<lb />
			Per contra, plaintiff&apos;s witness in his examination in chief has
			<lb />
			expressly stated that plaintiff learnt about the MBL (it states as &quot;carried on
			<lb />
			deck without liability for loss or damage howsoever caused&quot;), only when
			<lb />
			they received a copy of letter from the claims agents of Defendant, Gastaldi
			<lb />
			on or about 18-10-2004, which is Exhibit P-42. Paragraph 12 of the affidavit
			<lb />
			in lieu of examination in chief, reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;12 After entrustment of the said consignment to the 5 th Defendant as
			<lb />
			stated above, unknown to the plaintiff, it appears that the 5 th
			<lb />
			Defendant through the 6 th Defendants had entrusted the said
			<lb />
			consignment for carriage to the 2 nd and 3 rd Defendants from Antwerp
			<lb />
			to Mumbai. On receipt of the said consignment on board the 1 st
			<lb />
			Defendant vessel, the 3 rd Defendant apparently issued in favour of the
			<lb />
			6 th Defendant on Board Ocean Bill of Lading bearing no.BOMCV018
			<lb />
			dated 02/10/2004 (MBL). The said Ocean Bill of Lading mentions
			<lb />
			Shipper as the 6 th Defendant and Consignee as 7 th Defendant. The
			<lb />
			said Ocean Bill of Lading mentions the Port of Loading as Antwerp
			<lb />
			and Port of Discharge as Mumbai Seaport. The said Ocean Bill of
			<lb />
			Lading mentions that the said consignment would be carried on
			<lb />
			board the 1 st Defendant vessel. The Ocean Bill of Lading further
			<lb />
			states as &quot;Carried on Deck without Liability for loss or damage
			<lb />
			howsoever caused.&quot; The said Ocean Bill of Lading mentions freight
			<lb />
			payable at Hamburg. However, in the description of goods column it
			<lb />
			is mentioned as freight prepaid. The said ocean Bill of Lading
			<lb />
			appears to have been signed at Hamburg. The Plaintiff learnt the
			<lb />
			aforesaid facts when they received a copy of letter from the claims
			<lb />
			agents Gastaldi International srl on or about 18/10/2004. I am
			<lb />
			producing herewith a copy of the obverse and reverse of the Ocean
			<lb />
			Bill of Lading bearing no.BOMCV018 dated 02/10/2004. A copy of
			<lb />
			the said Bill of Lading (MBL) was received by the plaintiffs from the
			<lb />
			claims agents Gastaldi International srl.&quot; (emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			In the cross-examination by defendant, defendant has not even
			<lb />
			made an attempt to prove what P.W.-1 has stated was incorrect. Mere
			<lb />
			suggestion that plaintiff is guilty of non disclosure of material fact at the
			<lb />
			time of declaring the said consignment and at the time of issuing the
			<lb />
			insurance policy or with respect to the shipment, to which, plaintiff&apos;s
			<lb />
			witness has disagreed is not enough. In response to defendant&apos;s counsel&apos;s
			<lb />
			question after showing the HBL to P.W.-1, P.W.-1 confirmed, that was the
			<lb />
			document that plaintiff received from the bank, which was lodged with
			<lb />
			defendant no.9 (Exhibit P-17). Marine Open Cover (Exhibit P-6) provides as
			<lb />
			noted earlier for shipping particulars to be declared to defendant
			<lb />
			immediately upon receipt of shipping documents, and in his cross-
			<lb />
			examination, plaintiff has confirmed that HBL (Exhibit P-17) is what was
			<lb />
			received and that was submitted to defendant. The HBL does not disclose
			<lb />
			anywhere that the said consignment was stowed on deck. Therefore, there
			<lb />
			was no way that plaintiff would have known that the consignment was
			<lb />
			stowed on deck. In his cross-examination, in response to question no.261,
			<lb />
			P.W.-1 has confirmed that no bill of lading number and date was
			<lb />
			communicated at the time of declaration as shown in document dated 6-10-
			<lb />
			2004 (Exhibit P-8). Question nos.252, 257, 259, 261 and answers thereto in
			<lb />
			cross-examination of P.W.-1, are important and reproduced hereinbelow:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;(Witness is shown the bill of lading issued by Henderson Line Limited
			<lb />
			bearing no.002596 dated 04.10.2004 i.e. document P-17)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Q.252. Is this the document you received from the bank which you
			<lb />
			lodged with the defendant no.9?
			<lb />
			Ans. Yes .
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Q.257. I put it to you that the plaintiff is guilty of non-disclosure of
			<lb />
			material facts at the time of declaring the consignment and at the time
			<lb />
			of issuing of the insurance policy ?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ans : I do not agree.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Q.259. I put it to you that the plaintiff failed to disclose and suppressed
			<lb />
			material facts and circumstances with respect to the shipment of the
			<lb />
			consignment ?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ans. I do not agree.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			Q.261 At the time of declaration, for issuance of the insurance
			<lb />
			certificate, which bill of lading number and date did you mention to
			<lb />
			defendant no.9 ?
			<lb />
			Ans .No bill of lading number and date was communicated at the time
			<lb />
			of declaration as shown in document, dated 6 th October 2004, which
			<lb />
			document is at page 15 of the plaintiff&apos;s compilation of documents of
			<lb />
			2 nd May 2008.
			<lb />
			I must add, defendant&apos;s counsel also put a positive question to
			<lb />
			plaintiff&apos;s witness that plaintiff was not aware of bill of lading number and
			<lb />
			date before 12-10-2004 and bill of lading number and date was
			<lb />
			communicated to defendant only on 12-10-2004. Question nos.263 and
			<lb />
			265 of P.W.1&apos;s cross-examination and answers thereto read as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;Q.263. When did the plaintiff inform the defendant no.9 about the
			<lb />
			date and the number of the bill of lading&quot; ?
			<lb />
			Ans. The bill of lading number and date was communicated to the
			<lb />
			defendant no.9 as shown in the document at page no.33 of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff&apos;s compilation of documents of 2 nd May 2008 i.e. letter dated
			<lb />
			12 th October 2004.
			<lb />
			Q.265. Would it be correct to say that before 12 th October 2004 the
			<lb />
			plaintiff was not aware of the bill of lading number and date ?
			<lb />
			Ans. Yes, the plaintiff was not aware.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Therefore, defendant has failed to prove: (a) the said
			<lb />
			consignment being on deck was material fact as defendant&apos;s only witness
			<lb />
			stated that he does not know what was the meaning of on deck stowage and
			<lb />
			under deck stowage; and (b) Even for a moment we assume that on deck
			<lb />
			stowage was a material fact, still defendant has failed to prove that before
			<lb />
			declaration was made on 6-10-2004, plaintiff was aware that the said
			<lb />
			consignment was stowed on deck and hence guilty of non disclosure.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30
			<lb />
			Though, Ms Diwedi mentioned that plaintiff submitted wrong
			<lb />
			details regarding particulars of despatch, she did not even identify which are
			<lb />
			those alleged wrong details. Plaintiff had made a positive case that it came
			<lb />
			to know about on deck stowage only on 12-10-2004, whereas defendant did
			<lb />
			not cross-examine P.W.-1 to disapprove that. It is a rule of essential justice
			<lb />
			that whenever opponent has declined to avail himself of the opportunity to
			<lb />
			put his case in cross-examination, it must follow that the evidence tendered
			<lb />
			on that issue ought to be accepted. (Sarwan Singh Vs. State of Punjab 3 )
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31
			<lb />
			Ms Dwivedi relied upon a judgment of the English High Court
			<lb />
			of Justice (Kings Bench Division) in Alluvials Mining Machinery Company
			<lb />
			Vs. Stowe 4 to submit that the insurance company is not liable to indemnify
			<lb />
			plaintiff for the loss caused and when the consignment is carried on deck.
			<lb />
			I am afraid, this judgment does not aid Ms Dwivedi because there the
			<lb />
			assured had conceded that the policy provided that it would not cover goods
			<lb />
			carried on deck. There is no such concession in our case. Neither does the
			<lb />
			open cover or Marine Insurance Certificate or ICC(A) exclude cover for
			<lb />
			goods carried on deck. Moreover, in that case the insured were aware that
			<lb />
			the goods were carried on deck because bill of lading issued expressly had a
			<lb />
			disclaimer and that was not disclosed to the insurer. The facts in our case
			<lb />
			are totally different. Therefore, the said judgment is not applicable to this
			<lb />
			case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32/39
			<lb />
			adms-2-06.doc
			<lb />
			32
			<lb />
			Ms Dwivedi also relied upon the judgment of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court of India in the matter of M/s Bihar Supply Syndicate Vs. Asiatic
			<lb />
			Navigation &amp; Ors 5 to submit that no cause of action is established by
			<lb />
			plaintiff against defendant. That judgment was peculiar to its own facts and
			<lb />
			apart from pointing out paragraph 28 of the said judgment, Ms Dwivedi did
			<lb />
			not make any submissions. Paragraph 28 is totally unconnected to any facts
			<lb />
			in our present case, because that was concerning cross objections and
			<lb />
			provisions of Order 41 Rule 33 of Civil Procedure Code.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			33
			<lb />
			In the records and proceedings, I find another judgment given
			<lb />
			by defendant&apos;s counsel in the matter of Rangammal Vs. Kuppuswami &amp; Anr 6
			<lb />
			I am ignoring this judgment, because that was not referred to during the
			<lb />
			hearing and not even argued and it has been given after the matter was
			<lb />
			reserved for judgment. In any event, that judgment is only given to suggest
			<lb />
			a proposition that onus is on plaintiff to positively establish its case on the
			<lb />
			basis of material available and it cannot rely on the weakness or absence of
			<lb />
			defence to discharge its onus. There can be no quarrel on this proposition
			<lb />
			but once plaintiff has discharged its onus in an all risk policy that the goods
			<lb />
			has suffered a casualty due to a fortuitous event and there is a prima facie
			<lb />
			evidence of loss by an insured peril, the onus shifts to defendant to prove
			<lb />
			that loss in fact occurred in some way due to a risk which was not covered
			<lb />
			33/39
			<lb />
			adms-2-06.doc
			<lb />
			under the policy or for which it was not liable. That burden, defendant has
			<lb />
			to independently discharge and failure to discharge will result in decree to
			<lb />
			plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34
			<lb />
			To conclude, a) plaintiff has proved the loss is covered under
			<lb />
			the insurance policy issued by defendant, b) defendant has failed to prove
			<lb />
			that plaintiff&apos;s were aware and/or deemed to be aware that the suit
			<lb />
			consignment was carried on deck of the vessel, and, c) defendant has failed
			<lb />
			to prove that plaintiff has committed a breach of Sections 19 and 20 of the
			<lb />
			Marine Insurance Act 1963. Therefore, defendant is liable to indemnify
			<lb />
			plaintiff for the loss caused to the said consignment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35
			<lb />
			Now comes the issue of quantum. The insured value under the
			<lb />
			policy is Rs.64,56,157/-. Strangely, plaintiff has not claimed this amount ,
			<lb />
			but has claimed Rs.67,82,492/-, the break up of which is as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Sr. No. Particulars
			<lb />
			Amount
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			Invoice No.23 dt. 28/09/2004 of Turbowinds,
			<lb />
			Belgium for a set of windmill blade type 23.3 P
			<lb />
			for model T-600-18DS wind operated
			<lb />
			electricity generator
			<lb />
			Euro 81.640 =
			<lb />
			(C = Cost)
			<lb />
			Rs.46,66,542.00
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			Ocean freight charges as per cargo arrival
			<lb />
			notice CCX/2402341 dt. 17/11/2004 of Excel
			<lb />
			India Pvt Ltd.
			<lb />
			(F = freight)
			<lb />
			Rs.12,02,047.00
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			Marine Insurance Charges as per certificate
			<lb />
			no.180100/21/04/80402 dt. 6/10/04
			<lb />
			(I = Insurance)
			<lb />
			Rs.4,981.00
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			Marine Insurance Charges as per certificate
			<lb />
			No.180100/21/04/80403 dt. 6/10/04 (on
			<lb />
			duty part)
			<lb />
			(I = Insurance)
			<lb />
			Rs.1,868.00
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			Cost incurred at Italy for scrapping of the
			<lb />
			damaged blade as per Debit Note dated
			<lb />
			3/3/05 of Excel India Pvt Ltd.
			<lb />
			Rs.3,20,195.00
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			Incidentals &amp; others losses approx 10% in
			<lb />
			terms of the policy
			<lb />
			(+ 10%)
			<lb />
			Rs.5,86,859.00
			<lb />
			Total claim
			<lb />
			Rs.67,82,492.00
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			The basis of valuation under the policy was CIF + 10% extra.
			<lb />
			From the particulars of break up given above, item 1 relates to &quot;C&quot;, i.e., cost,
			<lb />
			item 2 relates to &quot;F&quot;, i.e., freight and items 3 and 4 relate to &quot;I&quot;, i.e.,
			<lb />
			insurance. These amounts are, therefore, certainly payable. As regards,
			<lb />
			items 5, it is claimed for cost incurred at Italy for scrapping the damaged
			<lb />
			blade as per the debit note dated 3-3-2005 (Exhibit P-56) of Excel India Pvt
			<lb />
			Ltd.,which is original defendant no.7. No submissions, however, were made
			<lb />
			by Mr. Narichania on how this head of claim is covered under the policy.
			<lb />
			Hence this has to be rejected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36
			<lb />
			Item 6 of the particulars of claim given is incidentals and other
			<lb />
			losses approximately 10% in terms of the policy. The amount claimed is
			<lb />
			Rs.5,86,859/-. Again no submissions were made by Mr. Narichania as to
			<lb />
			how this amount is payable under the policy. Therefore, this head of claim
			<lb />
			is rejected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37
			<lb />
			As regards item 1, 2, 3 and 4, the reason why I have said it is
			<lb />
			payable is because, in paragraph 34 of the affidavit in lieu of examination in
			<lb />
			chief P.W.-1 has stated as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;34. The plaintiff by its letter dated 04/03/2005 informed the 9 th
			<lb />
			Defendants that one blade which was discharged at Genova was
			<lb />
			disposed off. The Plaintiff further informed the 9 th Defendants that
			<lb />
			the Plaintiff had incurred storage charges, charges for clearing and
			<lb />
			scrapping of the said blade, port demurrage and other charges. The
			<lb />
			Plaintiff informed the 9 th Defendants that the Plaintiff was sending
			<lb />
			revised claim bill in the sum of Rs.67,82,492/-after taking into
			<lb />
			account the said expenses. The Plaintiff also forwarded to the 9 th
			<lb />
			Defendants copies of documents requested by the 9 th Defendant and
			<lb />
			also informed the 9 th Defendants that apart from the freight charges of
			<lb />
			Rs.12,02,047/-paid to the 7 th Defendants plaintiff also paid
			<lb />
			Rs.3,20,195/-to the 7 th Defendants. I am producing herewith an
			<lb />
			office copy of the plaintiff&apos;s said letter dated 04/03/2005 to the 9 th
			<lb />
			Defendants alongwith the revised claim bill.&quot;
			<lb />
			The Apex Court in Sarwan Singh (supra) in paragraph 8,
			<lb />
			observed that it is a rule of essential justice that whenever the opponent has
			<lb />
			declined to avail himself of the opportunity to put his case in cross-
			<lb />
			examination, it must follow that the evidence tendered on that issue ought
			<lb />
			to be accepted. The document (Exhibit P-56) has been received in evidence
			<lb />
			without any murmur from defendant. Defendant has not put any questions
			<lb />
			in cross-examination and, therefore, the evidence tendered by plaintiff
			<lb />
			ought to be accepted.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38
			<lb />
			Therefore, what is payable under the policy is:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Sr
			<lb />
			No.
			<lb />
			Particulars
			<lb />
			Amount
			<lb />
			(I) Invoice
			<lb />
			Rs.46,66,542.00
			<lb />
			(ii) Ocean Freight
			<lb />
			Rs.12,02,047.00
			<lb />
			(iii) Marine Insurance Charges
			<lb />
			Rs.
			<lb />
			4981.00
			<lb />
			(iv) Marine Insurance Charges
			<lb />
			Rs.
			<lb />
			1868.00
			<lb />
			Total
			<lb />
			Rs.58,75,438.00
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			39
			<lb />
			The other point that comes up for consideration is, as noted
			<lb />
			earlier, plaintiff has received a sum of Rs.34,00,000/-from defendant no.1
			<lb />
			to 7. Certainly, defendant has to be given credit for the said amount. As
			<lb />
			noted earlier, plaintiff had informed defendant about the settlement offers
			<lb />
			from original defendant no.1 to defendant no.7 and sought defendant&apos;s
			<lb />
			consent. Defendant did not consent nor pay. Therefore, plaintiff went ahead
			<lb />
			and mitigated its losses by accepting Rs.34 lakhs from defendant no.1 to
			<lb />
			defendant no.7 as per the break-up noted earlier. In his cross examination
			<lb />
			defendant&apos;s witness confirmed having received the letters informing
			<lb />
			defendant about the settlement offers from defendant no.1 to defendant
			<lb />
			no.7. According to defendant&apos;s witness, there was no question of defendant
			<lb />
			giving any answers to plaintiff&apos;s letters because it was conditions of the
			<lb />
			policy. Q.34 to Q.36 and answers thereto of defendant&apos;s witness in cross
			<lb />
			examination read as under :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(Witness is shown the documents marked as Exhibits P-2/2, P-2/4 and P-
			<lb />
			2/5)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Q.34. Do you agree that the plaintiff addressed letters to the advocate of
			<lb />
			defendant no.9 informing her of settlement offers received from the other
			<lb />
			defendants to the suit?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ans. Yes, I agree.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Q.35. What was the response of defendant no.9 to these letters?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ans. As per the policy terms and conditions, it was the agent&apos;s liability
			<lb />
			who made the shipment. So, there was no question of defendant no.9
			<lb />
			giving any answer to these letters. It was pure condition of the policy.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Q.36. Who is this &quot;agent&quot; you are referring to in your answer to Q.35?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ans. I do not remember. There may be 500 agents.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			But the fact is defendant&apos;s advocate had initially replied
			<lb />
			(Exhibit 2/3) as noted earlier. This witness of defendant does not even
			<lb />
			know that. From the answers given in the cross examination it is rather
			<lb />
			evident that defendant&apos;s witness had no idea what the matter was about and
			<lb />
			was giving unintelligible answers. Defendant&apos;s witness&apos;s evidence lacks
			<lb />
			credibility.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40
			<lb />
			As I have held above, a sum of Rs.58,75,438/-is payable under
			<lb />
			the policy. From this amount of Rs.58,75,438/-, a sum of Rs.34,00,000/-
			<lb />
			has to be deducted which would leave a sum of Rs.24,75,438/-payable by
			<lb />
			defendant to plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41
			<lb />
			Now comes the issue of interest, at what rate and for what
			<lb />
			period. Plaintiff has claimed interest at the rate of 18% p.a. from the date of
			<lb />
			suit until payment / realisation. No evidence has been led as to how and
			<lb />
			why 18% should be granted. Mr. Narichania submitted that under the claim
			<lb />
			proceedings for General Insurance Policy prescribed by IRDA, it is provided
			<lb />
			in regulation 15, clause 10 that in the event, the claim is not settled within
			<lb />
			30 days, the insurer shall be liable to pay interest at the rate, which is 2%
			<lb />
			above the bank rate from the date of receipt of last relevant and necessary
			<lb />
			document from the insured / claimant by insurer till the date of actual
			<lb />
			payment. Again, no evidence is led by plaintiff as to what was the &quot;bank
			<lb />
			rate&quot;. Counsel for defendant did not make any submissions, but simply
			<lb />
			stated that as the claim itself has to be dismissed, where is the question of
			<lb />
			paying any interest. I am allowing part of the claim. Therefore, interest is
			<lb />
			payable. In my view, interest at the rate of 12% p.a. would be a reasonable
			<lb />
			rate of interest, from the date of filing the suit.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			42
			<lb />
			By an order dated 30-1-2013, plaintiff withdrew the suit as
			<lb />
			against defendant nos.1 to 7. Mr. Narichania states that defendant nos.1
			<lb />
			and 2 gave a sum of Rs.5,00,400/-, defendant nos.3 and 4 gave
			<lb />
			Rs.11,48,910/-and defendant nos.5 to 7 together gave Rs.17,50,690/-,
			<lb />
			totalling to Rs.34,00,000/-and all the three payments were received by
			<lb />
			plaintiff on 30-1-2013, when plaintiff withdrew the suit as against
			<lb />
			defendant nos.1 to 7. Therefore, interest @ 12% p.a. shall be payable on
			<lb />
			Rs.58,75,438/-from 14-10-2005, the date on which the plaint was lodged,
			<lb />
			until 30-1-2013 and from 31-1-2013 on the balance amount of
			<lb />
			Rs.24,75,438/-until payment / realisation. Plaintiff is also be entitled to
			<lb />
			cost in the sum of Rs.5,00,000/-.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			43
			<lb />
			Suit stands decreed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			I
			<lb />
			Plaintiff will be entitled to a sum of -
			<lb />
			Interest @ 12% p.a. from 14-10-2005 to 30-
			<lb />
			Rs.58,75,438.00
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			1-2013 (8 years 16 days) -
			<lb />
			Less amount received from defendant nos.1
			<lb />
			to 7
			<lb />
			Total amount payable as on 30.01.2013
			<lb />
			Interest @ 12% p.a. from 31-1-2013 to 22-
			<lb />
			8-2019 on Rs.24,75,438.00 (6 years 203
			<lb />
			days)
			<lb />
			Rs.56,71,326.89
			<lb />
			____________________
			<lb />
			Rs.1,15,46,764.90
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			Rs. 34,00,000.00
			<lb />
			____________________
			<lb />
			Rs. 81,46,764.89 (A)
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			Rs. 19,47,525.41 (B)
			<lb />
			Total (A) + (B)
			<lb />
			Rs.1,00,94,290.30
			<lb />
			II
			<lb />
			Cost
			<lb />
			Rs. 5,00,000.00
			<lb />
			Sum total I + II
			<lb />
			Rs.1,05,94,290.30
			<lb />
			III Plus further interest from the date of judgment until payment /
			<lb />
			realisation will accrue at 12% pa. on Rs.24,75,438/--Rs.813.84 per
			<lb />
			day.
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			44
			<lb />
			All issues are answered accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(K.R. SHRIRAM, J.)
			<lb />
			Meera Jadhav
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
