<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			Mr.K.Selvaraj, learned counsel for writ petitioners in captioned
			<lb />
			nine writ petitions is before this Virtual Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. Learned counsel submits that similar matters were disposed of
			<lb />
			by this Court in and by a common order dated 25.10.2021 made in four
			<lb />
			writ petitions being W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021
			<lb />
			which reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2/36
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos.22915, 22917, 22920, 22922, 22925, 22927, 22929, 22932 and 22935 of 2021
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. Learned counsel for writ petitioners, on instructions, submits
			<lb />
			that he restricts and abridges the prayer to a simple Mandamus to dispose
			<lb />
			of representations (all dated 22.09.2021) made by each of the nine writ
			<lb />
			petitioners as done in the aforementioned four writ petitions and requests
			<lb />
			for a similar order. The details are as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Employees
		</head>
		<figure type="table">
			S.No Shop No./Retail
			<lb />
			Outlet No.
			<lb />
			Name of Writ
			<lb />
			Petitioner
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			4079
			<lb />
			S.Ramesh
			<lb />
			22915 of 2021
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			4153
			<lb />
			R.D.Veerasamy
			<lb />
			22917 of 2021
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			4176
			<lb />
			S.Krishnamoorthy 22920 of 2021
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			4359
			<lb />
			R.Kaleeswaran
			<lb />
			22922 of 2021
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			4501
			<lb />
			P.Udhayakumar
			<lb />
			22925 of 2021
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			4335
			<lb />
			M.Gopinath
			<lb />
			22927 of 2021
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			4452
			<lb />
			S.Senthil Kumar
			<lb />
			22929 of 2021
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			4122
			<lb />
			S.Shanmugam
			<lb />
			22932 of 2021
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			4075
			<lb />
			S.Sellappan
			<lb />
			22935 of 2021
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			4. Mr.K.Sathishkumar, learned standing counsel for &apos;Tamil Nadu
			<lb />
			State Marketing Corporation Limited&apos; [&apos;TASMAC&apos;] representing
			<lb />
			Mr.P.Arumugarajan, learned standing counsel for respondents in all nine
			<lb />
			writ petitions accepts notice.
			<lb />
			13/36
			<lb />
			https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos.22915, 22917, 22920, 22922, 22925, 22927, 22929, 22932 and 22935 of 2021
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. Owing to the narrow compass on which captioned matters turn,
			<lb />
			with the consent of learned counsel on both sides, main writ petitions are
			<lb />
			taken up.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6. Before this Court proceeds further, it is deemed appropriate to
			<lb />
			extract and reproduce the aforementioned nine representations dated
			<lb />
			22.09.2021 that have been placed before this Court (as part of the
			<lb />
			common typed set of papers). The nine representations are as follows:
			<lb />
			14/36
			<lb />
			7. Learned standing counsel for TASMAC points out that copies
			<lb />
			of representations do not contain signature of sender, but learned counsel
			<lb />
			for writ petitioners, on instructions, submits that the originals sent to the
			<lb />
			respective addressees are duly signed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8. Be that as it may, learned counsel for writ petitioner affirms that
			<lb />
			the scanned reproduction of the above are the representations. This is
			<lb />
			supported by sworn affidavits (writ affidavits). Therefore, it will be
			<lb />
			appropriate to direct the above representations to be disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9. There is no disputation or disagreement that similar writ
			<lb />
			petitions were disposed of by this Court vide aforementioned common
			<lb />
			order dated 25.10.2021. Therefore, the captioned nine writ petitions will
			<lb />
			also be disposed of by a similar common order.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. Captioned nine writ petitions are disposed of with a directive
			<lb />
			to first respondent to consider and dispose of all the nine writ petitioners&apos;
			<lb />
			33/36
			<lb />
			https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos.22915, 22917, 22920, 22922, 22925, 22927, 22929, 22932 and 22935 of 2021
			<lb />
			representations (all dated 22.09.2021) on its own merits, in accordance
			<lb />
			with law as expeditiously as the business of the first respondent would
			<lb />
			permit and in any event, within three weeks from today i.e., on or before
			<lb />
			17.11.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. Proceedings/orders disposing all the aforementioned nine
			<lb />
			representations of the nine writ petitioners shall be communicated to the
			<lb />
			respective writ petitioners under due acknowledgment within five
			<lb />
			working days from the dates of disposal of the representations. Though
			<lb />
			obvious, it is made clear that this Court has not expressed any opinion or
			<lb />
			view on the merits of the matter and the first respondent shall consider
			<lb />
			the representations on their own merits and in accordance with law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. Captioned nine Writ Petitions are disposed of in the aforesaid
			<lb />
			manner by this common order. There shall be no order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27.10.2021
			<lb />
			Speaking/Non-speaking order
			<lb />
			Index: Yes/No
			<lb />
			Internet : Yes/No
			<lb />
			mk
			<lb />
			34/36
			<lb />
			https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos.22915, 22917, 22920, 22922, 22925, 22927, 22929, 22932 and 22935 of 2021
			<lb />
			To
			<lb />
			1. The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Limited, (TASMAC),
			<lb />
			Rep.by its Managing Director,
			<lb />
			&quot;Thalamuthu Natarajan Maaligai&quot;,
			<lb />
			Gandhi-Irwin Road,
			<lb />
			Egmore, Chennai-600 008.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Limited, (TASMAC),
			<lb />
			Rep.by its Senior Regional Manager,
			<lb />
			LLA Building, Anna Salai, Chennai-600 002.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Limited, (TASMAC),
			<lb />
			Rep.by its District Manager,
			<lb />
			Kancheepuram (North)
			<lb />
			Industrial Estate, Thirumazhisai,
			<lb />
			Kancheepuram District-600 123.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35/36
			<lb />
			https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos.22915, 22917, 22920, 22922, 22925, 22927, 22929, 22932 and 22935 of 2021
			<lb />
			M.SUNDAR.J.,
			<lb />
			mk
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos.22915, 22917, 22920, 22922,
			<lb />
			22925, 22927, 22929, 22932 and 22935 of 2021
			<lb />
			27.10.2021
			<lb />
			36/36
			<lb />
			https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
