<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1. Whether reporters of local papers may be allowed
			<lb />
			to see the judgment?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. To be referred to the Reporter or not?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. Whether judgment should be reported in Digest?
			<lb />
			:
		</p>
		<head>
			PRADEEP NANDRAJOG, J.
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			In a nutshell, case of the prosecution is, that having
			<lb />
			lost in his endeavour to win back his wife Rani Chaudhary,
			<lb />
			decree for divorce in whose favour attained finality when
			<lb />
			Petition For Special Leave to Appeal filed by the appellant
			<lb />
			before the Supreme Court was dismissed on 24.8.1982, the
			<lb />
			appellant made up his mind to murder Kishan Sikand, with
			<lb />
			whom Rani Chaudhary was residing and had decided to get
			<lb />
			married to. Being an ex-serviceman; having knowledge of
			<lb />
			ammunition, the appellant procured the raw ingredients to
			<lb />
			manufacture a bobby trap bomb, and using parts of a hand-
			<lb />
			grenade, managed to manufacture a bobby trap bomb, which
			<lb />
			was converted into a parcel, and on 25.9.1982, at around 7.30
			<lb />
			-7.45 PM, the appellant left the parcel containing the bomb at
			<lb />
			the staircase leading to the first floor of 98, Sunder Nagar, New
			<lb />
			Delhi, in the rear portion whereof the deceased Kishan Sikand
			<lb />
			was residing along with Rani Chaudhary. The bomb reached
			<lb />
			the deceased on 2.10.1982 and since the parcel containing the
			<lb />
			bomb was addressed to the deceased, he opened the same
			<lb />
			and while so doing, triggered of the contraption, resulting in an
			<lb />
			explosion. The sharpnells inside the bomb pierced the body of
			<lb />
			the deceased who died at the spot due to the resultant
			<lb />
			injuries.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The FIR was registered on the day of the incident
			<lb />
			itself on 2.10.1982. Rani Chaudhary was at Sanawar (H.P.) on
			<lb />
			the day of the incident and returned to Delhi the next day.
			<lb />
			Her statement under Section 161 Cr.P.C. was recorded on
			<lb />
			3.10.1982.
			<lb />
			She informed the police therein about her
			<lb />
			turbulent marriage with the appellant and the divorce. She
			<lb />
			informed the police that the appellant had been extending
			<lb />
			threats to her to compel her to return to him and that had
			<lb />
			even been threatening Kishan Sikand.
			<lb />
			Apart from other
			<lb />
			persons whose statements were recorded during investigation,
			<lb />
			the statement of one Suresh Gopal, a close friend of the
			<lb />
			deceased and Rani Chaudhary was recorded on 5.10.1982.
			<lb />
			Needless to state, the appellant was a suspect from the very
			<lb />
			beginning but nothing incriminating against him could be
			<lb />
			gathered by the police in spite of the fact that the
			<lb />
			investigation was handed over to the Crime Branch of Delhi
			<lb />
			Police. On 19.3.1983 investigation of the case was entrusted
			<lb />
			to CBI.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			On the day of the crime, after police received
			<lb />
			information thereof, from the room on the first floor of 98,
			<lb />
			Sunder Nagar where the deceased died a huge quantity of
			<lb />
			debris was lifted and as noted in the seizure memo Ex.PW-69/C
			<lb />
			was converted into 9 packets. It was noted in the seizure
			<lb />
			memo that torn and burnt pieces of paper were a part of the
			<lb />
			debris lifted. Three days later i.e. on 4.10.1982, some more
			<lb />
			material was lifted from the room and converted into 4
			<lb />
			packets. Unfortunately, the seizure memo pertaining to the
			<lb />
			material lifted on 4.10.1982 was not made a part of the
			<lb />
			charge-sheet and could not be proved at the trial.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The thirteen packets were sent to the Central
			<lb />
			Forensic Science Laboratory on 7.10.1982 for a forensic
			<lb />
			analysis, which as per Ex.PW-62/F commenced on 12.10.1982.
			<lb />
			Needless to state, the first and the foremost thing required
			<lb />
			was to segregate the debris and thereafter subject the
			<lb />
			constituents thereof to a forensic analysis as also to try and
			<lb />
			put together the burnt pieces of paper, as if a jigsaw is being
			<lb />
			solved, for the reason, the said pieces of paper may have
			<lb />
			contained a valuable information.
			<lb />
			It may be noted that
			<lb />
			according to Rani Chaudhary and Suresh Gopal they had seen
			<lb />
			the sender&quot;s address on a slip of paper stuck to the parcel as
			<lb />
			also had seen the name and address of the recipient on a slip
			<lb />
			of paper stuck to the parcel.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			According to the prosecution, from the remnants
			<lb />
			i.e. the debris, on being segregated and reconstructed,
			<lb />
			Dr.G.R.Prasad (PW-62) could reconstruct two slips recording as
			<lb />
			under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Slip 1
			<lb />
			Slip 2
			<lb />
			PA …………..OST
			<lb />
			Shiri Krishan ……..
			<lb />
			98, Sunde……….agar
			<lb />
			From:
			<lb />
			Delhi Met……….e,
			<lb />
			290, Hauz Qu….i
			<lb />
			Delhi ….0006
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			The typescript of the two slips, as per the
			<lb />
			prosecution, was got typed by the appellant from an institute
			<lb />
			imparting typing training at Lajpat Nagar belonging to Shri
			<lb />
			N.D.Sethi PW-27 where the appellant had visited and got
			<lb />
			typed, on an envelope, the name of the addressee and the
			<lb />
			name of the sender. As per opinion of S.K.Gupta PW-75, an
			<lb />
			examiner of questioned documents, the transcript of the two
			<lb />
			slips matched the sample transcript S-7, obtained from one out
			<lb />
			of the thirteen typewriters kept at the typing institute of Shri
			<lb />
			N.D.Sethi. As per the prosecution, it was able to track the
			<lb />
			typewriter used for typing the name and address of the
			<lb />
			addressee and the name and address of the sender pursuant
			<lb />
			to the disclosure statement Ex.PW-28/A made by the
			<lb />
			appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Seventy five witnesses were examined by the
			<lb />
			prosecution. Apart from the police witnesses, the doctor who
			<lb />
			conducted the post-mortem of the deceased and the forensic
			<lb />
			experts who had analyzed the debris and the typescript on the
			<lb />
			two slips, witnesses were examined to prove the motive; to
			<lb />
			prove that the appellant was seen coming out of the house of
			<lb />
			the deceased at around 7.30 -7.45 PM on 25.9.1982; that the
			<lb />
			appellant had got typed the name and address of the sender
			<lb />
			as well as the addressee on paper which was pasted on the
			<lb />
			parcel in question; that the appellant was an ex-armyman; that
			<lb />
			the bobby trap bomb was created by using hand-grenades of
			<lb />
			Pakistani origin; that the conduct of the appellant after
			<lb />
			25.9.1982 was suspicious and suggestive of his being the
			<lb />
			author of the crime.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			We propose to briefly note the deposition of the
			<lb />
			witnesses, other than formal witnesses, before analyzing the
			<lb />
			impugned decision dated 28.4.2008, under which the
			<lb />
			appellant has been convicted for the offence of murdering
			<lb />
			Kishan Sikand and for the offences punishable under Section 3
			<lb />
			&amp; 4 of the Explosive Substance Act 1908.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Rani Chaudhary PW-1 deposed that she was earlier
			<lb />
			married to Sqn. Leader Pritam Singh and out of said wedlock
			<lb />
			two daughters, Mini and Maitri were born. On death of her
			<lb />
			husband
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			31.3.1971
			<lb />
			she
			<lb />
			married
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			appellant
			<lb />
			S.J.Chaudhary. Out of said wedlock one daughter named Sonal
			<lb />
			was born on 24.8.1972. Her matrimonial life was turbulent as
			<lb />
			the appellant treated her with cruelty. She lodged a report
			<lb />
			Ex.PW-1/B with the army authorities in February -March 1979.
			<lb />
			The appellant confined her in the house on 5.8.1979 and she
			<lb />
			had to jump out of the house. While so doing, she sprained
			<lb />
			her ankle and had to be treated by a homeopath as per
			<lb />
			prescription Ex.PW-1/D. On 1.9.1979 she sued for divorce in
			<lb />
			the Court of an Additional District Judge, Delhi by filing a
			<lb />
			petition Ex.PW-1/E. On 6.12.1979 an ex-parte divorce was
			<lb />
			granted by the Court in her favour. She knew deceased
			<lb />
			Krishan Sikand since 1969 -71 and over a period of time they
			<lb />
			grew fond of each other.
			<lb />
			On 12.9.1980 Krishan Sikand
			<lb />
			proposed marriage to her which she accepted. That on 20 th
			<lb />
			September, 1980 her birthday was celebrated by Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand at a restaurant in &quot;Oberoi Intercontinental&quot; and Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand had ordered a birthday cake on which her name was
			<lb />
			put as &quot;Rani Sikand&quot;. After dinner, as they went to the parking
			<lb />
			where their car was parked, she saw appellant sitting in a car
			<lb />
			in the parking area and the appellant trailed their car. On the
			<lb />
			way, she lost track of the car of the appellant, but saw the
			<lb />
			same parked outside her residence, at which, on the
			<lb />
			suggestion of Krishan Sikand, she decided to spend the night
			<lb />
			at the house of Krishan Sikand i.e. 98, Sunder Nagar.
			<lb />
			Appellant met her in her house the next day and she informed
			<lb />
			him that she and Krishan Sikand were planning to marry. On
			<lb />
			23.9.1980 she met the appellant at the shop of M/s. Bhagwan
			<lb />
			Dass Khanna and the appellant enquired from her whether a
			<lb />
			ring which she was getting repaired from said shop was gifted
			<lb />
			to her by Krishan Sikand. Since the appellant had been trailing
			<lb />
			her, Krishan Sikand expressed concern about her safety and
			<lb />
			requested her to stay with him at his house and that she
			<lb />
			agreed. The appellant continued to keep a watch on her
			<lb />
			movements and in July 1981 met her at Chungwa Restaurant
			<lb />
			and told her that he would kill her and himself. She received a
			<lb />
			telephone call on 31.7.1981 from the appellant requesting her
			<lb />
			to meet him. She refused, but at his persistence agreed to
			<lb />
			meet him. At the meeting, the appellant requested that she
			<lb />
			should leave Krishan Sikand. She refused to do so. The
			<lb />
			appellant used to constantly ring her, virtually compelling her
			<lb />
			to leave the house of Krishan Sikand as the appellant would
			<lb />
			threaten that unless he did so, he would kill Krishan Sikand.
			<lb />
			That on 15.9.1981, Krishan Sikand told her that the appellant
			<lb />
			had threatened to kill him and his father, unless she left his
			<lb />
			house.
			<lb />
			The appellant met her once again at Chungwa
			<lb />
			Restaurant on 24.9.1981 and reiterated his resolve to kill
			<lb />
			Krishan Sikand, unless she left his company. On 6.10.1981
			<lb />
			she rang up the mother of the appellant and informed her of
			<lb />
			the conversations she had with the appellant.
			<lb />
			That the
			<lb />
			appellant had made a complaint to the police regarding her
			<lb />
			stay at 98, Sunder Nagar and in response, on 14.10.1981, the
			<lb />
			police came to said house and made inquires from her; she
			<lb />
			informed them that she was staying with Krishan Sikand with
			<lb />
			her own free will as her marriage with the appellant had been
			<lb />
			dissolved. On 25.9.1982 Suresh Gopal, his wife Sushma Gopal
			<lb />
			visited Krishan Sikand and herself at 7.30 PM at 98 Sunder
			<lb />
			Nagar. Around 9:00 PM all of them headed towards Pandara
			<lb />
			Road Market for dinner. While descending from the first floor of
			<lb />
			98 Sunder Nagar, Krishan Sikand and Suresh Gopal were a
			<lb />
			little ahead of her and Sushma Gopal. Krishan saw a brownish
			<lb />
			coloured parcel ad-measuring 5&quot; x 3&quot; x 2&quot; lying on the second
			<lb />
			lower most landing of the stairs. Krishan picked it up and
			<lb />
			proceeded towards the car. Krishan&quot;s address on the parcel
			<lb />
			was written on a white patch of paper, which was pasted on it.
			<lb />
			On 2.10.1982, she left to attend Founder&quot;s Day Function of her
			<lb />
			children&quot;s school at Sanawar.
			<lb />
			Krishan Sikand could not
			<lb />
			accompany her due to some important matter. On 2.10.1982,
			<lb />
			at around 9:15 PM, at Sanawar School she received telephonic
			<lb />
			information that there was an emergency and she must return
			<lb />
			to Delhi. She took the Kalka Mail and reached Delhi the next
			<lb />
			morning, and at the station, Anil Sikand and his wife; the elder
			<lb />
			brother and sister-in-law of Krishan Sikand, informed her that
			<lb />
			Krishan was no more. That the tape Ex.PW-1/P2 contained her
			<lb />
			voice and the voice of the mother of the appellant. That the
			<lb />
			tape Ex.PW-1/P1 contained her voice and the voice of the
			<lb />
			appellant. That the letters Ex.PW-1/FF to Ex.PW-1/GG were
			<lb />
			written to her by the appellant. That envelopes Ex.PW-1/001
			<lb />
			to Ex.PW-1/14 were received by her from the appellant in
			<lb />
			which various letters were posted by the appellant to her.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			Dr.H.Lal PW-33 a medical officer deposed that the
			<lb />
			prescription Ex.PW-1/D was written by him, but he could not
			<lb />
			identify the patient.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			Sudhir Khanna PW-10 deposed that somewhere in
			<lb />
			July or August 1981, both Krishan Sikand and Rani Chaudhary
			<lb />
			had told him that the appellant was threatening Rani to leave
			<lb />
			the house of Krishan Sikand, on which he had suggested them
			<lb />
			to report the matter to the police as well as to tape the threats
			<lb />
			of the appellant, for which he gave them a Sony make
			<lb />
			walkman tape recorder.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			Kailash Nath Dwivedi PW-11 deposed that in 1981
			<lb />
			I.J.S. Chatwal had visited him in the month of September with
			<lb />
			his wife and daughter. His daughter Rani was mentally upset
			<lb />
			as she wanted to re-marry but her ex-husband was
			<lb />
			threatening her on that score, for which he suggested some
			<lb />
			puja.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			H.D.Sikand PW-19, father of the deceased Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand deposed that in mid September 1981, the appellant
			<lb />
			had telephoned him at his office and told him that if Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand fails to throw Rani Chaudhary out of his house, the
			<lb />
			appellant would cripple him i.e. Krishan Sikand and break his
			<lb />
			bones.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Smt.Davinder Singh PW-32 (mother-in-law of Rani
			<lb />
			from her previous marriage to Pritam Singh) deposed that
			<lb />
			somewhere in 1975-76, Rani Chaudhary requested her to
			<lb />
			permit her and her two daughters to stay with her as she was
			<lb />
			facing problems with the appellant who was maltreating her.
			<lb />
			After a year, she came back again and made a similar request
			<lb />
			at which she kept her in her house for six months. The
			<lb />
			appellant came to her house and requested her to advise Rani
			<lb />
			Chaudhary to live with him. On 31.7.1979 she and Rani went
			<lb />
			to see off Rani&quot;s daughters at the railway station, where the
			<lb />
			appellant was also present. While returning from the railway
			<lb />
			station, the appellant followed them to their house. The
			<lb />
			appellant kept knocking the door and wanted to get inside the
			<lb />
			house and insisted that he would take Rani with him. She
			<lb />
			informed the police, upon which the police came and spoke to
			<lb />
			the appellant and went away, but the appellant remained
			<lb />
			there and left in the morning. She had to lodge a complaint
			<lb />
			Ex.PW-31/A with the police.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			Shri M.M.Thapar PW-37 (brother-in-law of Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand) deposed that he knew the appellant since his school
			<lb />
			days and knew Rani after her marriage with the appellant.
			<lb />
			After a few years of their marriage, differences arose between
			<lb />
			them, which could not be resolved even though he tried to
			<lb />
			reconcile them. Rani Chaudhary used to complain about her
			<lb />
			being un-happy on account of maltreatment and that she
			<lb />
			wanted to separate from the appellant. The appellant and
			<lb />
			Rani used to argue in his presence and quarrel with each
			<lb />
			other. On one occasion, the appellant even slapped Rani in his
			<lb />
			presence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			Neelu Moolchandani PW-39 deposed that he knew
			<lb />
			Krishan Sikand and Ashok Sikand as they were in the same
			<lb />
			school and that he met Rani Chaudhary in 1980. On a couple
			<lb />
			of occasions Krishan Sikand had mentioned to him about
			<lb />
			threats received from the appellant to compel Krishan Sikand
			<lb />
			to throw out Rani from his house.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			Brig. Ashok Nath Luthra PW-42 (family friend of
			<lb />
			Rani Chaudhary) deposed that Rani Chaudhary had introduced
			<lb />
			him to Krishan Sikand. Thereafter, they started visiting each
			<lb />
			other&quot;s house. Rani had once mentioned to him that her
			<lb />
			relations with the appellant were strained and that she
			<lb />
			planned to marry Krishan Sikand. Rani had also told him that
			<lb />
			the appellant did not like her staying with Krishan Sikand and
			<lb />
			wanted her to leave his house and that the appellant had been
			<lb />
			harassing Krishan Sikand to compel him to leave Rani.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			Shri Gajbir Singh PW-44 deposed that he knew
			<lb />
			Krishan Sikand since 1970 as he had been participating with
			<lb />
			him in the Himalayan Car Rally. He knew Rani Chaudhary
			<lb />
			since 1979 whom he met for the first time at 98 Sunder Nagar.
			<lb />
			Around Diwali 1981, Krishan Sikand told him that he was
			<lb />
			receiving telephone calls from the appellant insisting upon him
			<lb />
			to turn Rani Chaudhary out of his house, otherwise the
			<lb />
			appellant would kill Krishan Sikand.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			Insp.Om Sagar PW-48 deposed that complaint
			<lb />
			Ex.PW-1/MM was assigned to him for necessary inquiry vide
			<lb />
			endorsement Ex.PW-48/A.
			<lb />
			He contacted complainant
			<lb />
			S.J.Chaudhary who had come to the police station on
			<lb />
			1.10.1981. On 13.10.1981 he came to him in afternoon and
			<lb />
			informed that Smt.Rani Chaudhary was present at 98, Sunder
			<lb />
			Nagar with Krishan Sikand. He went to the said place. On his
			<lb />
			enquiry they gave explanation Ex.PW-1/KK. He submitted his
			<lb />
			inquiry report Ex.PW-48/B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20.
			<lb />
			It is apparent that aforenoted witnesses were cited
			<lb />
			to establish motive on the part of the appellant. Motive being
			<lb />
			to avenge the loss of his wife to the deceased. Through the
			<lb />
			testimony of aforenoted witnesses, obviously, the prosecution
			<lb />
			intended to prove that the appellant was having an obsession
			<lb />
			with Rani and was desiring her company at all cost.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			We need not note the cross examination of the
			<lb />
			various aforenoted witnesses, save and except the cross
			<lb />
			examination of Rani PW-1, who was confronted with her
			<lb />
			statement recorded by the police under Section 161 Cr.P.C. in
			<lb />
			which she stated that she had seen the parcel with address
			<lb />
			thereupon written in hand and that when Krishan picked up
			<lb />
			the parcel she warned him to leave it, lest it might be
			<lb />
			containing a bomb and that on return from the dinner she was
			<lb />
			anxious to know where had the parcel been kept by Krishan.
			<lb />
			We may note that at portions marked &quot;B&quot; to &quot;B&quot;, &quot;F&quot; to &quot;F&quot;, &quot;J&quot; to
			<lb />
			&quot;J&quot; and &quot;K&quot; to &quot;K&quot; aforesaid statements find mention in Rani&quot;s
			<lb />
			statement recorded under Section 161 Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			Shri Anil Sikand PW-13, brother of the deceased,
			<lb />
			deposed that on 27.9.1982 he had gone to Naldhera Golf
			<lb />
			Course (in Shimla, Himachal Pradesh) with Bili, Shri H.S.Nath
			<lb />
			and another person whose name he does not remember. He
			<lb />
			saw the appellant there in a golf hut, with one Jagat Ram, a
			<lb />
			caddy master. The next day he again saw the appellant who
			<lb />
			sought his permission to join him and his friends for a game,
			<lb />
			which he initially declined, but at the persistence of the
			<lb />
			appellant made him join the game and while playing, the
			<lb />
			appellant enquired about the well being of Krishan Sikand.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			Birender Singh PW-43 deposed that he had gone to
			<lb />
			Naldera Golf Club to practice for the annual match due to be
			<lb />
			held on 2.10.1982. Besides himself, his cousin Harinder Singh
			<lb />
			Nath and Anil Sikand and a fourth person were present. He
			<lb />
			found the appellant practicing there and exchanged greetings
			<lb />
			with him. The appellant enquired if he could play with them,
			<lb />
			which offer was accepted. During the play, appellant enquired
			<lb />
			about Krishan Sikand being fine.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24.
			<lb />
			Dalip Suri PW-60, deposed that in September 1982
			<lb />
			he was posted in the office of Himachal Tourism. That on
			<lb />
			22.9.1982, booking of a log hut was made in the name of
			<lb />
			Col.S.J.Chaudhary for the period 26.9.1982 to 29.9.1982, in
			<lb />
			tourist bungalow Naldera Complex. He was allotted hut No.6
			<lb />
			vide permit no.Ex.PW-60/A.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25.
			<lb />
			From the evidence of the aforenoted witnesses, the
			<lb />
			prosecution intended to establish the inquisitive conduct of the
			<lb />
			appellant in enquiring about the well being of Krishan Sikand,
			<lb />
			when the appellant had met Anil Sikand and Birender Singh at
			<lb />
			the Golf Course at Naldhera Himachal Pradesh on 27.9.1982.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26.
			<lb />
			Shri Suresh Gopal PW-3 deposed that he knew the
			<lb />
			deceased and Rani Chaudhary and he and his wife had been
			<lb />
			visiting them at 98 Sunder Nagar, when Rani Chaudhary was
			<lb />
			staying with Krishan Sikand. On 25.9.1982, he and his wife
			<lb />
			visited Krishan Sikand. At that time he had seen a mechanic
			<lb />
			working on the car of Krishan Sikand. While going up, he did
			<lb />
			not notice any parcel lying on the stairs. He and his wife
			<lb />
			stayed in Krishan Sikand&quot;s apartment for about an hour and a
			<lb />
			half and then the four i.e. Krishan Sikand, Rani Chaudhary, his
			<lb />
			wife Sushma Gopal and himself went out for dinner at about
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.00 PM. While going down the first floor apartment of Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand, Krishan Sikand was leading them, followed by him and
			<lb />
			thereafter by his wife and Rani. On the second last landing of
			<lb />
			the steps, Krishan Sikand saw a parcel of brownish colour with
			<lb />
			a white paper slip marked &quot;A1&quot; pasted on it on which name and
			<lb />
			address of Krishan Sikand was typed. The parcel was 5&quot; x 3&quot; x
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3&quot; in size. While going towards the car, Krishan opened the
			<lb />
			mesh door of the electric meter and placed the parcel there, in
			<lb />
			a window sill, parallel to the driveway near the entrance door.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27.
			<lb />
			Vijay Ram PW-5 deposed that he was living in the
			<lb />
			servant quarters of 98 Sunder Nagar since 1968-69. He was
			<lb />
			working part-time for Mr.Kock who was living in the front
			<lb />
			portion of the first floor of 98 Sunder Nagar. Deceased Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand was living in the remaining portion of the first floor.
			<lb />
			The man staircase was used by both families for going to the
			<lb />
			first floor. Letters were left by the postman near the stairs on
			<lb />
			the first or the second landing, and he used to pick up the
			<lb />
			letters and deliver, those belonging to Mr.Kock to him, and
			<lb />
			those belonging to Krishan Sikand to him. On 2.10.1982, he
			<lb />
			was going to Sunder Nagar Market to fetch a crate of soda
			<lb />
			water bottles for Mr.Kock and when he reached near the
			<lb />
			meters on the landing of the staircase, he noted a brown
			<lb />
			colour parcel lying inside the iron jali door of the meter
			<lb />
			enclosure. The said parcel had a paper pasted on it on which
			<lb />
			address of Krishan Sikand was written. At that time a party
			<lb />
			was going on in the house of Ashok Sikand, the elder brother
			<lb />
			of Krishan Sikand who was residing on the front side of the
			<lb />
			ground floor. He gave that parcel to Shyam Lal and directed
			<lb />
			him to deliver it to deceased Krishan Sikand. But, Shyam Lal
			<lb />
			expressed his inability, due to his preoccupation with the
			<lb />
			party. Thereupon, he went upstairs to the kitchen of Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand and delivered the parcel to him, informing that the said
			<lb />
			parcel was found lying in the window sill of the enclosure of
			<lb />
			the meters. After about half an hour he returned from Sunder
			<lb />
			Nagar Market and heard an explosion when he was near the
			<lb />
			first landing of the stairs to the servant quarter. When he
			<lb />
			reached the room of Krishan Sikand where the explosion had
			<lb />
			taken place, he found him lying on the floor, bleeding in the
			<lb />
			drawing room.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28.
			<lb />
			Shyam Lal PW-6 deposed that he was working as a
			<lb />
			sweeper in 98 Sunder Nagar with Sikand for the last 12 years.
			<lb />
			He was working with them even for the period between
			<lb />
			25.9.1982 -2.10.1982. On 2.10.1982 he was going towards
			<lb />
			the front side park through the driveway, when Vijay PW-5 an
			<lb />
			employee of Kock met him, where the car was parked. He told
			<lb />
			him that he had found a parcel in the window sill near the
			<lb />
			meter and he wanted the same to be delivered to Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand, to whom it was addressed. The parcel was about 5&quot; in
			<lb />
			length. He expressed his inability to do so and told Vijay Ram
			<lb />
			to deliver it himself. After about half an hour, he heard an
			<lb />
			explosion on the first floor occupied by Krishan Sikand. He
			<lb />
			along with other persons went upstairs where they found
			<lb />
			Krishan Sikand lying injured and bleeding on the floor near the
			<lb />
			dining table.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			29.
			<lb />
			Mohd. Shafi PW-7, a mechanic in Sikand Motors for
			<lb />
			the last 30 years, deposed that on 25.9.1982 he had been
			<lb />
			requisitioned by Krishan Sikand and he had gone to examine
			<lb />
			and repair car No.DEB -1957 at 98 Sunder Nagar at about 5.30
			<lb />
			PM. Krishan Sikand came in that very car at about 6.00 PM
			<lb />
			from outside, gave him the keys and went upstairs. At about
			<lb />
			7.30 PM he saw Gopal PW-3 and his wife go upstairs.
			<lb />
			Thereafter he took the car for a trial run up to the zoo and
			<lb />
			when he was coming back via Sunder Nagar Market he saw the
			<lb />
			appellant coming out of the gate of 98 Sunder Nagar and
			<lb />
			proceed towards Sunder Nagar Market. This was after 15 -
			<lb />
			minutes of his having left for a trial run of the car. He parked
			<lb />
			the car near the stairs wherein he met Jaglal Shikari who told
			<lb />
			him that he had been summoned by Krishan Sikand for shikar
			<lb />
			and delivery of clothes. Thereafter he went upstairs and
			<lb />
			delivered the key of the car to Krishan Sikand and informed
			<lb />
			him of the arrival of Jaglal.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30.
			<lb />
			Relevant would it be to note that the undisputed
			<lb />
			position is that Mohd.Shafi&quot;s statement under Section
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C. was recorded on 16.7.1983 i.e. after over nine months
			<lb />
			of the date of occurrence of the offence, which took place on
			<lb />
			2.10.1982.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31.
			<lb />
			Sanjay Sikand PW-8 son of the deceased deposed
			<lb />
			that on 2.10.1982 his father expired due to an explosion which
			<lb />
			took place at about 5.30 PM. At that time he was attending a
			<lb />
			birthday party of his cousin being celebrated at the ground
			<lb />
			floor. Fifteen minutes before the explosion Sanjay Sikand with
			<lb />
			his friend Manu Aggarwal had taken some sandwiches and
			<lb />
			patties for his father when he noticed a parcel lying on the
			<lb />
			sideboard of the room which is opposite the pantry room. The
			<lb />
			parcel was brownish in colour and had a white thread double
			<lb />
			folded and was 5&quot; x 3&quot; x 3&quot; in size.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32.
			<lb />
			Krishan Lal PW-20 deposed that he was employed
			<lb />
			in the Delhi Golf Club since 1976 as a starter and knew the
			<lb />
			appellant who was a member of the club. As a starter his job
			<lb />
			was to maintain records of players as and when a game
			<lb />
			commenced together with the particulars of the caddy at the
			<lb />
			first tee. Entry encircled in red in the register Ex.PW-20/A was
			<lb />
			in his hand and was dated 25.9.1982 and that it recorded that
			<lb />
			the appellant had played golf in the company of three players
			<lb />
			from 1.36 PM to 5.22 PM.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			33.
			<lb />
			Relevant would it be to note that in cross-
			<lb />
			examination, the witness admitted that a full game of golf
			<lb />
			requires 7 ½ Km to be walked and that the players take a bath
			<lb />
			and refreshments after playing the game. That the appellant
			<lb />
			used to leave the club normally around 7.45 PM. On 25.9.1982,
			<lb />
			he had requested the appellant for a lift in the evening as he
			<lb />
			lived at Bhogal which was on the way to Friends Colony and in
			<lb />
			the car, requested the appellant to give him a bottle of rum to
			<lb />
			entertain guests. The appellant took him to his residence in
			<lb />
			Friends Colony and gave him a bottle of rum. On being re-
			<lb />
			examined by the learned Special Prosecutor, the witness
			<lb />
			stated that he had no record of leaving with the appellant at
			<lb />
			7.45 PM on 25.9.1982 and that his deposition to said effect
			<lb />
			was based on memory.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34.
			<lb />
			With reference to the testimony of aforenoted
			<lb />
			witnesses, the prosecution sought to establish that Mohd.Shafi
			<lb />
			had seen the appellant coming out of the gate of 98 Sunder
			<lb />
			Nagar on 25.9.1982 at around 7:45 PM and that 15 minutes
			<lb />
			prior thereto, at around 7:30 PM Suresh Gopal and his wife had
			<lb />
			come to 98 Sunder Nagar and while going up the steps to the
			<lb />
			first floor they did not see any parcel on the steps and that at
			<lb />
			around 9:00 PM when they i.e. Suresh Gopal and his wife along
			<lb />
			with the deceased and Rani were leaving the house, a parcel
			<lb />
			was found at the staircase which was picked up by Krishan
			<lb />
			Sikand and kept at the sill of a wire mesh enclosure containing
			<lb />
			the electricity meters at the landing of the staircase and that
			<lb />
			the parcel remained forgotten at the same place till it was
			<lb />
			noticed by Vijay Ram on 2.10.1982, who requested Shyam Lal
			<lb />
			to deliver the same to Krishan Sikand and on the refusal of
			<lb />
			Shyam Lal to do so, Vijay Ram himself delivered the parcel to
			<lb />
			Krishan Sikand and that the parcel exploded at around 5:30 PM
			<lb />
			when a birthday party was being celebrated at the ground
			<lb />
			floor of the house. It is apparent that the prosecution was
			<lb />
			attempting to prove that the appellant had left the parcel at
			<lb />
			the staircase of the house of the deceased on 25.9.1982.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35.
			<lb />
			N.D.Sethi PW-27 deposed that he has been running
			<lb />
			Janta Commercial College since 1951. He had 13 English
			<lb />
			typewriters in his establishment since 1982. Five typewriters
			<lb />
			were for learners and the remaining for speed shooters. On
			<lb />
			5.8.1983 CBI accompanied by the appellant had come to his
			<lb />
			institute at about 6.00 PM to 7.00 PM and took specimen
			<lb />
			typing from the machines of which Ex.PW-27/A was one type
			<lb />
			specimen. The typed specimens were seized vide seizure
			<lb />
			memo Ex.PW-28/B. That around 22 nd or 23 rd September 1982
			<lb />
			a person had come with a handwritten address and an
			<lb />
			envelope and had requested to type the address on the
			<lb />
			envelope. He referred the person to a beginner student to do
			<lb />
			the needful. That he could not identify the person who had
			<lb />
			come. 8 files containing sheets typed in the year 1982 were
			<lb />
			seized vide seizure memo Ex.PW-27/E on 9.9.1983. A machine
			<lb />
			Ex.P-21 was seized vide seizure memo Ex.PW-27/B and that
			<lb />
			the address on Ex.A-1 was got typed on the machine Ex.P-21.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36.
			<lb />
			Shri V.K.Tyagi PW-28 deposed that some CBI
			<lb />
			officers had requested him and one Mr.Mehrotra to come to
			<lb />
			their office. In his presence the appellant made a disclosure
			<lb />
			statement Ex.PW-28/A which was reduced in writing and
			<lb />
			signed by him and Mr.Mehrotra as also three CBI officers. The
			<lb />
			appellant disclosed that he had got typed the address of the
			<lb />
			addressee and the sender at a typing institute in Lajpat Nagar.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the appellant led the CBI officers to Janta
			<lb />
			Commercial College and pointed out a typewriter on which the
			<lb />
			same were typed. Thereafter, specimen of typescripts were
			<lb />
			obtained from the machines at Janta Commercial College.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37.
			<lb />
			From the testimony of PW-27 and PW-28, the
			<lb />
			prosecution sought to prove that pursuant to the disclosure
			<lb />
			statement made by the appellant, CBI officers came to know
			<lb />
			for the first time that the addresses of the sender and the
			<lb />
			addressee on the parcel bomb were got typed by the appellant
			<lb />
			at Janta Commercial College. (We shall be shortly noting the
			<lb />
			testimony of the typescript expert and his report pertaining to
			<lb />
			the sample typescript Ex.PW-27/A and the typescript on the
			<lb />
			reconstructed slips of paper recovered from the debris of the
			<lb />
			parcel bomb, containing the address of the sender and the
			<lb />
			addressee).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38.
			<lb />
			Dr.G.R.Prasad PW-62 deposed that he had been
			<lb />
			working as ballistic expert with CFSL and on 7.10.1982 he
			<lb />
			received 13 sealed parcels from Inspector -II, Crime Branch,
			<lb />
			Delhi; out of which parcel No.3 was a cloth envelope sealed
			<lb />
			with three seals of VM and it contained stained brown paper
			<lb />
			pieces with remnants of address thereon. He reconstructed, to
			<lb />
			the extent possible, two addresses by pasting together the
			<lb />
			remnants of the paper as recorded in his report dated
			<lb />
			20.10.1982 Ex.PW-62/G.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39.
			<lb />
			We note that the reconstructed papers as per
			<lb />
			report Ex.PW-62/G, are as noted hereinabove in para 5.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40.
			<lb />
			Shri V.K.Khanna PW-59, Senior Scientific Officer-
			<lb />
			cum-Assistant Chemical Examiner, CFSL deposed that certain
			<lb />
			questioned and standard documents were sent for
			<lb />
			examination and comparison by S.P., CBI, New Delhi vide letter
			<lb />
			Ex.PW-59/A.
			<lb />
			These documents were retained in the
			<lb />
			documents&quot; division on 25.10.1983 and the receipt was given
			<lb />
			by the case assistant CFSL. The questioned writings which
			<lb />
			were sent for examination were marked Q-1 to Q-79. The
			<lb />
			specimen writings were marked S-767 to S-784 and admitted
			<lb />
			writings were marked A-1 to A-55. The questioned writings
			<lb />
			were examined and compared with the standard writing with
			<lb />
			the help of scientific aids.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41.
			<lb />
			SK Gupta PW-75, Director, Dept. of Science and
			<lb />
			Technology, deposed that on 6.8.1983 he received a letter
			<lb />
			from S.P./ CIU (P) addressed to Director CFSL along with this
			<lb />
			letter, typed documents marked S-1 to S-14 of various type
			<lb />
			writers were received. The questioned document Q-1, Ex.PW-
			<lb />
			62/O, on which his opinion was sought had already been
			<lb />
			received in finger print division of the Laboratory. That the
			<lb />
			documents marked by him as S-1 to S-14 are Ex. PW-71/A-1 to
			<lb />
			A-14. S-7 is Ex.PW-27/A.
			<lb />
			He gave his report that the
			<lb />
			questioned document Q-1 i.e. Ex.PW-62/O was got typed on
			<lb />
			the same typewriting machine on which the sample typescript
			<lb />
			S-7, exhibited as Ex.PW-27/A, was got typed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			42.
			<lb />
			Briefly noted, the report is based on identifying
			<lb />
			certain sheets in the 8 files which were seized vide seizure
			<lb />
			memo Ex.PW-27/E, as relatable to the same typewriter to
			<lb />
			which the questioned typescript could be related to and
			<lb />
			additionally the fact that the questioned typescript was found
			<lb />
			relatable to the same typewriter on which the sample
			<lb />
			typescript S-7 was got typed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			43.
			<lb />
			Thus, through the testimony of PW-59, PW-64 and
			<lb />
			PW-75, the prosecution sought to establish that the addresses
			<lb />
			on the parcel containing the bomb were typed at the instance
			<lb />
			of the appellant from the machine Ex.P-21 belonging to Janta
			<lb />
			Commercial College owned by PW-27.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			44.
			<lb />
			Maj.R.R.Gupta PW-45, deposed that since 10.6.1983
			<lb />
			he was the Control Officer with Central Ammunition Depot of
			<lb />
			Government of India and that a record of ammunition was
			<lb />
			maintained of captured ammunition.
			<lb />
			That 82420 hand
			<lb />
			grenades of Pakistani origin were received between March
			<lb />
			1972 to June 1972 of which 168 hand grenades had POF 1958
			<lb />
			markings. That these hand grenades were issued to various
			<lb />
			units and some were destroyed during tests.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45.
			<lb />
			Arun Kumar Kalsi PW-50 deposed that he has been
			<lb />
			working in the ammunition factory since 1979 as Works
			<lb />
			Manager. Detonator sets of N-36 hand-grenades four seconds
			<lb />
			are also manufactured in his factory. He stated that on
			<lb />
			2.7.1983 CBI approached him and asked him to accompany
			<lb />
			them to enable them to have a look at the fragments of
			<lb />
			grenades and cap chambers. He noted that the cap chambers
			<lb />
			were broken into pieces. One piece contained the mark &quot;KF&quot;
			<lb />
			and the other portion contained the month and year of
			<lb />
			manufacture. He noted the month and the year marked as &quot;3-
			<lb />
			64&quot;. That the detonator sets were not available in the market
			<lb />
			and could not be manufactured by anybody else.
			<lb />
			After
			<lb />
			perusing the inspection notes and the records of the said
			<lb />
			detonator relating to March 1964, the report Ex.PW-50/A was
			<lb />
			prepared by him.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			46.
			<lb />
			Shri Vinayak PW-61, Principal Foreman, C.I.A.
			<lb />
			deposed that he is trained in inspection of armaments and
			<lb />
			forensic ballistics in respect of grenade and its fragments
			<lb />
			including grenades of Pakistan origin captured by the Indian
			<lb />
			Army. That he had examined the remnants of the exploded
			<lb />
			hand-grenade and his opinion is Ex.PW-61/A, as per which he
			<lb />
			had opined that the fragments sent to him were of hand
			<lb />
			grenade number M-36 and the base plug was of Pakistan
			<lb />
			origin.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			47.
			<lb />
			Through the testimony of PW-45, PW-50 and PW-61,
			<lb />
			the prosecution sought to prove that the bobby trap bomb,
			<lb />
			used as the explosive device which was the cause of the death
			<lb />
			of Krishan Sikand was created by the use of hand grenades
			<lb />
			manufactured in Pakistan and that some hand grenades which
			<lb />
			were captured by the Indian Army were distributed in the
			<lb />
			various units of the Indian Army.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			48.
			<lb />
			We need not note the testimony of the various
			<lb />
			police officers associated with the investigation as no
			<lb />
			submissions were advanced by learned counsel for the parties
			<lb />
			with reference to the investigation carried out. We also need
			<lb />
			not note the testimony of the doctor who conducted the post-
			<lb />
			mortem of the deceased, for the reason, it is not in dispute
			<lb />
			that the deceased died when sharpnels from an explosive
			<lb />
			device pierced his body causing excessive internal bleeding.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			49.
			<lb />
			The defence produced eight witnesses.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			50.
			<lb />
			Shri Rattan Sehgal DW-1, a retired IPS officer
			<lb />
			deposed that he knew the appellant S.J.Chaudhary for over last
			<lb />
			32 years as he was a family friend. That on 25.9.1982, Sh.
			<lb />
			Vinod Gupta, a common friend, had hosted a party and that he
			<lb />
			met the accused in the party at No.4, Friends Colony at about
			<lb />
			8.30 or 9 PM.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			51.
			<lb />
			Shri A.K. Nehra DW-2 deposed that on 25.9.1982 at
			<lb />
			about 7.30 PM he had visited the house of the appellant but
			<lb />
			the appellant was not present there. He was informed by Ms.
			<lb />
			Kishori that the appellant was on his way back from the Golf
			<lb />
			Club. He waited at the house of the appellant till about 8:00
			<lb />
			PM when appellant arrived accompanied by a short and fat
			<lb />
			fellow, wearing glasses, to whom the appellant handed a bottle
			<lb />
			of rum. Thereafter, they stayed at the residence of the
			<lb />
			appellant till 8.30 PM and he dropped the appellant at a party
			<lb />
			at No.4 Friends Colony.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			52.
			<lb />
			Lt. General R.M.Vohra DW-3, deposed that in the
			<lb />
			year 1971, the appellant was holding the rank of a Major in the
			<lb />
			army and fought the 1971 war under his command. That only
			<lb />
			officers of the Engineering Corps were trained in the
			<lb />
			manufacture of ammunition and that at the time when he was
			<lb />
			in command, the appellant had not undergone any such
			<lb />
			specialized training. That the appellant was a soldier attached
			<lb />
			to the Hudson Horse Regiment, a part of the armoured corp.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			53.
			<lb />
			Col. Rajender Kumar DW-4, a retired Army Officer
			<lb />
			deposed that he was commissioned in the Indian Army
			<lb />
			Ordnance Core. That the shelf life of an ignitor set is only
			<lb />
			eight years, after which it may malfunction or hang fire or may
			<lb />
			not fire at all.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			54.
			<lb />
			Retd. Brig. S.K.Grover DW-5, deposed that Ex.DW-
			<lb />
			4/A was written by the Ordnance Director, Army Head Quarters
			<lb />
			with regard to the shelf life of hand grenade and ignitor set on
			<lb />
			the request of appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			55.
			<lb />
			Retd. Col. A.S.Sundram DW-6, deposed that when in
			<lb />
			service, he was dealing with bobby traps, mines and
			<lb />
			demolition. That he commanded the bomb disposal unit in
			<lb />
			Delhi from 1982 to 1987 and had deposed in a number of
			<lb />
			cases pertaining to bomb explosion, the last one being Rajiv
			<lb />
			Gandhi assassination case. That he was familiar with
			<lb />
			improvised explosive devices and was also familiar with the
			<lb />
			functioning of hand grenades and could explain as to how a
			<lb />
			hand grenade functions.
			<lb />
			That he had brought a chart
			<lb />
			describing the components of a hand grenade which is about
			<lb />
			the size of 4 inches from top to bottom and 2 to 2 ½ inches in
			<lb />
			diameter. For being operated, a hand grenade is held in the
			<lb />
			hand along with its lever. The safety pin is removed to free
			<lb />
			the lever, which is held down by the finger. Once the grenade
			<lb />
			is released from the hand the lever flies away and the striker
			<lb />
			of the hand grenade comes down and hits the percussion cap
			<lb />
			which triggers the explosion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			56.
			<lb />
			Shri Darshan Dayal Goel DW-7, claiming to be an
			<lb />
			expert in examination of questioned documents, deposed that
			<lb />
			he had compared the questioned type script Q-1, Ex.PW-62/O,
			<lb />
			with the specimen type script S-7, Ex.PW-27/A, and other
			<lb />
			specimen typescripts which were seized from Janta
			<lb />
			Commercial College. That according to him, the differences
			<lb />
			mentioned by him in the questioned document Q-1 and sample
			<lb />
			typescript S-7 are not reasonably accounted for. Further the
			<lb />
			partially burnt and mutilated condition of document marked Q-
			<lb />
			1, does not provide sufficient data for basing a definite and
			<lb />
			irrefutable opinion that the questioned typescript marked Q-1
			<lb />
			and the sample typescript marked S-7 have been typed on the
			<lb />
			same typewriter. That the report Ex.DW-7/A was authored by
			<lb />
			him
			<lb />
			57.
			<lb />
			Dr.B.R.Sharma DW-8, deposed that the CFSL Report
			<lb />
			Ex.PW-64/A and Ex.PW-64/B submitted by Dr.S.R.Singh were
			<lb />
			based on an improper scientific analysis because proper
			<lb />
			instruments were not used to examine the various
			<lb />
			components qua which and upon which, the reports were
			<lb />
			given.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			58.
			<lb />
			Though the learned Trial Judge has noted the
			<lb />
			testimony of all the witnesses who deposed facts that the
			<lb />
			appellant had a motive to kill the deceased; namely PW-1, PW-
			<lb />
			10, PW-11, PW-19, PW-32, PW-37, PW-39, PW-42, PW-44 and
			<lb />
			PW-48, but reliance has been placed only upon the testimony
			<lb />
			of PW-1 and PW-19. With reference to the testimony of Rani
			<lb />
			Chaudhary PW-1 and H.D.Sikand PW-19, the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Judge has held as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;I have no reason to disbelieve the witnesses
			<lb />
			about the threats given to Ms. Rani Chaudhary
			<lb />
			and deceased Kishan Sikand. It is submitted by
			<lb />
			counsel for accused that Ms. Rani has deposed
			<lb />
			about the threats to save her skin. She was a
			<lb />
			clever lady and wanted to grab the property of
			<lb />
			deceased Kishan Sikand since she has already
			<lb />
			obtained a will in her favour by influencing the
			<lb />
			deceased. I find no merit in this argument. The
			<lb />
			deposition of Rani Chaudary about the threats is
			<lb />
			corroborated by the deposition of H.D.Sikand,
			<lb />
			father of deceased, against whose testimony
			<lb />
			nothing has been stated during the course of
			<lb />
			arguments. Believing the deposition of Ms. Rani
			<lb />
			Chaudhary, H.D.Sikand and other witnesses, I
			<lb />
			find that accused had motive to kill not only Ms.
			<lb />
			Rani Chaudhary but also deceased Kishan Sikand
			<lb />
			so that they don&quot;t live together against the
			<lb />
			wishes of the accsued.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			59.
			<lb />
			With reference to the testimony of Major R.R.Gupta
			<lb />
			PW-45, Dr. G.R.Prasad PW-62 and Dr. B.Moitra, PW-63 the
			<lb />
			learned Trial Judge has held as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;The fact that accused S.J.Chaudhary was
			<lb />
			Lieutenant Colonel in Indian Army has not been
			<lb />
			disputed.
			<lb />
			PW-45 Major R.R.Gupta of Central
			<lb />
			Ammunition Depot has deposed that in the year
			<lb />
			1972, captured ammunition including M-36 hand
			<lb />
			grenade (4 seconds), 1958 of POF marking were
			<lb />
			received in their Depot. These hand grenades
			<lb />
			were issued to various units between 1972 to
			<lb />
			1982. This evidence has not been questioned by
			<lb />
			the accused.
			<lb />
			The necessary inference that can be drawn from
			<lb />
			this fact is that the accused S.J.Chaudhary being
			<lb />
			a military officer could lay his hands on M-36
			<lb />
			hand grenade &quot;MK1 POF 1958&quot;. It is significant
			<lb />
			to observe here that this is the same make of
			<lb />
			hand grenade which has been found to be used
			<lb />
			for the explosion which caused death of Kishan
			<lb />
			Sikand. It is not denied by accused that he was
			<lb />
			in service and even after his arrest on 5.8.83, he
			<lb />
			was produced in the court in the custody of
			<lb />
			army.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for accused submitted that such
			<lb />
			hand grenades are available in clandestine
			<lb />
			market and this fact has been admitted by the
			<lb />
			witnesses produced by the prosecution.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			I cannot believe the version of the witness that
			<lb />
			hand grenade of Pakistan origin captured by
			<lb />
			Indian Army is available in clandestine market.
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			However, accused being a military officer had
			<lb />
			knowledge about hand grenade and its working.
			<lb />
			Packing of hand grenade in a shuttle cock box of
			<lb />
			that size after removing the safety pin shows his
			<lb />
			expertise.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			60.
			<lb />
			Discussing the issue pertaining to the sender&quot;s and
			<lb />
			addressee&quot;s address on the parcel bomb i.e. the two addresses
			<lb />
			reconstructed as per Ex.PW-62/O, noting the opinion of
			<lb />
			Sh.S.K.Gupta PW-75 and Sh. Darshan Dayal Goel DW-7, but
			<lb />
			without any detailed analysis of the two reports and without
			<lb />
			even discussing the issues which were projected in relation to
			<lb />
			expert testimony on typescripts, the learned Trial Judge has
			<lb />
			opined as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Since there were contradictory reports about
			<lb />
			similarities and dis-similarities in the typed
			<lb />
			address, I have perused, checked and compared
			<lb />
			the original and photocopy of the typed address
			<lb />
			with the respective reports. I find, reasons given
			<lb />
			by PW-75 Shri S.K.Gupta are more sound than
			<lb />
			reasons given by DW-7 Shri Darshan Dayal Goel,
			<lb />
			a private expert who otherwise is an interested
			<lb />
			witness. Dis-similarities could also be on account
			<lb />
			of natural wear and tear and on account of way
			<lb />
			and manner of typing.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			61.
			<lb />
			Whether it stood established that the parcel bomb
			<lb />
			was left at the second lower most landing of the staircase
			<lb />
			leading to the first floor of 98 Sunder Nagar, on 25.9.1982;
			<lb />
			with reference to the testimony of Rani PW-1, Suresh Gopal
			<lb />
			PW-3, Mohd. Shafi, PW-7 and Krishan Lal PW-20, the learned
			<lb />
			Trial Judge has held that the testimony of PW-20 established
			<lb />
			that the appellant had played golf at Delhi Golf Club till 5:22
			<lb />
			PM and that the Golf Club was at a distance of about 100 yards
			<lb />
			from the house. The learned Trial Judge has referred to the
			<lb />
			testimony of PW-1, PW-3 and PW-7 to return a finding that
			<lb />
			cumulatively read, their testimony established that the
			<lb />
			appellant was seen at 98 Sunder Nagar between 7:30 PM and
			<lb />
			8:00 PM and that the parcel bomb was placed at the staircase
			<lb />
			between said time.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			62.
			<lb />
			Giving no reasons as to why the testimony of DW-2
			<lb />
			Major A.K.Nehra inspired no confidence and without discussing
			<lb />
			the testimony of the other defence witnesses who deposed
			<lb />
			that the appellant was in his house at New Friends Colony by
			<lb />
			8:00 PM, while ignoring the testimony of PW-20 that the
			<lb />
			appellant remained in the club till around 7:45 PM, the learned
			<lb />
			Trial Judge has held as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;I find that PW-20 Kishan Lal has deposed that
			<lb />
			generally accused used to leave the club at
			<lb />
			about 7:45 PM. He has not stated that accused
			<lb />
			was inside the club till 7:45 PM on 25.9.82. PW-
			<lb />
			20, in his cross examination, has deposed that
			<lb />
			he took lift from accused S.J.Chaudhary to get
			<lb />
			one bottle of rum. If his statement is perused,
			<lb />
			the has not deposed this fact in his examination
			<lb />
			in chief. There is no mention of this fact in his
			<lb />
			statement under Section 161 Cr.P.C. In his cross
			<lb />
			examination, he has not explained as to how he
			<lb />
			remembered the date. There is no statement
			<lb />
			about the presence of accused from 5:22 PM to
			<lb />
			7:45 PM on 25.9.82 in the Golf Club by PW-20
			<lb />
			Shri Kishan Lal or anyone else. The version of
			<lb />
			PW-20 Shri Kishan Lal as deposed in his cross
			<lb />
			examination and of DW-2 Major A.K.Nehra
			<lb />
			cannot be accepted. If what is stated by PW-20
			<lb />
			Shri Kishan Lal was correct, he ought to have
			<lb />
			deposed the same in his examination in chief
			<lb />
			that he left with accused in connection with
			<lb />
			bottle of rum on 25.9.82.
			<lb />
			He should have
			<lb />
			explained in his examination in chief rather than
			<lb />
			deposing in the cross examination.
			<lb />
			This
			<lb />
			indicates that he wants to help the accused.
			<lb />
			Hence, silence of PW-20 Kishan Lal at the time of
			<lb />
			examination in chief and the version of PW-20
			<lb />
			Kishan Lal, in the cross examination, leads me to
			<lb />
			hold that no reliance can be placed on this part
			<lb />
			of his evidence. Similarly, the deposition of DW-
			<lb />
			2 Major A.K.Nehra also cannot be given any
			<lb />
			weight.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			63.
			<lb />
			The fact that the statement of Mohd. Shafi PW-7
			<lb />
			under Section 161 Cr.P.C. was recorded as late as on
			<lb />
			16.7.1983 (the date of offence being 2.10.1982), the defence
			<lb />
			argument that the witness was planted has been negated as
			<lb />
			under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;I find that accused S.J.Chaudhary has been
			<lb />
			noticed by PW-7 Mohd. Shafi coming out of the
			<lb />
			gate of 98, Sunder Nagar on 25.9.82.
			<lb />
			His
			<lb />
			statement under Section 161 Cr.P.C. was
			<lb />
			recorded on 16.7.83. The investigation of the
			<lb />
			present case was entrusted to CBI on 19.3.83.
			<lb />
			None of the investigating officers of CBI had
			<lb />
			hostility towards the accused. It is only after CBI
			<lb />
			officials made enquiries from PW-7 Mohd. Shafi
			<lb />
			that he explained whatever he recollected. This
			<lb />
			accounts for alleged delay in recording his
			<lb />
			statement.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			64.
			<lb />
			Under what circumstances the parcel reached the
			<lb />
			hands of the deceased on 2.10.1982, the learned Trial Judge
			<lb />
			has relied upon the testimony of Vijay Ram PW-5 who claimed
			<lb />
			to have seen the parcel bomb on the ledge behind a wire mesh
			<lb />
			housing the electricity meters of the house and having handed
			<lb />
			over the same to the deceased in the evening of 2.10.1982.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			65.
			<lb />
			With reference to the testimony of Anil Sikand PW-
			<lb />
			13 and Birender Singh PW-43, the two persons who had met
			<lb />
			the appellant at the Golf Club at Naldhera, Shimla on
			<lb />
			27.9.1982, the learned Trial Judge has held as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Why such an enquiry was made by accused
			<lb />
			from Anil Sikand particularly when he was not
			<lb />
			happy with Smt. Rani Chaudhary living with
			<lb />
			deceased Kishan Sikand. The accused has not
			<lb />
			denied that he made a specific quesry to Anil
			<lb />
			Sikand as to when he last spoke to deceased
			<lb />
			Kishan Sikand.
			<lb />
			This admitted circumstance
			<lb />
			indicates that the accused wanted to enquire as
			<lb />
			to how his actions have not shown results yet. It
			<lb />
			also indicates mens-rea of accused to kill Smt.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Rani Chaudhary or deceased Kishan Sikand or
			<lb />
			both. A person who is exchanging pleasantries
			<lb />
			in normal course is not expected to inquire in the
			<lb />
			manner in which the enquiry was made by
			<lb />
			accused S.J.Chaudhary from Anil Sikand.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			66.
			<lb />
			It seriously not being disputed that the deceased
			<lb />
			died due to a bomb explosion and that the splinters recovered
			<lb />
			from his body at the time of post-mortem were similar to the
			<lb />
			splinters gathered from the spot, the learned Trial Judge has
			<lb />
			concluded as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;1.
			<lb />
			On 2.10.82, at about 5:30 PM an
			<lb />
			explosion took place on the first floor of 98,
			<lb />
			Sunder Nagar and Kishan Sikand died in that
			<lb />
			explosion.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			2.
			<lb />
			In the post-mortem, the cause of death
			<lb />
			has been opined as shock and haemorrhage as a
			<lb />
			result of injuries caused to heart, lungs, kidney
			<lb />
			and brain which are ante mortem in nature and
			<lb />
			caused by an explosive device, likely from a
			<lb />
			grenade and necessarily fatal.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			3.
			<lb />
			The death of deceased Kishan Sikand
			<lb />
			was caused due to explosion of hand grenade of
			<lb />
			&quot;M 36 MKI POF 1958&quot; and the hand grenade is of
			<lb />
			Pakistan origin. The base plug recovered from
			<lb />
			the spot on 3.10.82 bears the marking &quot;No.36-
			<lb />
			M-MK.1-3-POF-1958&apos;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.
			<lb />
			Smt. Rani Chaudhary, wife of accused
			<lb />
			was, residing at 98 Sunder Nagar with deceased
			<lb />
			Kishan Sikand despite the threats by the accsued
			<lb />
			not to stay with him.
			<lb />
			Hence, accused
			<lb />
			S.J.Chaudhary had the motive for commission of
			<lb />
			this offence.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			5.
			<lb />
			Accused S.J.Chaudhary was Lieutenant
			<lb />
			Colonel in Indian Army. Ammunitions including
			<lb />
			M-36 hand grenades (4 seconds) of Pakistan
			<lb />
			origin of POF marking were captured during the
			<lb />
			war of 1971.
			<lb />
			It was received in Central
			<lb />
			Ammunition Depot in 1972 by PW-45 Major
			<lb />
			R.R.Gupta.
			<lb />
			These hand grenades were
			<lb />
			distributed to various units between 1972 to
			<lb />
			1982.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			6.
			<lb />
			Accused S.J.Chaudhary was in Army at
			<lb />
			the time of occurrence of the incident and could
			<lb />
			easily lay hands on Hand Grenade No. &quot;M 36 MKI
			<lb />
			POF 1958&quot;. It is not possible for a lay man to
			<lb />
			procure a hand grenade of Pakistan origin from
			<lb />
			clandestine market.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			7.
			<lb />
			On 25.9.82, accused S.J.Chaudhary
			<lb />
			played golf in Delhi Golf Club till 5:22 PM at Delhi
			<lb />
			Golf Club, which is 100 yards away from 98,
			<lb />
			Sunder Nagar, place of occurrence. Accused was
			<lb />
			in close proximity to place of occurrence of
			<lb />
			incident on 25.9.82.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			8.
			<lb />
			On 25.9.82, accused was seen coming
			<lb />
			out of gate of 98 Sunder Nagar at about 7:30 PM
			<lb />
			by PW-7 Mohd. Shafi, the car mechanic who had
			<lb />
			come there to repair the car of deceased Kishan
			<lb />
			Sikand.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			9.
			<lb />
			On 25.9.82, deceased Kishan Sinad
			<lb />
			accompanied by Ms.Rani, Shri Suresh Gopal and
			<lb />
			his wife Mrs. Sushma Gopal, while coming down
			<lb />
			from the first floor of 98, Sunder Nagar, noticed a
			<lb />
			parcel lying on the second landing of the
			<lb />
			staircase at about 9 PM.
			<lb />
			The parcel was
			<lb />
			addressed to deceased Kishan Sikand. He kept it
			<lb />
			in the window sill near the meter jalli. Ms. Rani,
			<lb />
			Shri Suresh Gopal and Smt. Sushma Gopal
			<lb />
			notices the brown colured parcel wherein the
			<lb />
			address of deceased Kishan Sikand, 98, Sunder
			<lb />
			Nagar was typed on a white paper slip pasted on
			<lb />
			the parcel and the sender&quot;s name was of some
			<lb />
			metal industry.
			<lb />
			They saw deceased Kishan
			<lb />
			Sikand keeping the parcel in the window sill near
			<lb />
			the meter jalli.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			10.
			<lb />
			Acccused S.J.Chaudhary was seen at 98,
			<lb />
			Sunder Nagar on the same day on which the
			<lb />
			parcel was seen for the first time at the second
			<lb />
			landing of the staircase by the deceased Kishan
			<lb />
			Sikand, Smt. Rani Chaudhary and Shri Suresh
			<lb />
			Gopal on 25.9.82.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			11.
			<lb />
			Accused S.J.Chaudhary had personal
			<lb />
			grudge against the deceased since the deceased
			<lb />
			was living with his wife and had no reason to visit
			<lb />
			the house of deceased Kishan Sikand. Therefore
			<lb />
			it can be said with reasonable definiteness that
			<lb />
			the accused had come to 98, Sunder Nagar to
			<lb />
			keep the parcel which had been addressed to
			<lb />
			deceased Kishan Sikand.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			12.
			<lb />
			It has also been established that the
			<lb />
			accused got the address of the deceased Kishan
			<lb />
			Sikand typed on a white paper from Janta
			<lb />
			Commercial College, Lajpat Nagat to paste the
			<lb />
			same on the parcel.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			13.
			<lb />
			Accused S.J.Chaudhary went to Naldhera
			<lb />
			on 26.9.82 on the next day, after the parcel was
			<lb />
			placed and seen at 98, Sunder Nagar.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			14.
			<lb />
			In the golf club at Naldhera, on 28.9.82
			<lb />
			accused S.J.Chaudhary had a talk with Shri Anil
			<lb />
			Sikand, brother of deceased Kishan Sikand. The
			<lb />
			specific query made by accused to Anil Sikand as
			<lb />
			to how was the deceased and when he spoke to
			<lb />
			him last conclusively establishes the mens-rea of
			<lb />
			the accused and that the accused was anxious to
			<lb />
			know about results of his action.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			15.
			<lb />
			On 2.10.82, at about 5 PM, PW-5 Vijay
			<lb />
			Ram, servant of Mr. Kock, tenant in front portion
			<lb />
			of first floor of 98, Sunder Nagar, noticed the
			<lb />
			brown coloured parcel lying in the window sill
			<lb />
			near the meter jalli. Since it was addressed to
			<lb />
			deceased Kishan Sikand.
			<lb />
			PW-5 Vijay Ram
			<lb />
			handed over the said parcel to deceased Kishan
			<lb />
			Sikand.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			16.
			<lb />
			On 2.10.82 at about 5:15 PM, PW Sanjay
			<lb />
			Sikand, son of deceased Kishan Sikand went
			<lb />
			upstairs on the first floor to give patties and
			<lb />
			sandwiches to his father Kishan Sikand and
			<lb />
			inquired about the brown coloured parcel lying
			<lb />
			on the side table.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			17.
			<lb />
			The description of the parcel given by
			<lb />
			Smt. Rani Chaudhary, Shri Suresh Gopal who had
			<lb />
			seen the same on 25.9.82 and the description of
			<lb />
			the parcel given by Vijay Ram and Sanjay Sikand
			<lb />
			who saw it on 2.10.82, is the same.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			18.
			<lb />
			The death of Kishan Sikand was caused
			<lb />
			after he opened the parcel which had been
			<lb />
			handed over to him by PW-5 Vijay Ram.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			19.
			<lb />
			It has been established that the parcel
			<lb />
			which was handed over byVijay Ram to deceased
			<lb />
			Kishan Sikand contained a shuttle cock box and
			<lb />
			the moment the hand grenade was taken out it
			<lb />
			blasted because of the pressure release system.
			<lb />
			The safety pin of the grenade was missing and it
			<lb />
			has been established that the hand grenade
			<lb />
			could have been packed only by a person who
			<lb />
			had thorough knowledge about ammunitions and
			<lb />
			in particular about hand grenades.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			20.
			<lb />
			It has therefore been conclusively
			<lb />
			established that he parcel that was placed by the
			<lb />
			accused at the second landing the staircase at
			<lb />
			98, Sunder Nagar on 25.9.82 was the same
			<lb />
			parcel which kept lying in the window sill near
			<lb />
			the meter jalli and was handed over to deceased
			<lb />
			Kishan Sikand on 2.10.82 by PW-5 Vijay Ram and
			<lb />
			the same parcel contained the hand grenade
			<lb />
			which exploded and caused death of deceased
			<lb />
			Kishan Sikand.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			67.
			<lb />
			The decision of the learned Trial Judge may be
			<lb />
			summarized as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			A.
			<lb />
			The appellant desired the return of Rani Choudhary and
			<lb />
			since the deceased was a stumbling block in the way of the
			<lb />
			appellant, the appellant had a motive to commit the crime i.e.
			<lb />
			to remove the deceased from the appellant&quot;s path.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			B.
			<lb />
			The conduct of the appellant of enquiring on 27.9.1982
			<lb />
			from Anil Sikand and Birender Singh the well being of the
			<lb />
			deceased was an indication of his inquisitive mind to know the
			<lb />
			result of his action (of delivering the parcel bomb to the
			<lb />
			deceased on 25.9.1982), the inquisitive mind being a guilty
			<lb />
			mind desirous of knowing the consequences of the act
			<lb />
			motivated by the guilty mind.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			C.
			<lb />
			The military background of the appellant from which a
			<lb />
			presumption could be raised about his knowledge of
			<lb />
			ammunition. The fact that the parcel bomb had remnants of a
			<lb />
			base plug bearing marking &quot;No.36-M-NK.1-3-POF-1958&quot; and
			<lb />
			that hand grenades of &quot;M 36 MK1 POF 1958&quot; were seized by
			<lb />
			the Indian Army and distributed to various units of the army in
			<lb />
			India in the year 1972, justified an inference to be drawn that
			<lb />
			the appellant could have accessed hand grenades captured by
			<lb />
			the Indian Army and that the same were used to manufacture
			<lb />
			the parcel bomb.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			D.
			<lb />
			That the appellant was in Delhi on 25.9.1982 and had
			<lb />
			played golf at the Delhi Golf Club till around 5:30 PM; the golf
			<lb />
			club being about being 100 yards away from 98 Sunder Nagar;
			<lb />
			the appellant was seen leaving the house at around 7:45 PM
			<lb />
			and prior thereto when Suresh Gopal entered the house, he
			<lb />
			saw no parcel bomb and when he i.e. Suresh Gopal along with
			<lb />
			his wife, the deceased and Rani left the house at around 9:00
			<lb />
			PM, the parcel bomb was seen on the steps leading to the first
			<lb />
			floor of the house. Thus, it was the appellant who delivered
			<lb />
			the parcel bomb on 25.9.1982. Linking the further evidence to
			<lb />
			the events of 2.10.1982, the finding returned is that the
			<lb />
			testimony of Vijay Ram PW-5 established that the parcel bomb
			<lb />
			remained unattended at the ledge behind the wire mesh at the
			<lb />
			staircase on the ground floor till 2.10.1982, when it was
			<lb />
			noticed, per chance, by Vijay Ram who handed over the same
			<lb />
			to the deceased.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			E.
			<lb />
			The address of the sender and the addressee on the
			<lb />
			parcel bomb was got typed from Janta Commercial College and
			<lb />
			said fact came to the knowledge of the police pursuant to the
			<lb />
			disclosure statement of the appellant; the proof of the
			<lb />
			addresses being got typed from Janta Commercial College was
			<lb />
			the opinion of S.K.Gupta PW-75.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			68.
			<lb />
			It is no doubt true that from the testimony of Rani
			<lb />
			Choudhary PW-1, Sudhir Khanna PW-10, Kailash Nath Dwivedi
			<lb />
			PW-11, H.D.Sikand PW-19, Smt.Davinder Singh PW-32, Shri
			<lb />
			M.M.Thapar PW-37, Neelu Moolchandani PW-39, Brig. Ashok
			<lb />
			Nath Luthra PW-42, Shri Gajbir Singh PW-44 and Insp. Om
			<lb />
			Sagar PW-48, an inference can be drawn that the appellant
			<lb />
			had a strong desire, bordering on an obsession, to have Rani
			<lb />
			Choudhary back with him in his house as his wife and since
			<lb />
			Rani Choudhary, who had obtained a divorce from the
			<lb />
			appellant, was contemplating a matrimonial bond with the
			<lb />
			deceased, the appellant had a motive to kill the deceased.
			<lb />
			But, three letters dated 20.10.1980, 16.11.1980 and 3.3.1982
			<lb />
			being Ex.PW-1/FF, Ex.PW-1/GG and Ex.PW-1/NN, written by the
			<lb />
			appellant to Rani Choudhary, throw light on something else.
			<lb />
			The three letters read as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			Ex.PW-1/FF
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			22 Oct 80
			<lb />
			Dearest Rani
			<lb />
			Having tried, in vain, to obtain an opportunity of
			<lb />
			speaking with you, I am resorting to this letter as I
			<lb />
			do not want a lack of communication between us
			<lb />
			to be a cause for my not being able to convey,
			<lb />
			properly, my feelings to you. You can tear this
			<lb />
			letter up right now -in case you feel it is a waste
			<lb />
			of your time -or dwell upon its contents and
			<lb />
			arrive at a considered decision, if you see any
			<lb />
			sense in it.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			I have known you long enough to know what you
			<lb />
			value in life. I also know the extent to which you
			<lb />
			will rebel if something is forced upon you -hence
			<lb />
			this hones and final suggestion I make for your
			<lb />
			consideration.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Notwithstanding all that has happened up till
			<lb />
			today, let us forgive and forget each other&quot;s
			<lb />
			mistakes. If for no other reason then at least for
			<lb />
			the sake of those who we have brought into this
			<lb />
			world.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			My suggestion is briefly as under:-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			1. We give our marriage on last chance in the
			<lb />
			manner prescribed hereafter.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) We live together
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) I will bear all expenses, and liabilities of running a
			<lb />
			home
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) I will NOT interfere with your way of living, your
			<lb />
			lifestyle, your choice of friends, your choice of
			<lb />
			leisure and entertainment or any other thing that
			<lb />
			you may be accustomed to and will agree to abide
			<lb />
			by any other conditions that you may wish to
			<lb />
			stipulate.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d) I will reduce to a legal document, if so desired by
			<lb />
			you, so as to make the above conditions binding.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e) If after ONE year of our living together, you are
			<lb />
			not happy or satisfied to continue, I will arrange a
			<lb />
			divorce or conditions mutually agreeable to us
			<lb />
			both.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			2. In case the above makes sense then we can
			<lb />
			discuss with each other, in the presence of your
			<lb />
			friends/relatives or any one else, if necessary, the
			<lb />
			exact modalities involved.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Rani I love you very much and I would be failing if
			<lb />
			I did not draw your attention to the fact that NO
			<lb />
			sacrifice is too great for those who we have
			<lb />
			brought into this world.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			To scar them with
			<lb />
			complexes resultant of a broken home is neither
			<lb />
			justifiable nor sensible -particularly as both of us
			<lb />
			have the basic intelligence and capacity to be able
			<lb />
			to concede to one another&quot;s point of view.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			I am offering you a blank cheque and you have no
			<lb />
			need to forgo anything nor alter radically your way
			<lb />
			of life as my proposal involves an honest attempt
			<lb />
			-and that too for only ONE year. After all one
			<lb />
			year will rob neither you nor me of any thing to
			<lb />
			valuable -yet it may provide our children a
			<lb />
			multitude of blessing and benefits of a home.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			I do hope, Rani, you will give this letter of mine
			<lb />
			the consideration it deserves and will let me know
			<lb />
			your decision in due course.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			I love you.
			<lb />
			Yours
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Jiti
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ex.PW-1/GG
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			16/11/80
			<lb />
			Dearest Rani,
			<lb />
			It is always difficult to put words to paper -yet I
			<lb />
			keep trying.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			I am back in Bangalore -couldn&quot;t see you before
			<lb />
			leaving. Hope you had a nice shoot and were not
			<lb />
			too tired at the end of it. How does your back
			<lb />
			take it? I am sure the only way to build it back to
			<lb />
			its original strength would be to exercise it in just
			<lb />
			this manner -actually driving out into the country
			<lb />
			and let it take a bit of a bashing.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Back to the subject -Rani must we fight each
			<lb />
			other &amp; to what end?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			I learnt from Mani and Nita of your visit to Thapar
			<lb />
			House (a couple of weeks ago) -it left me very
			<lb />
			sad to think of you having to face the &quot;hostile
			<lb />
			environment&quot; that you so keenly seem to want to
			<lb />
			adopt. Why? And to what purpose? Just look
			<lb />
			around you and see what riches you already
			<lb />
			have.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Two lovely girls from &quot;Peter Papa&quot; and an
			<lb />
			adorable one from &quot;Jiti Papa&quot;. Mimi -the lovely
			<lb />
			one who is having her periods on time (4 th ?)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			It warmed my heart to tears to know that life is
			<lb />
			actually progressing around us -and we seem to
			<lb />
			be moving backwards. Shortly she (Mimi) will
			<lb />
			have the normal problesm of an adolescent (sp!)
			<lb />
			-and who does she turn to -Mama no doubt -
			<lb />
			but there is always a need to &quot;talk&quot; to an
			<lb />
			understanding &quot;Papa&quot; Who will that be now that
			<lb />
			&quot;Peter Papa&quot; is not with us. Surely &quot;Jiti Papa&quot;
			<lb />
			could have done? Then in next to no time it will
			<lb />
			be Mytri -exactly the same processes -evolution
			<lb />
			does not stand still for marital problems to be
			<lb />
			resolved. Then what? What gain if you or I win
			<lb />
			our personal battle against each other if we were
			<lb />
			to lose the Campaign? And that is a certainty -
			<lb />
			this litigation will only prove the age old adage -
			<lb />
			settling out of court is always better than trying it
			<lb />
			within.
			<lb />
			What is there to settle for? I see you, Rani, as a
			<lb />
			woman in a period in life that you have not been
			<lb />
			able to deny yourself -the grand sweeping
			<lb />
			p0assion, (illicit or otherwise) the last flush of
			<lb />
			your youth, the final careless autumn that
			<lb />
			preceeds middle age -the desire to prolong what
			<lb />
			you feel you have missed out on -attention,
			<lb />
			adulation and pursuit by millions of elligibles and
			<lb />
			to take it all before accepting the ultimate
			<lb />
			inevitable role of a family figure-head -a mother -
			<lb />
			! doling out love, affection and guidance to those
			<lb />
			you have brought into the world. Well whats
			<lb />
			wrong with that &amp; who am I to deny you all that?
			<lb />
			-Take it all Rani -live your life to let no regrets
			<lb />
			remain but do return to your anchor before you
			<lb />
			destroy it -the anchor is none other than the
			<lb />
			home &amp; family that you already have. M, M &amp; S
			<lb />
			with J hanging around -hovering -in the
			<lb />
			background. In many ways even I will have to be
			<lb />
			grateful to Krishan for having kept you involved
			<lb />
			enough to prevent you making a spectacle of
			<lb />
			yourself -In giving you a zest for appreciating
			<lb />
			things that I failed to -like shooting, running a
			<lb />
			home and invoking an arousal of that motherly
			<lb />
			instinct that no woman can be or do without. For
			<lb />
			that alone you owe it to him to see that you do
			<lb />
			not let him down too suddenly -he has already
			<lb />
			been hurt badly once. But what has to be done,
			<lb />
			has to be done and you have to make that
			<lb />
			decision your own self. You have to weigh your
			<lb />
			family against the untold unhappiness that could
			<lb />
			be brought about by your continuing to live with
			<lb />
			him. You do not, surely, want him to be isolated
			<lb />
			or alienated from his own Kin, as that would
			<lb />
			inevitably be, should you choose to stick to him.
			<lb />
			The choice therefore really is to let him find
			<lb />
			someone more readily mergeable with his family
			<lb />
			and for you to salvage what little you have
			<lb />
			already -rather than start everything afresh
			<lb />
			jeopardizing the happiness of both his kin and
			<lb />
			ours. Let us review what the essentials are and
			<lb />
			take what God has given us with gratitude and
			<lb />
			thanks.
			<lb />
			Should you choose to return to your own family -
			<lb />
			both you &amp; I stand to lose a little face in society -
			<lb />
			but not too much that cannot be erased.
			<lb />
			The other alternative defies my powers to foresee
			<lb />
			what all it could entail.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			It is not easy for me to put this to pen but better
			<lb />
			that I do so than risk a stone being left unturned.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Whatever I love you or not is now totally
			<lb />
			immaterial -the point is do you and I love
			<lb />
			enough, those that we have, and do we have it
			<lb />
			within us to sacrifice for them, our individual
			<lb />
			loves?
			<lb />
			Deliberate and only then act. Try to keep at least
			<lb />
			this letter to yourself. I continue to love you as
			<lb />
			before.
			<lb />
			Yours,
			<lb />
			Jiti
			<lb />
			P.S. Please acknowledge
			<lb />
			-I would hate to have this go astray.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
			x
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Ex.PW-1/NN
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			3/3/82
			<lb />
			Bangalore
			<lb />
			Deares Rani,
			<lb />
			Congratulations! You should win!!
			<lb />
			Your lawyer sounded more convincing than mine.
			<lb />
			For whatever wrongs I might have done to you -
			<lb />
			advertently or inadvertently -have been paid for
			<lb />
			(fully) by me thro the humiliation I suffered
			<lb />
			walking to and fro &quot;up the aisle&quot; of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court to which you were a witness. We are now
			<lb />
			Quits!! I wish you well as I love you -as you fully
			<lb />
			well know. Neither you nor I can control the
			<lb />
			destiny set for us -be happy &amp; most of all -be at
			<lb />
			peace with your mind.
			<lb />
			My &quot;cross&quot; shall be that I&quot;ll love you more and
			<lb />
			more as the time goes by -I pray that GOD gives
			<lb />
			me the strength to bear it.
			<lb />
			Love, Goodbye
			<lb />
			Jiti
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			69.
			<lb />
			Each letter brings out, not only the poet in the
			<lb />
			appellant, but a desire to have Rani Choudhary back in the
			<lb />
			house; not for himself, but for the sake of the three daughters,
			<lb />
			two born to Rani Choudhary from her previous marriage and
			<lb />
			the third born to Rani Choudhary and the appellant. The
			<lb />
			letters bring out that the appellant had reconciled to the fact
			<lb />
			that his finances could not feed the luxurious life style to which
			<lb />
			Rani Choudhary had got accustomed to. The appellant had
			<lb />
			reconciled to Rani Choudhary continuing a relationship,
			<lb />
			plutonic as well as physical, with her friends. They bring out
			<lb />
			the desire of the appellant to have Rani Choudhary returning
			<lb />
			to the house, not as a wife, but as a mother; for the sake of the
			<lb />
			well being and future of the three daughters who were
			<lb />
			budding flowers and required the emotional support of a
			<lb />
			mother.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			70.
			<lb />
			Unfortunately, the learned Trial Judge has totally
			<lb />
			eschewed a reference to the afore noted three letters, the last
			<lb />
			of which was written when arguments were concluded before
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court in the proceedings which had emanated
			<lb />
			out of the petition seeking divorce filed by Rani Choudhary. It
			<lb />
			shows that the appellant had understood the mood of the
			<lb />
			Bench and had congratulated Rani Choudhary for having a
			<lb />
			better counsel than him. The letter shows that the appellant
			<lb />
			had reconciled to the inevitable will of God.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			71.
			<lb />
			Thus, there is scope for an argument that inasmuch
			<lb />
			as there is evidence wherefrom a motive can be attributed to
			<lb />
			the appellant; there is an equal scope for an argument that
			<lb />
			there is evidence on record wherefrom said motive gets
			<lb />
			negated.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			72.
			<lb />
			But, for the purposes of our decision we proceed on
			<lb />
			the basis that the appellant had a motive to kill the deceased
			<lb />
			and that the prosecution has successfully established the
			<lb />
			motive.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			73.
			<lb />
			It is no doubt true that conduct of an accused is
			<lb />
			relevant and admissible evidence under Section 8 of the
			<lb />
			Evidence Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			74.
			<lb />
			With reference to the testimony of Anil Sikand PW-
			<lb />
			13 and Birender Singh PW-43, the learned Trial Judge has held
			<lb />
			that by the fact that the appellant enquired from them on
			<lb />
			28.9.1982, the well being of the deceased, is a circumstance
			<lb />
			which indicates that the accused wanted to enquire as to how
			<lb />
			his actions have not shown results yet. The learned Trial Judge
			<lb />
			has further held that the same also indicates mens rea to kill
			<lb />
			the deceased or Rani Chaudhary or both.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			75.
			<lb />
			We find a process of convulted reasoning adopted
			<lb />
			by the learned Trial Judge while drawing inferences against the
			<lb />
			appellant on the testimony of PW-13 and PW-43. As per the
			<lb />
			testimony of the said witnesses the appellant was more than
			<lb />
			an acquaintance; he was a friend. He desired to play a game
			<lb />
			of golf with them, to which they agreed. Anil Sikand is the
			<lb />
			brother of Kishan Sikand. By extending the usual courtesy
			<lb />
			expected from a friend by a friend i.e. of asking the well-being
			<lb />
			of the family, we find no scope to infer the desire of a guilty
			<lb />
			mind to know as to why the acts motivated by the guilty mind
			<lb />
			have not achieved the desired result.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			76.
			<lb />
			In a somewhat similar circumstance, in the decision
			<lb />
			reported as 2005 (11) SCC 600 State (NCT of Delhi) vs. Navjot
			<lb />
			Sandhu, where a few days after the attack by terrorist on the
			<lb />
			Parliament of India, accused S.A.R.Gilani&quot;s brother-in-law had
			<lb />
			inquisitively asked S.A.R.Gilani over the telephone as to how
			<lb />
			were things in Delhi, to which S.A.R.Gilani had responded that
			<lb />
			things were looking fine, the inference drawn by the Trial
			<lb />
			Judge that S.A.R.Gilani was telling his brother that his grand
			<lb />
			design was achieving its end; an inference negated by a
			<lb />
			Division Bench of this Court as a perverse inference, was
			<lb />
			affirmed by the Supreme Court to be a perverse inference.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			77.
			<lb />
			Logic guides us that to justify an inference being
			<lb />
			drawn from a fact, the same has to be the only inference
			<lb />
			possible, negating any other inference which may be drawn.
			<lb />
			From the mere fact of the appellant enquiring about the health
			<lb />
			and well being of the deceased from Anil Sikand and Birender
			<lb />
			Singh on 28.9.1982, no logical person can say that the only
			<lb />
			inference possible is the desire of the appellant to know as to
			<lb />
			why his acts have not borne the requisite consequences.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			78.
			<lb />
			It has to be noted that the deceased was no
			<lb />
			ordinary person. He was the son of a reputed business family
			<lb />
			in Delhi. His death, that too a violent death was bound to
			<lb />
			attract media coverage, a fact which actually took place on
			<lb />
			3.10.1982 i.e. media coverage of the death of Kishan Sikand.
			<lb />
			The appellant was thus not expected to rely upon information
			<lb />
			given to him by PW-13 and PW-43, for the reason he would
			<lb />
			have received the necessary information through the media.
			<lb />
			Be that as it may, de-hors this line of reasoning, which may be
			<lb />
			speculative (we concede), we hold, for the reasons given in
			<lb />
			para 75 to 77 above, that the inference of a guilty mind drawn
			<lb />
			by the learned Trial Judge with reference to conduct of the
			<lb />
			appellant is contrary to logic and the principles of law on which
			<lb />
			inferences are required to be drawn.
			<lb />
			Said incriminating
			<lb />
			circumstance has thus to be removed while listing the
			<lb />
			incriminating evidence and circumstances against the
			<lb />
			appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			79.
			<lb />
			The evidence on record does establish that the
			<lb />
			remnants of a base plug bearing marking &quot;No.36-M-NK.1-3-
			<lb />
			POF-1958&quot; were recovered from the debris at the spot by SI
			<lb />
			Vishnu Madan PW-69 who had reached the first floor of the
			<lb />
			house where the explosion took place on 2.10.1982. The
			<lb />
			evidence on record also establishes that in the year 1972 hand
			<lb />
			grenades seized by the Indian Army of Pakistan origin of the
			<lb />
			make &quot;M 36 MK1 POF 1958&quot; were distributed to various army
			<lb />
			units in India. The evidence on record also establishes that the
			<lb />
			appellant was a soldier attached to Hudson Horse Regiment, a
			<lb />
			part of the armoured corp of the Indian Army.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			80.
			<lb />
			But, from said four facts, is it possible to draw the
			<lb />
			inference that the only conclusion possible is that the
			<lb />
			appellant had accessed hand grenades captured by the Indian
			<lb />
			Army and had knowledge to fabricate the bobby trap bomb by
			<lb />
			using the ill gotten hand grenades accessed by him.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			81.
			<lb />
			We have already held above that the theory of logic
			<lb />
			guides us that to draw an inference from facts, the inference
			<lb />
			drawn should be the only one possible and if there are more
			<lb />
			than one inferences which can be drawn from a given set of
			<lb />
			facts, it would be impermissible to draw only one inference.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			82.
			<lb />
			There is no evidence that any hand grenade of
			<lb />
			Pakistan make which was handed over to the various units of
			<lb />
			the Indian Army was stolen or was missing. Unless said fact
			<lb />
			was proved, we see no scope to draw any inference of
			<lb />
			somebody misusing any such hand grenade. Thus, the very
			<lb />
			foundation on which the inference has been drawn by the
			<lb />
			learned Trial Judge is knocked out.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			83.
			<lb />
			Besides, merely because the appellant was an ex
			<lb />
			army man, is no ground to draw an adverse inference that he
			<lb />
			had knowledge of ammunition to manufacture or assemble the
			<lb />
			bobby trap bomb. There is a difference in having knowledge
			<lb />
			of use of ammunition and knowledge of manufacture of
			<lb />
			ammunition. The evidence on record is that the appellant was
			<lb />
			attached to a regiment which was a part of the armoured corp
			<lb />
			of the Indian Army. The armoured corp does not sit in the
			<lb />
			ordinance factory. It is stationed either at the garrison or at
			<lb />
			the forward posting. Its members are taught the use of arms
			<lb />
			and ammunition. They are not imparted the knowledge of
			<lb />
			manufacturing ammunition. DW-6 an expert at bomb disposal,
			<lb />
			having commanded the bomb disposal unit in Delhi from 1982
			<lb />
			to 1987, has deposed with respect to the complexities of a
			<lb />
			hand grenade.
			<lb />
			Indeed, his testimony brings out the
			<lb />
			complexities of the knowledge required to be imbibed before a
			<lb />
			person can dismantle a live hand grenade and use its
			<lb />
			components to create a bobby trap bomb.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			84.
			<lb />
			It is unfortunate that the learned Trial Judge has not
			<lb />
			even bothered to look into the testimony of DW-6.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			85.
			<lb />
			We are noting that the learned Trial Judges are
			<lb />
			short circuiting defence witnesses, holding that they are
			<lb />
			interested witnesses. Indeed, in the instant case, the learned
			<lb />
			Trial Judge has trivialized most of the defence witnesses by
			<lb />
			inserting a line qua them that they are interested witnesses.
			<lb />
			Defence witnesses are entitled to be treated at par with the
			<lb />
			witnesses of the prosecution and their evidence has to be
			<lb />
			discussed and analyzed on the same process of reasoning
			<lb />
			which is adopted to discuss and analyze the testimony of the
			<lb />
			witnesses of the prosecution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			86.
			<lb />
			The learned Trial Judge has held that explosive
			<lb />
			devices were not freely available in the market, as was
			<lb />
			projected to by the defence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			87.
			<lb />
			The year of the offence is 1982. It was the peak of
			<lb />
			terrorism in the State of Punjab and the State of Jammu &amp;
			<lb />
			Kashmir. Ammunition to manufacture bombs is obviously not
			<lb />
			available in the open market. It has to be procured from the
			<lb />
			underworld. Indeed, in the year 1982 explosive devices were
			<lb />
			being freely used by terrorists not only in the State of Punjab,
			<lb />
			the State of Jammu &amp; Kashmir, but all over India. Delhi had
			<lb />
			witnessed a series of transistor bomb blasts in the year 1982.
			<lb />
			The learned Trial Judge could not have ignored said historical
			<lb />
			facts.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			88.
			<lb />
			Since there is no evidence to show that the
			<lb />
			appellant was imparted knowledge or had acquired knowledge
			<lb />
			in the making of ammunition and that there is no evidence
			<lb />
			that any hand grenade of Pakistani origin distributed in the
			<lb />
			year 1972 to the various regiments of the Indian Army was
			<lb />
			stolen, we hold that the inference drawn by the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Judge with reference to the army background of the appellant,
			<lb />
			as the author/manufacturer of the parcel bomb is incorrect.
			<lb />
			We hold that said incriminating circumstance against the
			<lb />
			appellant has to be excluded.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			89.
			<lb />
			Did the appellant leave the parcel bomb at the
			<lb />
			steps of 98 Sunder Nagar on 25.9.1982? With reference to the
			<lb />
			testimony of Suresh Gopal PW-3, Rani Choudhary PW-1,
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi PW-7 and Kishan Lal PW-20, the learned Trial Judge
			<lb />
			has held that the said fact stood established.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			90.
			<lb />
			Briefly put, the reasoning of the learned Trial Judge
			<lb />
			is that the testimony of Suresh Gopal PW-3 establishes that he
			<lb />
			and his wife reached the house at around 7:30 PM and saw
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi PW-7 repair the car of the deceased and when
			<lb />
			Suresh Gopal and his wife went upstairs to reach the first floor
			<lb />
			of the house where the deceased resided they did not see any
			<lb />
			packet. Mohd.Shafi drove the car which he was repairing for a
			<lb />
			test drive and returned after a few minutes and saw the
			<lb />
			appellant leave the house of the deceased. Thereafter, as
			<lb />
			deposed to by Suresh Gopal and Rani Chaudhary, when the
			<lb />
			said two witnesses along with the wife of Suresh Gopal and the
			<lb />
			deceased descended from the first floor to go out for dinner at
			<lb />
			Pandara Road Market, at around 9:00 PM, the parcel
			<lb />
			(containing the bomb) was noticed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			91.
			<lb />
			The most crucial witness for the prosecution as also
			<lb />
			the defence, is obviously Mohd.Shafi PW-7.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			92.
			<lb />
			We propose to discuss the creditworthiness of
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi before discussing the creditworthiness of the
			<lb />
			testimony of Rani Choudhary and Suresh Gopal on said issue.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			93.
			<lb />
			At the outset it assumes some significance that
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi&quot;s statement under Section 161 Cr.P.C. was
			<lb />
			recorded on 16.7.1983 i.e. after nearly nine and a half months
			<lb />
			of the incident. It is also of some significance that Mohd.Shafi
			<lb />
			is an employee of Sikand Motors, the family concern of the
			<lb />
			deceased and his father and brothers. It is also significant to
			<lb />
			note that in the statement of Suresh Gopal recorded on
			<lb />
			5.10.1983 under Section 161 Cr.P.C. he has not stated that
			<lb />
			when he came to the house of the deceased on 25.9.1983, he
			<lb />
			had seen Mohd.Shafi. We note that when cross-examined,
			<lb />
			Suresh Gopal stated: I did tell to both crime branch about my
			<lb />
			seeing a mechanic working on the car on 25 th Sept.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(confronted with Ex.PW-3/DC and DD where it is not so
			<lb />
			mentioned). Now, one of the two situation has to exist. Either
			<lb />
			Suresh Gopal did not inform the police and hence it was not
			<lb />
			recorded in his statement by the police that he had seen a
			<lb />
			mechanic, or he had said so. If Suresh Gopal did not state so,
			<lb />
			it is apparent that he was made to improve upon his statement
			<lb />
			to afford a good ground to justify the introduction of
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi, who otherwise would appear to be a planted
			<lb />
			witness. Alternatively, if Suresh Gopal had told the police of
			<lb />
			having seen a mechanic working upon the car of the deceased,
			<lb />
			we see no scope for the police not questioning the mechanic
			<lb />
			who was seen by Suresh Gopal.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			94.
			<lb />
			Under both circumstances, we feel, it to be our
			<lb />
			duty, to now carefully analyze the testimony of Mohd.Shafi.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			95.
			<lb />
			We quote from his testimony:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;………….It was about 7:30 PM when I was about to set
			<lb />
			the bonnet of the car after having repaired it. I saw
			<lb />
			Gopal and his wife come there and go upstairs. I knew
			<lb />
			them prior thereto. Thereafter to have a trial run I
			<lb />
			took that car out up to zoo and was coming back via
			<lb />
			the Sunder Nagar Market when I saw one Jiti near the
			<lb />
			gate of 98 Sunder Nagar coming out of the said 98,
			<lb />
			Sunder Nagar and going towards the Sunder Nagar
			<lb />
			Market. It was after 15 -20 minutes of my going for a
			<lb />
			trial run of the car. Said Jiti is the accused person in
			<lb />
			the Court. I have never seen the accused at 98
			<lb />
			Sunder Nagar, prior thereto. I knew the accused prior
			<lb />
			thereto. I parked the car at the same place near the
			<lb />
			stairs.
			<lb />
			Thereafter Juglal, Shikari of Dharu Hara
			<lb />
			(Haryana) came there whom I had known for quite
			<lb />
			some time.
			<lb />
			He had told me that he had been
			<lb />
			summoned by Kishan Sikand for shikar and for
			<lb />
			delivery of clothes. Thereafter, I went and delivered
			<lb />
			the key of the car to Kishan Sikand and informed him
			<lb />
			of the arrival of Juglal who told me that Juglal be
			<lb />
			handed over a blue coloured pant given to me by
			<lb />
			Kishan Sikand and he told that shikar program would
			<lb />
			take effect a fortnight hence of which he would be
			<lb />
			informed and I then came back informed Juglal
			<lb />
			delivered the pant and then both of us came.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			96.
			<lb />
			Going by the testimony of Mohd.Shafi, it is apparent
			<lb />
			that after he had seen the appellant leave 98 Sunder Nagar
			<lb />
			and after he parked the car outside the gate, after the trial
			<lb />
			run, he went upstairs to deliver the key of the car to Kishan
			<lb />
			Sikand. If any parcel had been left on the staircase by the
			<lb />
			appellant, it had to be before Mohd.Shafi went upstairs.
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi has not deposed of having seen any parcel on the
			<lb />
			staircase. As per the prosecution the size of the parcel was 5&quot;
			<lb />
			x 3&quot; x 3&quot;, a size which could not have gone unnoticed by
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi. Further, Mohd.Shafi has categorically deposed
			<lb />
			that he knew the deceased prior thereto i.e. prior to
			<lb />
			25.9.1982. The only capacity in which Mohd.Shafi could have
			<lb />
			known the appellant would be that he was the ex-husband of
			<lb />
			Rani Sikand, who was living with his Master i.e. Kishan Sikand.
			<lb />
			Being an employee of Kishan Sikand, we find it strange that
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi did not voluntarily informed the police of having
			<lb />
			seen the appellant coming out of the house of the deceased.
			<lb />
			The manner in which the crime was committed would have
			<lb />
			raised the eyebrows of many and especially those who were
			<lb />
			associated with the deceased. As layman, their instincts would
			<lb />
			search for the suspect. Natural human conduct of Mohd.Shafi
			<lb />
			would be to suspect the involvement of the appellant and
			<lb />
			report the presence of the appellant at the house of the
			<lb />
			deceased on 25.9.1982. The conduct of Mohd.Shafi in not
			<lb />
			doing so in another factor which has weighed with us while
			<lb />
			considering the evidentiary worth of the testimony of
			<lb />
			Mohd.Shafi.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			97.
			<lb />
			Let us dovetail the testimony of Rani Chaudhary
			<lb />
			into the testimony of Mohd.Shafi. She claims to have seen a
			<lb />
			parcel at the second step at the ground floor. She disclaimed
			<lb />
			four statements attributable to her as recorded in her
			<lb />
			statement under Section 161 Cr.P.C. on 3.10.1982. The four
			<lb />
			statements are:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			A.
			<lb />
			The parcel found had an address written by hand
			<lb />
			thereon.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			B.
			<lb />
			When Krishan picked up the parcel I warned him
			<lb />
			lest it might be containing a bomb.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			C.
			<lb />
			After return from dinner I was anxious to know
			<lb />
			where said parcel had been kept by Krishan.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			D.
			<lb />
			I did not know where the parcel had been put by
			<lb />
			Krishan.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			98.
			<lb />
			The learned Trial Judge has accepted Rani
			<lb />
			Chaudhary&quot;s statement in Court that aforesaid four statements
			<lb />
			were not made by her.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			99.
			<lb />
			It has to be noted that after the initial investigation
			<lb />
			was conducted on 2.10.1982 by SI Vishnu Madan PW-69, the
			<lb />
			investigation on the following day i.e. 3.10.1982 was taken
			<lb />
			over by Insp.R.P.Kochar, In charge of the Crime Branch, who
			<lb />
			deposed that on 3.10.1982 he recorded the statement of Rani
			<lb />
			Chaudhary. We note that Insp.R.P.Kochar has not stated that
			<lb />
			he incorrectly recorded the statement of Rani Chaudhary.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			100.
			<lb />
			It was not the murder of an ordinary man. A
			<lb />
			socialite and a scion of a rich industrialist family was the
			<lb />
			victim. The family clout or otherwise the pressure on the
			<lb />
			police, to solve the crime is evidenced by the fact that the very
			<lb />
			next day of the crime i.e. on 3.10.1982 the investigation was
			<lb />
			handed over to the special cell i.e. the Crime Branch Cell
			<lb />
			dealing with homicidal death of Delhi Police. The pressure on
			<lb />
			Insp.R.P.Kochar to crack the case and his reputation being at
			<lb />
			stake would make him all the more cautious, ruling out the
			<lb />
			possibility of Insp.R.P.Kochar incorrectly recording the
			<lb />
			statement of Rani Chaudhary.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			101.
			<lb />
			There is obviously something more than meets the
			<lb />
			eye in the testimonies of PW-1, PW-3 and PW-7, who have
			<lb />
			obviously spoken to corroborate each other, but in a manner,
			<lb />
			and especially with reference to their statements under
			<lb />
			Section 161 Cr.P.C., which suggests that PW-3 has made
			<lb />
			improvements so that the presence of PW-7 is corroborated.
			<lb />
			PW-1 has disclaimed her statements which are uncomfortable
			<lb />
			to the prosecution as they demolish the theory of the parcel
			<lb />
			lying unattended for 7 days behind the wire mesh on the
			<lb />
			ground floor where the electricity meters were housed.
			<lb />
			Indeed, the four statements of Rani Chaudhary in her
			<lb />
			statement under Section 161 Cr.P.C. establish her anxiety qua
			<lb />
			the parcel. It shows her concern for the parcel even when
			<lb />
			everybody returned after the dinner. It is not possible that
			<lb />
			everybody forgot about the parcel for 7 days. That apart, Vijay
			<lb />
			Ram PW-5 has deposed that the letters meant for Mr.Kock and
			<lb />
			the deceased who were residing on the first floor of the house
			<lb />
			used to be left at the staircase by the postman and he used to
			<lb />
			distribute the same i.e. those addressed to Mr.Kock used to be
			<lb />
			handed over to him and those addressed to the deceased used
			<lb />
			to be handed over to him. This shows that the residents of the
			<lb />
			first floor had a habit to keep a look out for letters delivered by
			<lb />
			the postman, and addressed to them. Keeping in view said
			<lb />
			habit it becomes all the more improbable that a parcel of the
			<lb />
			size 5&quot; x 3&quot; x 3&quot; would remain unnoticed for 7 days.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			102.
			<lb />
			Kishan Lal PW-20 has been partially believed by the
			<lb />
			learned Trial Judge. His testimony that the appellant had
			<lb />
			played golf at the Delhi Golf Club from 1:36 PM to 5:22 PM on
			<lb />
			25.9.1982 has been accepted by the learned Trial Judge; and
			<lb />
			for good reason, inasmuch as the entry in the register Ex.PW-
			<lb />
			20/A so recorded. From the fact that 98 Sunder Nagar is at a
			<lb />
			distance of 100 meters from the Delhi Golf Club, the learned
			<lb />
			Trial Judge has opined that the testimony of PW-20 establishes
			<lb />
			the presence of the appellant near Sunder Nagar in the
			<lb />
			evening of 25.9.1982. The testimony of Kishan Lal that all
			<lb />
			those who play a full game of golf, covering 7½ kms, usually
			<lb />
			freshen up by taking a bath and some refreshment at the club
			<lb />
			and that the appellant did so has been disbelieved by the
			<lb />
			learned Trial Judge as also his further testimony that on
			<lb />
			25.9.1982 he had gone to the house of the appellant from the
			<lb />
			club; they had left at 7:30 PM and he had taken a bottle of rum
			<lb />
			from the appellant at New Friends Colony. The reasoning
			<lb />
			given by the learned Trial Judge is that the witness has
			<lb />
			introduced said facts during cross examination and that they
			<lb />
			do not find mentioned in his statement under Section 161
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			103.
			<lb />
			The scope of cross examination by an accused is
			<lb />
			fairly wide. In examination in chief, a witness answers only
			<lb />
			those questions which are put to him by the prosecutor. If the
			<lb />
			prosecutor chooses to selectively examine a witness, it does
			<lb />
			not mean that the accused has to restrict the cross
			<lb />
			examination within the bounds of the examination in chief.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			104.
			<lb />
			The test of an ordinary prudent person and how an
			<lb />
			ordinary prudent person carries out his affairs has been
			<lb />
			evolved by Courts to probablize the contemporaneous events,
			<lb />
			in respect whereof evidence is brought before a Court, through
			<lb />
			the testimony of witnesses. Indeed, the test of an ordinary
			<lb />
			prudent person is based on a rational and a logic, being that, a
			<lb />
			presumption arises that ordinary course of events are followed
			<lb />
			by ordinary human beings. Thus, that a man took breakfast in
			<lb />
			the morning would be accepted by the Court without any
			<lb />
			proof, inasmuch as ordinary human conduct is to take
			<lb />
			breakfast in the morning.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			105.
			<lb />
			The month of September, in the city of Delhi, is a
			<lb />
			hot month. Summers close in Delhi by mid October and
			<lb />
			autumn commences by that time of the month.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			documentary record i.e. Ex.PW-20/A shows that the appellant
			<lb />
			and his friends had played golf from 1:36 PM to 5:22 PM i.e. for
			<lb />
			nearly 4 hours. They walked a distance of 7½ kms. Without
			<lb />
			any further proof, on basis of ordinary human conduct, we find
			<lb />
			substance in the testimony of PW-20 that like all other
			<lb />
			members and as on all other days, after playing the game of
			<lb />
			golf, the appellant refreshed himself by taking a bath at the
			<lb />
			club followed by some refreshments.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			106.
			<lb />
			But, that would still leave scope for an argument
			<lb />
			that still, the possibility of the appellant being at 98 Sunder
			<lb />
			Nagar at around 7:45 PM cannot be ruled out. We concede
			<lb />
			this position.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			107.
			<lb />
			It takes us back to the testimony of PW-1, PW-3 and
			<lb />
			PW-7.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			108.
			<lb />
			For our reasons noted hereinabove, while
			<lb />
			discussing certain features of the testimony of said 3
			<lb />
			witnesses, and keeping in mind the principle of law that at a
			<lb />
			criminal trial, wherever two views are possible or a doubt
			<lb />
			arises, the benefit of the view favourable to the accused and
			<lb />
			benefit of doubt to the accused has to be given; it cannot be
			<lb />
			ignored that there is every possibility of Mohd.Shafi being
			<lb />
			introduced as a witness and through his mouth padding up the
			<lb />
			case of the prosecution cannot be ruled out. Further, finding it
			<lb />
			destructive of their theory of the parcel bomb being delivered
			<lb />
			on 25.9.1982, Rani disowning her statements recorded under
			<lb />
			Section 161 Cr.P.C. by the police cannot be ruled out. As
			<lb />
			regards PW-3, his improving upon his statement under Section
			<lb />
			161 Cr.P.C. to corroborate the presence of Mohd.Shafi is also
			<lb />
			suggestive of the attempt made by the prosecution to make
			<lb />
			the 3 witnesses speak in tandem.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			109.
			<lb />
			A question would arise, why would the prosecution
			<lb />
			do so? Indeed, this question would arise in all such cases
			<lb />
			where a Court finds that the evidence has been padded up.
			<lb />
			The answer to this question is difficult to be answered because
			<lb />
			there are hundreds and hundreds of reason why human beings
			<lb />
			tell lies. But, in the instant case, we may venture an answer
			<lb />
			which is reasonable and probable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			110.
			<lb />
			The accused had met Anil Sikand, the brother of the
			<lb />
			deceased, at Naldhera Golf Club in Shimla on the 27 th and 28 th
			<lb />
			of September, 1982. Anil Sikand would have told said fact to
			<lb />
			Rani Chaudhary and even the police personnel. The appellant
			<lb />
			had a booking for a log hut at the Golf Club in Shimla till the
			<lb />
			29 th September, 1982. Nobody knew his whereabouts after
			<lb />
			30 th September, 1982, the day he would have left the Golf Club
			<lb />
			at Shimla by afternoon. (Check out time is 12:00 noon the day
			<lb />
			after the night of the booking). It would have been fatal for
			<lb />
			the prosecution to have floated a theory that the parcel bomb
			<lb />
			was delivered by the appellant on 2 nd October, 1982, for if he
			<lb />
			was not in Delhi on said day, the plea of alibi would possibly
			<lb />
			have been established with lethal precision.
			<lb />
			Thus, the
			<lb />
			prosecution, possibly centering on 25.9.1982 as the relevant
			<lb />
			date is explainable because on said date, evidenced by Ex.PW-
			<lb />
			20/A, there was unimpeachable evidence to show the
			<lb />
			appellant&quot;s presence in Delhi. If we now view Rani&quot;s statement
			<lb />
			under Section 161 Cr.P.C., it makes perfect sense for her to
			<lb />
			have told the police that the parcel was suspected by her to be
			<lb />
			containing a bomb and it was at her insistence that the
			<lb />
			deceased left the parcel at the sill behind the wire mesh
			<lb />
			housing the electricity meters. But unfortunately for her, the
			<lb />
			said statement, though in harmony with her statement,
			<lb />
			demolishes the case of the prosecution that the parcel
			<lb />
			remained unattended as an innocent object. Her statement
			<lb />
			under Section 161 Cr.P.C. would be in conformity with human
			<lb />
			conduct. If a man, going out for dinner, finds a parcel of
			<lb />
			dimension 5&quot; x 3&quot; x 3&quot;, the normal conduct would be to pick
			<lb />
			up the parcel and either go back to the living apartment and
			<lb />
			keep it inside or carry it along and place it in the car in which
			<lb />
			the onward movement of the man and his friends took place,
			<lb />
			unless stopped by somebody from doing so.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			111.
			<lb />
			It is not an insignificant fact that, as deposed to by
			<lb />
			Sanjay Sikand PW-8, the son of the deceased, a birthday party
			<lb />
			of Veeraj Sikand, the nephew of the deceased, was being held
			<lb />
			at the ground floor on 2.10.1982. At the party friends and
			<lb />
			guests would be invited. So is the presumption. There is a
			<lb />
			greater likelihood of the parcel in question being transported
			<lb />
			to the premises on said date, for the reason, many a times,
			<lb />
			those, who for some reason or the other cannot attend a
			<lb />
			birthday party, do send a present through a carrier. The party
			<lb />
			was a perfect occasion for somebody to sneak in the parcel.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			112.
			<lb />
			The testimony of PW-20 and the register Ex.PW-
			<lb />
			20/A are good evidence to prove that from 1:36 PM to 5:22 PM
			<lb />
			on 25.9.1982, the appellant was playing golf with his friends at
			<lb />
			the Delhi Golf Club. Is this the normal activity of a human
			<lb />
			being who is carrying a bomb with him with a mission to plant
			<lb />
			the bomb at a place where the victim is targeted? A scheming
			<lb />
			and a plotting mind i.e. an evil mind would be looking for an
			<lb />
			opportunity to give effect to the ill conceived desire. Even
			<lb />
			hardened criminals would be strategizing and planning the
			<lb />
			execution of their intent at a point of time, immediately
			<lb />
			preceding the act committed by the body. The conduct of the
			<lb />
			appellant in being merry with his friends in playing a game of
			<lb />
			golf for nearly 4 hours on 25.9.1982 is an indication that the
			<lb />
			mind was neither scheming, nor plotting, nor designing. No
			<lb />
			strategies were being plotted in the mind. In the midst of
			<lb />
			nature, at the golf course, the mind was free of the worldly
			<lb />
			affairs except the pleasure of the game of golf.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			113.
			<lb />
			Regretfully, the learned Trial Judge has made no
			<lb />
			attempt to give a 360˚ look to the evidence of the relevant
			<lb />
			witnesses who have deposed facts pertaining to the delivery of
			<lb />
			the parcel bomb by the appellant on 25.9.1982. For our
			<lb />
			reasons noted hereinabove, we are of the opinion that if not
			<lb />
			more, the appellant is entitled to a benefit of doubt, for if not
			<lb />
			wholly untrustworthy, the testimony of the witnesses on said
			<lb />
			aspect is not free from doubt and is not of a kind which
			<lb />
			inspires full confidence. We thus hold that the conclusion
			<lb />
			arrived at by the learned Trial Judge that the evidence
			<lb />
			conclusively establishes that the appellant had left the parcel
			<lb />
			containing the bomb on 25.9.1982 is not justified in the facts
			<lb />
			and circumstances of the instant case. We may add that we
			<lb />
			are ignoring the testimony of the defence witnesses who have
			<lb />
			deposed that the appellant had attended a party at 4, Friends
			<lb />
			Colony at 9:00 PM and prior thereto was in his house at around
			<lb />
			8:00 PM.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			114.
			<lb />
			We reach the last and the most crucial stage of the
			<lb />
			evidence. The evidence pertaining to Ex.PW-62/O i.e. the
			<lb />
			recreated slips, in a damaged condition, painstakingly pasted
			<lb />
			together from the remnants of the explosion by G.R.Prasad
			<lb />
			PW-62. The same, as recreated, are as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Slip 1
			<lb />
			Slip 2
			<lb />
			PA …………..OST
			<lb />
			Shiri Krishan ……..
			<lb />
			98, Sunde……….agar
			<lb />
			From:
			<lb />
			Delhi Met……….e,
			<lb />
			290, Hauz Qu….i
			<lb />
			Delhi ….0006
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			115.
			<lb />
			PW-75 has deposed that his report Ex.PW-75/C is
			<lb />
			correct and that as per him the typewriter used for typing the
			<lb />
			sample typescript S-7 is the typewriter on which Ex.PW-62/O
			<lb />
			has been got typed. On the contrary DW-7 Darshan Dayal
			<lb />
			Goel has opined that in view of the inadequacy of the sample
			<lb />
			to be tested, no conclusive opinion can be given. He has
			<lb />
			referred to various dissimilarities noted by him.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			116.
			<lb />
			Unfortunately for us, the learned Trial Judge has
			<lb />
			just not discussed the law on the subject pertaining to the
			<lb />
			appreciation of evidence of a witness who opines on a subject
			<lb />
			of science. The learned Trial Judge has not noted the intrinsic
			<lb />
			merits and demerits of the report of the two experts. In a
			<lb />
			cryptic manner, the learned Trial Judge has returned a finding:
			<lb />
			Since there were contradictory reports about similarities and
			<lb />
			dis-similarities in the typed address, I have perused, checked
			<lb />
			and compared the original and photocopy of the typed address
			<lb />
			with the respective reports. I find, reasons given by PW-75
			<lb />
			Shri S.K.Gupta are more sound than reasons given by DW-7
			<lb />
			Shri Darshan Dayal Goel, a private expert who otherwise is an
			<lb />
			interested witness. Dis-similarities could also be on account of
			<lb />
			natural wear and tear and on account of way and manner of
			<lb />
			typing.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			117.
			<lb />
			At the outset, we see no reason for the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Judge to record a perfunctory finding that DW-7, a private
			<lb />
			expert is an interested witness. What is the interest of DW-7,
			<lb />
			has not been brought out. We have noted hereinabove in para
			<lb />
			85 that defence witnesses are entitled to the same respect
			<lb />
			and consideration as the witnesses of the prosecution and that
			<lb />
			there is no presumption that the defence witnesses tell lies.
			<lb />
			The credibility of every witness and the evidentiary worth of
			<lb />
			the testimony of a witness has to be evaluated on the
			<lb />
			recognized principles of evaluation of evidence, be it the
			<lb />
			witnesses of the prosecution or the defence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			118.
			<lb />
			Thus, we carry out the task of evaluating the
			<lb />
			creditworthiness of the testimony of PW-75 and DW-7. We
			<lb />
			shall be critically looking at the testimony of PW-75, but before
			<lb />
			that, we need to note the law on the subject, pertaining to the
			<lb />
			testimony of a person who claims to be an expert on an issue
			<lb />
			of scientific or technical knowledge.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			119.
			<lb />
			In Frye vs. United States 54 App.D.C. 46 (1923) the
			<lb />
			Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia described the
			<lb />
			device concerning the admissibility of evidence of an expert,
			<lb />
			on a subject of science, technology or special knowledge, in
			<lb />
			the following words:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Just when a scientific principle or discovery crosses
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			line
			<lb />
			between
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			experimental
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			demonstrable stages is difficult to define.
			<lb />
			Somewhere in this twilight zone the evidential force
			<lb />
			of the principle must be recognized, and while
			<lb />
			courts will go a long way in admitting expert
			<lb />
			testimony deduced from a well-recognized scientific
			<lb />
			principle or discovery, the thing from which the
			<lb />
			deduction is made must be sufficiently established
			<lb />
			to have gained general acceptance in the particular
			<lb />
			field in which it belongs.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			120.
			<lb />
			Since its formulation, in the year 1923, the
			<lb />
			&quot;general acceptance&quot; test (in the legal field known as the
			<lb />
			Frye&quot;s test) has been much debated and the scholarship
			<lb />
			on its scope and application is legion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			121.
			<lb />
			But various known texts, on the issue of
			<lb />
			admissibility of expert evidence, such as &quot;P. Gianelli &amp; E.
			<lb />
			Imwinkelried: SCIENTIFIC EVIDENCE&quot;; &quot;J.Weinstein &amp; M.
			<lb />
			Berger : WEINSTEIN&quot;s EVIDENCE&quot; and &quot;Scientific Evidence
			<lb />
			by Lacey&quot; agree, that at a trial, while admitting expert
			<lb />
			evidence on a matter of science, technology or
			<lb />
			specialized knowledge, it has to be ensured that the
			<lb />
			testimony of the expert is not only relevant but
			<lb />
			additionally is also reliable. (Underline emphasized).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			122.
			<lb />
			Since evidentiary reliability is based on
			<lb />
			scientific validity, the standard under which the test of
			<lb />
			reliability of the evidence is: Whether the principles on
			<lb />
			which the testimony is based has general acceptance in
			<lb />
			the field to which it (the opinion of the expert) belongs
			<lb />
			and that the expert has based his opinion keeping into
			<lb />
			account the said principles.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			123.
			<lb />
			Thus, an expert opinion based on a methodology,
			<lb />
			which diverges significantly from the procedures accepted by
			<lb />
			recognized authorities in the field would not be evidentially
			<lb />
			reliable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			124.
			<lb />
			Pertaining to evidentiary reliability of an expert
			<lb />
			opinion, the Frye&quot;s test has three fundamental components:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a) It has to be satisfactorily shown that the expert
			<lb />
			evidence/opinion relates to a scientific, technical or other
			<lb />
			specialized knowledge and that the theory or technique
			<lb />
			applicable to the science, technology or specialized field is
			<lb />
			based on a methodology, hypothesis or tests which has/have
			<lb />
			been subjected to peer review and publication i.e. there exists
			<lb />
			standards controlling the techniques&quot; operation and the same
			<lb />
			are generally accepted and additionally that it has been
			<lb />
			accepted that the relationship of the technique to methods has
			<lb />
			been established to be reliable keeping into account known or
			<lb />
			potential rate of error.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) The author of the opinion qualifies to be called an expert;
			<lb />
			by knowledge, skill, experience, training or education. It has
			<lb />
			to be kept in mind that the level of expertise may not affect
			<lb />
			the admissibility of evidence of the expert but certainly affects
			<lb />
			the weight to be accorded to the opinion of the expert.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) The proffered experts&quot; testimony must reveal that the
			<lb />
			methodology, hypothesis or techniques applicable and the
			<lb />
			theory behind the principles applicable have been applied by
			<lb />
			the expert and that the expert is mindful of the known or
			<lb />
			potential rate of error in the derivative of the technique or
			<lb />
			methodology to the subject thereof.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			125.
			<lb />
			Indeed, an expert evidence can be both powerful
			<lb />
			and at the same time quite misleading because of the difficulty
			<lb />
			in evaluating it.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			126.
			<lb />
			Though, in many countries, by way of legislative
			<lb />
			enactments, rules have been enacted governing the
			<lb />
			admissibility and relevance of expert testimony, but the basic
			<lb />
			principles laid down in Frye&quot;s test continue to apply because of
			<lb />
			the inherent strength of logic in the principles enunciated in
			<lb />
			Frye&quot;s test.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			127.
			<lb />
			How the Frye&quot;s test continues to be preserved in
			<lb />
			such jurisdictions where legislative enactments exist codifying
			<lb />
			the rules on the subject can best be illustrated with reference
			<lb />
			to the decision of the US Supreme Court in the decision
			<lb />
			reported as William Dallbert vs Merrell Dow Pharmaceuticals
			<lb />
			Inc. (1993) 123 L. Ed. 2d 469. The Federal Rules of Evidence
			<lb />
			were the subject matter of consideration in said decision on
			<lb />
			the issue of admissibility and relevance of expert testimony on
			<lb />
			matters of science, technology and specialized knowledge.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			128.
			<lb />
			Rule 702 of the Federal Rules of Evidence,
			<lb />
			governing expert testimony, reads as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;If scientific, technical, or other specialized
			<lb />
			knowledge will assist the trier of fact to understand
			<lb />
			the evidence or to determine a fact in issue, a
			<lb />
			witness qualified as an expert by knowledge, skill,
			<lb />
			experience, training, or education, may testify
			<lb />
			thereto in the form of an opinion or otherwise.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			129.
			<lb />
			Noting that the words &quot;general acceptance in the
			<lb />
			particular field in which it belongs&quot;, an integral part of Frye&quot;s
			<lb />
			test, do not find mention, express or implied, in the rule, the
			<lb />
			US Supreme Court opined that the language of Rule 702
			<lb />
			places no restriction of general acceptance in the field to
			<lb />
			which the opinion of the expert belongs and therefore all
			<lb />
			scientific testimony or evidence is admissible. But, the Court
			<lb />
			immediately cautioned that issue of reliability of scientific
			<lb />
			testimony has to be duly considered. To quote from the
			<lb />
			decision:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;The primary locus of this obligation is Rule 702,
			<lb />
			which clearly contemplates some degree of
			<lb />
			regulation of the subjects and the theories about
			<lb />
			which an expert may testify. &quot;If scientific, technical
			<lb />
			or other specialized knowledge will assist the trier
			<lb />
			of facts to understand the evidence or to determine
			<lb />
			a fact in issue&quot; an expert &quot;may testify thereto.&quot; The
			<lb />
			subject of an expert&quot;s testimony must be scientific
			<lb />
			knowledge.
			<lb />
			The adjective &quot;scientific&quot; implies a
			<lb />
			grounding in the methods and procedures of
			<lb />
			science. Similarly the word &quot;knowledge&quot; connotes
			<lb />
			more than subjective belief or unsupported
			<lb />
			speculation.
			<lb />
			The term applies to any body of
			<lb />
			known facts or to any body of ideas inferred from
			<lb />
			such facts or accepted as truths on good grounds.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			………….. In order to qualify as &quot;scientific
			<lb />
			knowledge&quot;, an inference or assertation must be
			<lb />
			derived by the scientific method.
			<lb />
			Proposed
			<lb />
			testimony must be supported by appropriate
			<lb />
			validation -i.e., &quot;good grounds&quot; based on what is
			<lb />
			known. In short, the requirement that an expert&quot;s
			<lb />
			testimony pertaining to scientific knowledge
			<lb />
			establishes a standard of evidentiary reliability.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			130.
			<lb />
			With reference to the words &quot;will assist the trier of
			<lb />
			fact to understand the evidence or to determine a fact in
			<lb />
			issue&quot;, the words which find mention in Rule 702, it was
			<lb />
			opined:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;This entails a preliminary assessment of whether
			<lb />
			the reasoning or methodology underlining the
			<lb />
			testimony is scientifically valid and of whether that
			<lb />
			reasoning or methodology properly can be applied
			<lb />
			to the facts in issue. …………………… Ordinarily, a
			<lb />
			key question to be answered in determining
			<lb />
			whether a theory or technique is scientific
			<lb />
			knowledge that will assist the trier of fact will be
			<lb />
			whether it can be tested. ……. Another pertinent
			<lb />
			consideration is whether the theory or technique
			<lb />
			has been subjected to peer review and publication.
			<lb />
			……. The fact of publication (or lack thereof) in a
			<lb />
			peer-reviewed journal thus will be a relevant,
			<lb />
			though not dispositive, consideration in assessing
			<lb />
			the scientific validity of a particular technique or
			<lb />
			methodology on which an opinion is premised.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			131.
			<lb />
			It is apparent to every logical mind that the key to
			<lb />
			determine whether a theory or technique is scientific
			<lb />
			knowledge which will assist the trier of fact is whether the
			<lb />
			theory or technique can be and has been tested. Thus, while
			<lb />
			summarizing the impact of the legislation on Frye&quot;s test, the
			<lb />
			Court concluded as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;To summarize: &quot;general acceptance&quot; is not a
			<lb />
			necessary precondition to the admissibility of
			<lb />
			scientific evidence under the Federal Rules of
			<lb />
			Evidence, but the Rules of Evidence do assign to
			<lb />
			the Trial Judge the task of ensuring that an experts&quot;
			<lb />
			testimony both rests on a reliable foundation and is
			<lb />
			relevant to the task at hand. Pertinent evidence
			<lb />
			based on scientifically valid principles will satisfy
			<lb />
			those demands.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			132.
			<lb />
			Since trier of a fact i.e. a Judge or a Jury is not
			<lb />
			expected to be an expert, the relevance of publication in a
			<lb />
			peer-reviewed journal was highlighted by the US Supreme
			<lb />
			Court. Not only that, the US Supreme Court cautioned that
			<lb />
			with reference to standard text, known rate of errors must be
			<lb />
			kept in mind while deciding the evidentiary value of an expert
			<lb />
			opinion. To quote:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Additionally, in the case of a particular scientific
			<lb />
			technique, the court ordinarily should consider the
			<lb />
			known or potential rate of error, see, e.g., United
			<lb />
			States v. Smith, 869 F2d 348, 353-354 (CA7 1989)
			<lb />
			(surveying
			<lb />
			studies
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			error
			<lb />
			rate
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			spectrographic voice identification technique), and
			<lb />
			the existence and maintenance of standards
			<lb />
			controlling the technique&quot;s operation. See United
			<lb />
			States v. Williams, 583 F2d 1194, 1198 (CA2 1978)
			<lb />
			(noting
			<lb />
			professional
			<lb />
			organization&quot;s
			<lb />
			standard
			<lb />
			governing spectrographic analysis), cert denied,
			<lb />
			439 US 1117, 59 L Ed 2d 77, 99 S Ct 1025 (1979).&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			133.
			<lb />
			The science relating to typescripts is of recent
			<lb />
			origin. In the year 1952, in the decision reported as AIR 1952
			<lb />
			SC 343 Hanumant vs. State of MP the Supreme Court held
			<lb />
			that an opinion of an expert on a typescript was inadmissible
			<lb />
			in evidence. But, with the advancement of technology, it
			<lb />
			became acceptable that certain parameters could be
			<lb />
			identified, if not absolute, on a probability to identify features
			<lb />
			of a typing machine. The reason is that typewriters are
			<lb />
			manufactured in industrialized countries by many makers who
			<lb />
			have made individual approaches to the problem of producing
			<lb />
			a reliable and effective machine. Despite its simplicity of
			<lb />
			operation, a typewriter is a fairly complicated machine having
			<lb />
			a complicated mechanism of operation, for it is assembled
			<lb />
			from approximately two thousand parts which require
			<lb />
			something like twenty thousand different operations to
			<lb />
			produce the result i.e. the typescript. Not only are typewriters
			<lb />
			assembled from many components, but their action is the
			<lb />
			resultant of a number of interlocking adjustments which have
			<lb />
			to be made before the machine can be taken into service.
			<lb />
			Further, when a typist is typing at a rate of sixty words a
			<lb />
			minute, he or she motivates about two hundred working parts
			<lb />
			a second, so that the creation of a line of transcript is the end
			<lb />
			product of many motions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			134.
			<lb />
			Once a machine is put into use, it suffers wear and
			<lb />
			tear which has an increasing effect on the work it produces.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			135.
			<lb />
			Those who had a concern with a typewriter started
			<lb />
			realizing that if typescripts from machines of different
			<lb />
			manufacturers is compared, certain differences in the design
			<lb />
			of the typeface will be apparent, because few manufacturers
			<lb />
			have identical views on what is the most pleasing and
			<lb />
			serviceable design for type characters.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			136.
			<lb />
			This means that in most cases it is possible to
			<lb />
			identify the make of the machine for a particular specimen of
			<lb />
			typescript by taking into consideration the design of the type.
			<lb />
			Thus, the science pertaining to a typescript has a high level of
			<lb />
			accuracy if it has to be determined as to which particular
			<lb />
			brand of typewriter has been used to type the script. For this,
			<lb />
			the experts in the field, have, as noted by Wilson R. Harrison in
			<lb />
			the book &quot;Suspect Documents: Their Scientific Examination&quot;,
			<lb />
			created a databank of different manufacturers of typewriters
			<lb />
			as also the characteristics of the design of the letters
			<lb />
			introduced by them over the years.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			137.
			<lb />
			Wilson R. Harrison has a post-graduate degree as
			<lb />
			also a master&quot;s degree in Forensic Sciences and for twenty
			<lb />
			four years served with Forensic Science Laboratories before
			<lb />
			retiring as the Director, Home Office, Forensic Science
			<lb />
			Laboratory, Llanishen Cardiff. Since January 1938 he served
			<lb />
			as the Director of the Laboratory till he wrote the book
			<lb />
			&quot;Suspected Documents&quot; in the year 1958. He is considered to
			<lb />
			be an authority on suspect documents including typescripts.
			<lb />
			Pertaining to the ease with which the science of typescript can
			<lb />
			be used to identify the particular make of a machine, at page
			<lb />
			242 of the book (Fourth Indian Reprint 2008), the learned
			<lb />
			Author opines:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;If
			<lb />
			typescript
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			machines
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			different
			<lb />
			manufacturers is compared, certain differences in
			<lb />
			the design of the typefaces will be apparent,
			<lb />
			because few manufacturers have identical views on
			<lb />
			what is the most pleasing and serviceable design
			<lb />
			for type-written characters. This means that in
			<lb />
			some cases, at least, it will be possible to identify
			<lb />
			the make of the machine used for a particular
			<lb />
			specimen of typescript by taking into consideration
			<lb />
			the design of the type.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			138.
			<lb />
			As noted above, once put to use, a typing machine
			<lb />
			suffers wear and tear which has an increasing effect on the
			<lb />
			work it produces. The effect has been penned by the learned
			<lb />
			Author, Wilson R. Harrison, at pages 245, 246 and 247 as
			<lb />
			under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;If an examination is carried out on specimens of
			<lb />
			typescript from well-worn machines, it will be
			<lb />
			observed that in some of the specimens every
			<lb />
			example of certain letters or figures will be found to
			<lb />
			be defective. Portions of the character will be found
			<lb />
			to be missing altogether, or there will be obvious
			<lb />
			distortion of the outline. ……. Typescript derived
			<lb />
			from a machine in poor condition will be found to
			<lb />
			print very unevenly, the depth of the impression
			<lb />
			being variable over the surface of the character.
			<lb />
			This defect will be the more apparent when the
			<lb />
			touch has been light and the ribbon well used.
			<lb />
			Some characters will be found to be more heavily
			<lb />
			imprinted at the bottom, the top being hardly
			<lb />
			visible, whilst with others the reverse is the case.
			<lb />
			…….. When the line of type is inspected as a whole,
			<lb />
			it will become apparent that not all of the
			<lb />
			imperfections in the typescript are associated with
			<lb />
			the manner in which the outlines of the character
			<lb />
			are reproduced. One of the most obvious defects is
			<lb />
			the occurrence of errors in the lateral spacing of the
			<lb />
			typescript along the line. These &quot;errors in horizontal
			<lb />
			alignment,&quot; as they are termed, are mostly
			<lb />
			noticeable because any crowding of the characters
			<lb />
			is associated with neighbouring gaps which throw
			<lb />
			the overcrowding into relief.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			139.
			<lb />
			But, the learned Author hastens to caution at page
			<lb />
			248 as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Finally, it must not be assumed that all variation in
			<lb />
			alignment characteristics is due to wear and loose
			<lb />
			bearings, for lack of rhythm on the part of the typist
			<lb />
			may be responsible, more especially for variation in
			<lb />
			horizontal alignment characteristics.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			140.
			<lb />
			Thus, it is apparent that to be treated as
			<lb />
			characteristic of a typewriter, alignment variations require a
			<lb />
			careful scrutiny to check whether the same are a result of lack
			<lb />
			of rhythm on the part of the typist or attributable as a
			<lb />
			characteristic to the machine. To put it differently, a clever
			<lb />
			person can prepare a sample typescript by cleverly timing the
			<lb />
			rhythm so as to recreate alignment variations and give an
			<lb />
			appearance that the same are characteristic of a typewriter.
			<lb />
			Thus, in relation to variations in alignment, expert opinion
			<lb />
			must show that the expert has kept in mind, whether the
			<lb />
			alignment variation is attributable to the machine or to the
			<lb />
			typist.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			141.
			<lb />
			Analyzing the determination of characteristics of
			<lb />
			the letters of a typewriter, to a further scrutiny, at page 250,
			<lb />
			the learned Author opines that the characteristics (noted in
			<lb />
			para 20 above) have to be further analyzed in great detail so
			<lb />
			that some estimation may be made of their value. While so
			<lb />
			doing, the learned author has prefaced the further discussion
			<lb />
			by drawing the attention to five limitations in the process of
			<lb />
			further analysis, one of them being; to quote (the last line of
			<lb />
			the third para at page 251):-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;This limitation also applies when but a small
			<lb />
			amount of transcript is in question.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			142.
			<lb />
			The reason for the limitation afore-noted is given by
			<lb />
			the learned author at page 261; to quote:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;When a typeface is imperfect, a corresponding
			<lb />
			defect must occur in every printed character made
			<lb />
			while it is in this condition. As already pointed out,
			<lb />
			defects in the outline of the printed character are
			<lb />
			occasioned by factors other than faulty typeface.
			<lb />
			Many of these factors, such as faulty ribbon, are
			<lb />
			temporary, whilst others, such as those due to a
			<lb />
			pitted platened, are sporadic in their influence on
			<lb />
			the outline of the printed characters. The test of
			<lb />
			consistency must be applied before any defect in
			<lb />
			outline can be attributed to a faulty typeface.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			…….. The test of consistency cannot be applied
			<lb />
			when only a limited amount of transcript is in
			<lb />
			question, for few, if any, other specimens of the
			<lb />
			characters with defective outlines may be available
			<lb />
			for comparison.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			143.
			<lb />
			As per the learned Author (see page 256),
			<lb />
			characters such as &quot;o&quot;, &quot;O&quot;, &quot;e&quot; and &quot;u&quot; are of little diagnostic
			<lb />
			value and the search must begin with letters such as &quot;a&quot;, &quot;g&quot;, &quot;t&quot;
			<lb />
			and &quot;r&quot; which are chosen because of the wide variation in
			<lb />
			design which is encountered in different makes of machines
			<lb />
			pertaining to said letters.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			144.
			<lb />
			It is apparent even to a layman who has seen a
			<lb />
			typewriter in operation, if the typeface is struck at an angle,
			<lb />
			distortion of the outline of letters is the fallout. The learned
			<lb />
			Author says (at page 258):-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Flattening of the outline on a typeface is generally
			<lb />
			caused by a blow which falls normally on to its
			<lb />
			surface; if the typeface is struck at an angle,
			<lb />
			distortion of the outline rather than flattening is
			<lb />
			likely to be the consequence. The portions of the
			<lb />
			typeface liable to become damaged in this way are
			<lb />
			the serifs, which may be bent, and the curved
			<lb />
			outlines of the ovals of such letters as &quot;g&quot;, &quot;a&quot; and
			<lb />
			&quot;d&quot; become unsymmetrical.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			145.
			<lb />
			But, the learned Author immediately cautions at
			<lb />
			page 258 itself:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;When a serif is seen to be either bent, or twisted,
			<lb />
			there can be no doubt that the typeface is faulty,
			<lb />
			but when the serif is not reproduced in the printed
			<lb />
			character, it cannot likely be assumed that this is
			<lb />
			due to the outline of the typeface being defective.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			146.
			<lb />
			Thus, it is apparent that mere absence of a serif i.e.
			<lb />
			it not being reproduced in the printed character is no ground
			<lb />
			by itself to assume the same to be a distinctive characteristic
			<lb />
			of the machine. As per the learned author, at page 259:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;This means that it is unsafe to regard a typeface
			<lb />
			as being characterized by a defective serif, unless
			<lb />
			the stroke from which the serif is missing is seen to
			<lb />
			have been deeply printed without any trace of the
			<lb />
			serif being apparent. Missing serifs are far more
			<lb />
			common than other defects such as gaps in the
			<lb />
			outline, and consequently are of less evidentiary
			<lb />
			value in characterizing the work of a typewriter.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			147.
			<lb />
			Thus, apart from the little diagnostic value of the
			<lb />
			letters &quot;o&quot;, &quot;O&quot;, &quot;e&quot; and &quot;u&quot;, missing serifs have little evidentiary
			<lb />
			value while determining the peculiar characteristics of a
			<lb />
			typewriter.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			148.
			<lb />
			Since quality of a ribbon, the force with which a
			<lb />
			typist punches the keys of a typewriter and the quality of
			<lb />
			paper; all affect the quality of the print, the learned author
			<lb />
			opines that three copies of the specimen text should be
			<lb />
			prepared with a light, medium and a heavy touch respectively
			<lb />
			and at least one specimen should be prepared on same or
			<lb />
			similar paper. Otherwise, the imperfect impressions which
			<lb />
			occur due to the quality of the paper as also imperfect
			<lb />
			impressions which occur due to the touch on the key may be
			<lb />
			attributed to the machine.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			149.
			<lb />
			The learned author further notes that lateral,
			<lb />
			vertical and slope misalignments are often noted in
			<lb />
			typescripts. A lateral misalignment means that two letters are
			<lb />
			squeezed with a resultant and a noticeable gap between the
			<lb />
			said two letters and the next. Vertical misalignment means
			<lb />
			that letters are printed above or below the line of type. Slope
			<lb />
			misalignment means that letters are printed with a slant i.e.
			<lb />
			appear with a slope.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			150.
			<lb />
			But, the learned Author cautions that such defects
			<lb />
			have to be appreciated in light of the possible reasons thereof,
			<lb />
			all of which do not necessarily relate to the machine and
			<lb />
			hence to its identity.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			151.
			<lb />
			Non-rhythmic operation of a machine is a likely
			<lb />
			cause of errors in horizontal alignment. At page 263, the
			<lb />
			learned author opines:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Some authorities go so far as to declare that errors
			<lb />
			in horizontal alignment are practically useless for
			<lb />
			identifying the work of a machine, but in the
			<lb />
			experience of the author this is not the case, and to
			<lb />
			neglect the presence of any consistent errors in this
			<lb />
			regard is to disregard evidence which may prove of
			<lb />
			the greatest value, especially when small amounts
			<lb />
			of typescripts are in question.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			152.
			<lb />
			It is apparent that pertaining to errors in horizontal
			<lb />
			alignment, the experts are not in agreement on their
			<lb />
			evidentiary worth. The learned author, based on experience,
			<lb />
			feels to the contrary. We may hasten to add that the learned
			<lb />
			author has not given any reasons for the note of disagreement
			<lb />
			and has preferred to rest his opinion on his experience.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			153.
			<lb />
			As per the learned author, errors in vertical
			<lb />
			alignment pertaining to capital letters have not to be put at
			<lb />
			par with errors in vertical alignment pertaining to small letters.
			<lb />
			As per the learned author vertical misalignments pertaining to
			<lb />
			capital letters are usually occasioned due to the typist failing
			<lb />
			to sufficiently depress the shift key, required to be punched, to
			<lb />
			print the capital letters or due to the typist striking the key of
			<lb />
			the next letter to be printed before the carriage on the type
			<lb />
			basket has had time to resume its normal position. Hence,
			<lb />
			vertical misalignments or error in vertical alignment pertaining
			<lb />
			to capital letters has minimal evidentiary value.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			154.
			<lb />
			Discussing error in slope alignment, the learned
			<lb />
			Author, at page 265, cautions:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;This error in alignment must not be confused with
			<lb />
			the deliberate slope of a degree or so, given to such
			<lb />
			characters as &quot;t&quot; and &quot;f&quot; to correct the optical illusion
			<lb />
			which would make these characters appear to slope
			<lb />
			if they were adjusted to be perfectly upright.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			155.
			<lb />
			Pertaining to errors in slope alignment as being
			<lb />
			distinctive of a characteristic, explaining the cause thereof i.e.
			<lb />
			the reason behind, the learned Author writes:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Obvious and consistent defects in slope are caused
			<lb />
			by the twisting of the type bars, which causes them
			<lb />
			to depart from their correct alignment and
			<lb />
			consequently to print a character with an incorrect
			<lb />
			slope. Slope misalignment due to this defect is
			<lb />
			outside the control of the typist, so that constant
			<lb />
			errors of this description enable the work of the
			<lb />
			machine to be characterized.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			156.
			<lb />
			It is thus apparent that there is unanimity amongst
			<lb />
			the authors that subject to certain letters which are given a
			<lb />
			deliberate slope such as &quot;t&quot; and &quot;f&quot; (to correct the optical
			<lb />
			illusion) a consistent defect in slope alignment can be
			<lb />
			attributed as a peculiar characteristic of a machine. Vertical
			<lb />
			misalignments of capital letters are of not much use while
			<lb />
			attributing a peculiar characteristic to a machine. Pertaining
			<lb />
			to horizontal misalignments, there is no unanimity of opinion
			<lb />
			amongst the various authors as to their evidentiary value.
			<lb />
			But, based on his experience the learned author feels that
			<lb />
			horizontal misalignments have good evidentiary value and
			<lb />
			need to be taken into account especially when a limited
			<lb />
			quantity of typescript is available.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			157.
			<lb />
			At pages 265 to 267, the learned author discusses
			<lb />
			faults in typescripts pertaining to double impressions, irregular
			<lb />
			margins, letter and line spacing.
			<lb />
			Pertaining to double
			<lb />
			impressions, the learned author opines that the fault is
			<lb />
			comparatively rare and the presence of a double impression is
			<lb />
			an identifying feature of some importance. The theory behind
			<lb />
			a double impression is that if a key is sharply struck in a
			<lb />
			normal manner, the momentum of the heavy typeface will
			<lb />
			cause the thin steel type-bar to bend when its motion is
			<lb />
			arrested, so that the typeface follows on to deliver a single
			<lb />
			sharp blow to the ribbon which has been thrust between it and
			<lb />
			the paper. If a machine is defective, the vibration of the type
			<lb />
			bar would result in a second fainter blow being struck. Since
			<lb />
			the extremes of motion of the carriage of a typewriter are
			<lb />
			controlled by margin stops which get thrown out of action by
			<lb />
			pressure on the appropriate release keys, sometimes carriages
			<lb />
			tend to rebound from the stop which controls the left hand
			<lb />
			margin. When the motion of the carriage is stopped by the
			<lb />
			right hand stop, the keys are locked to prevent further
			<lb />
			characters being printed. With a defective machine this may
			<lb />
			not happen, so that the lines of type will exhibit a number of
			<lb />
			superimposed letters at the extreme right. This betrays the
			<lb />
			typewriter by revealing its identity. Letter and line spacing, as
			<lb />
			per the learned author are the result of the numbers of the
			<lb />
			letters to an inch. For example, in the most popular style
			<lb />
			known as pica, ten letters get printed in one inch space. In the
			<lb />
			style known as elite, twelve letters get printed in an inch.
			<lb />
			Letter spacing is governed by the escapement, which in turn
			<lb />
			governs the movement of the carriage. When the escapement
			<lb />
			is faulty, crowding and irregularity of the type becomes
			<lb />
			evident. These are also characteristics attributable to a worn
			<lb />
			out machine and hence can identify and relate a particular
			<lb />
			print to a machine.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			158.
			<lb />
			The concluding remarks by the learned author are
			<lb />
			important. They summarize the pitfalls i.e. inherent limitation
			<lb />
			of the science of typescript. At page 275 the learned author
			<lb />
			writes:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;When the comparison of two specimens of
			<lb />
			typescript has been completed, the examiner must
			<lb />
			sum up the evidence in order to form his conclusion
			<lb />
			as to whether both were typed on the same
			<lb />
			machine or not.
			<lb />
			His task is almost invariably
			<lb />
			complicated by the fact that typewriters are subject
			<lb />
			to variation; it is extremely unlikely, that any two
			<lb />
			specimens of typescript, even when derived from
			<lb />
			the same machine at the same time, are ever
			<lb />
			perfect replicas, and when an interval elapses and
			<lb />
			the effects of wear, misuse and repair have to be
			<lb />
			taken into account, they may differ superficially in
			<lb />
			many respects. Any information which might be
			<lb />
			forthcoming concerning the interval which has
			<lb />
			elapsed between the typing of the two specimens,
			<lb />
			which is the older, the amount of use the machine
			<lb />
			receives, and any repairs which may have been
			<lb />
			effected, will be of considerable assistance, so that
			<lb />
			efforts should be made to provide enlightenment on
			<lb />
			these points.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			The examiner finds his greatest difficulty when he
			<lb />
			has to assess the significance of consistent
			<lb />
			differences in the two specimens of typescript.
			<lb />
			Some he may safely attribute to the condition of
			<lb />
			the ribbon, the state of the platen and the nature of
			<lb />
			the surface of the paper. Other he may dismiss as
			<lb />
			being due to the way in which the machine was
			<lb />
			operated, but when this has been done, there will
			<lb />
			often remain some dissimilarities for which there is
			<lb />
			no easily demonstrable explanation.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			If the two specimens of typescript have little in
			<lb />
			common in the way of outstanding characteristics
			<lb />
			such as broken and defective typefaces, gross
			<lb />
			errors in alignment or obviously defective
			<lb />
			impressions, it may be that these slight differences
			<lb />
			indicate that two different machines of the same
			<lb />
			model and not a single machine are concerned.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			159.
			<lb />
			To summarize, the text suggests that where the
			<lb />
			dispute relates to an issue whether interpolations have been
			<lb />
			made on a typescript after it was typed and a different
			<lb />
			typewriter has been used, it is easy to answer the same
			<lb />
			because of the ease with which differences can be spotted.
			<lb />
			Similarly, where the issue is, whether with the use of the same
			<lb />
			typewriter additions and interpolations have been made after
			<lb />
			the document was drawn up and executed, it becomes easy
			<lb />
			for an expert to detect the same because of the spacing of the
			<lb />
			words typed later on because it is very difficult to so adjust the
			<lb />
			paper on the same typewriter so that the space between the
			<lb />
			two lines is the same. Similarly, the margins also let the cat
			<lb />
			out of the bag. Further, where the dispute pertains to the
			<lb />
			make, the brand and the year of manufacturer of the
			<lb />
			typewriter; with reference to the databank created by
			<lb />
			accredited agencies pertaining to the features of typewriters
			<lb />
			manufactured by different companies and features introduced
			<lb />
			from year to year in different models, it is easy to determine
			<lb />
			the make of the typewriter used for typing the script. But,
			<lb />
			where the dispute pertains to the issue whether the disputed
			<lb />
			typescript is the result of the use of a particular typewriter, the
			<lb />
			question is beset with problems and even for an expert is not
			<lb />
			easy to be answered. Further, for resolution of this dispute,
			<lb />
			one has not to jump to easy conclusions and the opinion has to
			<lb />
			be with reference to the various cross checks and balances
			<lb />
			noted herein above, keeping into account the minimal
			<lb />
			evidentiary value of certain features and greater evidentiary
			<lb />
			value of some.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			160.
			<lb />
			A rule of caution to be observed by the expert has
			<lb />
			been brought out by Elbridge W. Stein, an examiner of
			<lb />
			documents in Philadelphia, and an internationally renowned
			<lb />
			expert on typescripts has written an article title &quot;Type writing
			<lb />
			as Evidence&quot; which summarizes the various steps which a
			<lb />
			typescript expert must follow to arrive at a conclusion with
			<lb />
			reference to the opinion sought pertaining to a typescript. He
			<lb />
			writes, inter alia, as follows:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;An enlarged photograph correctly designed and
			<lb />
			accurately made of a document or of the
			<lb />
			particular part in dispute may alone end a law
			<lb />
			suit. A photograph may present facts to a jury
			<lb />
			more effectively than any verbal testimony. As
			<lb />
			was said in a recent decision, &quot;But no statement
			<lb />
			the witness could have made would have made
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			impression
			<lb />
			created
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			pictorial
			<lb />
			presentation of his criticisms and conclusion.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Accurate
			<lb />
			enlarged
			<lb />
			photographs
			<lb />
			make
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			permanent record of physical facts as seen
			<lb />
			through the microscope and have a distinct
			<lb />
			advantage for court use, as they show an entire
			<lb />
			letter or signature in permanently enlarged form,
			<lb />
			while the microscope shows only a small part of it
			<lb />
			to one observer. A juryman without experience in
			<lb />
			the use of a microscope usually has difficulty in
			<lb />
			seeing and understanding what it discloses, but
			<lb />
			an enlarged photograph may be as easy for him
			<lb />
			to see and understand as newspaper print.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			With modern highly corrected lenses, color
			<lb />
			sensitive plats, proper contrast light filters and
			<lb />
			specially constructed cameras, it is possible to
			<lb />
			make scientifically accurate photographs. Colored
			<lb />
			obscuring stamps or defacing marks on a
			<lb />
			document may be made invisible in a photograph;
			<lb />
			and faint writing or writing in blue, yellow or green
			<lb />
			ink may be made more legible.
			<lb />
			Finally, and
			<lb />
			perhaps most important of all, photographs
			<lb />
			permit of a side-by-side arrangement of genuine
			<lb />
			and disputed writings in such a way as to make
			<lb />
			comparison easy which would be impossible with
			<lb />
			the original writings.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			161.
			<lb />
			As noted above, in India, till the year 1952 expert
			<lb />
			opinion pertaining to a typescript was held to be inadmissible
			<lb />
			in evidence and the position continued to be the same till the
			<lb />
			year 1996, when in the decision reported as (1996) 2 SCC 428
			<lb />
			S.J.Choudhry Vs. CBI it was held that keeping in view the
			<lb />
			advancement in science and technology world over, it was
			<lb />
			accepted that the study of transcript was a science and hence
			<lb />
			evidence of an expert pertaining to a typescript was
			<lb />
			admissible in evidence. But, no decision probably exists (in
			<lb />
			any case, none was cited before us), where a court of record in
			<lb />
			India had considered the evidentiary value of the testimony of
			<lb />
			an expert pertaining to a typescript. Even decisions abroad
			<lb />
			show very few case law on the subject. We shall discuss the
			<lb />
			same soon after, but would note at the outset that the
			<lb />
			decisions show that where the fact in issue was whether two
			<lb />
			typewriters were used to create the transcript in dispute, the
			<lb />
			question was answered with ease with reference to the
			<lb />
			testimony of the expert witnesses.
			<lb />
			But, whenever the
			<lb />
			question was to the identity of a typewriter, considerable
			<lb />
			difficulty was encountered. Only one reported decision has
			<lb />
			been noticed by us where said issue was considered and in
			<lb />
			said decision certain guidelines for appreciation of evidence of
			<lb />
			the expert by the jury were set out. The decision shows that
			<lb />
			probably, even the so called experts in the field are not aware
			<lb />
			of the norms developed in the field pertaining to a typescript
			<lb />
			and in particular when the question relates to the identity of a
			<lb />
			particular typewriter as the source of the transcript.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			162.
			<lb />
			During argument of the appeal, Sh.K.T.S.Tulsi,
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel cited:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			A.
			<lb />
			36 ALR 4 th 598
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			B.
			<lb />
			1952 OK 104 In Re CRAVENS&quot; ESTATE. CRAVENS et
			<lb />
			al. V. CRAVENS.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			C.
			<lb />
			209 NYS 88 The People of the State of New York,
			<lb />
			Respondent Vs. Henry H. Werblow, Appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			D.
			<lb />
			1999 ORE 571 State Vs. Swank.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			E.
			<lb />
			498 PA 267 In Re ESTATE OF Paul CIAFFONI.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			F.
			<lb />
			214 NY 75 The People of the State of New York,
			<lb />
			Respondent Vs. Edwin H. Risley, Appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			163.
			<lb />
			Sh.Ram Jethmalani learned senior counsel for the
			<lb />
			appellant cited 83 F.Supp.2d 515 United States Vs. Van Wyk.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			164.
			<lb />
			Whereas Sh.K.T.S.Tulsi urged that the decisions
			<lb />
			cited by him establish that the science of typescripts has
			<lb />
			attained perfection of the highest order reaching the level of
			<lb />
			100% accuracy and that a good expert can with 100%
			<lb />
			accuracy determine the source of a typescript; Sh.Ram
			<lb />
			Jethmalani urged to the contrary and submitted that in certain
			<lb />
			fields the science pertaining to analysis of typescripts, at best,
			<lb />
			would probabilize the likely source of the origin of a typescript
			<lb />
			and it is impossible to identify the source with 100% accuracy.
			<lb />
			Thus, Sh.Ram Jethmalani, learned senior counsel for the
			<lb />
			appellant urged that the rule of prudence requiring
			<lb />
			corroboration to the identity of the typewriter used to generate
			<lb />
			the typescript should be followed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			165.
			<lb />
			Analyzing the decisions cited by learned senior
			<lb />
			counsel, it would be relevant to note that the first decision
			<lb />
			cited by Sh.K.T.S.Tulsi did not relate to the question of identity
			<lb />
			of the typewriter with reference to the disputed document but
			<lb />
			related to the authorship thereof and the Court was discussing
			<lb />
			the attributes of a typewriter relating to typing technique and
			<lb />
			the linguistics with reference whereto the expert had testified
			<lb />
			to show the authorship of the document in dispute. It was
			<lb />
			noted that stylistic similarities, such as use of colon,
			<lb />
			punctuation mark etc. can bring out the personal traits of the
			<lb />
			author of the document i.e. the typist, and with reference to
			<lb />
			the writings of the author, i.e. expressions used, it was
			<lb />
			possible to identify the author of the document.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			166.
			<lb />
			The decision on said aspect of the matter hardly
			<lb />
			relates to the issue at hand for the reason even without a
			<lb />
			typewriter being used, even if the document was scribed in
			<lb />
			any other manner, such kind of styles could be detected by
			<lb />
			any linguistic expert to identify the authorship of the
			<lb />
			document.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			167.
			<lb />
			The second facet of dispute noted in the said
			<lb />
			decision pertained to whether it was possible to determine
			<lb />
			whether certain pages of a document were replaced. It was
			<lb />
			opined that where the question is whether the document is the
			<lb />
			result of a typescript emerging from one or two typewriters, it
			<lb />
			is possible to answer the same for the reason it is difficult to
			<lb />
			use a second typewriter, while changing a page or two of a
			<lb />
			document, and have identical margins, besides, it is easy to
			<lb />
			note extensive dissimilarities when two typewriters are used.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			168.
			<lb />
			The second decision i.e. in CRAVENS&quot; ESTATE&quot;s case
			<lb />
			also related to two typewriters being used; the second being
			<lb />
			used after erasing parts of a typescript and retyping thereon.
			<lb />
			In the decision in Henry H. Werblow&quot;s case the question again
			<lb />
			related to use of two typewriters. The same is the position in
			<lb />
			Swank&quot;s case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			169.
			<lb />
			The decision in Paul Ciaffoni&quot;s case, once again
			<lb />
			pertained to the issue of authorship of the will with reference
			<lb />
			to issues of stylistic deviations.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			170.
			<lb />
			The decision in Edwin H. Risley&quot;s case, makes an
			<lb />
			interesting reading, and relates to the identity of the
			<lb />
			typewriter being the source of the document in dispute. By a
			<lb />
			split verdict, 2:1, the Court of appeals set aside the verdict of
			<lb />
			the jury and remanded the matter to the jury for fresh
			<lb />
			adjudication.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			171.
			<lb />
			It was alleged against Edwin H. Risley that he had
			<lb />
			used an Underwood machine in his office to make
			<lb />
			interpolations in a document. He denied having done so. Two
			<lb />
			experts were cited by The People of the State of New York to
			<lb />
			prove that he had done so. One was a typescript expert and
			<lb />
			the other a professor of Mathematics having expertise in the
			<lb />
			theory of probability. The evidence of the typescript expert, as
			<lb />
			noted in the decision was as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;There was a sharp conflict at the trial on the
			<lb />
			important question of fact whether the words
			<lb />
			claimed to have been forged were written upon the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s typewriter. The People&quot;s case in that
			<lb />
			respect depends almost wholly on expert evidence,
			<lb />
			offered to show that certain alleged defects in the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s typewriter corresponded with defects in
			<lb />
			the typewritten words; and that evidence, so far as
			<lb />
			it was visualized for the jury, consisted of exhibits
			<lb />
			prepared by the People&quot;s expert. Of the thirteen
			<lb />
			similar defects testified to by him, two were variable
			<lb />
			and concededly may be eliminated, one was the
			<lb />
			slant of the letter &quot;t,&quot; which the People&quot;s witnesses
			<lb />
			admitted was a common occurrence, and ten were
			<lb />
			due to alleged defects in the type. The People&quot;s
			<lb />
			expert witnesses who examined the type of the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s machine with a microscope were able
			<lb />
			to name five defects, which their testimony on
			<lb />
			cross-examination tended to show were common on
			<lb />
			used machines. Those defects existed in three
			<lb />
			letters most generally used. The photographs, ten
			<lb />
			diameters enlarged, are claimed to show five other
			<lb />
			defects, consisting of the letter &quot;s&quot; being heavy in
			<lb />
			the upper and lighter in the lower parts, the letter
			<lb />
			&quot;a&quot; being heavy in the lower and lighter in the
			<lb />
			upper parts, and an almost imperceptible swerve in
			<lb />
			one of the down strokes of the letter &quot;m&quot; .&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			172.
			<lb />
			The professor of Mathematics; Prof. Snyder,
			<lb />
			deposed that the probability of the combination of said defects
			<lb />
			occurring in another typewriter was once in 400,00,00,000
			<lb />
			(Four Hundred Crores).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			173.
			<lb />
			The Court discussed the issue as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Even assuming that the alleged eleven defects,
			<lb />
			variable as they were in extent and character in the
			<lb />
			disputed writing and the standards, had some
			<lb />
			resemblance to defects in the defendant&quot;s
			<lb />
			typewriter, the likelihood of similar defects in type
			<lb />
			recurring in another typewriter would depend on the
			<lb />
			dies from which they were made, on the process of
			<lb />
			manufacture, on the greater likelihood of particular
			<lb />
			parts, such as serifs, being broken by use, on the
			<lb />
			material composing the type, on the way in which
			<lb />
			the machine had been used, and doubtless on many
			<lb />
			other things which do not now occur to me; and yet
			<lb />
			the problem was sought to be determined by a so-
			<lb />
			called law of mathematical probability regardless of
			<lb />
			actual experience, physical facts or the element of
			<lb />
			human agency, and on the assumption manifestly
			<lb />
			false that a given thing was as liable to happen as
			<lb />
			not to happen. Upon selected data, which may or
			<lb />
			may not have been the ones involved in the
			<lb />
			problem, it was computed that the same slant of the
			<lb />
			letter &quot;t&quot; would occur once in 256 times, like
			<lb />
			computation were made as to each of the alleged
			<lb />
			defects and by compounding the results it was
			<lb />
			computed that all would occur in combination once
			<lb />
			in 4,000,000,000 times. Thus the happening of a
			<lb />
			past even was sought to be established not by
			<lb />
			witnesses of the
			<lb />
			fact, not by proof of the
			<lb />
			circumstances surrounding it or the causes
			<lb />
			contributing to it, but by an abstract doctrine of
			<lb />
			chances, which was put before the jury as a
			<lb />
			demonstration to a mathematical certainty.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			174.
			<lb />
			The aforesaid decision brings out the extreme
			<lb />
			importance of confirming the expert testimony within proper
			<lb />
			limits in a case admitting of such opportunity to err. It is
			<lb />
			important to note that the likelihood of a similar defect in a
			<lb />
			type recurring in another typewriter not only depends on the
			<lb />
			manner in which a typewriter is used and with passage of time
			<lb />
			deteriorates but also depends on the dies from which the
			<lb />
			characters are produced; the process of manufacture; the
			<lb />
			material composing the type; the likelihood of particular parts
			<lb />
			such as serifs being broken, etc. The decision also guides us
			<lb />
			that where an expert has eschewed a consideration of said
			<lb />
			factors, the report would be a poor report. The decision also
			<lb />
			brings out that where the issue is the identification of a
			<lb />
			particular machine as the source of a typescript, the answer to
			<lb />
			the question is beset with many problems.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			175.
			<lb />
			The decision in Van Wyk&quot;s case cited by Sh.Ram
			<lb />
			Jethmalani is a decision of recent origin rendered by the Third
			<lb />
			Circuit Court in the year 2000. The question related to the
			<lb />
			identity of a typewriter as the source of a transcript. The
			<lb />
			expert Mr. Fitzgerald had testified under Rule 104 of the
			<lb />
			Federal Rules of Evidence.
			<lb />
			The methodology applied by
			<lb />
			Fitzgerald for his opinion, as noted in the decision is as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Fitzgerald testified to the specific methodology he
			<lb />
			uses in determining authorship. First, he normally
			<lb />
			separates and catalogs the writings either
			<lb />
			chronologically or by victim. In this case, because
			<lb />
			there were handwritten and typewritten writings, he
			<lb />
			divided them into four categories: Known Typings
			<lb />
			(&quot;KT&quot;), Known Writings (&quot;KW&quot;), Questioned Typings
			<lb />
			(&quot;QT&quot;), and Questioned Writings (&quot;QW&quot;). Then he
			<lb />
			read the twenty-two letters to obtain a sense for the
			<lb />
			&quot;feel&quot; of the writings. Third, he color coded the
			<lb />
			issues contained in the writings into four categories:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(1) punctuation and spelling; (2) threat; (3)
			<lb />
			interesting phrases; and (4) correct or incorrect
			<lb />
			&quot;trip&quot; phrases such as use of &quot;there&quot; or &quot;their&quot;, use
			<lb />
			of &quot;to&quot;, &quot;two,&quot; or &quot;too,&quot; and&quot; &quot;your,&quot; or &quot;you&quot;re.&quot;
			<lb />
			Next, Fitzgerald created a chart and determined
			<lb />
			whether a particular word, abbreviation, or phrase
			<lb />
			was used correctly or was an idiosyncrasy. His
			<lb />
			results were reviewed by two other law enforcement
			<lb />
			officers. No sources outside the FBI have reviewed
			<lb />
			his reports.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			176.
			<lb />
			Commenting upon the expert opinion the Court
			<lb />
			observed:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Although
			<lb />
			Fitzgerald
			<lb />
			employed
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			particular
			<lb />
			methodology that may be subject to testing, neither
			<lb />
			Fitzgerald nor the Government has been able to
			<lb />
			identify a known rate of error, establish what amount
			<lb />
			of sample is necessary for an expert to be able to
			<lb />
			reach a conclusion as to probability of authorship, or
			<lb />
			pinpoint any meaningful peer review. Additionally, as
			<lb />
			defendant argues, there is no universally recognized
			<lb />
			standard for certifying an individual as an expert in
			<lb />
			Forensic Stylistics.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Various judicial decisions regarding handwriting
			<lb />
			analysis, while not identical to text analysis, are
			<lb />
			instructive because handwriting analysis seems to
			<lb />
			suffer similar weaknesses in scientific reliability,
			<lb />
			namely the following: no known error rate, no
			<lb />
			professional or academic degrees in the field, no
			<lb />
			meaningful peer review, and no agreement as to how
			<lb />
			many exemplars are required to establish the
			<lb />
			probability of authorship.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			177.
			<lb />
			The decision in Van Wyk&quot;s case pertains to the
			<lb />
			expert testimony to the authorship of a document i.e. in the
			<lb />
			field of Forensic Stylistics, but guides us the pitfalls of the
			<lb />
			science with reference to identification of a criteria to
			<lb />
			determine, inter alia known rate of errors; lack of text accepted
			<lb />
			by the experts in the field on the question of adequacy of a
			<lb />
			sample; no criteria published by any accredited agency to
			<lb />
			determine as to who could possibly hold himself out to be an
			<lb />
			expert because professional or academic degrees in the field
			<lb />
			are not awarded.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			178.
			<lb />
			Perusing the testimony of S.K.Gupta PW-75, as
			<lb />
			deposed to in his examination in chief, he has a Masters
			<lb />
			degree in Chemistry from Calcutta University. As admitted by
			<lb />
			him in his cross examination his only training in the mechanism
			<lb />
			of a typewriter is, to quote: &quot;I had received three days&quot; training
			<lb />
			in Godrage Typewriter manufacture at Bombay……. The
			<lb />
			training of three days at Bombay done by me was at the
			<lb />
			manufacturing plant relating to assembly of the typewriters. I
			<lb />
			did not work with any other company manufacturing
			<lb />
			typewriters to study the characteristics of the typewriters from
			<lb />
			the stand point of classification.&quot; When questioned as to in
			<lb />
			how many cases he has opined with reference to typescripts he
			<lb />
			stated that besides the instant case he has given his opinion in
			<lb />
			two other cases but his opinions were not considered by the
			<lb />
			Courts in said two cases because in one case he was
			<lb />
			discharged without being examined and in the other case the
			<lb />
			Court did not take into account his opinion because of the then
			<lb />
			existing law which did not make admissible expert evidence
			<lb />
			pertaining to typescripts. Though PW-75 claimed to have
			<lb />
			authored articles on the subject of typescripts, but failed to
			<lb />
			disclose particulars of any articles published by him.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			179.
			<lb />
			It is apparent that PW-75 fails to satisfy the second
			<lb />
			of the three fundamental components of Frye&quot;s test namely the
			<lb />
			requirement of the author of the opinion qualifying to be called
			<lb />
			an expert, by knowledge, skill, experience, training or
			<lb />
			education. Admittedly, PW-75 has no formal education in the
			<lb />
			science of typescripts, in respect whereof we find a big
			<lb />
			problem because no university is awarding degrees or
			<lb />
			diplomas in the field of typescripts. Further, in India, we have
			<lb />
			no accreditation agency where one can register oneself an
			<lb />
			expert on a typescript. The witness has led no evidence of any
			<lb />
			special knowledge gained by him except for a three days&quot; stint
			<lb />
			with Godrage, a company which manufactures typewriters.
			<lb />
			Analyzing three typescripts (including the one in question) is to
			<lb />
			meager an experience.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			180.
			<lb />
			As noted in para 141 above, as per Wilson R.
			<lb />
			Harrison, there are five limitations in the analysis of a
			<lb />
			typescript, one of the five being: &quot;this limitation also applies
			<lb />
			when but a small amount of transcript is in question&quot;. It would
			<lb />
			be interesting to note that PW-75 when cross examined on
			<lb />
			28.1.1997 admitted that Wilson R. Harrison is a leading
			<lb />
			authority on typescripts.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			181.
			<lb />
			Whereas the defence expert i.e. Sh.Darshan Dayal
			<lb />
			Goel has been candid in deposing: &quot;I am of the opinion that it
			<lb />
			is not possible to express definite and irrefutable opinion that
			<lb />
			the questioned typescript mark Q-1 and the sample typescript
			<lb />
			S-7 have been typed on one and the same type machine.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			PW-75 has not been candid on the subject. As per Wilson R.
			<lb />
			Harrison, and as noted in para 148 above, since the force with
			<lb />
			which a typist punches the keys of a typewriter, the quality of
			<lb />
			a ribbon and the quality of paper, all affect the quality of the
			<lb />
			print; a good expert, to rule out unforeseen errors occurring
			<lb />
			due to said three attributes, should obtain three sample
			<lb />
			typescripts, one each with a light, medium and heavy touch
			<lb />
			respectively and at least one specimen should be prepared on
			<lb />
			same or similar paper. If not so done, according to the learned
			<lb />
			author: &quot;Otherwise, the imperfect impressions which occur due
			<lb />
			to the quality of the paper as also imperfect impressions which
			<lb />
			occur due to the touch on the key may be attributed to the
			<lb />
			machine.&quot; PW-75 has thrown to the winds the said rule of
			<lb />
			caution. The further problem in the instant case has emerged
			<lb />
			in the admission of PW-75, who on being cross examined on
			<lb />
			21.3.1977 admitted: &quot;It is correct that the questioned
			<lb />
			document does not contain clear impressions due to
			<lb />
			mutilation&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			182.
			<lb />
			Thus, we have a three-fold problem. The first is the
			<lb />
			inadequacy of the typescripts.
			<lb />
			The second is that the
			<lb />
			questioned document does not contain clear impression due to
			<lb />
			it being mutilated. The third is that PW-75 has not taken three
			<lb />
			prints of the specimen text, one each, with a light, medium
			<lb />
			and a heavy touch, nor has he obtained a sample on the same
			<lb />
			or similar paper. In our opinion, said three factors are by
			<lb />
			themselves sufficient justification to not base a conclusive
			<lb />
			opinion on the issue with reference to expert testimony. In
			<lb />
			fact the admission by PW-75 that the questioned document
			<lb />
			does not contain clear impressions due to mutilation is a very
			<lb />
			important facet to be taken notice of, for the reason the whole
			<lb />
			analysis of a typescript when the issue is to the identity of a
			<lb />
			typewriter as the source of the transcript, is heavily dependent
			<lb />
			upon the identification of features in the letters of the keys
			<lb />
			when punched and commonsense tells us that where a
			<lb />
			document is mutilated and the impressions are not clear due
			<lb />
			to said reason, it would be most unsafe, unless corroborated
			<lb />
			by other evidence, to base the decision on the testimony of
			<lb />
			the expert. Missing serifs, slopping letters, broken type faces
			<lb />
			etc. are the keys to locate the individual characteristic
			<lb />
			acquired by a machine over a period of time i.e. the result of
			<lb />
			wear and tear.
			<lb />
			To identify the same with a degree of
			<lb />
			certainty, the blurring of the impressions due to a questioned
			<lb />
			paper being mutilated resulting in clarity of the imprints being
			<lb />
			blurred would certainly impede the certainty of the said
			<lb />
			features. Lastly, we find another problem in the manner in
			<lb />
			which PW-75 have attempted to analyze the questioned
			<lb />
			typescript. We find from the record that he has simply
			<lb />
			obtained a photograph of the questioned document on the
			<lb />
			same scale as it exists, without enlarging the same. The
			<lb />
			decision in Edwin H. Risley&quot;s case (supra) shows that the
			<lb />
			experts abroad enlarge the photographs by ten diameters. It
			<lb />
			is obvious that a safe analysis can be done with enlarged
			<lb />
			photographs for the reason the distinctive characteristics of
			<lb />
			the keys of a typewriter have to be determined with reference
			<lb />
			to the typescript and clarity is brought about by enlargement.
			<lb />
			PW-75, was cross examined on the issue of enlargement of
			<lb />
			photographs on 17.3.1997. He stated: I agree with Osborn
			<lb />
			observation on the role of enlarged photography as a period
			<lb />
			message that is relevant during those periods. (Vol. but in
			<lb />
			modern days examinations are made direct from original
			<lb />
			documents with microscope etc.). I prepared notes at the time
			<lb />
			of examination. (Vol. after making the final notes I destroyed
			<lb />
			the loose notes…. My report in this case Ex.PW-75/C is based
			<lb />
			on those notes prepared by me). We note that the next
			<lb />
			question put to the witness was as to why did he destroy his
			<lb />
			notes, when he knew that he would be examined in Court. He
			<lb />
			responded that this was his usual practice.
			<lb />
			The third
			<lb />
			component of the Frye&quot;s test is that the proffered experts&quot;
			<lb />
			testimony must reveal that the methodology, hypothesis or
			<lb />
			techniques applicable and the theory behind the principles
			<lb />
			applicable have been applied by the expert and that the
			<lb />
			expert is mindful of the known or potential rate of error in the
			<lb />
			derivative of the technique or methodology to the subject
			<lb />
			thereof; a test which appears to have been not successfully
			<lb />
			passed by PW-75. It is not out of place to record here that
			<lb />
			when PW-75 was cross examined with reference to the
			<lb />
			nuances of his techniques applied to which he responded that
			<lb />
			he had destroyed his notes. It is apparent that a crucial piece
			<lb />
			of evidence i.e. the notes and observations of the expert were
			<lb />
			not available before the Court and the enlarged photographs,
			<lb />
			being not taken, it would be virtually impossible for the Court
			<lb />
			to check the veracity of the report, unless the Court calls for a
			<lb />
			microscope and sits down as an expert to carry out the
			<lb />
			exercise of analyzing the typescript.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			183.
			<lb />
			We note that in his cross examination on 21.3.1977
			<lb />
			PW-75 admitted the following:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the letters &quot;r&quot; and &quot;i&quot; in the word
			<lb />
			Krishan in Q-1 (Ex.PW-62/O) are not touching each other. It is
			<lb />
			also correct that the combination of the letters &quot;r&quot; and &quot;i&quot; in the
			<lb />
			word Krishan in specimen writings S-7 Ex.PW-27/A are
			<lb />
			touching each other.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the letter &quot;h&quot; in the word Krishan in
			<lb />
			Q-1 Ex.PW-62/A is complete and without any break. It is
			<lb />
			correct that the letter &quot;h&quot; similarly placed in word Krishan in S-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			7 Ex.PW-27/A is not complete.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the base of letter &quot;u&quot; in word
			<lb />
			Sunder in S-7 Ex.PW-27/A is higher than the base of letter &quot;S&quot;
			<lb />
			in the word Sunder. It is correct that it is not so in Q-1 Ex.PW-
			<lb />
			62/O in the word Sunder.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the difference of two tangents of
			<lb />
			&quot;9&quot; and &quot;8&quot; in &quot;S-7&quot; encircled &quot;X&quot; in Ex.PW-27/A is more than Q-1.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(v)
			<lb />
			There is a difference between the circular formation
			<lb />
			of the lower loop of letter &quot;g&quot; in &quot;agar&quot; in Q-1 Ex.PW-62/O and in
			<lb />
			S-7 Ex.PW-27/A. It is more elongated in Q-1 than in S-7.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the gap between the letters &quot;n&quot; &quot;d&quot;
			<lb />
			in the word &quot;Sunder&quot; in Q-1 is lesser than the gap between the
			<lb />
			two letters in S-7 at portion Z and Z-1.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vii)
			<lb />
			It is incorrect that the right part of the lower serif in
			<lb />
			&quot;p&quot; in S-7 is missing. Volunteered : It is present to some
			<lb />
			extent.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(viii)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the serif of lower curve in the letter
			<lb />
			&quot;S&quot; in &quot;OST&quot; in Q-1 is raised upwards.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ix)
			<lb />
			It is correct that there is smudging of ink in the
			<lb />
			body of letter &quot;A&quot; in the top line in Q-1. Similar smudging of ink
			<lb />
			to that extent is not there in S-7.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(x)
			<lb />
			It is correct that there is a regular gap between the
			<lb />
			letters &quot;o&quot; and &quot;m&quot; in the word &quot;From&quot; in Q-1, whereas the
			<lb />
			combination of the letters &quot;o&quot; and &quot;m&quot; in the word &quot;From&quot; in S-7
			<lb />
			at portion A in S-7 are touching each other at point A.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xi)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the gap in the curve of letter &quot;p&quot; in
			<lb />
			Q-1 in the top line is smaller than similar letter &quot;p&quot; in S-7.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xii)
			<lb />
			It is also correct that the space inside the oval of &quot;O&quot;
			<lb />
			in S-7 is bigger than the similar letter &quot;O&quot; in Q-1.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xiii)
			<lb />
			It is correct that the lower base of &quot;F&quot; in the word
			<lb />
			&quot;From&quot; in S-7 is lower than the base of the letter &quot;r&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			184.
			<lb />
			In his report Ex.PW-75/C, Shri S.K.Gupta PW-75 has
			<lb />
			opined:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;However, I have observed three differences between
			<lb />
			Q-1 and S-7 which are described below:-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			The upper serif of h is clear in Q1 whereas it is
			<lb />
			missing in S7.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			The i dotting of the letter small i is almost
			<lb />
			touching its body in Q1 whereas it is separate
			<lb />
			in S7. The right serif at the base of the letter
			<lb />
			small i in Q-1 is shorter than the left side serif
			<lb />
			but in S7 it is clear and almost equal on both
			<lb />
			sides.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			The lower loop of the letter &quot;g&quot; differs in its
			<lb />
			shape between Q1 and S7.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			185.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, Shri S.K.Gupta has proceeded to explain
			<lb />
			the reasons for the said differences and as to why the same do
			<lb />
			not reveal dissimilarities. It is relevant that inasmuch as
			<lb />
			similarities are relevant to prove the identity, existence of
			<lb />
			dissimilarities displaces the proof of identity. This is simple
			<lb />
			logic.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			186.
			<lb />
			Having admitted thirteen dissimilarities during
			<lb />
			cross-examination, ignoring by us twelve other dissimilarities
			<lb />
			which were put to the witness, which he denied, no attempt
			<lb />
			has been made by S.K.Gupta to explain the said thirteen
			<lb />
			dissimilarities, which he admitted, as being consistent with the
			<lb />
			proof of identity of the machine in question being the source of
			<lb />
			the disputed typescript as also the source of the sample
			<lb />
			typescript.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			187.
			<lb />
			A Judge is not expected to be an expert and
			<lb />
			therefore we do not take upon ourselves the mantle of being
			<lb />
			an expert. But, it is our duty to test the credibility and the
			<lb />
			evidentiary worth of a report of an expert with reference to
			<lb />
			internationally accepted text to satisfy the judicial conscious
			<lb />
			that the caution required to be observed; the cross checks to
			<lb />
			be carried out; the pitfalls to be avoided and the possibility of
			<lb />
			the known rate of error occurring have been kept in view by
			<lb />
			the expert.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			188.
			<lb />
			Cumulatively seen, for the reasons noted herein
			<lb />
			above in paras 182 to 186, we hold that it would be unsafe to
			<lb />
			return a finding on the identity of the typewriter with reference
			<lb />
			to the testimony of PW-75, unless we find corroboration by
			<lb />
			other independent evidence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			189.
			<lb />
			Do we have any?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			190.
			<lb />
			N.D.Sethi PW-27 is the witness whose testimony
			<lb />
			needs to be considered. He has deposed that around 22 nd or
			<lb />
			23 rd September 1982 some person had come with a
			<lb />
			manuscript address and an envelope and had requested to
			<lb />
			type it and he referred him to a student who was a beginner to
			<lb />
			do the needful and he did the same. He admitted that he had
			<lb />
			not read the manuscript nor could be identify the person
			<lb />
			concerned.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			191.
			<lb />
			From the aforesaid inchoate testimony of PW-27, it
			<lb />
			cannot be inferred that the appellant was the person who had
			<lb />
			gone to his typing school on 22 nd or 23 rd September 1982 with
			<lb />
			a request to type the sender&quot;s and addressee&quot;s address on
			<lb />
			Ex.PW-62/O. Any person could have gone on said dates and
			<lb />
			got anything typed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			192.
			<lb />
			The witness is clear and very categoric that the
			<lb />
			person who came got the sender&quot;s and the addressee&quot;s name
			<lb />
			typed on an envelope. In the instant case the address of the
			<lb />
			addressee and the sender is on slips of paper pasted on a
			<lb />
			sheet of paper used as a wrapper to wrap the parcel bomb.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			193.
			<lb />
			It is relevant to note that CBI officers had first
			<lb />
			contacted N.D.Sethi, as deposed to by him, on 5.8.1983 i.e.
			<lb />
			after nearly ten months of 22 nd or 23 rd September 1982. It is
			<lb />
			difficult to believe that a trivial customer who got performed a
			<lb />
			trivial act at the typing school i.e. got typed, on a single sheet
			<lb />
			or two sheets, the address of the addressee and the address of
			<lb />
			the sender, for which work not a farthing was paid, would be
			<lb />
			within the contemplation of N.D.Sethi.
			<lb />
			There is every
			<lb />
			probability and possibility that N.D.Sethi has gone along with
			<lb />
			the CBI under compulsion and with a heavy heart, evidenced
			<lb />
			by the fact that he has spoken the bare minimum and inchoate
			<lb />
			facts, probably to satisfy CBI officers, and at the same time
			<lb />
			live with his conscience.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			194.
			<lb />
			To conclude, the only admissible evidence which
			<lb />
			remains against the appellant is that of motive. That too, by
			<lb />
			ignoring the three letters of the appellant, contents whereof
			<lb />
			have been noted in para 68 above and our analysis of what
			<lb />
			emerges from the said three letters as discussed in para 69
			<lb />
			above. But, motive, being presumptive evidence is weak
			<lb />
			evidence and by itself cannot form a chain of circumstances so
			<lb />
			complete that the only inference possible is the guilt of the
			<lb />
			accused; ruling out his innocence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			195.
			<lb />
			It is unfortunate that a crime is going unpunished,
			<lb />
			but we cannot hang any person for the crime unless our
			<lb />
			judicial conscience is satisfied that the evidence on record
			<lb />
			conclusively establishes the guilt of the person charged for the
			<lb />
			offence and brought before us. Our decisions have to be
			<lb />
			based on legally admissible evidence, properly brought before
			<lb />
			us and analyzed on the known principles of law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			196.
			<lb />
			The appeal is allowed. Impugned judgment and
			<lb />
			order dated 28.4.2008 is set aside. The appellant is acquitted
			<lb />
			of the charge of having murdered Kishan Sikand as also of the
			<lb />
			charge under Section 3 and 4 of the Explosive Substance Act
			<lb />
			1908.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			197.
			<lb />
			The appellant is directed to be set free, unless
			<lb />
			otherwise required in any other case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			PRADEEP NANDRAJOG, J.
			<lb />
			ARUNA SURESH, J.
			<lb />
			May 15, 2009
			<lb />
			mm
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
