<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			By way of the present appeal under section 21(4) of the National Investigation Agency
			<lb />
			Act 2008 (‘NIA Act’, for short), the appellant Asif
			<lb />
			Iqbal Tanha, a 25 year old student, pursuing his final year of the B.A.
			<lb />
			(Hons.). (Persian) Programme at the Jamia Milia Islamia University, New
			<lb />
			Delhi (&apos;Jamia University&apos;, for short) impugns order dated 26.10.2020 made
			<lb />
			by the learned Special Court (&apos;impugned order&apos;, for short), whereby the
			<lb />
			appellant&apos;s second application seeking enlargement on bail has been
			<lb />
			rejected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. The appellant is presently in judicial custody, having been arrested on
			<lb />
			19.05.2020 in case FIR No. 59/2020 dated 06.03.2020 registered under
			<lb />
			sections 147 / 148 / 149 / 120B Indian Penal Code 1860 (&apos;IPC&apos;, for
			<lb />
			short) at P.S.: Crime Branch (&apos;subject FIR&apos;, for short) in connection
			<lb />
			with the incidents of violence and rioting that occurred in North-East
			<lb />
			Delhi between 22.02.2020 and 26.02.2020. It may be noted that
			<lb />
			offences under sections 109 / 114 / 124A / 153A / 186 / 201 / 212 /
			<lb />
			295 / 302 / 307 / 341 /353 / 395 / 419 / 420 / 427 / 435 / 436 / 452 / 454
			<lb />
			/ 468 / 471 / 34 IPC, sections 3 / 4 of the Prevention of Damage to
			<lb />
			Public Property Act, 1984 (&apos;PDPP Act&apos;, for short), sections 25 / 26 of
			<lb />
			Arms Act, 1959 and sections 13 / 16 / 17 / 18 of the Unlawful
			<lb />
			Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967 (&apos;UAPA&apos;, for short) were
			<lb />
			subsequently added to the subject FIR. At the time of his arrest in the
			<lb />
			subject FIR on 19.05.2020, the appellant was already in judicial
			<lb />
			custody in a different case arising from FIR No. 298/2019 dated
			<lb />
			16.12.2019 registered under sections 143 / 147 / 148 / 149 / 435 / 427 /
			<lb />
			323 / 186 / 353 / 332 / 308 / 341 / 120B / 34 IPC and sections 3 / 4 of
			<lb />
			the PDPP Act at P.S.: Jamia Nagar, New Delhi. For completeness it
			<lb />
			may be mentioned that FIR No. 298/2019 was registered in connection
			<lb />
			with protests held in Delhi in 2019 against the Citizenship
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(Amendment) Act 2019 (&apos;CAA&apos;, for short) passed by the Parliament
			<lb />
			and the exercise proposed to be undertaken by the Central Government
			<lb />
			for creating a National Register of Citizens (&apos;NRC&apos;, for short). It must
			<lb />
			be mentioned that in case FIR No. 298/2019 the appellant has since
			<lb />
			been admitted to regular bail by the learned Sessions Court, Saket, New
			<lb />
			Delhi.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. Charge-sheet dated 16.09.2020 has been filed in the subject FIR inter
			<lb />
			alia against the appellant (&apos;subject charge-sheet&apos;, for short); and though
			<lb />
			supplementary charge-sheets dated 22.11.2020 and 01.03.2021 have
			<lb />
			also been filed in the subject FIR, the said other charge-sheets do not
			<lb />
			relate to the appellant and are therefore not relevant for purposes of the
			<lb />
			present proceedings. Vidé order dated 17.09.2020 the learned Special
			<lb />
			Court has taken cognizance of the offences alleged in the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet except offences under sections 124A / 153A / 109 / 120B
			<lb />
			of the IPC, since requisite sanction for prosecution from the State
			<lb />
			Government was awaited for those offences as of the date of the
			<lb />
			impugned order. Charges have not yet been framed against the
			<lb />
			appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4. In a Criminal Miscellaneous Petition bearing CRL.M.C. No. 2119/2020
			<lb />
			filed by the respondent/State against order of the trial court directing
			<lb />
			the State to provide a hardcopy of the charge-sheet to all accused
			<lb />
			persons, further proceedings in the trial before the learned Special
			<lb />
			Court were stayed by a learned Single Judge of this court vidé order
			<lb />
			dated 10.11.2020; which stay order has however since been vacated by
			<lb />
			the learned single Judge vidé order dated 23.03.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Essence of allegations against Appellant &amp;
			<lb />
			role assigned to him
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			5. The essential allegations against the appellant as contained in the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet as also set-out in reply dated 24.07.2020 filed by
			<lb />
			the Special Cell, Delhi Police before the learned Special Court
			<lb />
			opposing the appellant&apos;s bail application are the following :
			<lb />
			a)
			<lb />
			that the appellant is one of the main conspirators as well as
			<lb />
			instigators behind the riots that happened in the North-East
			<lb />
			parts of Delhi from 22.02.2020 to 26.02.2020; that the appellant
			<lb />
			played an active role in the conspiracy and is one of the
			<lb />
			&apos;masterminds&apos;;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			that the appellant is a member of the Student Islamic
			<lb />
			Organisation (&apos;SIO&apos;, for short);
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			that on 13.12.2019, a protest was held at Gate No. 7 of Jamia
			<lb />
			University and the appellant, alongwith other co-accused
			<lb />
			persons, formed the Jamia Co-ordination Committee (&apos;JCC&apos;, for
			<lb />
			short). The JCC was formed to protest against the CAA;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			that on 17.12.2019, a WhatsApp group of the JCC was formed
			<lb />
			to monitor, control and manage the protest sites in Delhi; and
			<lb />
			the office of the JCC was set-up in a room at Gate No. 18 of
			<lb />
			Jamia University;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			that at a meeting of members of the JCC and representatives of
			<lb />
			another entity called &apos;Pinjra Tod&apos;, it was decided to hold a
			<lb />
			chakkajam in North-East Delhi (chakkajam being loosely
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			translatable as a form of protest in which protesters cause
			<lb />
			complete stoppage of vehicles and blockade of roads);
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			f)
			<lb />
			that as part of the conspiracy, women and children were
			<lb />
			mobilized to prevent the police from using force against them;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			g)
			<lb />
			that for the foregoing purposes, the co-conspirators gave
			<lb />
			directions to the appellant; and the appellant, alongwith other
			<lb />
			co-accused persons ratified them;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			h)
			<lb />
			that the appellant provided a SIM card to one of the co-accused,
			<lb />
			in the office of the JCC, using which the latter posted directions
			<lb />
			and instructions on the JCC WhatsApp group;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			i)
			<lb />
			that co-accused persons instructed the appellant to visit Muslim
			<lb />
			majority and Muslim dominated areas for campaigning as part
			<lb />
			of the protest; and the appellant was also instructed to co-
			<lb />
			ordinate with local Imams to mobilize people for the protest;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			j)
			<lb />
			that on 22.02.2020, an urgent meeting of the JCC was called at
			<lb />
			the Jafrabad Metro Station while the road there was blocked; at
			<lb />
			which meeting the appellant said that he had spoken to other
			<lb />
			co-accused persons, who had told the appellant that
			<lb />
			preparations for riots &quot;were ready&quot;. Furthermore, the appellant
			<lb />
			had also said at that meeting that other co-accused persons had
			<lb />
			told him that they were prepared and ready for riots &quot;if anything
			<lb />
			happens&quot;;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			k)
			<lb />
			that as per plan, on 23.02.2020 messages relating to urgent
			<lb />
			mobilisation were posted on the JCC WhatsApp group, after
			<lb />
			which riots occurred in Delhi;
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			l)
			<lb />
			that active members of the JCC were responsible for the riots
			<lb />
			that occurred in Delhi, as per a well designed conspiracy;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			m)
			<lb />
			that the appellant, alongwith other co-accused persons, was an
			<lb />
			active radical member of the JCC;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			n)
			<lb />
			that the motive of the JCC was to create riots, which led to the
			<lb />
			death of several people in Delhi;
			<lb />
			o)
			<lb />
			that from the evidence collected so far, there remains no doubt
			<lb />
			that the appellant played a key part in the conspiracy, whereby
			<lb />
			he organised mobilisation of a mob of a particular community,
			<lb />
			thereby flaring-up communal passion and instigated them to
			<lb />
			commit violence; while simultaneously other co-conspirators
			<lb />
			were &quot;actually collecting and organising the means and
			<lb />
			material&quot; through which the mob was to indulge in violence and
			<lb />
			rioting; and
			<lb />
			p)
			<lb />
			that it is clear that the case pertains to a very deep-rooted and
			<lb />
			sinister conspiracy conceived and executed by the appellant to
			<lb />
			create unrest in the society and to uproot a lawfully constituted
			<lb />
			government by employing unconstitutional and violent means;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			q)
			<lb />
			that the appellant&apos;s role in relation to the foregoing &quot;has been
			<lb />
			described in great detail by the witnesses&quot; in their statements
			<lb />
			recorded under sections 161 and 164 of the Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			In the aforesaid reply to the appellant&apos;s bail application before
			<lb />
			the learned Special Court, the respondent has also said that : &quot;it is
			<lb />
			learned that funds were sent by Jamia and terrorist for protest&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6. The subject charge-sheet dated 16.09.2020 which relates to the
			<lb />
			appellant is stated to run into some 19000 pages. The portions of the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet that are alleged to contain specific allegations
			<lb />
			against the appellant, as referred to by the learned Additional Solicitor
			<lb />
			General appearing for the Delhi Police (Special Cell), are extracted in a
			<lb />
			separate Annexure to this judgment for ease of reference.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Genesis of UAPA
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			7. The genesis of The Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act 1967 lies in
			<lb />
			the recommendations of the Committee on National Integration and
			<lb />
			Regionalisation set-up by the National Integration Council to look inter
			<lb />
			alia into the aspect of putting reasonable restrictions on certain
			<lb />
			freedoms in the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India. As
			<lb />
			reflected in the Statement of Objects and Reasons of the UAPA, it was
			<lb />
			pursuant to the recommendations of the said committee that the
			<lb />
			Parliament enacted the Constitution (Sixteenth Amendment) Act 1963
			<lb />
			to impose reasonable restrictions in the interests of sovereignty and
			<lb />
			integrity of India on:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(i) the freedom of speech and expression;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) the right to assemble peacefully and without arms; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) the right to form associations and unions.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			8. Pursuant thereto, the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Bill was
			<lb />
			introduced in the Parliament to make powers available for dealing with
			<lb />
			activities directed against the sovereignty and integrity of India, which
			<lb />
			bill came on the statute book as the Unlawful Activities (Prevention)
			<lb />
			Act 1967 (&apos;UAPA&apos;, for short) w.e.f. 30.12.1967.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Enactment &amp; Amendment of UAPA &amp; Legislative
			<lb />
			Competence
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			9. The Preamble to the UAPA as originally enacted read as follows :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;An Act to provide for the more effective prevention of certain
			<lb />
			unlawful activities of individuals and associations and for matters
			<lb />
			connected therewith&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			10. In 2004, the Preamble to the UAPA was amended and &apos;terrorist
			<lb />
			activities&apos; were brought within its fold by amending the Preamble and
			<lb />
			long-title with retrospective effect from 21.09.2004. The amended
			<lb />
			Preamble reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;An Act to provide for the more effective prevention of certain
			<lb />
			unlawful activities of individuals and associations, and dealing with
			<lb />
			terrorist activities and for matters connected therewith&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. Subsequently, in order to give effect to certain resolutions passed by the
			<lb />
			Security Council of the United Nations and to give effect to the
			<lb />
			Prevention and Suppression of the Terrorism (Implementation of
			<lb />
			Security Council Resolution) Order 2007 and to make special provision
			<lb />
			for prevention of, and for coping with, terrorist activities and for
			<lb />
			matters connected therewith or incidental thereto, the UAPA was
			<lb />
			further amended in 2008 inter alia by substituting the then existing
			<lb />
			section 15 relating to &apos;terrorist act&apos; under the UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. At this point it will be relevant to allude briefly to Article 246 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution of India and the three Lists set-out in the Seventh
			<lb />
			Schedule to the Constitution. Put very briefly, Article 246 sets-out the
			<lb />
			legislative competence of the Parliament and of the State Legislatures
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			under the scheme of our Constitution; and says that the Parliament has
			<lb />
			exclusive power to make laws with respect to any matter enumerated in
			<lb />
			List-I appearing in the Seventh Schedule which is called the &apos;Union
			<lb />
			List&apos;, that the State Legislature has exclusive powers to make laws for
			<lb />
			such State with respect to any matter enumerated in List-II of the
			<lb />
			Seventh Schedule, called the &apos;State List&apos;; and that the Parliament and
			<lb />
			the State Legislature have concurrent powers to make laws with respect
			<lb />
			to matters enumerated in List-III of the Seventh Schedule, called the
			<lb />
			&apos;Concurrent List&apos;. In the context of the present matter, what is to be
			<lb />
			noticed is that the UAPA has been enacted by Parliament and must
			<lb />
			therefore have been enacted in relation to a matter appearing in Entry 1
			<lb />
			and/or Entry 93 of List-I, namely the Union List in the Seventh
			<lb />
			Schedule of the Constitution since no other legislative subject appears
			<lb />
			to cover the enactment of the UAPA. Entries 1 and 93 of List-I read as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;!
			<lb />
			SEVENTH SCHEDULE !
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			[Article 246]
			<lb />
			List I -Union List
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			1. Defence of India and every part thereof including preparation for
			<lb />
			defence and all such acts as may be conducive in times of war to its
			<lb />
			prosecution and after its termination to effective demobilisation.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			93. Offences against laws with respect to any of the matters in this
			<lb />
			List.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			13. It further requires to be noticed that Entry 1 of List-II refers to matters
			<lb />
			of &apos;public order&apos;, which subject therefore falls within the legislative
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			competence of the State Legislature; and Entry 1 of List-III relates to
			<lb />
			matters of &apos;criminal law&apos;, including all matters included in the IPC but
			<lb />
			excluding offences against laws with respect to any matter specified in
			<lb />
			List-I or List-II and excluding the use of Naval, Military, Air Force or
			<lb />
			any other Armed Forces of the Union. The purpose of referring to Entry
			<lb />
			1 of List-I (Defence of India) and Entry 2 of List-II (Public Order) is to
			<lb />
			take notice of the fact that since UAPA is a central legislation, it would
			<lb />
			have been enacted in relation to the &apos;defence of India&apos; as contra-
			<lb />
			distinct from &apos;public order&apos;, since it must be presumed that when the
			<lb />
			Parliament enacted the UAPA, it was acting within the scope of its
			<lb />
			powers under the constitutional scheme and was therefore enacting a
			<lb />
			legislation relating to a matter that was within its competence under
			<lb />
			Article 246 and the Seventh Schedule of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. Post the amendments made from time-to-time, as of date, the
			<lb />
			provisions of the UAPA that are relevant for the purposes of the present
			<lb />
			matter are extracted below :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;2. Definitions.-(1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise
			<lb />
			requires,-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			…..
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(k) &quot;terrorist act&quot; has the meaning assigned to it in Section 15, and
			<lb />
			the expressions &quot;terrorism&quot; and &quot;terrorist&quot; shall be construed
			<lb />
			accordingly;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(l) &quot;terrorist gang&quot; means any association, other than terrorist
			<lb />
			organisation, whether systematic or otherwise, which is concerned
			<lb />
			with, or involved in, terrorist act;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(m) &quot;terrorist organisation&quot; means an organisation listed in the
			<lb />
			First Schedule or an organisation operating under the same name
			<lb />
			as an organisation so listed;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			…..
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(o) &quot;unlawful activity&quot;, in relation to an individual or association,
			<lb />
			means any action taken by such individual or association (whether
			<lb />
			by committing an act or by words, either spoken or written, or by
			<lb />
			signs or by visible representation or otherwise),-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i) which is intended, or supports any claim, to bring about, on
			<lb />
			any ground whatsoever, the cession of a part of the territory
			<lb />
			of India or the secession of a part of the territory of India
			<lb />
			from the Union, or which incites any individual or group of
			<lb />
			individuals to bring about such cession or secession; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) which disclaims, questions, disrupts or is intended to
			<lb />
			disrupt the sovereignty and territorial integrity of India; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) which causes or is intended to cause disaffection against
			<lb />
			India;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * * &quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;15. Terrorist act.-(1) Whoever does any act with intent to
			<lb />
			threaten or likely to threaten the unity, integrity, security,
			<lb />
			economic security, or sovereignty of India or with intent to strike
			<lb />
			terror or likely to strike terror in the people or any section of the
			<lb />
			people in India or in any foreign country,-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) by using bombs, dynamite or other explosive substances or
			<lb />
			inflammable substances or firearms or other lethal weapons or
			<lb />
			poisonous or noxious gases or other chemicals or by any other
			<lb />
			substances (whether biological radioactive, nuclear or otherwise) of
			<lb />
			a hazardous nature or by any other means of whatever nature to
			<lb />
			cause or likely to cause -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i) death of, or injuries to, any person or persons; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) loss of, or damage to, or destruction of, property; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) disruption of any supplies or services essential to the life
			<lb />
			of the community in India or in any foreign country; or
			<lb />
			(iii-a) damage to, the monetary stability of India by way of
			<lb />
			production or smuggling or circulation of high quality
			<lb />
			counterfeit Indian paper currency, coin or of any other
			<lb />
			material; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iv) damage or destruction of any property in India or in a
			<lb />
			foreign country used or intended to be used for the defence of
			<lb />
			India or in connection with any other purposes of the
			<lb />
			Government of India, any State Government or any of their
			<lb />
			agencies; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) overawes by means of criminal force or the show of criminal
			<lb />
			force or attempts to do so or causes death of any public functionary
			<lb />
			or attempts to cause death of any public functionary; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) detains, kidnaps or abducts any person and threatens to kill or
			<lb />
			injure such person or does any other act in order to compel the
			<lb />
			Government of India, any State Government or the Government of a
			<lb />
			foreign country or an international or inter-governmental
			<lb />
			organisation or any other person to do or abstain from doing any
			<lb />
			act; or (sic)
			<lb />
			commits a terrorist act.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Explanation.-For the purpose of this sub-section,-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) &quot;public functionary&quot; means the constitutional authorities
			<lb />
			or any other functionary notified in the Official Gazette by the
			<lb />
			Central Government as public functionary;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) &quot;high quality counterfeit Indian currency&quot; means the
			<lb />
			counterfeit currency as may be declared after examination by
			<lb />
			an authorised or notified forensic authority that such currency
			<lb />
			imitates or compromises with the key security features as
			<lb />
			specified in the Third Schedule.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) The terrorist act includes an act which constitutes an offence
			<lb />
			within the scope of, and as defined in any of the treaties specified in
			<lb />
			the Second Schedule.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;16. Punishment for terrorist act.-(1) Whoever commits a
			<lb />
			terrorist act shall,-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) if such act has resulted in the death of any person, be punishable
			<lb />
			with death or imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) in any other case, be punishable with imprisonment for a term
			<lb />
			which shall not be less than five years but which may extend to
			<lb />
			imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;17. Punishment for raising funds for terrorist act.-Whoever, in
			<lb />
			India or in a foreign country, directly or indirectly, raises or
			<lb />
			provides funds or collects funds, whether from a legitimate or
			<lb />
			illegitimate source, from any person or persons or attempts to
			<lb />
			provide to, or raises or collects funds for any person or persons,
			<lb />
			knowing that such funds are likely to be used, in full or in part by
			<lb />
			such person or persons or by a terrorist organisation or by a
			<lb />
			terrorist gang or by an individual terrorist to commit a terrorist act,
			<lb />
			notwithstanding whether such funds were actually used or not for
			<lb />
			commission of such act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a
			<lb />
			term which shall not be less than five years but which may extend to
			<lb />
			imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Explanation.-For the purpose of this section,-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) participating, organising or directing in any of the acts
			<lb />
			stated therein shall constitute an offence;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) raising funds shall include raising or collecting or
			<lb />
			providing funds through production or smuggling or
			<lb />
			circulation of high quality counterfeit Indian currency; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) raising or collecting or providing funds, in any manner for
			<lb />
			the benefit of, or, to an individual terrorist, terrorist gang or
			<lb />
			terrorist organisation for the purpose not specifically covered
			<lb />
			under Section 15 shall also be construed as an offence.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;18. Punishment for conspiracy, etc.-Whoever conspires or
			<lb />
			attempts to commit, or advocates, abets, advises or incites, directs
			<lb />
			or knowingly facilitates the commission of, a terrorist act or any
			<lb />
			act preparatory to the commission of a terrorist act, shall be
			<lb />
			punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less
			<lb />
			than five years but which may extend to imprisonment for life, and
			<lb />
			shall also be liable to fine.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;43-D. Modified application of certain provisions of the Code.-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code or any other
			<lb />
			law, every offence punishable under this Act shall be deemed to be a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence within the meaning of clause (c) of Section 2 of
			<lb />
			the Code, and &quot;cognizable case&quot; as defined in that clause shall be
			<lb />
			construed accordingly.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			…..
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(5) Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, no person
			<lb />
			accused of an offence punishable under Chapters IV and VI of this
			<lb />
			Act shall, if in custody, be released on bail or on his own bond
			<lb />
			unless the Public Prosecutor has been given an opportunity of
			<lb />
			being heard on the application for such release:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Provided that such accused person shall not be released on bail or
			<lb />
			on his own bond if the Court, on a perusal of the case diary or the
			<lb />
			report made under Section 173 of the Code is of the opinion that
			<lb />
			there are reasonable grounds for believing that the accusation
			<lb />
			against such person is prima facie true.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(6) The restrictions on granting of bail specified in sub-section (5) is
			<lb />
			in addition to the restrictions under the Code or any other law for
			<lb />
			the time being in force on granting of bail.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Construction of bail provisions under similar
			<lb />
			legislations
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			15. Before we examine the provision relating to bail under UAPA, it would
			<lb />
			benefit if we briefly examine the bail provisions under other similar
			<lb />
			statutes. Grant of bail has been restricted and stringent conditions have
			<lb />
			been engrafted for admitting accused persons on bail under several
			<lb />
			other legislations relating to serious offences. It would be useful at this
			<lb />
			point to allude to the construction placed by the courts upon such
			<lb />
			provisions. A comparative chart of the bail provisions under such
			<lb />
			comparable legislations is given as Annexure -A to this judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Bail under the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic
			<lb />
			Substances Act 1985 (&apos;NDPS Act&apos;)
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			16. Interpreting section 37 of the NDPS Act, in State of Kerala &amp; Ors. vs.
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			Rajesh &amp; Ors. , the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			2
			<lb />
			&quot;20. The expression &quot;reasonable grounds&quot; means something more
			<lb />
			than prima facie grounds. It contemplates substantial probable
			<lb />
			causes for believing that the accused is not guilty of the alleged
			<lb />
			offence. The reasonable belief contemplated in the provision
			<lb />
			requires existence of such facts and circumstances as are
			<lb />
			sufficient in themselves to justify satisfaction that the accused is
			<lb />
			not guilty of the alleged offence. In the case on hand, the High Court
			<lb />
			seems to have completely overlooked the underlying object of
			<lb />
			Section 37 that in addition to the limitations provided under the
			<lb />
			CrPC, or any other law for the time being in force, regulating the
			<lb />
			grant of bail, its liberal approach in the matter of bail under the
			<lb />
			NDPS Act is indeed uncalled for.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			cf. Annexure-A to judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			17. In Union of India vs. Shiv Shanker Kesari , the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			Court has said :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;7. The expression used in Section 37(1)(b)(ii) is &quot;reasonable
			<lb />
			grounds&quot;. The expression means something more than prima facie
			<lb />
			grounds. It connotes substantial probable causes for believing that
			<lb />
			the accused is not guilty of the offence charged and this reasonable
			<lb />
			belief contemplated in turn points to existence of such facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances as are sufficient in themselves to justify recording
			<lb />
			of satisfaction that the accused is not guilty of the offence charged.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;8. The word &quot;reasonable&quot; has in law the prima facie meaning of
			<lb />
			reasonable in regard to those circumstances of which the actor,
			<lb />
			called on to act reasonably, knows or ought to know. It is difficult to
			<lb />
			give an exact definition of the word &quot;reasonable&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;&quot;7. … In Stroud&apos;s Judicial Dictionary, 4th Edn., p.
			<lb />
			2258 states that it would be unreasonable to expect an
			<lb />
			exact definition of the word &apos;reasonable&apos;. Reason varies
			<lb />
			in its conclusions according to the idiosyncrasy of the
			<lb />
			individual, and the times and circumstances in which he
			<lb />
			thinks. The reasoning which built up the old scholastic
			<lb />
			logic sounds now like the jingling of a child&apos;s toy.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(See Municipal Corpn. of Delhi v. Jagan Nath Ashok
			<lb />
			Kumar [(1987) 4 SCC 497] (SCC p. 504, para 7) and
			<lb />
			Gujarat Water Supply and Sewerage Board v. Unique
			<lb />
			Erectors (Gujarat) (P) Ltd. [(1989) 1 SCC 532]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;9. It is often said that &apos;an attempt to give a specific meaning to the
			<lb />
			word &quot;reasonable&quot; is trying to count what is not number and
			<lb />
			measure what is not space&apos;. The author of Words and Phrases
			<lb />
			(Permanent Edn.) has quoted from Nice &amp; Schreiber, In re [123 F
			<lb />
			987 at p. 988] to give a plausible meaning for the said word. He
			<lb />
			says &apos;the expression &quot;reasonable&quot; is a relative term, and the facts
			<lb />
			of the particular controversy must be considered before the
			<lb />
			(2007) 7 SCC 798.
			<lb />
			question as to what constitutes reasonable can be determined&apos;. It is
			<lb />
			not meant to be expedient or convenient but certainly something
			<lb />
			more than that.&quot; [Ed.: As observed in Rena Drego v. Lalchand
			<lb />
			Soni, (1998) 3 SCC 341, p. 346, para 9.]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;10. The word &quot;reasonable&quot; signifies &quot;in accordance with
			<lb />
			reason&quot;. In the ultimate analysis it is a question of fact, whether a
			<lb />
			particular act is reasonable or not depends on the circumstances in
			<lb />
			a given situation. (See Municipal Corpn. of Greater Mumbai v.
			<lb />
			Kamla Mills Ltd. [(2003) 6 SCC 315] )
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;11. The court while considering the application for bail with
			<lb />
			reference to Section 37 of the Act is not called upon to record a
			<lb />
			finding of not guilty. It is for the limited purpose essentially
			<lb />
			confined to the question of releasing the accused on bail that the
			<lb />
			court is called upon to see if there are reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			believing that the accused is not guilty and records its satisfaction
			<lb />
			about the existence of such grounds. But the court has not to
			<lb />
			consider the matter as if it is pronouncing a judgment of acquittal
			<lb />
			and recording a finding of not guilty.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Bail under Terrorist &amp; Disruptive Activities
			<lb />
			(Prevention) Act 1987 (&apos;TADA&apos;)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has interpreted section 20(8) TADA in
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			State of Maharashtra vs. Anand Chintaman Dighe , in the following
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			words :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;5. Sub-section (8) of Section 20 of the Act clearly provides that
			<lb />
			unless the court is satisfied for the reasons to be recorded that there
			<lb />
			are reasonable grounds to believe that the respondent is not
			<lb />
			involved in disruptive activities, bail shall ordinarily be refused.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			cf. Annexure-A to judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			4
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(1990) 1 SCC 397.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of
		</p>
		<item>
			!
			<lb />
			Even under the provisions of Sections 437 and 438 of the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, the powers of the Sessions Judge are not
			<lb />
			unfettered. The salient principles in granting bail in grave crimes
			<lb />
			have not been taken note of.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;7. There are no hard and fast rules regarding grant or refusal of
			<lb />
			bail, each case has to be considered on its own merits. The matter
			<lb />
			always calls for judicious exercise of discretion by the court. Where
			<lb />
			the offence is of serious nature the court has to decide the question
			<lb />
			of grant of bail in the light of such considerations as the nature and
			<lb />
			seriousness of offence, character of the evidence, circumstances
			<lb />
			which are peculiar to the accused, a reasonable possibility of
			<lb />
			presence of the accused not being secured at the trial and the
			<lb />
			reasonable apprehension of witness being tampered with, the larger
			<lb />
			interest of the public or such similar other considerations.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. A Constitutional Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Kartar Singh
			<lb />
			vs. State of Punjab , while inter alia determining the constitutional
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			validity of Section 20(8) of TADA, held:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;341. The learned Additional Solicitor General attempts to meet the
			<lb />
			above arguments stating that there is no question of
			<lb />
			unconstitutionality of the provision and in fact, the conditions
			<lb />
			imposed under clause (b) of sub-section (8) is in consonance with
			<lb />
			the requirements prescribed under clauses (i) and (ii) of sub-section
			<lb />
			(1) of Section 437 and clause (b) of sub-section (3) of that section.
			<lb />
			In any event, according to him, the conduct of an accused seeking
			<lb />
			bail in the context of his background and the nature of crime
			<lb />
			committed are to be evaluated before the concession of bail can be
			<lb />
			granted and that the evaluation is fundamentally from the point of
			<lb />
			view of his likelihood of either tampering with the evidence or
			<lb />
			(1994) 3 SCC 569.
			<lb />
			unleashing a threat to the society during the period when he may
			<lb />
			be allowed to be on bail. He also quotes another observation of
			<lb />
			Krishna Iyer, J. in Gudikanti [(1978) 1 SCC 240] in support of his
			<lb />
			submission which reads : (SCC p. 245, para 12)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;All deprivation of liberty is validated by social defence
			<lb />
			and individual correction along an anti-criminal
			<lb />
			direction. Public justice is central to the whole scheme
			<lb />
			of bail law. Fleeing justice must be forbidden but
			<lb />
			punitive harshness should be minimised. … No seeker
			<lb />
			of justice shall play confidence tricks on the court or
			<lb />
			community.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;352. It is true that on many occasions, we have come across cases
			<lb />
			wherein the prosecution unjustifiably invokes the provisions of the
			<lb />
			TADA Act with an oblique motive of depriving the accused persons
			<lb />
			from getting bail and in some occasions when the courts are
			<lb />
			inclined to grant bail in cases registered under ordinary criminal
			<lb />
			law, the investigating officers in order to circumvent the authority
			<lb />
			of the courts invoke the provisions of the TADA Act. This kind of
			<lb />
			invocation of the provisions of TADA in cases, the facts of which
			<lb />
			do not warrant, is nothing but sheer misuse and abuse of the Act
			<lb />
			by the police. Unless, the public prosecutors rise to the occasion
			<lb />
			and discharge their onerous responsibilities keeping in mind that
			<lb />
			they are prosecutors on behalf of the public but not the police and
			<lb />
			unless the Presiding Officers of the Designated Courts discharge
			<lb />
			their judicial functions keeping in view the fundamental rights
			<lb />
			particularly of the personal right and liberty of every citizen as
			<lb />
			enshrined in the Constitution to which they have been assigned
			<lb />
			the role of sentinel on the qui vive, it cannot be said that the
			<lb />
			provisions of TADA Act are enforced effectively in consonance
			<lb />
			with the legislative intendment.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Bail under Maharashtra Control of Organised
			<lb />
			Crime Act 1999 (&apos;MCOCA&apos;)
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			20. Dealing with section 21 MCOCA, which is the bail provision under
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			that statute, in State of Maharashtra vs. Vishwanath Maranna Shetty ,
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court holds :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;30. The analysis of the relevant provisions of MCOCA, similar
			<lb />
			provision in the NDPS Act and the principles laid down in both the
			<lb />
			decisions shows that substantial probable cause for believing that
			<lb />
			the accused is not guilty of the offence for which he is charged
			<lb />
			must be satisfied. Further, a reasonable belief provided points to
			<lb />
			existence of such facts and circumstances as are sufficient to justify
			<lb />
			the satisfaction that the accused is not guilty of the alleged offence.
			<lb />
			We have already highlighted the materials placed in the case on
			<lb />
			hand and we hold that the High Court has not satisfied the twin tests
			<lb />
			as mentioned above while granting bail.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Bail under Prevention of Terrorism Act 2002
			<lb />
			(&apos;POTA&apos;)
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			21. Section 49 (6) and (7) POTA has been explained by the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in State of T.N. vs R.R. Gopal alias Nakkeeran
			<lb />
			Gopal , as follows :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;12. It is to be seen that at the stage of granting bail, the court does
			<lb />
			not decide the merits of the matter. Of course, a prima facie view
			<lb />
			has to be formed in the court in order to satisfy itself that there are
			<lb />
			cf. Annexure-A to judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(2012) 10 SCC 561.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			cf. Annexure-A to judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			9
			<lb />
		</head>
		<item>
			cf. Annexure-A to judgment.
			<lb />
			grounds for believing that the accused is not guilty of committing the
			<lb />
			offence he is charged with. However, such a prima facie view must
			<lb />
			be based on very cogent material. The High Court has relied on
			<lb />
			alleged discrepancies of the description of the weapon. One must
			<lb />
			keep in mind that the articles recovered have been sent to the court
			<lb />
			and are in custody of the court. It must also be noted that the first of
			<lb />
			the documents, relied upon by the High Court was in Tamil
			<lb />
			language. The other documents are in English. Some police officer
			<lb />
			has translated it from Tamil to English. If some police officer
			<lb />
			wrongly translates the type of weapon one cannot conclude with any
			<lb />
			reasonable certainty that there was no recovery. It is to be seen that
			<lb />
			under Section 4 mere possession not just of an arm but also of an
			<lb />
			ammunition, is sufficient. Ammunition has also been allegedly
			<lb />
			recovered. There is no discrepancy in the description of the
			<lb />
			ammunition. Thus, at this stage it is difficult to sustain the finding of
			<lb />
			the High Court that due to the discrepancies in the description of
			<lb />
			weapon the non-existence of recovery was so probable that the
			<lb />
			Court could act on the supposition that the recovery did not exist.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;14. Further, when bail is granted the court has to ensure that the
			<lb />
			accused would not abscond and/or that he would not tamper with
			<lb />
			the evidence or witnesses. The High Court does not seem to have
			<lb />
			applied its mind to this aspect at all. It has not adverted to these
			<lb />
			matters and made no provisions in respect thereof.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. In Paza Neduraman and Ors vs. State , a Division Bench of the
			<lb />
			12
			<lb />
			Madras High Court has said this :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;6. The language of sub-section (6) of Sec. 49 of POTA, however,
			<lb />
			only suggests that a person accused of an offence punishable under
			<lb />
			this Act (POTA) shall not be released on bail or on his own bond
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2003) SCC OnLine Mad 166.
			<lb />
			12
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			unless the Public Prosecutor is heard by the court. This subsection
			<lb />
			is also being read by the Prosecution as a repository of the power to
			<lb />
			grant bail because of the peculiar language thereof which presumes
			<lb />
			the existence of such a power. The only additional condition added
			<lb />
			by the subsection is the requirement of giving an opportunity to the
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor before the order of release on bail or on bond is
			<lb />
			passed. Sub-section (7), however, is a departure from the normal
			<lb />
			rule in the sense that it heightens the burden on the defence. The
			<lb />
			language suggests that where the Public Prosecutor opposes the
			<lb />
			bail application, such accused could not be released on bail until
			<lb />
			the Court is satisfied that there are grounds for believing that he is
			<lb />
			innocent. The plain meaning would be that instead of showing
			<lb />
			that there is no prima facie case against him for his conviction, the
			<lb />
			accused would have to show that there is a prima facie case for his
			<lb />
			acquittal. Then comes the questioned proviso which suggests that
			<lb />
			after the expiry of one year from the date of detention of the
			<lb />
			accused, the provisions of sub-section (6) of Sec. 49 shall apply. We
			<lb />
			shall go to the other provisions later on but, at this juncture, it
			<lb />
			would be better to see the logic applied by the Special Court.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;8. … The language of sub-section (7) is complementary to
			<lb />
			subsection (6). It suggests that where during such hearing the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor opposes the bail application of the accused then, it
			<lb />
			would have to be shown to the Court and the Court would have to be
			<lb />
			satisfied that there exists some material or ground suggesting that
			<lb />
			the accused is not guilty of committing such offence. Plainly
			<lb />
			speaking, it would be for the defence to plead and prove to the
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the Court a prima facie case for acquittal.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Bail under Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act 1967
			<lb />
			(&apos;UAPA&apos;)
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			23. Opining specifically on section 43D(5) of the UAPA, in its seminal and
			<lb />
			recent verdict in National Investigation Agency vs. Zahoor Ahmad
			<lb />
			Shah Watali , (&apos;Watali&apos;, for short) the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has
			<lb />
			13
			<lb />
			said this:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;23. By virtue of the proviso to sub-section (5), it is the duty of the
			<lb />
			Court to be satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			believing that the accusation against the accused is prima facie
			<lb />
			true or otherwise. Our attention was invited to the decisions of this
			<lb />
			Court, which has had an occasion to deal with similar special
			<lb />
			provisions in TADA and MCOCA. The principle underlying those
			<lb />
			decisions may have some bearing while considering the prayer for
			<lb />
			bail in relation to the offences under the 1967 Act as well. Notably,
			<lb />
			under the special enactments such as TADA, MCOCA and the
			<lb />
			Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985, the Court is
			<lb />
			required to record its opinion that there are reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			believing that the accused is &quot;not guilty&quot; of the alleged offence.
			<lb />
			There is a degree of difference between the satisfaction to be
			<lb />
			recorded by the Court that there are reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			believing that the accused is &quot;not guilty&quot; of such offence and the
			<lb />
			satisfaction to be recorded for the purposes of the 1967 Act that
			<lb />
			there are reasonable grounds for believing that the accusation
			<lb />
			against such person is &quot;prima facie&quot; true. By its very nature, the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;prima facie true&quot; would mean that the materials/
			<lb />
			evidence collated by the investigating agency in reference to the
			<lb />
			accusation against the accused concerned in the first information
			<lb />
			report, must prevail until contradicted and overcome or disproved
			<lb />
			by other evidence, and on the face of it, shows the complicity of
			<lb />
			such accused in the commission of the stated offence. It must be
			<lb />
			good and sufficient on its face to establish a given fact or the
			<lb />
			(2019) 5 SCC 1.
			<lb />
			chain of facts constituting the stated offence, unless rebutted or
			<lb />
			contradicted. In one sense, the degree of satisfaction is lighter
			<lb />
			when the Court has to opine that the accusation is &quot;prima facie
			<lb />
			true&quot;, as compared to the opinion of the accused &quot;not guilty&quot; of
			<lb />
			such offence as required under the other special enactments. In
			<lb />
			any case, the degree of satisfaction to be recorded by the Court for
			<lb />
			opining that there are reasonable grounds for believing that the
			<lb />
			accusation against the accused is prima facie true, is lighter than
			<lb />
			the degree of satisfaction to be recorded for considering a discharge
			<lb />
			application or framing of charges in relation to offences under the
			<lb />
			1967 Act. Nevertheless, we may take guidance from the exposition in
			<lb />
			Ranjitsing Brahmajeetsing Sharma [(2005) 5 SCC 294], wherein a
			<lb />
			three-Judge Bench of this Court was called upon to consider the
			<lb />
			scope of power of the Court to grant bail…
			<lb />
			&quot;24. A priori, the exercise to be undertaken by the Court at this
			<lb />
			stage-of giving reasons for grant or non-grant of bail-is
			<lb />
			markedly different from discussing merits or demerits of the
			<lb />
			evidence. The elaborate examination or dissection of the evidence is
			<lb />
			not required to be done at this stage. The Court is merely expected
			<lb />
			to record a finding on the basis of broad probabilities regarding
			<lb />
			the involvement of the accused in the commission of the stated
			<lb />
			offence or otherwise.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;25. From the analysis of the impugned judgment [Zahoor Ahmad
			<lb />
			Shah Watali v. NIA, 2018 SCC OnLine Del 11185], it appears to us
			<lb />
			that the High Court has ventured into an area of examining the
			<lb />
			merits and demerits of the evidence. For, it noted that the evidence
			<lb />
			in the form of statements of witnesses under Section 161 are not
			<lb />
			admissible. Further, the documents pressed into service by the
			<lb />
			investigating agency were not admissible in evidence. It also noted
			<lb />
			that it was unlikely that the document had been recovered from the
			<lb />
			residence of Ghulam Mohammad Bhatt till 16-8-2017 (para 61 of
			<lb />
			the impugned judgment). Similarly, the approach of the High Court
			<lb />
			in completely discarding the statements of the protected witnesses
			<lb />
			recorded under Section 164 CrPC, on the specious ground that the
			<lb />
			same was kept in a sealed cover and was not even perused by the
			<lb />
			Designated Court and also because reference to such statements
			<lb />
			having been recorded was not found in the charge-sheet already
			<lb />
			filed against the respondent is, in our opinion, in complete disregard
			<lb />
			of the duty of the Court to record its opinion that the accusation
			<lb />
			made against the accused concerned is prima facie true or
			<lb />
			otherwise. That opinion must be reached by the Court not only in
			<lb />
			reference to the accusation in the FIR but also in reference to the
			<lb />
			contents of the case diary and including the charge-sheet (report
			<lb />
			under Section 173 CrPC) and other material gathered by the
			<lb />
			investigating agency during investigation.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;26. Be it noted that the special provision, Section 43-D of the 1967
			<lb />
			Act, applies right from the stage of registration of FIR for the
			<lb />
			offences under Chapters IV and VI of the 1967 Act until the
			<lb />
			conclusion of the trial thereof. To wit, soon after the arrest of the
			<lb />
			accused on the basis of the FIR registered against him, but before
			<lb />
			filing of the charge-sheet by the investigating agency; after filing of
			<lb />
			the first charge-sheet and before the filing of the supplementary or
			<lb />
			final charge-sheet consequent to further investigation under Section
			<lb />
			173(8) CrPC, until framing of the charges or after framing of the
			<lb />
			charges by the Court and recording of evidence of key witnesses,
			<lb />
			etc. However, once charges are framed, it would be safe to assume
			<lb />
			that a very strong suspicion was founded upon the materials
			<lb />
			before the Court, which prompted the Court to form a presumptive
			<lb />
			opinion as to the existence of the factual ingredients constituting
			<lb />
			the offence alleged against the accused, to justify the framing of
			<lb />
			charge. In that situation, the accused may have to undertake an
			<lb />
			arduous task to satisfy the Court that despite the framing of
			<lb />
			charge, the materials presented along with the charge-sheet
			<lb />
			(report under Section 173 CrPC), do not make out reasonable
			<lb />
			grounds for believing that the accusation against him is prima
			<lb />
			facie true. Similar opinion is required to be formed by the Court
			<lb />
			whilst considering the prayer for bail, made after filing of the first
			<lb />
			report made under Section 173 of the Code, as in the present case.
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			&quot;27. For that, the totality of the material gathered by the
			<lb />
			investigating agency and presented along with the report and
			<lb />
			including the case diary, is required to be reckoned and not by
			<lb />
			analysing individual pieces of evidence or circumstance. In any
			<lb />
			case, the question of discarding the document at this stage, on the
			<lb />
			ground of being inadmissible in evidence, is not permissible. For,
			<lb />
			the issue of admissibility of the document/evidence would be a
			<lb />
			matter for trial. The Court must look at the contents of the
			<lb />
			document and take such document into account as it is.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;30. In our opinion, the High Court, having noticed that the
			<lb />
			Designated Court had not looked at the stated statements presented
			<lb />
			in a sealed cover, coupled with the fact that the application under
			<lb />
			Section 44 filed by the investigating agency was pending before the
			<lb />
			Designated Court, and before finally answering the prayer for grant
			<lb />
			of bail, should have directed the Designated Court to first decide the
			<lb />
			said application and if allowed, consider the redacted statements, to
			<lb />
			form its opinion as to whether there are reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			believing that the accusation made against the respondent is prima
			<lb />
			facie true or otherwise. For, in terms of Section 43-D, it is the
			<lb />
			bounden duty of the Court to peruse the case diary and/or the
			<lb />
			report made under Section 173 of the Code and all other relevant
			<lb />
			material/evidence produced by the investigating agency, for
			<lb />
			recording its opinion.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;47. The fact that there is a high burden on the accused in terms of
			<lb />
			the special provisions contained in Section 43-D(5) to demonstrate
			<lb />
			that the prosecution has not been able to show that there exist
			<lb />
			reasonable grounds to show that the accusation against him is
			<lb />
			prima facie true, does not alter the legal position expounded in K.
			<lb />
			Veeraswami [(1991) 3 SCC 655], to the effect that the charge-sheet
			<lb />
			need not contain detailed analysis of the evidence. It is for the
			<lb />
			Court considering the application for bail to assess the material/
			<lb />
			evidence presented by the investigating agency along with the
			<lb />
			report under Section 173 CrPC in its entirety, to form its opinion as
			<lb />
			to whether there are reasonable grounds for believing that the
			<lb />
			accusation against the named accused is prima facie true or
			<lb />
			otherwise.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. Harmonising the power to grant bail on considerations of violation of
			<lb />
			Part-III of the Constitution with the restrictions imposed by UAPA and
			<lb />
			explaining that the nature of section 43D(5) UAPA is less stringent than
			<lb />
			that of section 37 NDPS, in Union of India vs. K.A. Najeeb , a 3-
			<lb />
			14
			<lb />
			Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;17. …at commencement of proceedings, the courts are expected to
			<lb />
			appreciate the legislative policy against grant of bail but the rigours
			<lb />
			of such provisions will melt down where there is no likelihood of
			<lb />
			trial being completed within a reasonable time and the period of
			<lb />
			incarceration already undergone has exceeded a substantial part of
			<lb />
			the prescribed sentence…
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;19. Yet another reason which persuades us to enlarge the
			<lb />
			Respondent on bail is that Section 43-D(5) of the UAPA is
			<lb />
			comparatively less stringent than Section 37 of the NDPS Act.
			<lb />
			Unlike the NDPS where the competent court needs to be satisfied
			<lb />
			that prima facie the accused is not guilty and that he is unlikely to
			<lb />
			commit another offence while on bail; there is no such pre-condition
			<lb />
			under the UAPA. Instead, Section 43-D(5) of UAPA merely provides
			<lb />
			another possible ground for the competent Court to refuse bail, in
			<lb />
			addition to the well-settled considerations like gravity of the
			<lb />
			offence, possibility of tampering with evidence, influencing the
			<lb />
			(2021) 3 SCC 713.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			14
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			witnesses or chance of the accused evading the trial by absconsion
			<lb />
			etc.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Appellant&apos;s Submissions
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. Mr. Siddharth Aggarwal, learned counsel for the appellant has
			<lb />
			principally made the following submissions:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i)
			<lb />
			It is submitted that the subject FIR viz. FIR No. 59/2020 dated
			<lb />
			06.03.2020 registered at P.S.: Crime Branch was initially
			<lb />
			registered under sections 147 / 148 / 149 / 120B IPC, which are
			<lb />
			all bailable offences. Subsequently however, on 19.04.2020
			<lb />
			offences under the UAPA were added to the subject FIR;
			<lb />
			investigation in which is also now complete and subject charge-
			<lb />
			sheet dated 16.09.2020 has now been filed naming 15 accused
			<lb />
			persons in such charge-sheet.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			It is submitted that on a perusal of the subject charge-sheet
			<lb />
			alongwith other material on which the prosecution relies,
			<lb />
			including statements of witnesses (some of which are protected
			<lb />
			witnesses) recorded under sections 161 and 164 Cr.P.C., will
			<lb />
			show that even prima facie no offence is made-out against the
			<lb />
			appellant that would warrant his continued custody;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			It is further submitted that in any event, no offence under
			<lb />
			section 15 of the UAPA, which defines &quot;Terrorist Act&quot; nor any
			<lb />
			offence under section 18 which defines &quot;Punishment for
			<lb />
			Conspiracy, etc.&quot; or any offence engrafted in Chapter IV and/or
			<lb />
			Chapter VI is made-out against the appellant. Consequently, the
			<lb />
			stringent provisions contained in section 43D(5) of the UAPA
			<lb />
			against grant of bail are not attracted at all;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			In the alternative it is submitted, that though the material on
			<lb />
			record does not even make-out the offence of engaging in any
			<lb />
			unlawful activity as defined in section 2(1)(o) and as punishable
			<lb />
			under section 13 of UAPA, even assuming that that issue is
			<lb />
			debatable, the harsh provisions against release on bail under
			<lb />
			section 43D(5) have no application to an offence punishable
			<lb />
			under section 13, since it falls under Chapter III of UAPA;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(v)
			<lb />
			Insofar as the allegations of an offence under section 124A IPC
			<lb />
			are concerned, it is submitted that serious as these allegations
			<lb />
			may be, they are still only to be dealt with under the ordinary
			<lb />
			penal law and do not take the matter into the scope and ambit of
			<lb />
			UAPA; and therefore section 43D(5) UAPA has no application.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. To flesh-out his submissions, Mr. Aggarwal has drawn the attention of
			<lb />
			this court to certain portions of the subject charge-sheet, which portions
			<lb />
			are essentially the same as those referred to by the learned ASG, which
			<lb />
			are extracted and discussed below in this judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Respondent&apos;s Submissions
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. Written Submissions dated 22.03.2021 have been filed on behalf of the
			<lb />
			respondent/Delhi Police, summarising the arguments made by Mr.
			<lb />
			Aman Lekhi, learned Additional Solicitor General appearing on their
			<lb />
			behalf, which are detailed herein below. Dealing with the role of the
			<lb />
			appellant in the offences alleged, the learned ASG has relied upon
			<lb />
			certain portions of the subject FIR and the subject charge-sheet, which
			<lb />
			are extracted as screenshots in Annexure -B to this judgment for ease
			<lb />
			of reference.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i)
			<lb />
			That considering the &quot;totality of evidence, including the
			<lb />
			statements of the protected witnesses, the documentary
			<lb />
			evidence and other evidences collected&quot;, the complicity of the
			<lb />
			appellant in the offences of which he is accused is prima facie
			<lb />
			established, within the meaning of section 43D(5) UAPA. It is
			<lb />
			urged that the test to justify rejection of bail is whether on the
			<lb />
			evidence available it is possible to arrive at the conclusion that
			<lb />
			the case against the appellant is prima facie true. It is not the
			<lb />
			purport of a bail proceeding that evidence be weighed and
			<lb />
			benefit of doubt be given to the appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			It is argued that the present case is one of &quot;serious disturbance
			<lb />
			of public order undermining security of state&quot; as distinguished
			<lb />
			from one directed against the individuals, and the acts in their
			<lb />
			degree, extent and reach justifying the invocation of the
			<lb />
			provisions under which the appellant is accused. Moreover, it is
			<lb />
			submitted that the &quot;context and circumstances in which the acts
			<lb />
			were committed would clearly cause reactions affecting not
			<lb />
			merely specific individuals but disorders of most extreme
			<lb />
			gravity&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			It has been argued that a communally surcharged environment
			<lb />
			was deliberately created by the conspirators, sharply dividing
			<lb />
			the religious communities hardening cleavages and eliminating
			<lb />
			any possibility of consensus, apart from disavowing all belief in
			<lb />
			the efficacy and worth of the existing system and portraying the
			<lb />
			political establishment as inimical to a religious community.
			<lb />
			Having roused sentiments and having created a sense of
			<lb />
			insecurity, the &quot;likelihood that any act or disorder would have
			<lb />
			the potential of tumultuous consequences could not only be
			<lb />
			foreseen but it is apparent that the conspirators desired these
			<lb />
			consequences&quot;; and the intent to disrupt the unity and strike
			<lb />
			terror is obvious. Not merely physical and mental damage but
			<lb />
			prolonged psychological effect was produced affecting the
			<lb />
			society as a whole, disturbing its even tempo and tranquility
			<lb />
			and creating a general sense of fear and insecurity.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			Relying upon Kartar Singh (supra), it has been submitted that
			<lb />
			the proviso to section 43D(5) UAPA bars release on bail if, on
			<lb />
			perusal of the case diary or report under section 173 Cr.P.C., the
			<lb />
			court is of the opinion that there are &quot;reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			believing that the accusations against such persons are prima
			<lb />
			facie true&quot;; and that the source of the power of the Special
			<lb />
			Court to grant bail is not in section 43D(5) UAPA which only
			<lb />
			places limitations on the grant of bail is referable to section 437
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C. since the Special Court is a Court other than the High
			<lb />
			Court and Court of Sessions. While the power of the High
			<lb />
			Court and Court of Sessions to grant bail is conferred by section
			<lb />
			439 Cr.P.C. which, unlike section 437 Cr.P.C., is unfettered by
			<lb />
			any conditions or limitations under section 437 Cr.P.C.,
			<lb />
			however, bail cannot be granted &quot;if there appear to be
			<lb />
			reasonable grounds for believing that an accused is guilty of an
			<lb />
			offence punishable with death or imprisonment for life&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(v)
			<lb />
			Referring to the observations of the Supreme Court in Martin
			<lb />
			Burn Ltd. vs. R.N. Bangerjee , the State has argued that a
			<lb />
			15
			<lb />
			prima facie case does not mean a case proved to the hilt but a
			<lb />
			case which can be said to be established if the evidence which
			<lb />
			is led in support of the same were believed; and that while
			<lb />
			determining whether a prima facie case has been made-out the
			<lb />
			relevant consideration is whether on the evidence led it was
			<lb />
			possible to arrive at the conclusion in question and not whether
			<lb />
			that was the only conclusion which could be arrived at on that
			<lb />
			evidence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			It is also pointed-out that in State of Gujarat vs. Gadhvi
			<lb />
			Rambhai Nathabhai and Ors , while construing section 20(8)
			<lb />
			16
			<lb />
			TADA, which provision imposed a far more onerous
			<lb />
			responsibility than the one under section 43D(5) UAPA, the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held that the power to grant bail cannot
			<lb />
			be exercised in a manner virtually amounting to an order of
			<lb />
			acquittal, giving benefit of doubt to the accused after weighing
			<lb />
			the evidence collected during investigation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vii) The learned ASG has read the verdict of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in Watali (supra) to submit that the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court has said that at the stage of granting or denying bail under
			<lb />
			UAPA, an elaborate examination or dissection of the evidence
			<lb />
			is not required and the court is merely expected to record a
			<lb />
			finding on the basis of broad probabilities regarding the
			<lb />
			AIR 1958 SC 79.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(1994) 5 SC 111.
			<lb />
			16
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			involvement of the accused in the commission of the stated
			<lb />
			offence or otherwise. It is pointed-out that relying on Watali
			<lb />
			(supra), this court in Ghulam Mohd. Bhat vs. National
			<lb />
			Investigating Agency , has said that the determination to be
			<lb />
			17
			<lb />
			made by this court at the stage of dealing with a bail application
			<lb />
			is within a very narrow compass and what the court is required
			<lb />
			to examine is the issue whether there are reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			believing that the accusations made against the appellant are
			<lb />
			&quot;prima facie true&quot;, which means the test to justify rejection of
			<lb />
			bail is whether on the evidence available it is possible to arrive
			<lb />
			at the conclusion that the case against the appellant is prima
			<lb />
			facie true.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(viii) The State says therefore, that the case against the appellant is
			<lb />
			one of conspiracy to commit a crime, which is itself punishable
			<lb />
			as a substantive offence and every individual offence
			<lb />
			committed pursuant to conspiracy is a separate and distinct
			<lb />
			offence; and though all conspirators may not be liable for an
			<lb />
			individual offence, they are all guilty of the offence of
			<lb />
			conspiracy. It is further argued that it not necessary to prove
			<lb />
			that the parties actually came together and expressly agreed to
			<lb />
			have a common design; nor that they knew all details of the
			<lb />
			conspiracy, as long as the conspirators took several steps all
			<lb />
			towards the realisation of the object of conspiracy through a
			<lb />
			continued period of time, which it is urged, the record clearly
			<lb />
			shows in the instant case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(2019) SCC OnLine Del 9431.
			<lb />
			17
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ix)
			<lb />
			It is submitted that a perusal of the record will show that the
			<lb />
			appellant and the other conspirators, by their acts, pursued the
			<lb />
			same object, often by the same means, one performing one part
			<lb />
			of the act and the other performing the other part, so as to
			<lb />
			complete it with a view to attainment of the same object.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(x)
			<lb />
			The State says that even if the objective of the conspiracy did
			<lb />
			not originate with the appellant or he joined after it was formed,
			<lb />
			he would even then be as guilty; and whatever may have been
			<lb />
			said or done by any of the conspirators in pursuance of the
			<lb />
			common design would be considered to be an act of the
			<lb />
			appellant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xi)
			<lb />
			The State in fact submits that despite the unreliability of
			<lb />
			hearsay evidence, it is admissible in conspiracy prosecutions
			<lb />
			and that the rule of admissibility of evidence is relaxed in cases
			<lb />
			of conspiracy, since the principle of agency is attracted.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xii) Most importantly, it is the case of the prosecution, that the
			<lb />
			conspiratorial design contemplated something much more dire
			<lb />
			and malevolent, with repercussions on public tranquility that
			<lb />
			are far more serious than ordinary forms of political protest. It
			<lb />
			is further alleged that the chakkajam which was planned was
			<lb />
			with a &quot;difference&quot; and the intention was &quot;to stop milk and
			<lb />
			water&quot; and was to be done not only in Delhi but in &quot;every place
			<lb />
			where it was possible for Muslims&quot; to organise it. It was
			<lb />
			intended to &quot;cause riots and fear&quot;. To support this submission
			<lb />
			the State draws attention to the portion of the subject charge-
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			sheet extracted as Screenshot 1 and 2 in Annexure -B attached
			<lb />
			to this judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xiii) As evidence of the &quot;general agreement between the
			<lb />
			conspirators with regard to the common purpose&quot;, the State
			<lb />
			draws attention of this court to a portion of the purported
			<lb />
			statement dated 19.06.2020 of one of protected witnesses
			<lb />
			named Hector. To support this submission the State draws
			<lb />
			attention to the portion of the subject charge-sheet extracted as
			<lb />
			Screenshot 3 in Annexure -B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xiv) The State alleges thereby that &quot;a radical approach animated by
			<lb />
			extremist intent giving a different orientation to words of
			<lb />
			ordinary connotation like chakkajam is self-evident&quot;. To support
			<lb />
			this, the State has relied upon page No. 2052 of the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet as well as the statement of a protected witness
			<lb />
			named Bond, which portions are extracted as Screenshot 4 and
			<lb />
			5 in Annexure -B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xv) The CAA only provided an excuse for the agitation, the real
			<lb />
			motivation of which was to denounce the existing system and
			<lb />
			create extreme disenchantment with it. Reliance has been
			<lb />
			placed by the State on the portion at page 2048 of the charge-
			<lb />
			sheet, which has been extracted as Screenshot 6 in Annexure -
			<lb />
			B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xvi) It is argued that the subject charge-sheet further shows that the
			<lb />
			actions of the conspirators was premeditated, which is apparent
			<lb />
			from the meetings of 16.12.2019 and 17.12.2019, which
			<lb />
			followed the protest at the Parliament and at Jamia University
			<lb />
			on 13.12.2019 and 15.12.2019 respectively; and the two events
			<lb />
			having failed to yield desired results, the conspirators realised
			<lb />
			that stray or isolated events would not serve in achieving the
			<lb />
			objective of widespread turmoil, for which reason at the
			<lb />
			meetings of 16.12.2019 and 17.12.2019, in which the appellant
			<lb />
			had also participated, it was decided to hold protests in &quot;an
			<lb />
			organised and planned way&quot; and for this purpose the JCC was
			<lb />
			constituted; which, it is alleged, used religious identity as the
			<lb />
			tool to achieve its objectives. To support this submission,
			<lb />
			attention of the court is invited to pages 2045, 2057-59,
			<lb />
			2067-68 and 2070 of the subject charge-sheet, which portions
			<lb />
			are extracted as Screenshot 7, 8a-8c, 9a-9b and 10 in Annexure
			<lb />
			-B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xvii) The above alleged objective of the JCC is stated to be
			<lb />
			corroborated by the statements recorded under section 164
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C. of the protected witness Bond and James.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xviii) The State contends that the object of JCC, with which the
			<lb />
			appellant is alleged to have been associated, was aligned with
			<lb />
			that of Muslim Students of JNU being run by one of the co-
			<lb />
			accused/co-conspirator; and was to debunk the secular values of
			<lb />
			the Constitution and to aggravate differences between the
			<lb />
			communities so as to cause social disharmony and bring out a
			<lb />
			feeling of disunity.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xix) It is also alleged that the co-conspirators committed themselves
			<lb />
			to &quot;avoiding over secularisation of movement&quot;, for which
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			reference is made to portions of pages 2025 -26 of the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet, which are extracted as Screenshot 11 in Annexure
			<lb />
			-B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xx) It is contended that the pamphlets were inflammatory and
			<lb />
			incendiary, were deliberately provocative and seditious in
			<lb />
			content and clearly undermined the State. In this regard the
			<lb />
			State refers to page 2040 of the subject charge-sheet, which is
			<lb />
			extracted as Screenshot 12 in Annexure -B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxi) Mr. Lekhi contends that the CAA had nothing to do with Indian
			<lb />
			Muslims; that there was no project to disenfranchise and
			<lb />
			definitely nothing to justify the allegation that Muslims will be
			<lb />
			put in detention camps. It is alleged that the endeavour of the
			<lb />
			co-conspirators was therefore only to inflame passions, whip-up
			<lb />
			religious frenzy and foment violence. The &quot;burning&quot; of Assam,
			<lb />
			&quot;killing&quot; of people and &quot;disruption&quot; of Delhi was intended
			<lb />
			towards that end.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxii) It is urged that there was thus, an &quot;emphasis upon division and
			<lb />
			polarisation through narrowing the areas of mutual engagement
			<lb />
			b y e m p h a s i s i n g e t h n o c u l t u r a l n a t i o n a l i s m o v e r
			<lb />
			cosmopolitanism and using the excuse of a political protest to
			<lb />
			give primacy to religion&quot;; and a general disenchantment was
			<lb />
			sought to be created affecting the security of the State.
			<lb />
			Reference in this regard was made by the State to the statement
			<lb />
			dated 25.06.2020 of protected witness named Romeo, which is
			<lb />
			extracted as Screenshot 13 in Annexure -B, alleging that the
			<lb />
			actions therefore had the tendency of creating public disorder of
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			the most extreme gravity and demonstrated not just disaffection
			<lb />
			to the country but disloyalty to it.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxiii) Though it is conceded that the appellant was excluded from the
			<lb />
			JCC after he was named in other FIRs, it is contended that such
			<lb />
			exclusion was nominal and the appellant continued to be
			<lb />
			associated with and participated in the objects of the conspiracy,
			<lb />
			which it is alleged, is apparent from his involvement in the
			<lb />
			meeting at Jamia University on 22.02.2020.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxiv) It is argued that the &quot;voice of sanity&quot; (allegedly of one of the
			<lb />
			protected witness) was shut-out. Attention of the court was
			<lb />
			drawn in this regard to portions of pages 2205-06 of the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet, which portions are extracted as Screenshot
			<lb />
			14a-14b in Annexure -B; and it is submitted that the ill-boding
			<lb />
			intent of the secrecy of the real objective was apparent from the
			<lb />
			message of one of the co-conspirator / co-accused advising
			<lb />
			members from desisting sharing the real plans of conspirators in
			<lb />
			public. Reference in this regard was made to the portion of the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet extracted as Screenshot 15 in Annexure -
			<lb />
			B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxv) It is alleged that in pursuance of the object, the &quot;continued
			<lb />
			steps&quot; towards the &quot;shared intent&quot; is apparent from page 2210
			<lb />
			of the subject charge-sheet, which portion is extracted as
			<lb />
			Screenshot 16 in Annexure -B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxvi) The State further argues that the appellant was part of the JCC
			<lb />
			meeting which was held on 22.02.2020 which further shows
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			that his so-called exclusion on 24.01.2020 was &quot;mere trickery
			<lb />
			to disguise his continued involvement and participation in the
			<lb />
			conspiracy&quot;; and that he &quot;remained party&quot; to the plan to affect
			<lb />
			public tranquility by &quot;engineering riots&quot;. To support this
			<lb />
			allegation, the State relies upon the statement of protected
			<lb />
			witnesses Bond and James which have been extracted as
			<lb />
			Screenshot 17 and 18 in Annexure -B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxvii) It is urged that the fact that the protest planned was &quot;not a
			<lb />
			typical protest&quot; normal in the political culture or democracy but
			<lb />
			one far more evil and injurious geared towards extremely grave
			<lb />
			consequences. To bolster this contention, the State relies upon
			<lb />
			alleged statements of protected witness Victor (page 1527-1531
			<lb />
			of the subject charge-sheet), Silver (page 1542-1545), Ct. Sunil
			<lb />
			(page 1662-1667), Ct. (GD) Mukesh (page 1681-1682), HC
			<lb />
			(GD) G. Nallaperumal (page 1682-1684 ) and Ct. (GD) Srinivas
			<lb />
			Rao (page 1684-1685), SI. Bheesham Rana (page 1801-1802)
			<lb />
			and Harender at (page 1802-1803), which are extracted as
			<lb />
			Screenshot 19a-19e, 20a-20c, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25 and 26 in
			<lb />
			Annexure -B.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxviii)It is alleged that the breach of public order was neither small
			<lb />
			nor insignificant but was grave and serious affecting public
			<lb />
			tranquility, impacting unity and integrity and creating terror;
			<lb />
			and that not merely law and order was affected but the even
			<lb />
			&quot;tempo of the life of the community was also disturbed&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxix) The State contends that the subject charge-sheet shows that
			<lb />
			there were 53 deaths including those of public functionaries,
			<lb />
			over seven hundred people were injured, deployment of an
			<lb />
			additional police force of 7800 was needed over and above the
			<lb />
			2200 policemen already deployed; that &quot;protests were
			<lb />
			coordinated across Delhi and covered diverse areas like Jamia,
			<lb />
			Seelampur, Khajuri, Hauzrani, Khureji and Jafrabad&quot;, with
			<lb />
			there being plans to extend this protest across other cities of the
			<lb />
			country; and that there was extensive and widespread
			<lb />
			destruction of property involving settlement of claims of
			<lb />
			approximately Rs. 22 crores. As many as 16,381 PCR calls
			<lb />
			were received between 22.02.2020 and 26.02.2020; and
			<lb />
			cartridges, knives and swords, broken glass bottle (used for
			<lb />
			petrol bombs) and even scissors were weaponised and loose
			<lb />
			stones were liberally used.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxx) It is argued that the activity in its essential quality may not be
			<lb />
			different from another act but in its potentiality and in its effect
			<lb />
			upon public tranquility there can be a vast difference. Reliance
			<lb />
			in this behalf is placed on the decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in Arun Ghosh vs. State of West Bengal , :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			18
			<lb />
			&quot;3. … Take for instance, a man stabs another. People
			<lb />
			may be shocked and even disturbed, but the life of the
			<lb />
			community keeps moving at an even tempo, however
			<lb />
			much one may dislike the act. Take another case of a
			<lb />
			town where there is communal tension. A man stabs a
			<lb />
			member of the other community. This is an act of a
			<lb />
			very different sort. Its implications are deeper and it
			<lb />
			affects the even tempo of life and public order is
			<lb />
			(1970) 1 SCC 98.
			<lb />
			jeopardized because the repercussions of the act
			<lb />
			embrace large sections of the community and incite
			<lb />
			them to make further breaches of the law and order
			<lb />
			and to subvert the public order. An act by itself is not
			<lb />
			determinant of its own gravity. In its quality it may not
			<lb />
			differ from another but in its potentiality it may be very
			<lb />
			different. …&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(xxxi) It is further argued that the same principle was reiterated by the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Giridhari Parmanand Vadhava vs.
			<lb />
			State of Maharashtra , in the context of what constitutes a
			<lb />
			19
			<lb />
			terrorist act, where the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court holds that it is
			<lb />
			the impact of the crime and its fallout on the society and
			<lb />
			potentiality of such crime in producing fear in the minds of the
			<lb />
			people or a section of the people which makes a crime, a
			<lb />
			terrorist activity under section 3(1) of TADA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxxii) Much emphasis was laid by the learned ASG on the word
			<lb />
			&apos;likely&apos; being part of section 15, to urge that even presuming
			<lb />
			that &apos;intention&apos; is not held to be disclosed on the appellant&apos;s
			<lb />
			part, the &apos;likelihood&apos; of what section 15 contemplates will
			<lb />
			attract the provision. It is argued that the word &apos;likely&apos; means
			<lb />
			&quot;of such nature or so circumstantial as to make probable&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxxiii)The State accordingly alleges that the actions of the co-
			<lb />
			conspirators, including the appellant were (i) premeditated (ii)
			<lb />
			directed at a wider audience (iii) involved attacks on symbolic
			<lb />
			targets including civilians (iv) entailed acts of violence seen by
			<lb />
			the society as &quot;extra normal&quot; intended to provoke an
			<lb />
			(1996) 11 SCC 179.
			<lb />
			19
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			overreaction serving as a catalyst for more general conflict and
			<lb />
			publicised as a political cause inducing both fear and a sense of
			<lb />
			insecurity, by reason of which the characteristics of &apos;terrorism&apos;
			<lb />
			as set-out by Paul Wilikson and cited in People&apos;s Union For
			<lb />
			Civil Liberties and Anr. vs. Union of India , (&apos;PUCL&apos;, for
			<lb />
			20
			<lb />
			short) and Mohd. Iqbal M. Shaikh and Ors. vs. State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra are duly satisfied. The State argues that under
			<lb />
			21
			<lb />
			the UAPA, it is not just the intent to threaten the unity and
			<lb />
			integrity but the likelihood to threaten the unity and integrity,
			<lb />
			not just the intent to strike terror but the likelihood to strike
			<lb />
			terror, not just the use of firearms but the use of any means of
			<lb />
			whatsoever nature, the means not just causing but likely to
			<lb />
			cause not just death but injuries to any person or persons or loss
			<lb />
			or damage or destruction of property, constitutes terrorist act
			<lb />
			within the meaning of section 15 of UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxxiv)It is urged that moreover, under section 18 of UAPA, not merely
			<lb />
			conspiracy to commit a terrorist act but an attempt to commit or
			<lb />
			advocating the commission or advising it or inciting or
			<lb />
			directing or knowingly facilitating commission of a terrorist act
			<lb />
			is also punishable. In fact, even acts preparatory to commission
			<lb />
			of terrorist acts are punishable under section 18 of UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxxv) It is submitted that the objection of the appellant that a case is
			<lb />
			not made-out under UAPA is based on assessing the degree of
			<lb />
			sufficiency and credibility of evidence not the absence of its
			<lb />
			(2004) 9 SCC 580.
			<lb />
			20
			<lb />
			(1998) 4 SCC 494.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			existence but the extent of its applicability; but that such
			<lb />
			objection of the appellant is outside the scope of section 43D(5)
			<lb />
			of the UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xxxvi)Distinguishing the present case from that in K.A. Najeeb
			<lb />
			(supra), the State argues that the reason for grant of bail in that
			<lb />
			case was &quot;long period of incarceration and unlikelihood of the
			<lb />
			trial being completed anytime in the near future&quot;; and that in
			<lb />
			K.A. Najeeb (supra), the High Court had relied upon a judgment
			<lb />
			of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Shaheen Welfare Association
			<lb />
			vs. Union of India and Ors , wherein it was held that &quot;no one
			<lb />
			22
			<lb />
			can justify gross delay in disposal of cases when undertrial
			<lb />
			perforce remains in jail giving rise to possible situations that
			<lb />
			may justify invocation of Article 21&quot;; and that the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court did not interfere with the order passed by the
			<lb />
			High Court because of &quot;there being no likelihood of trial being
			<lb />
			completed within the reasonable time and the period of
			<lb />
			incarceration already undergone has exceeded a substantial part
			<lb />
			of the prescribed sentence&quot;. It is pointed-out that in State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra vs. Abdul Hamid Haji Mohammed ,
			<lb />
			23
			<lb />
			notwithstanding section 19 of TADA providing for an appeal to
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court from an order passed by the Designated
			<lb />
			Court, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court had yet held that in extreme
			<lb />
			cases where accusations are ex facie not constituting an offence,
			<lb />
			power under Article 226 of the Constitution can be invoked but
			<lb />
			(1996) 2 SC 616.
			<lb />
			22
			<lb />
			(1994) 2 SCC 664.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			that in the present case the appellant has not chosen to invoke
			<lb />
			Article 226 of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Analysis of section 15 UAPA
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			28. Before applying the additional conditions engrafted in section 43D(5)
			<lb />
			UAPA, it would be advisable to first analyse if the allegations against
			<lb />
			the appellant contained in the subject charge-sheet even prima facie
			<lb />
			disclose the commission of an offence under sections 15 and 18 of the
			<lb />
			UAPA. Although section 15 of the UAPA defines &apos;terrorist act&apos; and
			<lb />
			section 18 provides for &apos;punishment for conspiracy for committing a
			<lb />
			terrorist act, including an attempt to commit or advocating, abetting,
			<lb />
			advising or inciting the commission of a terrorist act, as also of any act
			<lb />
			preparatory to the commission of a terrorist act&apos;, the word &apos;terrorism&apos; or
			<lb />
			&apos;terror&apos; has nowhere been defined in the UAPA. For completeness it
			<lb />
			may be noticed that section 2(1)(k) of the UAPA says that the phrase
			<lb />
			&apos;terrorist act&apos; shall have the meaning as assigned to it in section 15 and
			<lb />
			that the expressions &apos;terrorism&apos; and &apos;terrorist&apos; shall be construed
			<lb />
			accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			29. What however, is &apos;terrorism&apos; or &apos;terror&apos;, from which the meaning of
			<lb />
			&apos;terrorist act&apos; and other related words may be derived?
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. The concept and construction of terrorism has been dealt-with by the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in relation to earlier legislations inter alia in
			<lb />
			the decisions discussed below.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31. In Hitendra Vishnu Thakur &amp; Ors. vs. State of Maharashtra &amp; Ors. ,
			<lb />
			24
			<lb />
			defining terrorism, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says :
			<lb />
			(1994) 4 SCC 602.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;7. &apos;Terrorism&apos; is one of the manifestations of increased
			<lb />
			lawlessness and cult of violence. Violence and crime constitute a
			<lb />
			threat to an established order and are a revolt against a civilised
			<lb />
			society. &apos;Terrorism&apos; has not been defined under TADA nor is it
			<lb />
			possible to give a precise definition of &apos;terrorism&apos; or lay down what
			<lb />
			constitutes &apos;terrorism&apos;. It may be possible to describe it as use of
			<lb />
			violence when its most important result is not merely the physical
			<lb />
			and mental damage of the victim but the prolonged psychological
			<lb />
			effect it produces or has the potential of producing on the society
			<lb />
			as a whole. There may be death, injury, or destruction of property
			<lb />
			or even deprivation of individual liberty in the process but the
			<lb />
			extent and reach of the intended terrorist activity travels beyond
			<lb />
			the effect of an ordinary crime capable of being punished under
			<lb />
			the ordinary penal law of the land and its main objective is to
			<lb />
			overawe the Government or disturb harmony of the society or
			<lb />
			&quot;terrorise&quot; people and the society and not only those directly
			<lb />
			assaulted, with a view to disturb even tempo, peace and tranquillity
			<lb />
			of the society and create a sense of fear and insecurity. A &apos;terrorist&apos;
			<lb />
			activity does not merely arise by causing disturbance of law and
			<lb />
			order or of public order. The fall out of the intended activity must
			<lb />
			be such that it travels beyond the capacity of the ordinary law
			<lb />
			enforcement agencies to tackle it under the ordinary penal law.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Experience has shown us that &apos;terrorism&apos; is generally an attempt to
			<lb />
			acquire or maintain power or control by intimidation and causing
			<lb />
			fear and helplessness in the minds of the people at large or any
			<lb />
			section thereof and is a totally abnormal phenomenon. What
			<lb />
			distinguishes &apos;terrorism&apos; from other forms of violence, therefore,
			<lb />
			appears to be the deliberate and systematic use of coercive
			<lb />
			intimidation. More often than not, a hardened criminal today takes
			<lb />
			advantage of the situation and by wearing the cloak of &apos;terrorism&apos;,
			<lb />
			aims to achieve for himself acceptability and respectability in the
			<lb />
			society because unfortunately in the States affected by militancy, a
			<lb />
			&apos;terrorist&apos; is projected as a hero by his group and often even by the
			<lb />
			misguided youth. It is therefore, essential to treat such a criminal
			<lb />
			and deal with him differently than an ordinary criminal capable of
			<lb />
			being tried by the ordinary courts under the penal law of the land.
			<lb />
			Even though the crime committed by a &apos;terrorist&apos; and an ordinary
			<lb />
			criminal would be overlapping to an extent but then it is not the
			<lb />
			intention of the Legislature that every criminal should be tried
			<lb />
			under TADA, where the fall out of his activity does not extend
			<lb />
			beyond the normal frontiers of the ordinary criminal activity.
			<lb />
			Every &apos;terrorist&apos; may be a criminal but every criminal cannot be
			<lb />
			given the label of a &apos;terrorist&apos; only to set in motion the more
			<lb />
			stringent provisions of TADA. The criminal activity in order to
			<lb />
			invoke TADA must be committed with the requisite intention as
			<lb />
			contemplated by Section 3(1) of the Act by use of such weapons as
			<lb />
			have been enumerated in Section 3(1) and which cause or are likely
			<lb />
			to result in the offences as mentioned in the said section.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32. TADA deals with activity &quot;which cannot be classified as a mere law
			<lb />
			and order problem or disturbance of public order or even disturbance of
			<lb />
			the even tempo of the life of the community of any specified locality,
			<lb />
			but is of the nature which cannot be tackled as an ordinary criminal
			<lb />
			activity under the ordinary penal law by the normal law enforcement
			<lb />
			agencies because the intended extent and reach of the criminal activity
			<lb />
			of the &apos;terrorist&apos; is such which travels beyond the gravity of the mere
			<lb />
			disturbance of public order even of a &apos;virulent nature&apos; and may at times
			<lb />
			transcend the frontiers of the locality...&quot;, as explained by the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in Kartar Singh (supra) :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;68. The terrorism, the Act (TADA) contemplates, cannot be
			<lb />
			classified as mere disturbance of &apos;public order&apos; disturbing the
			<lb />
			&quot;even tempo of the life of community of any specified locality&quot; -
			<lb />
			in the words of Hidayatullah, C.J. in Arun Ghosh v. State of W.B.
			<lb />
			[(1970) 1 SCC 98] but it is much more, rather a grave emergent
			<lb />
			situation created either by external forces particularly at the
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			frontiers of this country or by anti-nationals throwing a challenge
			<lb />
			to the very existence and sovereignty of the country in its
			<lb />
			democratic polity.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			33. Since the theme of section 15 is evidently the intent or likelihood of an
			<lb />
			act threatening (i) the security of the State, described variously in the
			<lb />
			section as unity, integrity, security, economic security, sovereignty and
			<lb />
			(ii) of striking terror, it is necessary to understand the concept and
			<lb />
			distinction between &quot;law and order&quot;, &quot;public order&quot; and &quot;security of
			<lb />
			the State&quot;, as eloquently explained by Hidayatullah, J. (as the learned
			<lb />
			Chief Justice then was) of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Ram
			<lb />
			Manohar Lohia (Dr) vs. State of Bihar :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			25
			<lb />
			&quot;55. It will thus appear that just as &quot;public order&quot; in the rulings of
			<lb />
			this Court (earlier cited) was said to comprehend disorders of less
			<lb />
			gravity than those affecting &quot;security of State&quot;, &quot;law and order&quot;
			<lb />
			also comprehends disorders of less gravity than those affecting
			<lb />
			&quot;public order&quot;.
		</item>
		<head>
			One has to imagine three concentric circles. Law
			<lb />
			and order represents the largest circle within which is the next
			<lb />
			circle representing public order and the smallest circle represents
			<lb />
			security of State. It is then easy to see that an act may affect law
			<lb />
			and order but not public order just as an act may affect public
			<lb />
			order but not security of the State.…
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			34. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Kartar Singh (supra) observed:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;67. In order to ascertain the pith and substance of the impugned
			<lb />
			enactments, the preamble, Statement of Objects and Reasons, the
			<lb />
			legal significance and the intendment of the provisions of these
			<lb />
			Acts, their scope and the nexus with the object that these Acts seek
			<lb />
			to subserve must be objectively examined in the background of the
			<lb />
			AIR 1966 SC 740.
			<lb />
			25
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			totality of the series of events -due to the unleashing of terrorism,
			<lb />
			waves after waves, leading to the series of bomb blasts causing
			<lb />
			extensive damage to the properties, killing of hundreds of people,
			<lb />
			the blood-curdling incidents during which the blood of the sons of
			<lb />
			the soil had been spilled over the soil of their motherland itself, the
			<lb />
			ruthless massacre of the defenceless and innocent people especially
			<lb />
			of poor as if they were all &apos;marked for death&apos; or for &apos;human
			<lb />
			sacrifice&apos; and the sudden outbreak of violence, mass killing of army
			<lb />
			personnel, jawans of Border Security Force, government officials,
			<lb />
			politicians, statesmen, heads of religious sects by using bombs and
			<lb />
			sophisticated lethal weapons thereby injecting a sense of insecurity
			<lb />
			in the minds of the people, with the intention of destabilizing the
			<lb />
			sovereignty or overthrowing the Government as established by law.
			<lb />
			The way in which the alleged violent crimes is shown to have been
			<lb />
			perpetrated, the manner in which they have been cruelly executed,
			<lb />
			the vulnerable territorial frontiers which form part of the scene of
			<lb />
			unprecedented and unprovoked occurrences, lead to an
			<lb />
			inescapable illation and conclusion that the activities of the
			<lb />
			terrorists and disruptionists pose a serious challenge to the very
			<lb />
			existence of sovereignty as well as to the security of India
			<lb />
			notwithstanding the fact whether such threats or challenges come by
			<lb />
			way of external aggression or internal disturbance.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;113. Though normally the plain ordinary grammatical meaning of
			<lb />
			an enactment affords the best guide and the object of interpreting a
			<lb />
			statute is to ascertain the intention of the legislature enacting it,
			<lb />
			other methods of extracting the meaning can be resorted to if the
			<lb />
			language is contradictory, ambiguous or leads really to absurd
			<lb />
			results so as to keep at the real sense and meaning. See (1)
			<lb />
			Salmond : Jurisprudence, 11th Edn. p. 152, (2) South Asia
			<lb />
			Industries (P) Ltd. v. S. Sarup Singh [AIR 1966 SC 346, 348] (AIR
			<lb />
			at p. 348), and (3) G. Narayanaswami v. G. Panneerselvam [(1972)
			<lb />
			3 SCC 717] (SCC at p. 720).&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. Illustrating what terrorist acts might be, in PUCL (supra), the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court says :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;6. In all acts of terrorism, it is mainly the psychological element
			<lb />
			that distinguishes it from other political offences, which are
			<lb />
			invariably accompanied with violence and disorder. Fear is
			<lb />
			induced not merely by making civilians the direct targets of violence
			<lb />
			but also by exposing them to a sense of insecurity. It is in this
			<lb />
			context that this Court held in Mohd. Iqbal M. Shaikh v. State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra [(1998) 4 SCC 494] that: (SCC p. 504, para 7)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;[I]t is not possible to give a precise definition of
			<lb />
			terrorism or to lay down what constitutes terrorism. But
			<lb />
			… it may be possible to describe it as use of violence
			<lb />
			when its most important result is not merely the
			<lb />
			physical and mental damage of the victim but the
			<lb />
			prolonged psychological effect it produces or has the
			<lb />
			potential of producing on the society as a whole. … if
			<lb />
			the object of the activity is to disturb harmony of the
			<lb />
			society or to terrorize people and the society with a view
			<lb />
			to disturb the even tempo, tranquillity of the society, and
			<lb />
			a sense of fear and insecurity is created in the minds of a
			<lb />
			section of the society at large, then it will, undoubtedly,
			<lb />
			be held to be a terrorist act.&quot;
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;8. All these terrorist strikes have certain common features. They
			<lb />
			could be very broadly grouped into three:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			1. Attack on the institution of democracy, which is the
			<lb />
			very basis of our country (by attacking Parliament,
			<lb />
			Legislative Assembly etc.). And the attack on economic
			<lb />
			system by targeting economic nerve centres.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			2. Attack on symbols of national pride and on security/
			<lb />
			strategic installations (e.g. Red Fort, military
			<lb />
			installations and camps, radio stations etc.).
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			3. Attack on civilians to generate terror and fear
			<lb />
			psychosis among the general populace. The attack at
			<lb />
			worshipping places to injure sentiments and to whip
			<lb />
			communal passions. These are designed to position the
			<lb />
			people against the Government by creating a feeling of
			<lb />
			insecurity.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;9. Terrorist acts are meant to destabilise the nation by
			<lb />
			challenging its sovereignty and integrity, to raze the constitutional
			<lb />
			principles that we hold dear, to create a psyche of fear and
			<lb />
			anarchism among common people, to tear apart the secular fabric,
			<lb />
			to overthrow democratically elected government, to promote
			<lb />
			prejudice and bigotry, to demoralise the security forces, to thwart
			<lb />
			the economic progress and development and so on. This cannot be
			<lb />
			equated with a usual law and order problem within a State. On the
			<lb />
			other hand, it is inter-State, international or cross-border in
			<lb />
			character. Fight against the overt and covert acts of terrorism is
			<lb />
			not a regular criminal justice endeavour. Rather, it is defence of
			<lb />
			our nation and its citizens. It is a challenge to the whole nation
			<lb />
			and invisible force of Indianness that binds this great nation
			<lb />
			together. Therefore, terrorism is a new challenge for law
			<lb />
			enforcement. By indulging in terrorist activities organised groups or
			<lb />
			individuals, trained, inspired and supported by fundamentalists and
			<lb />
			anti-Indian elements are trying to destabilise the country. This new
			<lb />
			breed of menace was hitherto unheard of. Terrorism is definitely a
			<lb />
			criminal act, but it is much more than mere criminality. Today the
			<lb />
			Government is charged with the duty of protecting the unity,
			<lb />
			integrity, secularism and sovereignty of India from terrorists, both
			<lb />
			from outside and within the borders. To face terrorism we need new
			<lb />
			approaches, techniques, weapons, expertise and of course new laws.
			<lb />
			In the abovesaid circumstances Parliament felt that a new anti-
			<lb />
			terrorism law is necessary for a better future. This parliamentary
			<lb />
			resolve is epitomised in POTA.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36. More recently in Yakub Abdul Razak Memon vs State of Maharashtra
			<lb />
			through CBI, Bombay , the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held:
			<lb />
			26
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;809. The term &quot;terrorism&quot; is a concept that is commonly and
			<lb />
			widely used in everyday parlance and is derived from the Latin word
			<lb />
			&quot;terror&quot; which means the state of intense fear and submission to it.
			<lb />
			There is no particular form of terror, hence, anything intended to
			<lb />
			create terror in the minds of general public in order to endanger the
			<lb />
			lives of the members and damage to public property may be termed
			<lb />
			as a terrorist act and a manifestation of terrorism. Black&apos;s Law
			<lb />
			Dictionary defines terrorism as:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;Terrorism.-The use or threat of violence to intimidate
			<lb />
			or cause panic, esp. as a means of affecting political
			<lb />
			conduct.&quot; (8th Edn., p. 1512.)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;810. Terrorism is a global phenomenon in today&apos;s world and India
			<lb />
			is one of the worst victims of terrorist acts. Terrorism has a long
			<lb />
			history of being used to achieve political, religious and ideological
			<lb />
			objectives. Acts of terrorism can range from threats to actual
			<lb />
			assassinations, kidnappings, airline hijackings, bomb scares, car
			<lb />
			bombs, building explosions, mailing of dangerous materials,
			<lb />
			computer based attacks and the use of chemical, biological, and
			<lb />
			nuclear weapons-weapons of mass destruction (WMD).
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;
		</item>
		<p>
			816. The United Nations Security Council in its 2004 Resolution
			<lb />
			[Ed. : UN Doc. S/RES/1566 (2004); Resolution 1566 (2004)
			<lb />
			adopted by the Security Council on 8-10-2004.] denounced
			<lb />
			&quot;terrorist acts&quot; as follows&quot;
			<lb />
			&quot;criminal acts, including against civilians, committed
			<lb />
			with the intent to cause death or serious bodily injury,
			<lb />
			or taking of hostages, with the purpose to provoke a
			<lb />
			state of terror in the general public or in a group of
			<lb />
			(2013) 13 SCC 1.
			<lb />
			26
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			persons or particular persons, intimidate a population
			<lb />
			or compel a Government or an international
			<lb />
			organisation to do or abstain from doing any act,
			<lb />
			which constitute offences within the scope of and as
			<lb />
			defined in the international conventions and protocols
			<lb />
			relating to terrorism, are under no circumstances
			<lb />
			justifiable by considerations or a political,
			<lb />
			philosophical, ideological, racial, ethnic, religious or
			<lb />
			other similar nature,...&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37. In Zameer Ahmed Latifur Rehman Sheikh vs. State of Maharashtra
			<lb />
			&amp; Ors , dealing with the constitutionality of MCOCA and opining on
			<lb />
			27
			<lb />
			the distinction between &apos;public order&apos; and &apos;security of the State&apos;, the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says :
			<lb />
			&quot;31. It has been time and again held by this Court that the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;public order&quot; is of a wide connotation. In Romesh
			<lb />
			Thappar v. State of Madras [AIR 1950 SC 124] it has been held by
			<lb />
			this Court that &quot;public order&quot; signifies a state of tranquillity which
			<lb />
			prevails among the members of a political society as a result of
			<lb />
			internal regulations enforced by the Government which they have
			<lb />
			established. This Court, in para 10, at AIR p. 128, quoted a passage
			<lb />
			from Stephen&apos;s Criminal Law of England, wherein he observed as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Unlawful assemblies, riots, insurrections, rebellions,
			<lb />
			levying of war, are offences which run into each other
			<lb />
			and are not capable of being marked off by perfectly
			<lb />
			defined boundaries. All of them have in common one
			<lb />
			feature, namely, that the normal tranquillity of a
			<lb />
			civilised society is in each of the cases mentioned
			<lb />
			(2010) 5 SCC 246.
			<lb />
			27
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			disturbed either by actual force or at least by the show
			<lb />
			and threat of it.&quot;
			<lb />
			This Court further observed that though all these offences
			<lb />
			involve disturbances of public tranquillity and are in theory
			<lb />
			offences against public order, the difference between them is
			<lb />
			only one of degree. The Constitution thus requires a line,
			<lb />
			perhaps only a rough line, to be drawn between the fields of
			<lb />
			public order or tranquillity and those serious and aggravated
			<lb />
			forms of public disorder which are calculated to endanger
			<lb />
			the security of the State.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;32. In Supdt., Central Prison v. Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia [AIR
			<lb />
			1960 SC 633] this Court had held that &quot;public order&quot; is
			<lb />
			synonymous with public safety and tranquillity, and it is the
			<lb />
			absence of any disorder involving a breach of local significance in
			<lb />
			contradistinction to national upheavals, such as revolution, civil
			<lb />
			strife, war, affecting the security of the State.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;33. Subsequently, in Ram Manohar Lohia (Dr.) v. State of Bihar
			<lb />
			[AIR 1966 SC 740], Hidayatullah, J., held that any contravention of
			<lb />
			law always affected order, but before it could be said to affect
			<lb />
			public order, it must affect the community at large. He was of the
			<lb />
			opinion that offences against &quot;law and order&quot;, &quot;public order&quot;, and
			<lb />
			&quot;security of State&quot; are demarcated on the basis of their gravity. The
			<lb />
			said observation is as follows: (AIR pp. 758-59, para 52)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;52. It will thus appear that just as &apos;public order&apos; in the
			<lb />
			rulings of this Court (earlier cited) was said to
			<lb />
			comprehend disorders of less gravity than those
			<lb />
			affecting &apos;security of State&apos;, &apos;law and order&apos; also
			<lb />
			comprehends disorders of less gravity than those
			<lb />
			affecting &apos;public order&apos;. One has to imagine three
			<lb />
			concentric circles. Law and order represents the largest
			<lb />
			circle within which is the next circle representing public
			<lb />
			order and the smallest circle represents security of State.
			<lb />
			It is then easy to see that an act may affect law and
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			order but not public order just as an act may affect
			<lb />
			public order but not security of the State.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;34. The Constitution Bench of this Court in Madhu Limaye v. Sub-
			<lb />
			Divisional Magistrate, Monghyr [(1970) 3 SCC 746] while
			<lb />
			adopting and explaining the scope of the test laid down in Ram
			<lb />
			Manohar Lohia (Dr.) v. State of Bihar [AIR 1966 SC 740] stated
			<lb />
			that the State is at the centre of the society. Disturbances in the
			<lb />
			normal functioning of the society fall into a broad spectrum, from
			<lb />
			mere disturbance of the serenity of life to jeopardy of the State. The
			<lb />
			acts become more and more grave as we journey from the periphery
			<lb />
			of the largest circle towards the centre. In this journey we travel first
			<lb />
			through public tranquillity, then through public order and lastly to
			<lb />
			the security of the State. This Court further held that in the judgment
			<lb />
			of this Court, the expression &quot;in the interest of public order&quot; as
			<lb />
			mentioned in the Constitution of India encompasses not only those
			<lb />
			acts which disturb the security of the State or acts within ordre
			<lb />
			publique as described but also certain acts which disturb public
			<lb />
			tranquillity or are breaches of the peace. It is not necessary to give
			<lb />
			the expression a narrow meaning because, as has been observed, the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;in the interest of public order&quot; is very wide.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. In the same judgment observing that a court must always presume that
			<lb />
			a statute was within the legislative competence of the legislature that
			<lb />
			drafted it, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court further says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;39. It is also a cardinal rule of interpretation that there shall
			<lb />
			always be a presumption of constitutionality in favour of a statute
			<lb />
			and while construing such statute every legally permissible effort
			<lb />
			should be made to keep the statute within the competence of the
			<lb />
			State Legislature. (Reference may be made to Charanjit Lal
			<lb />
			Chowdhury v. Union of India [AIR 1951 SC 41], T.M.A. Pai
			<lb />
			Foundation v. State of Karnataka [(2002) 8 SCC 481] and
			<lb />
			Karnataka Bank Ltd. v. State of A.P. [(2008) 2 SCC 254] )&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39. In the same judgment the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has also explained
			<lb />
			the intention of Legislature in enacting UAPA and has said that UAPA
			<lb />
			falls under Entry 1 of List-I of the Seventh Schedule of the
			<lb />
			Constitution:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;64. Prior to the 2004 Amendment, UAPA did not contain the
			<lb />
			provisions to deal with terrorism and terrorist activities. By the 2004
			<lb />
			Amendment, new provisions were inserted in UAPA to deal with
			<lb />
			terrorism and terrorist activities. The Preamble of UAPA was also
			<lb />
			amended to state that the said Act is enacted to provide for the more
			<lb />
			effective prevention of certain unlawful activities of individuals and
			<lb />
			associations, and dealing with terrorist activities and for matters
			<lb />
			connected therewith.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			&quot;
		</p>
		<p>
			65. In the 2008 Amendment, the Preamble has again been amended
			<lb />
			and the amended Preamble now also contains a reference to the
			<lb />
			Resolution adopted by the Security Council of the United Nations on
			<lb />
			28-9-2001 and also makes reference to the other resolutions passed
			<lb />
			by the Security Council requiring the States (nations which are
			<lb />
			members of the United Nations) to take action against certain
			<lb />
			terrorist and terrorist organisations. It also makes reference to the
			<lb />
			order issued by the Central Government in exercise of power under
			<lb />
			Section 2 of the United Nations (Security Council) Act, 1947 which
			<lb />
			is known as the Prevention and Suppression of Terrorism
			<lb />
			(Implementation of Security Council Resolutions) Order, 2007.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;72. The precise reason why we have extracted the list of terrorist
			<lb />
			organisations under UAPA hereinbefore is to bring to the fore the
			<lb />
			contrast between the two legislations which are in question before
			<lb />
			us. The exhaustive list of terrorist organisations in the First
			<lb />
			Schedule to UAPA has been included in order to show the type and
			<lb />
			nature of the organisations contemplated under that Act. A careful
			<lb />
			look of the same would indicate that all the organisations
			<lb />
			mentioned therein have as their aims and objects undermining
			<lb />
			and prejudicially affecting the integrity and sovereignty of India,
			<lb />
			which certainly stand on a different footing when compared to the
			<lb />
			activities carried out by the forces like the appellant.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;75. A perusal of the Preamble, the Statement of Objects and
			<lb />
			Reasons and the interpretation clauses of MCOCA and UAPA would
			<lb />
			show that both the Acts operate in different fields and the ambit
			<lb />
			and scope of each is distinct from the other. So far as MCOCA is
			<lb />
			concerned, it principally deals with prevention and control of
			<lb />
			criminal activity by organised crime syndicate or gang within India
			<lb />
			and its purpose is to curb a wide range of criminal activities
			<lb />
			indulged in by organised syndicate or gang. The aim of UAPA, on
			<lb />
			the other hand, is to deal with terrorist and certain unlawful
			<lb />
			activities, which are committed with the intent to threaten the
			<lb />
			unity, integrity, security or sovereignty of India or with the intent
			<lb />
			to strike terror in the people or any section of the people in India
			<lb />
			or in any foreign country or relate to cessation or secession of the
			<lb />
			territory of India.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;77. The offence of terrorist act under Section 15 and the offence of
			<lb />
			unlawful activity under Section 2(1)(o) of UAPA have some elements
			<lb />
			in commonality. The essential element in both is the challenge or
			<lb />
			threat or likely threat to the sovereignty, security, integrity and
			<lb />
			unity of India. While Section 15 requires some physical act like use
			<lb />
			of bombs and other weapons, etc., Section 2(1)(o) takes in its
			<lb />
			compass even written or spoken words or any other visible
			<lb />
			representation intended or which supports a challenge to the unity,
			<lb />
			sovereignty, integrity and security of India. The said offences are
			<lb />
			related to the defence of India and are covered by Entry 1 of the
			<lb />
			Union List.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;78. Moreover, the meaning of the term &quot;unlawful activity&quot; in
			<lb />
			MCOCA is altogether different from the meaning of the term
			<lb />
			&quot;unlawful activity&quot; in UAPA. It is also pertinent to note that MCOCA
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			does not deal with the terrorist organisations which indulge in
			<lb />
			terrorist activities and similarly, UAPA does not deal with organised
			<lb />
			gangs or crime syndicate of the kind specifically targeted by
			<lb />
			MCOCA. Thus, the offence of organised crime under MCOCA and the
			<lb />
			offence of terrorist act under UAPA operate in different fields and
			<lb />
			are of different kinds and their essential contents and ingredients are
			<lb />
			altogether different.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40. Another sacrosanct principle of interpretation of penal provisions is
			<lb />
			that they must be construed strictly and narrowly, to ensure that a
			<lb />
			person who was not within the legislative intendment does not get
			<lb />
			roped into a penal provision. Also, the more stringent a penal provision,
			<lb />
			the more strictly it must be construed. A brief reference to the decisions
			<lb />
			of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in this behalf may be made here.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41. In A.K. Roy vs. Union of India and Ors. , dealing with the validity of
			<lb />
			28
			<lb />
			certain provisions of the National Security Ordinance/Act, which were
			<lb />
			challenged as unconstitutional on the ground of vagueness, and which
			<lb />
			ordinance provided for preventive detention, the majority of a 5-Judge
			<lb />
			Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court partly accepted the challenge,
			<lb />
			holding that what constitutes &apos;essential services and supplies&apos; should
			<lb />
			have been specified and published in advance by a law, order or
			<lb />
			notification, and says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;62. The requirement that crimes must be defined with appropriate
			<lb />
			definiteness is regarded as a fundamental concept in criminal law
			<lb />
			and must now be regarded as a pervading theme of our
			<lb />
			Constitution since the decision in Maneka Gandhi [AIR 1978 SC
			<lb />
			597]. The underlying principle is that every person is entitled to be
			<lb />
			(1982) 1 SCC 271.
			<lb />
			28
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			informed as to what the State commands or forbids and that the
			<lb />
			life and liberty of a person cannot be put in peril on an ambiguity.
			<lb />
			However, even in the domain of criminal law, the processes of which
			<lb />
			can result in the taking away of life itself, no more than a reasonable
			<lb />
			degree of certainty has to be accepted as a fact. Neither the criminal
			<lb />
			law nor the Constitution requires the application of impossible
			<lb />
			standards and therefore, what is expected is that the language of
			<lb />
			the law must contain an adequate warning of the conduct which
			<lb />
			may fall within the proscribed area, when measured by common
			<lb />
			understanding. In criminal law, the legislature frequently uses
			<lb />
			vague expressions like &apos;bring into hatred or contempt&apos;, or
			<lb />
			&apos;maintenance of harmony between different religious groups&apos;, or
			<lb />
			&apos;likely to cause disharmony or … hatred or ill will&apos;, or &apos;annoyance
			<lb />
			to the public&apos; [see Sections 124-A, 153-A(1)(b), 153-B(1)(c), and
			<lb />
			268 of the Penal Code]. These expressions, though they are
			<lb />
			difficult to define, do not elude a just application to practical
			<lb />
			situations. The use of language carries with it the inconvenience
			<lb />
			of the imperfections of language.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;63. We see that the concepts aforesaid, namely, &apos;defence of
			<lb />
			India&apos;, &apos;security of India&apos;, &apos;security of the State&apos; and &apos;relations of
			<lb />
			India with foreign powers&apos;, which are mentioned in Section 3 of
			<lb />
			the Act, are not of any great certainty or definiteness. But in the
			<lb />
			very nature of things they are difficult to define. We cannot
			<lb />
			therefore strike down these provisions of Section 3 of the Act on the
			<lb />
			ground of their vagueness and uncertainty. We must, however, utter
			<lb />
			a word of caution that since the concepts are not defined,
			<lb />
			undoubtedly because they are not capable of a precise definition,
			<lb />
			courts must strive to give to those concepts a narrower
			<lb />
			construction than what the literal words suggest. While construing
			<lb />
			laws of preventive detention like the National Security Act, care
			<lb />
			must be taken to restrict their application to as few situations as
			<lb />
			possible. Indeed, that can well be the unstated premise for
			<lb />
			upholding the constitutionality of clauses like those in Section 3,
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			which are fraught with grave consequences to personal liberty, if
			<lb />
			construed liberally.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;64. What we have said above in regard to the expressions
			<lb />
			&apos;defence of India&apos;, &apos;security of India&apos;, &apos;security of the State&apos; and
			<lb />
			&apos;relations of India with foreign powers&apos; cannot apply to the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance
			<lb />
			of supplies and services essential to the community&quot; which occurs
			<lb />
			in Section 3(2) of the Act. Which supplies and services are
			<lb />
			essential to the community can easily be defined by the legislature
			<lb />
			and indeed, legislations which regulate the prices and possession of
			<lb />
			essential commodities either enumerate those commodities or confer
			<lb />
			upon the appropriate Government the power to do so. In the
			<lb />
			absence of a definition of &apos;supplies and services essential to the
			<lb />
			community&apos;, the detaining authority will be free to extend the
			<lb />
			application of this clause of sub-section (2) to any commodities or
			<lb />
			services the maintenance of supply of which, according to him, is
			<lb />
			essential to the community.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;65. But that is not all. The Explanation to sub-section (2) gives to
			<lb />
			the particular phrase in that sub-section a meaning which is not
			<lb />
			only uncertain but which, at any given point of time, will be difficult
			<lb />
			to ascertain or fasten upon. … We find it quite difficult to
			<lb />
			understand as to which are the remaining commodities outside the
			<lb />
			scope of the Act of 1980, in respect of which it can be said that the
			<lb />
			maintenance of their supplies is essential to the community. The
			<lb />
			particular clause in sub-section (2) of Section 3 of the National
			<lb />
			Security Act is, therefore, capable of wanton abuse in that, the
			<lb />
			detaining authority can place under detention any person for
			<lb />
			possession of any commodity on the basis that the authority is of
			<lb />
			the opinion that the maintenance of supply of that commodity is
			<lb />
			essential to the community. We consider the particular clause not
			<lb />
			only vague and uncertain but, in the context of the Explanation,
			<lb />
			capable of being extended cavalierly to supplies, the maintenance of
			<lb />
			which is not essential to the community. To allow the personal
			<lb />
			liberty of the people to be taken away by the application of that
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			clause would be a flagrant violation of the fairness and justness of
			<lb />
			procedure which is implicit in the provisions of Article 21.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;67. We do not, however, propose to strike down the power given to
			<lb />
			detain persons under Section 3(2) on the ground that they are acting
			<lb />
			in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of supplies and
			<lb />
			services essential to the community. The reason for this is that it is
			<lb />
			vitally necessary to ensure a steady flow of supplies and services
			<lb />
			which are essential to the community, and if the State has the power
			<lb />
			to detain persons on the grounds mentioned in Section 3(1) and the
			<lb />
			other grounds mentioned in Section 3(2), it must also have the
			<lb />
			power to pass orders of detention on this particular ground. What
			<lb />
			we propose to do is to hold that no person can be detained with a
			<lb />
			view to preventing him from acting in any manner prejudicial to
			<lb />
			the maintenance of supplies and services essential to the
			<lb />
			community unless, by a law, order or notification made or
			<lb />
			published fairly in advance, the supplies and services, the
			<lb />
			maintenance of which is regarded as essential to the community
			<lb />
			and in respect of which the order of detention is proposed to be
			<lb />
			passed, are made known appropriately, to the public.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			42. In Sanjay Dutt vs State through CBI (II) , a 5-Judge Constitution
			<lb />
			29
			<lb />
			Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court cites with approval its decision in
			<lb />
			Niranjan Singh Karam Singh Punjabi vs Jitendra Bhimraj Bijjaya ,
			<lb />
			30
			<lb />
			and says :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;17. … Applying the settled rule of construction of penal statutes in
			<lb />
			Niranjan Singh Karam Singh Punjabi v. Jitendra Bhimraj Bijjaya
			<lb />
			[(1990) 4 SCC 76], a Division Bench of this Court speaking through
			<lb />
			(1994) 5 SCC 410.
			<lb />
			29
			<lb />
			(1990) 4 SCC 76.
			<lb />
			30
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			one of us (Ahmadi, J.) construing certain provisions of the TADA Act
			<lb />
			reiterated the principle thus: (SCC pp. 85-86, para 8)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;The Act is a penal statute. Its provisions are drastic in
			<lb />
			that they provide minimum punishments and in certain
			<lb />
			cases enhanced punishments also; make confessional
			<lb />
			statements made to a police officer not below the rank of
			<lb />
			a Superintendent of Police admissible in evidence and
			<lb />
			mandates raising of a rebuttable presumption on proof
			<lb />
			of facts stated in clauses (a) to (d) of sub-section (1) of
			<lb />
			Section 21. Provision is also made in regard to the
			<lb />
			identification of an accused who is not traced through
			<lb />
			photographs. There are some of the special provisions
			<lb />
			introduced in the Act with a view to controlling the
			<lb />
			menace of terrorism. These provisions are a departure
			<lb />
			from the ordinary law since the said law was found to be
			<lb />
			inadequate and not sufficiently effective to deal with the
			<lb />
			special class of offenders indulging in terrorist and
			<lb />
			disruptive activities. There can, therefore, be no doubt
			<lb />
			that the legislature considered such crimes to be of an
			<lb />
			aggravated nature which could not be checked or
			<lb />
			controlled under the ordinary law and enacted deterrent
			<lb />
			provisions to combat the same. The legislature,
			<lb />
			therefore, made special provisions which can in certain
			<lb />
			respects be said to be harsh, created a special forum for
			<lb />
			the speedy disposal of such cases, provided for raising a
			<lb />
			presumption of guilt, placed extra restrictions in regard
			<lb />
			to the release of the offender on bail, and made suitable
			<lb />
			changes in the procedure with a view to achieving its
			<lb />
			objects. It is well settled that statutes which impose a
			<lb />
			term of imprisonment for what is a criminal offence
			<lb />
			under the law must be strictly construed.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Therefore when a law visits a person with serious penal
			<lb />
			consequences extra care must be taken to ensure that
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			those whom the legislature did not intend to be covered
			<lb />
			by the express language of the statute are not roped in
			<lb />
			by stretching the law.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			With respect, we fully concur with the above perception for
			<lb />
			construing the provisions of the TADA Act&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			43. In Ranjitsing Brahmajeetsing Sharma vs. State of Maharashtra and
			<lb />
			Anr , a 3-Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			31
			<lb />
			&quot;23. Interpretation clauses contained in Sections 2(d), 2(e) and 2(f)
			<lb />
			are interrelated. An &quot;organised crime syndicate&quot; refers to an
			<lb />
			&quot;organised crime&quot; which in turn refers to &quot;continuing unlawful
			<lb />
			activity&quot;. As at present advised, it may not be necessary for us to
			<lb />
			consider as to whether the words &quot;or other unlawful means&quot;
			<lb />
			c o n t a i n e d i n S e c t i o n 2 ( e ) s h o u l d b e re a d &quot; e j u s d e m
			<lb />
			generis&quot;/&quot;noscitur a sociis&quot; with the words (i) violence, (ii) threat
			<lb />
			of violence, (iii) intimidation, or (iv) coercion. We may, however,
			<lb />
			notice that the word &quot;violence&quot; has been used only in Sections 146
			<lb />
			and 153-A of the Penal Code, 1860. The word &quot;intimidation&quot; alone
			<lb />
			has not been used therein but only Section 506 occurring in Chapter
			<lb />
			XXII thereof refers to &quot;criminal intimidation&quot;. The word &quot;coercion&quot;
			<lb />
			finds place only in the Contract Act. If the words &quot;unlawful means&quot;
			<lb />
			are to be widely construed as including any or other unlawful
			<lb />
			means, having regard to the provisions contained in Sections 400,
			<lb />
			401 and 413 IPC relating to commission of offences of cheating or
			<lb />
			criminal breach of trust, the provisions of the said Act can be
			<lb />
			applied, which prima facie, does not appear to have been intended
			<lb />
			by Parliament.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			&quot;
		</p>
		<p>
			24. The Statement of Objects and Reasons clearly states as to why
			<lb />
			the said Act had to be enacted. Thus, it will be safe to presume that
			<lb />
			the expression &quot;any unlawful means&quot; must refer to any such act
			<lb />
			(2005) 5 SCC 294.
			<lb />
			31
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of
		</p>
		<item>
			!
			<lb />
			which has a direct nexus with the commission of a crime which
			<lb />
			MCOCA seeks to prevent or control. In other words, an offence
			<lb />
			falling within the definition of organised crime and committed by an
			<lb />
			organised crime syndicate is the offence contemplated by the
			<lb />
			Statement of Objects and Reasons. There are offences and offences
			<lb />
			under the Penal Code, 1860 and other penal statutes providing for
			<lb />
			punishment of three years or more and in relation to such offences
			<lb />
			more than one charge-sheet may be filed. As we have indicated
			<lb />
			hereinbefore, only because a person cheats or commits a criminal
			<lb />
			breach of trust, more than once, the same by itself may not be
			<lb />
			sufficient to attract the provisions of MCOCA. Furthermore, mens
			<lb />
			rea is a necessary ingredient for commission of a crime under
			<lb />
			MCOCA.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;38. We are furthermore of the opinion that the restrictions on the
			<lb />
			power of the court to grant bail should not be pushed too far. If the
			<lb />
			court, having regard to the materials brought on record, is
			<lb />
			satisfied that in all probability he may not be ultimately convicted,
			<lb />
			an order granting bail may be passed. ...What would further be
			<lb />
			necessary on the part of the court is to see the culpability of the
			<lb />
			accused in his involvement in the commission of an organised crime
			<lb />
			either directly or indirectly. The court at the time of considering the
			<lb />
			application for grant of bail shall consider the question from the
			<lb />
			angle as to whether he was possessed of the requisite mens rea.…&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			44. To complete the analysis as regards the presumption of constitutionality
			<lb />
			of a statute, a brief reference may also be made to this presumption as
			<lb />
			explained succinctly in Shri Ram Krishna Dalmia &amp; Ors. vs. Shri
			<lb />
			Justice S.R. Tendolkar &amp; Ors , where a 5-Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			32
			<lb />
			Supreme Court says:
			<lb />
			AIR 1958 SC 538.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			&quot;11. …The principle enunciated above has been consistently
			<lb />
			adopted and applied in subsequent cases. The decisions of this
			<lb />
			Court further establish-
			<lb />
			…
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(c) that it must be presumed that the legislature understands
			<lb />
			and correctly appreciates the need of its own people, that its
			<lb />
			laws are directed to problems made manifest by experience
			<lb />
			and that its discriminations are based on adequate
			<lb />
			grounds;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d) that the legislature is free to recognise degrees of harm
			<lb />
			and may confine its restrictions to those cases where the
			<lb />
			need is deemed to be the clearest;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e) that in order to sustain the presumption of
			<lb />
			constitutionality the court may take into consideration
			<lb />
			matters of common knowledge, matters of common report,
			<lb />
			the history of the times and may assume every state of facts
			<lb />
			which can be conceived existing at the time of legislation;
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(f) that while good faith and knowledge of the existing
			<lb />
			conditions on the part of a legislature are to be presumed, if
			<lb />
			there is nothing on the face of the law or the surrounding
			<lb />
			circumstances brought to the notice of the court on which the
			<lb />
			classification may reasonably be regarded as based, the
			<lb />
			presumption of constitutionality cannot be carried to the
			<lb />
			extent of always holding that there must be some undisclosed
			<lb />
			and un-known reasons for subjecting certain individuals or
			<lb />
			corporations to hostile or discriminating legislation.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			The above principles will have to be constantly borne in mind by the
			<lb />
			court when it is called upon to adjudge the constitutionality of any
			<lb />
			particular law attacked as discriminatory and violative of the equal
			<lb />
			protection of the laws.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45. Since the event that led to the registration of the subject FIR arose from
			<lb />
			a protest allegedly organised and arranged inter alia by the appellant, it
			<lb />
			would be worthwhile at this point to appreciate the constitutional
			<lb />
			protection offered under our jurisprudence to the &apos;right to protest&apos;,
			<lb />
			which right has been repeatedly and unequivocally been held to be part
			<lb />
			of the fundamental rights guaranteed under our Constitution. The right
			<lb />
			to protest has been discussed and expatiated in various judgements, a
			<lb />
			reference to some of which is made below.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			46. In Mazdoor Kisan Shakti Sangathan vs Union of India and Anr , the
			<lb />
			33
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;48. …Undoubtedly, holding peaceful demonstrations by the
			<lb />
			citizenry in order to air its grievances and to ensure that these
			<lb />
			grievances are heard in the relevant quarters, is its fundamental
			<lb />
			right. This right is specifically enshrined under Articles 19(1)(a)
			<lb />
			and 19(1)(b) of the Constitution of India. Article 19(1)(a) confers a
			<lb />
			very valuable right on the citizens, namely, right of free speech.
			<lb />
			Likewise, Article 19(1)(b) gives the right to assemble peacefully and
			<lb />
			without arms. Together, both these rights ensure that the people of
			<lb />
			this country have the right to assemble peacefully and protest
			<lb />
			against any of the actions or the decisions taken by the
			<lb />
			Government or other governmental authorities which are not to
			<lb />
			the liking. Legitimate dissent is a distinguishable feature of any
			<lb />
			democracy. Question is not as to whether the issue raised by the
			<lb />
			protestors is right or wrong or it is justified or unjustified. The
			<lb />
			fundamental aspect is the right which is conferred upon the
			<lb />
			affected people in a democracy to voice their grievances.
			<lb />
			Dissenters may be in minority. They have a right to express their
			<lb />
			views. A particular cause which, in the first instance, may appear
			<lb />
			to be insignificant or irrelevant may gain momentum and
			<lb />
			(2018) 17 SCC 324.
			<lb />
			33
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			acceptability when it is duly voiced and debated. That is the reason
			<lb />
			that this Court has always protected the valuable right of peaceful
			<lb />
			and orderly demonstrations and protests.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;49. In Babulal Parate v. State of Maharashtra [AIR 1961 SC
			<lb />
			884], this Court observed: (AIR p. 891, para 31)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;31. The right of citizens to take out processions or to
			<lb />
			hold public meetings flows from the right in Article
			<lb />
			19(1)(b) to assemble peaceably and without arms and
			<lb />
			the right to move anywhere in the territory of India.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;50. In Kameshwar Prasad v. State of Bihar [AIR 1962 SC 1166]
			<lb />
			the Court was mainly dealing with the question whether the right to
			<lb />
			make a demonstration is protected under Articles 19(1)(a) and (b)
			<lb />
			and whether a government servant is entitled to this right. This
			<lb />
			Court held: (AIR p. 1171, para 13)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;13. … A demonstration might take the form of an
			<lb />
			assembly and even then the intention is to convey to
			<lb />
			the person or authority to whom the communication is
			<lb />
			intended the feelings of the group which assembles. It
			<lb />
			necessarily follows that there are forms of
			<lb />
			demonstration which would fall within the freedoms
			<lb />
			guaranteed by Articles 19(1)(a) and 19(1)(b). It is
			<lb />
			needless to add that from the very nature of things a
			<lb />
			demonstration may take various forms; it may be noisy
			<lb />
			and disorderly, for instance stone-throwing by a crowd
			<lb />
			may be cited as an example of a violent and disorderly
			<lb />
			demonstration and this would not obviously be within
			<lb />
			Article 19(1)(a) or (b). It can equally be peaceful and
			<lb />
			orderly such as happens when the members of the group
			<lb />
			merely wear some badge drawing attention to their
			<lb />
			grievances.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;51. The Supreme Court has also gone beyond upholding the
			<lb />
			right to protest as a fundamental right and has held that the State
			<lb />
			must aid the right to assembly of the citizens. In the Constitution
			<lb />
			Bench judgment, Himat Lal K. Shah v. Commr. of Police [(1973)
			<lb />
			1 SCC 227], while dealing with the challenge to the Rules framed
			<lb />
			under the Bombay Police Act regulating public meetings on streets,
			<lb />
			held that the Government has power to regulate which includes
			<lb />
			prohibition of public meetings on streets or highways to avoid
			<lb />
			nuisance or disruption to traffic and thus, it can provide a public
			<lb />
			meeting on roads, but it does not mean that the Government can
			<lb />
			close all the streets or open areas for public meetings, thus
			<lb />
			denying the fundamental right which flows from Articles 19(1)(a)
			<lb />
			and (b). The Court held: (SCC pp. 239 &amp; 248, paras 33 &amp; 70)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;33. This is true but nevertheless the State cannot by
			<lb />
			law abridge or take away the right of assembly by
			<lb />
			prohibiting assembly on every public street or public
			<lb />
			place. The State can only make regulations in aid of
			<lb />
			the right of assembly of each citizen and can only
			<lb />
			impose reasonable restrictions in the interest of public
			<lb />
			order.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			70. Public meeting in open spaces and public streets
			<lb />
			forms part of the tradition of our national life. In the
			<lb />
			pre-Independence days such meetings have been held
			<lb />
			in open space and public streets and the people have
			<lb />
			come to regard it as a part of their privileges and
			<lb />
			immunities. The State and the local authority have a
			<lb />
			virtual monopoly of every open space at which an
			<lb />
			outdoor meeting can be held. If, therefore, the State or
			<lb />
			Municipality can constitutionally close both its streets
			<lb />
			and its parks entirely to public meetings, the practical
			<lb />
			result would be that it would be impossible to hold any
			<lb />
			open-air meetings in any large city. The real problem is
			<lb />
			that of reconciling the city&apos;s function of providing for
			<lb />
			the exigencies of traffic in its streets and for the
			<lb />
			recreation of the public in its parks, with its other
			<lb />
			obligations, of providing adequate places for public
			<lb />
			discussion in order to safeguard the guaranteed right
			<lb />
			of public assembly. The assumption made by Justice
			<lb />
			Holmes is that a city owns its parks and highways in the
			<lb />
			same sense and with the same rights as a private owner
			<lb />
			owns his property with the right to exclude or admit
			<lb />
			anyone he pleases. That may not accord with the
			<lb />
			concept of dedication of public streets and parks. The
			<lb />
			parks are held for public and the public streets are also
			<lb />
			held for the public. It is doubtless true that the State or
			<lb />
			local authority can regulate its property in order to
			<lb />
			serve its public purposes. Streets and public parks exist
			<lb />
			primarily for other purposes and the social interest
			<lb />
			promoted by untrammelled exercise of freedom of
			<lb />
			utterance and assembly in public street must yield to
			<lb />
			social interest which prohibition and regulation of
			<lb />
			speech are designed to protect. But there is a
			<lb />
			constitutional difference between reasonable regulation
			<lb />
			and arbitrary exclusion.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;52. While adjudicating with respect to the validity of police action
			<lb />
			against protestors, this Court again reiterated that right to protest
			<lb />
			was a fundamental right guaranteed to the citizens under Article
			<lb />
			19. In Ramlila Maidan Incident, In re [(2012) 5 SCC 1], the Court
			<lb />
			observed that the right to assembly and peaceful agitations were
			<lb />
			basic features of a democratic system and the Government should
			<lb />
			encourage exercise of these rights: (SCC p. 99, para 245)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;245. Freedom of speech, right to assemble and
			<lb />
			demonstrate by holding dharnas and peaceful
			<lb />
			agitations are the basic features of a democratic
			<lb />
			system. The people of a democratic country like ours
			<lb />
			have a right to raise their voice against the decisions
			<lb />
			and actions of the Government or even to express their
			<lb />
			resentment over the actions of the Government on any
			<lb />
			subject of social or national importance. The
			<lb />
			Government has to respect and, in fact, encourage
			<lb />
			exercise of such rights. It is the abundant duty of the
			<lb />
			State to aid the exercise of the right to freedom of speech
			<lb />
			as understood in its comprehensive sense and not to
			<lb />
			throttle or frustrate exercise of such rights by exercising
			<lb />
			its executive or legislative powers and passing orders or
			<lb />
			taking action in that direction in the name of reasonable
			<lb />
			restrictions. The preventive steps should be founded on
			<lb />
			actual and prominent threat endangering public order
			<lb />
			and tranquillity, as it may disturb the social order. This
			<lb />
			delegated power vested in the State has to be exercised
			<lb />
			with great caution and free from arbitrariness. It must
			<lb />
			serve the ends of the constitutional rights rather than to
			<lb />
			subvert them.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;53. Further, in Anita Thakur [(2016) 15 SCC 525], the Court
			<lb />
			recognised that the right to peaceful protest was a fundamental
			<lb />
			right under Articles 19(1), (b) and (c) of the Constitution, subject to
			<lb />
			reasonable restrictions. It was finally held that in that while the
			<lb />
			protestors turned violent first, the police used excessive force: (SCC
			<lb />
			pp. 533-34, paras 12-13 &amp; 15)
			<lb />
			&quot;12. ..... The &quot;right to assemble&quot; is beautifully captured
			<lb />
			in an eloquent statement that &quot;an unarmed, peaceful
			<lb />
			protest procession in the land of &quot;salt satyagraha&quot;, fast-
			<lb />
			unto-death and &quot;do or die&quot; is no jural anathema&quot;. It
			<lb />
			hardly needs elaboration that a distinguishing feature
			<lb />
			of any democracy is the space offered for legitimate
			<lb />
			dissent. One cherished and valuable aspect of political
			<lb />
			life in India is a tradition to express grievances through
			<lb />
			direct action or peaceful protest. Organised, non-violent
			<lb />
			protest marches were a key weapon in the struggle for
			<lb />
			Independence, and the right to peaceful protest is now
			<lb />
			recognised as a fundamental right in the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			13. Notwithstanding above, it is also to be borne in
			<lb />
			mind that the aforesaid rights are subject to reasonable
			<lb />
			restrictions in the interest of the sovereignty and
			<lb />
			integrity of India, as well as public order. It is for this
			<lb />
			reason, the State authorities many a times designate
			<lb />
			particular areas and routes, dedicating them for the
			<lb />
			purpose of holding public meetings.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			15. Thus, while on the one hand, citizens are guaranteed
			<lb />
			fundamental right of speech, right to assemble for the
			<lb />
			purpose of carrying peaceful protest processions and
			<lb />
			right of free movement, on the other hand, reasonable
			<lb />
			restrictions on such right can be put by law. Provisions
			<lb />
			of IPC and CrPC, discussed above, are in the form of
			<lb />
			statutory provisions giving powers to the State to
			<lb />
			ensure that such public assemblies, protests, dharnas
			<lb />
			or marches are peaceful and they do not become
			<lb />
			&quot;unlawful&quot;. At the same time, while exercising such
			<lb />
			powers, the authorities are supposed to act within the
			<lb />
			limits of law and cannot indulge into excesses.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;61. Undoubtedly, right of people to hold peaceful protests and
			<lb />
			demonstrations, etc. is a fundamental right guaranteed under Articles
			<lb />
			19(1)(a) and 19(1)(b) of the Constitution. The question is as to
			<lb />
			whether disturbances, etc. caused by it to the residents, as mentioned
			<lb />
			in detail by the NGT, is a larger public interest which outweighs the
			<lb />
			rights of protestors to hold demonstrations at Jantar Mantar Road
			<lb />
			and, therefore, amounts to reasonable restriction in curbing such
			<lb />
			demonstrations. Here, we agree with the detailed reasoning given by
			<lb />
			the NGT that holding of demonstrations in the way it has been
			<lb />
			happening is causing serious discomfort and harassment to the
			<lb />
			residents. At the same time, it is also to be kept in mind that for quite
			<lb />
			some time Jantar Mantar has been chosen as a place for holding
			<lb />
			demonstrations and was earmarked by the authorities as well. Going
			<lb />
			by the dicta in Asha Ranjan [(2017) 4 SCC 397], principle of primacy
			<lb />
			cannot be given to one right whereby the right of the other gets totally
			<lb />
			extinguished. Total extinction is not balancing. Balancing would mean
			<lb />
			curtailing one right of one class to some extent so that the right of the
			<lb />
			other class is also protected.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			&quot;62. We feel that the pathetic conditions which were caused as a
			<lb />
			result of the processions, demonstrations and agitations, etc. at the
			<lb />
			Jantar Mantar were primarily because of the reason that the
			<lb />
			authorities did not take necessary measures to regulate the same.
			<lb />
			Had adequate and sufficient steps been taken by the authorities to
			<lb />
			ensure that such dharnas and demonstrations are held within their
			<lb />
			bounds, it would have balanced the rights of protestors as well as the
			<lb />
			residents. For example, the dharnas and protests were allowed to be
			<lb />
			stretched almost on the entire Jantar Mantar Road, on both sides, and
			<lb />
			even across the width of the road. Instead, a particular area could
			<lb />
			have been earmarked for this purpose, sufficiently away from the
			<lb />
			houses, etc. so that there is no unnecessary blockage of roads and
			<lb />
			pathways. Likewise, the demonstrators were allowed to go on with
			<lb />
			nonstop slogans, even at odd hours, at night, and that too with the use
			<lb />
			of loudspeakers, etc. The authorities could have ensured that such
			<lb />
			slogans are within the parameters of noise pollution norms and there
			<lb />
			are no shoutings or slogans at night hours or early morning hours.
			<lb />
			Again, these dharnas, agitations and processions could be prohibited
			<lb />
			on certain occasions, for example, whenever some foreign dignitaries
			<lb />
			visit and pass through the said area or other such sensitive occasions.
			<lb />
			The authorities could also ensure that the protestors do not bring their
			<lb />
			trucks/buses, etc. and park those vehicles in and around the residential
			<lb />
			buildings; the protestors are not allowed to pitch up their tents and
			<lb />
			stay for days together; they are not allowed to bathe or wash their
			<lb />
			clothes using Delhi Jal Board tankers or defecate in the open, on
			<lb />
			pavements; and do not create any unhygienic situations. The
			<lb />
			authorities could also examine, while allowing such demonstration, as
			<lb />
			to the number of protestors who are likely to participate and could
			<lb />
			refuse permission to hold any such demonstration, etc. when the
			<lb />
			number is going to be abnormally large which, if allowed, would per
			<lb />
			se create hardships of various kinds to the residents. These are some of
			<lb />
			the examples given by us. The underlying message is that certain
			<lb />
			categories of peaceful protests and demonstrations, in a guarded and
			<lb />
			regulated manner, could be allowed so as to enable the protestors to
			<lb />
			exercise their right and, at the same time, ensuring that no
			<lb />
			inconvenience of any kind is caused to the residents.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;64. At this juncture, while discussing the aspect of balancing of the
			<lb />
			two rights, we have to keep in mind certain other relevant factors as
			<lb />
			well. In the first instance, what needs to be noted is that a portion of
			<lb />
			Ramlila Maidan has been earmarked for such demonstrations, etc.
			<lb />
			Therefore, that space is already available. One of the arguments
			<lb />
			raised by the petitioner in the writ petition and the appellants in the
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			appeal is that Ramlila Maidan is far away from that portion of New
			<lb />
			Delhi area where there is a concentration of &quot;power&quot; and, therefore,
			<lb />
			holding protests and demonstration at a far place in Ramlila Maidan
			<lb />
			would have no impact or very little effect. It was stressed that the
			<lb />
			purpose of holding such demonstrations and raising slogans is that
			<lb />
			they reach persons concerned for whom these are meant. This may be
			<lb />
			correct. However, it is also to be borne in mind that we are living in
			<lb />
			an era of technology where a concerned voice by a group of persons
			<lb />
			can reach the right quarters by numerous means. Electronic and
			<lb />
			print media play a pivotal role. Then, we have social media and
			<lb />
			various applications like &quot;WhatsApp&quot;, &quot;Twitter&quot;, &quot;Instagram&quot;, etc.
			<lb />
			which take no time in spreading such events. .......&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			True connotation of &apos;terrorist act&apos; &amp;
			<lb />
			do accusations make-out an offence
			<lb />
			under UAPA
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			47. First and foremost, this court would be required to consider whether the
			<lb />
			allegations against the appellant in the subject charge-sheet make-out
			<lb />
			any offence under Chapters IV and/or VI of the UAPA, and if so, which
			<lb />
			offence or offences are disclosed. As seen from the discussion above,
			<lb />
			the offences alleged against the appellant under Chapter IV are
			<lb />
			offences under sections 15, 17 and 18, all of which fall under Chapter
			<lb />
			IV of the UAPA. Section 15 engrafts the offence of &apos;terrorist act&apos;,
			<lb />
			section 17 lays-down the punishment for raising funds for committing a
			<lb />
			terrorist act and section 18 engrafts the offence of &apos;punishment for
			<lb />
			conspiracy etc. to commit a terrorist act or any act preparatory to
			<lb />
			commit a terrorist act&apos;. At this point, we would remind ourselves that
			<lb />
			&apos;terrorist act&apos;, including conspiracy and act preparatory to the
			<lb />
			commission of a terrorist act, were brought within the purview of the
			<lb />
			UAPA by an amendment made in 2004, on the heels of the Parliament
			<lb />
			repealing POTA in the year 2004, TADA having already been repealed
			<lb />
			in 1995. Evidently therefore, the phrase &apos;terrorist act&apos; must get its
			<lb />
			colour and flavour from the problem of terrorism as was earlier
			<lb />
			addressed by the Parliament under TADA and POTA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			48. Though, as seen above, the phrase &apos;terrorist act&apos; has been defined in a
			<lb />
			very wide and detailed manner within section 15 itself, in our opinion,
			<lb />
			the court must be careful in employing the definitional words and
			<lb />
			phrases used in section 15 in their absolute literal sense or use them
			<lb />
			lightly in a manner that would trivialise the extremely heinous offence
			<lb />
			of &apos;terrorist act&apos;, without understanding how terrorism is different even
			<lb />
			from conventional, heinous crime.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			49. As observed by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Hitendra Vishnu Thakur
			<lb />
			(supra), the extent and reach of terrorist activity must travel beyond the
			<lb />
			effect of an ordinary crime and must not arise merely by causing
			<lb />
			disturbance of law and order or even public order; and must be such
			<lb />
			that it travels beyond the capacity of the ordinary law enforcement
			<lb />
			agencies to deal with it under the ordinary penal law. The following
			<lb />
			words of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Hitendra Vishnu Thakur
			<lb />
			(supra) bear repetition:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;…&apos;terrorism&apos; is generally an attempt to acquire or maintain power or
			<lb />
			control by intimidation and causing fear and helplessness in the minds of
			<lb />
			the people at large or any section thereof and is a totally abnormal
			<lb />
			phenomenon …&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			50. Furthermore, in the same judgment the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;...it is not the intention of the Legislature that every criminal should be
			<lb />
			tried under TADA, where the fall out of his activity does not extend beyond
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			the normal frontiers of the ordinary criminal activity. Every &apos;terrorist&apos;
			<lb />
			may be a criminal but every criminal cannot be given the label of a
			<lb />
			&apos;terrorist&apos; only to set in motion the more stringent provisions of TADA
			<lb />
			…&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			51. The same sense and meaning has been echoed by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in PUCL (supra) where, quoting Mohd. Iqbal M Shaikh, the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;…it may be possible to describe it as use of violence when its most
			<lb />
			important result is not merely the physical and mental damage of the
			<lb />
			victim but the prolonged psychological effect it produces or has the
			<lb />
			potential of producing on the society as a whole …&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			52. Furthermore, in PUCL (supra) the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court also
			<lb />
			observes that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;... Terrorist acts are meant to destabilise the nation by
			<lb />
			challenging its sovereignty and integrity, to raze the
			<lb />
			constitutional principles that we hold dear, to create a psyche
			<lb />
			of fear and anarchism among common people, to tear apart
			<lb />
			the secular fabric, to overthrow democratically elected
			<lb />
			government, to promote prejudice and bigotry, to demoralise
			<lb />
			the security forces, to thwart the economic progress and
			<lb />
			development and so on. This cannot be equated with a usual
			<lb />
			law and order problem within a State. On the other hand, it is
			<lb />
			inter-State, international or cross-border in character. Fight
			<lb />
			against the overt and covert acts of terrorism is not a regular
			<lb />
			criminal justice endeavour. Rather, it is defence of our nation
			<lb />
			and its citizens. It is a challenge to the whole nation and
			<lb />
			invisible force of Indianness that binds this great nation
			<lb />
			together ...&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			53. Again, in Yakub Abdul Razak Memon (supra), the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court refers to acts of terrorism by saying that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;... Acts of terrorism can range from threats to actual assassinations,
			<lb />
			kidnappings, airline hijackings, bomb scares, car bombs, building
			<lb />
			explosions, mailing of dangerous materials, computer based attacks and
			<lb />
			the use of chemical, biological, and nuclear weapons-weapons of mass
			<lb />
			destruction (WMD)&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			54. In our view therefore, notwithstanding the fact that the definition of
			<lb />
			&apos;terrorist act&apos; in section 15 UAPA is wide and even somewhat vague,
			<lb />
			the phrase must partake of the essential character of terrorism and the
			<lb />
			phrase &apos;terrorist act&apos; cannot be permitted to be casually applied to
			<lb />
			criminal acts or omissions that fall squarely within the definition of
			<lb />
			conventional offences as defined inter alia under the IPC. We remind
			<lb />
			ourselves of the principle laid down by the Constitution Bench of the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in A.K. Roy (supra) where it said that the
			<lb />
			requirement that crimes must be defined with an appropriate
			<lb />
			definitiveness is a fundamental concept of criminal law and must be
			<lb />
			regarded as a pervading theme of our Constitution since the decision
			<lb />
			in Maneka Gandhi vs. Union of India ; and that the underlying
			<lb />
			34
			<lb />
			principle is that every person is entitled to be informed as to what the
			<lb />
			State commands or permits and the life and liberty of the person
			<lb />
			cannot be put on peril of an ambiguity. The Constitution Bench
			<lb />
			further says that to stand true to this principle what is expected is that
			<lb />
			the language of the law must contain adequate warning of the conduct
			<lb />
			1978 (1) SCC 248
			<lb />
			34
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			which may fall within the proscribed area &apos;when measured by common
			<lb />
			understanding&apos;. Most importantly, the Constitution Bench observes,
			<lb />
			and it is imperative that we extract the words again:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;... These expressions, though they are difficult to define, do not
			<lb />
			elude a just application to practical situations. The use of language
			<lb />
			carries with it the inconvenience of the imperfections of
			<lb />
			language...&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;...We must, however, utter a word of caution that since the concepts
			<lb />
			are not defined, undoubtedly because they are not capable of a
			<lb />
			precise definition, courts must strive to give to those concepts a
			<lb />
			narrower construction than what the literal words suggest ...&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			55. Also noteworthy are the words of another Constitution Bench of the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Sanjay Dutt (supra) to the effect that when
			<lb />
			law visits a person with serious penal consequences, the courts must
			<lb />
			take extra care to ensure that those to whom the legislature did not
			<lb />
			intend to be covered by the express language of the statute &quot;are not
			<lb />
			roped in by stretching the law&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			56. It is therefore clearly the position in our jurisprudence that where a
			<lb />
			provision of law engrafting serious penal consequences is vague, such
			<lb />
			provision must be construed narrowly in order to bring it within the
			<lb />
			constitutional framework; and must be applied in a just and fair way,
			<lb />
			lest it unjustly ropes within its ambit persons whom the Legislature
			<lb />
			never intended to punish. Where the court finds that an act or omission
			<lb />
			is adequately addressed and dealt with by the ordinary penal law of the
			<lb />
			land, the court must not countenance a State agency &apos;crying wolf&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			57. In our opinion, the intent and purport of the Parliament in enacting the
			<lb />
			UAPA, and more specifically in amending it in 2004 and 2008 to bring
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			terrorist activity within its scope, was, and could only have had been, to
			<lb />
			deal with matters of profound impact on the &apos;Defence of India&apos;,
			<lb />
			nothing more and nothing less. Absent this, UAPA could not have been
			<lb />
			enacted by the Parliament since the only entries in List-I of the Seventh
			<lb />
			Schedule to the Constitution that would bring the statute within the
			<lb />
			legislative competence of the Parliament are Entry 1 read with Entry 93
			<lb />
			relating to the Defence of India and offences with respect to the
			<lb />
			Defence of India. It was neither the intent nor purport of enacting
			<lb />
			UAPA that other offences of the usual and ordinary kind, however
			<lb />
			grave, egregious or heinous in their nature and extent, should also be
			<lb />
			covered by UAPA, since such conventional matters would have fallen
			<lb />
			within Entry 1 of List-II (State List) and/or Entry 1 of List-III
			<lb />
			(Concurrent List) of the Seventh Schedule to our Constitution. In order
			<lb />
			to lean in favour of constitutionality of the provisions of section 15, 17
			<lb />
			and 18 of the UAPA, as we must, it must be taken that the Parliament
			<lb />
			acted within the realm of its legislative competence and that UAPA
			<lb />
			came to be enacted and amended in 2004 and 2008 to address issues
			<lb />
			relating to the &apos;Defence of India&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			58. In the above view of the scope and ambit of UAPA, and in particular
			<lb />
			sections 15, 17 and 18 thereof, and based on the allegations made in the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet against the appellant as highlighted before us on
			<lb />
			behalf of the State, what we find is the following:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(a)
			<lb />
			The essential aim and intent of the activities, in which the
			<lb />
			appellant is alleged to have been involved, was to orchestrate
			<lb />
			and participate in a protest across the city of Delhi to oppose
			<lb />
			the enactment of the CAA, which was perceived as a law
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			intended to deprive members of the Muslim community of
			<lb />
			citizenship of the Republic of India;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(b)
			<lb />
			The allegation is that, alongwith co-conspirators, the
			<lb />
			appellant engaged in various steps and actions, the object of
			<lb />
			which was to organise a protest and take it to a crescendo that
			<lb />
			would lead to a chakkajam, namely to cause complete
			<lb />
			stoppage of vehicles and blockade of roads, so that supplies
			<lb />
			and services to the people of Delhi are adversely affected;
			<lb />
			and also to spread fear and cause riots;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(c)
			<lb />
			There is no allegation in the subject charge-sheet that the
			<lb />
			appellant was leading the co-conspirators, who are alleged to
			<lb />
			have been indulging in the aforestated acts; nor that he had
			<lb />
			formed the JCC; nor that he was even the group
			<lb />
			administrator of any of the WhatsApp groups, which, the
			<lb />
			allegation goes, were formed with the sinister aim of
			<lb />
			organising a protest against the CAA that would cause havoc
			<lb />
			amongst the ordinary citizenry;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(d)
			<lb />
			The appellant is stated to be a member of the SIO and the
			<lb />
			JCC, admittedly neither of which is a banned organisation or
			<lb />
			terrorist organisation listed in the First Schedule to the
			<lb />
			UAPA. The JCC in fact is not even an organisation but only
			<lb />
			an inchoate committee, defined perhaps only by the
			<lb />
			WhatsApp group that it runs;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(e)
			<lb />
			The common refrain running through the subject charge-
			<lb />
			sheet, as seen from the extracts cited and relied upon by the
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			State, is that the appellant&apos;s co-conspirators directed and
			<lb />
			instructed him to do certain things, including to visit Muslim
			<lb />
			areas, coordinate with local Imams, and help in orchestrating
			<lb />
			the anti-CAA protests at various locations in Delhi;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(f)
			<lb />
			There is no allegation in the subject charge-sheet that the
			<lb />
			anti-CAA protest extended even to the whole of the National
			<lb />
			Capital Territory of Delhi; and a perusal of the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet shows that the protest and the disruptions it is
			<lb />
			alleged to have caused were restricted to North-East Delhi. It
			<lb />
			would therefore be a stretch to say that the protest affected
			<lb />
			the community at large for it to qualify as an act of terror;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(g)
			<lb />
			In fact, from the extracts of the subject charge-sheet cited on
			<lb />
			behalf of the State, which are the most material allegations
			<lb />
			against the appellant, this court is able to discern only one
			<lb />
			specific, particular and overt act that the appellant is stated
			<lb />
			to have committed, namely that he handed over a SIM card
			<lb />
			given to him by someone else, to a co-conspirator / co-
			<lb />
			accused, which, it is further alleged, was used by the said co-
			<lb />
			accused to send messages on a WhatsApp group. Other than
			<lb />
			this one action that is specifically attributed to the appellant,
			<lb />
			this court is unable to discern any other act or omission
			<lb />
			attributed specifically to the appellant;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(h)
			<lb />
			Furthermore, there is no allegation whatsoever that the arms,
			<lb />
			ammunition and other articles, that were supposedly to be
			<lb />
			used as weapons, were recovered from or at the instance of
			<lb />
			the appellant. In this context the provisions of section 43E of
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			the UAPA may be noted, which contain a presumption
			<lb />
			against an accused person, to the effect that unless the
			<lb />
			contrary is shown, the court shall presume that the accused
			<lb />
			had committed an offence under section 15 provided it is
			<lb />
			proved that the arms, explosives or other substances were
			<lb />
			recovered from the possession of the accused and there is
			<lb />
			reason to believe that these were used in the commission of
			<lb />
			the offence; or finger prints or other definitive evidence
			<lb />
			suggesting involvement of the accused was found at the site
			<lb />
			of the offence. In the present case, since there is not even a
			<lb />
			whisper of an allegation that any of the articles referred to
			<lb />
			above were even recovered from the possession or at the
			<lb />
			instance of the appellant, the question of any presumption
			<lb />
			arising under section 43E does not arise;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i)
			<lb />
			The State is at pains to argue that section 15 contemplates not
			<lb />
			only an act &apos;with intent to threaten&apos; the foundations of a
			<lb />
			nation but also any act &apos;likely to threaten&apos; such foundations.
			<lb />
			It is further stressed that not only is the &apos;intent to strike
			<lb />
			terror&apos; outlawed under section 15 but also an act that is
			<lb />
			&apos;likely to strike terror&apos;. The point sought to be made is that
			<lb />
			even the likelihood that the appellant&apos;s acts or omissions may
			<lb />
			threaten the nation are an offence within the meaning of
			<lb />
			sections 15 and 18 of the UAPA. Having given our anxious
			<lb />
			consideration to this aspect of &apos;likelihood&apos; of threat and
			<lb />
			terror, we are of the view that the foundations of our nation
			<lb />
			stand on surer footing than to be likely to be shaken by a
			<lb />
			protest, however vicious, organised by a tribe of college
			<lb />
			students or other persons, operating as a coordination
			<lb />
			committee from the confines of a University situate in the
			<lb />
			heart of Delhi;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(j)
			<lb />
			It has been a recurrent theme, repeatedly urged by the State,
			<lb />
			that what was contemplated and in fact brought to fruition
			<lb />
			was not a typical protest but an aggravated protest which
			<lb />
			was intended to disrupt the life of the community in Delhi.
			<lb />
			We find ourselves unpersuaded and unconvinced with this
			<lb />
			submission since we find it is not founded on any specific
			<lb />
			factual allegation and we are of the view that the mere use of
			<lb />
			alarming and hyperbolic verbiage in the subject charge-sheet
			<lb />
			will not convince us otherwise. In fact, upon a closer scrutiny
			<lb />
			of the submissions made on behalf of the State, we find that
			<lb />
			the submissions are based upon inferences drawn by the
			<lb />
			prosecuting agency and not upon factual allegations;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(k)
			<lb />
			It is the admitted position that the protest that is alleged to
			<lb />
			have been the culmination of the so-called conspiracy, in
			<lb />
			which inter alia the appellant participated, was neither
			<lb />
			banned nor outlawed. The protest was monitored by law
			<lb />
			enforcement agencies; and it is precisely by reason of
			<lb />
			disorderliness of the protest that the appellant is also an
			<lb />
			accused in another FIR bearing No. 298/2019 dated
			<lb />
			16.12.2019, in which however the appellant has already been
			<lb />
			enlarged on bail vidé order dated 28.05.2020 by the learned
			<lb />
			ASJ, Saket District Courts, New Delhi;
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(l)
			<lb />
			In the statutory framework of the now repealed TADA and
			<lb />
			POTA, before allowing a bail plea, the court was required to
			<lb />
			assess whether the accused person was &apos;not guilty&apos; of the
			<lb />
			offence alleged; and therefore the burden was clearly on the
			<lb />
			defence to disprove the allegations on a prima facie basis.
			<lb />
			Correspondingly therefore, under section 43D(5) of the
			<lb />
			UAPA, where, before allowing a bail plea, the court is
			<lb />
			required to assess if the accusation against an accused is
			<lb />
			prima facie true, the burden to demonstrate the prima facie
			<lb />
			veracity of the allegation must fall upon the prosecution. The
			<lb />
			requirement of being satisfied that an accused is &apos;not guilty&apos;
			<lb />
			under TADA or POTA meant that the court must have
			<lb />
			reasons to prima facie exclude guilt; whereas the requirement
			<lb />
			of believing an accusation to be &apos;prima facie true&apos; would
			<lb />
			mean that the court must have reason to prima facie accept
			<lb />
			guilt of the accused persons, even if on broad probabilities;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(m)
			<lb />
			The decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Watali (supra)
			<lb />
			proscribes the court from delving into the merits or demerits
			<lb />
			of the evidence at the stage of deciding a bail plea; and as a
			<lb />
			sequitur, for assessing the prima facie veracity of the
			<lb />
			accusations, the court would equally not delve into the
			<lb />
			suspicions and inferences that the prosecution may seek to
			<lb />
			draw from the evidence and other material placed with the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet. To bring its case within Chapter IV of
			<lb />
			the UAPA the State must therefore, without calling upon the
			<lb />
			court to draw inferences and conclusions, show that the
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			accusations made against the appellant prima facie disclose
			<lb />
			the commission of a &apos;terrorist act&apos; or a &apos;conspiracy&apos; or an &apos;act
			<lb />
			preparatory&apos; to the commission of a terrorist act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			59. In so far as the reliance placed by the State on the decision in Ghulam
			<lb />
			Mohd. Bhat (supra) is concerned, to which decision one of us was a
			<lb />
			member, we need only say that in that case charges had already been
			<lb />
			framed against the appellant therein and two co-accused had already
			<lb />
			pleaded guilty; whereby, after appreciating the evidence adduced
			<lb />
			alongwith the charge-sheet, the Special Court had already determined
			<lb />
			that the accusations against the appellant therein were prima facie true;
			<lb />
			and the order framing charges was not under challenge before the High
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			60. In this case, we find that the State&apos;s attempt to show that the
			<lb />
			accusations made against the appellant are prima facie true, does not
			<lb />
			commend itself for acceptance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			61. Once we are of the opinion, as we are in the present case, that there are
			<lb />
			no reasonable grounds for believing that the accusations against the
			<lb />
			appellant are prima facie true, the Proviso to section 43D(5) would not
			<lb />
			apply; and we must therefore fall back upon the general principles of
			<lb />
			grant or denial of bail to an accused person charged with certain
			<lb />
			offences.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Right to Protest
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			62. Since this matter emanates from a protest organised by certain persons,
			<lb />
			which the State alleges, was no ordinary protest but one that has shaken
			<lb />
			or is likely to have shaken, the entire foundations of our Republic, we
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			feel compelled to discuss what might be the permissible contours of a
			<lb />
			protest that would not threaten our nation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			63. In this context we examined, when, the constitutionally guaranteed
			<lb />
			right to protest, which derives from the rights under Article 19(1)(b) of
			<lb />
			the Constitution to &quot;assemble peaceably and without arms&quot;, crosses the
			<lb />
			line and ventures into commission of a cognizable offence under the
			<lb />
			ordinary penal law; and even more so, when, the right to protest further
			<lb />
			crosses into the territory of becoming a terrorist act or a conspiracy or
			<lb />
			an act preparatory to commission of a terrorist act under the UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			64. The observations of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Mazdoor Kisan
			<lb />
			Shakti Sangathan (supra) appear to us to be the most lucid and pithy
			<lb />
			answer as to the contours of legitimate protest and these bear repetition.
			<lb />
			In the said decision the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says that legitimate
			<lb />
			dissent is a distinguishable feature of any democracy and the question
			<lb />
			is not whether the issue raised by the protestors is right or wrong or
			<lb />
			whether it is justified or unjustified, people have the right to express
			<lb />
			their views; and a particular cause, which in the first instance, may
			<lb />
			appear to be insignificant or irrelevant may gain momentum and
			<lb />
			acceptability when it is duly voiced and debated. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court further says that a demonstration may take various forms : it may
			<lb />
			be noisy, disorderly and even violent, in which case it would not fall
			<lb />
			within the permissible limits of Articles 19(1)(a) or 19(1)(b) and in
			<lb />
			such case the Government has the power to regulate, including
			<lb />
			prohibit, such protest or demonstration. The Government may even
			<lb />
			prohibit public meetings, demonstrations or protests on streets or
			<lb />
			highways to avoid nuisance or disturbance of traffic but the
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			Government cannot close all streets or open areas for public meetings
			<lb />
			thereby defeating the fundamental right that flows from Articles 19(1)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(a) and 19(1)(b) of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			65. Assuming, without however expressing any opinion thereon, that in the
			<lb />
			present case the protest in question crossed the limit of what is
			<lb />
			permissible under Articles 19(1)(a) and 19(1)(b) and went into the
			<lb />
			forbidden realm of a non-peaceful protest, first of all there is nothing to
			<lb />
			show that the Government had prohibited the protest at the relevant
			<lb />
			time, much less is there anything to show that the appellant was the
			<lb />
			perpetrator or conspirator or was involved in any illegal protest. In any
			<lb />
			case, whatever offences are alleged to have been committed by reason
			<lb />
			of the protests having turned non-peaceful are subject matter of F.I.R.
			<lb />
			No. 298/2019, in which the appellant is an accused and in which he has
			<lb />
			already been admitted to bail and will face trial in due course. There is
			<lb />
			absolutely nothing in the subject charge-sheet, by way of any specific
			<lb />
			or particularised allegation that would show the possible commission of
			<lb />
			a &apos;terrorist act&apos; within the meaning of section 15 UAPA; or an act of
			<lb />
			&apos;raising funds&apos; to commit a terrorist act under section 17; or an act of
			<lb />
			&apos;conspiracy&apos; to commit or an &apos;act preparatory&apos; to commit, a terrorist act
			<lb />
			within the meaning of section 18 UAPA. We are unable to discern in
			<lb />
			the subject charge-sheet the elemental factual ingredients that are a
			<lb />
			must to found the offences defined under section 15, 17 or 18 UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			66. In our view, on an objective reading of the allegations contained in the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet, there is complete lack of any specific,
			<lb />
			particularised, factual allegations, that is to say allegations other than
			<lb />
			those sought to be spun by mere grandiloquence, contained in the
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet that would make-out the ingredients of the
			<lb />
			offences under sections 15, 17 or 18 UAPA. Foisting extremely grave
			<lb />
			and serious penal provisions engrafted in sections 15, 17 and 18 UAPA
			<lb />
			frivolously upon people, would undermine the intent and purpose of the
			<lb />
			Parliament in enacting a law that is meant to address threats to the very
			<lb />
			existence of our Nation. Wanton use of serious penal provisions would
			<lb />
			only trivialise them. Whatever other offence(s) the appellant may or
			<lb />
			may not have committed, at least on a prima facie view, the State has
			<lb />
			been unable to persuade us that the accusations against the appellant
			<lb />
			show commission of offences under sections 15, 17 or 18 UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			67. On another note, the learned ASG has attempted to distinguish the
			<lb />
			decision of a 3-Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in K. A.
			<lb />
			Najeeb (supra), submitting that that decision came to be made in the
			<lb />
			backdrop of an extended period of incarceration of the accused person
			<lb />
			as an undertrial and there being no likelihood of the trial being
			<lb />
			completed in a reasonable time. This, the learned ASG says, is not the
			<lb />
			case in the present matter. As presently advised, though the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet has been filed, there are some 740 prosecution witnesses,
			<lb />
			including public witnesses, protected witnesses, police witnesses cited
			<lb />
			in it; and trial is yet to commence. Should this court then wait until the
			<lb />
			appellant has languished in prison for a long enough time to be able to
			<lb />
			see that it will be impossible to complete the deposition of 740
			<lb />
			prosecution witnesses in any foreseeable future, especially in view of
			<lb />
			the prevailing pandemic when all proceedings in the trial are effectively
			<lb />
			stalled? Should this court wait till the appellant&apos;s right to a speedy trial
			<lb />
			guaranteed under Article 21 of the Constitution is fully and completely
			<lb />
			negated, before it steps in and wakes-up to such violation? We hardly
			<lb />
			think that that would be the desirable course of action. In our view the
			<lb />
			court must exercise foresight and see that trial in the subject charge-
			<lb />
			sheet will not see conclusion for many-many years to come; which
			<lb />
			warrants, nay invites, the application of the principles laid down by the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in K. A. Najeeb (supra).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			68. Since we are of the view that no offence under sections 15, 17 or 18
			<lb />
			UAPA is made-out against the appellant on a prima facie appreciation
			<lb />
			of the subject charge-sheet and the material collected and cited by the
			<lb />
			prosecution, the additional limitations and restrictions for grant of bail
			<lb />
			under section 43D(5) UAPA do not apply; and the court may therefore
			<lb />
			fall back upon the usual and ordinary considerations for bail under the
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			69. In this behalf the submission made on behalf of the State, which we
			<lb />
			must address, is that the High Court while deciding an appeal under
			<lb />
			section 21 of the NIA Act must consider the grant or denial of bail only
			<lb />
			within the parameters of section 437 Cr.P.C. and not section 439
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C. since the High Court is seized of an appeal arising from the
			<lb />
			Special Court, which (latter) has acted under section 437 Cr.P.C., since
			<lb />
			in dealing with a case under the UAPA, the Special Court is not a Court
			<lb />
			of Sessions. Although, the learned ASG contends that this is the
			<lb />
			principle laid down by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Kartar Singh
			<lb />
			(supra), we are unable to find any precept to that effect laid down in
			<lb />
			Kartar Singh (supra). Moreover, to say that while considering a bail
			<lb />
			plea, even if in an appeal under section 21 of the NIA Act, the High
			<lb />
			Court would be constrained by the restrictive power for bail under
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			section 437 Cr.P.C., in our view, does violence both to the express
			<lb />
			wording of section 437 Cr.P.C. as also to the wider powers of the High
			<lb />
			Court with regard to bail under section 439 Cr.P.C. It requires to be
			<lb />
			noticed that section 439 Cr.P.C. in so many words applies to &quot;a Court
			<lb />
			other than the High Court or Court of Sessions&quot;. These words in
			<lb />
			section 437 Cr.P.C. cannot be deemed to have been amended by any
			<lb />
			provision of the NIA Act or the UAPA. Moreover, it does not appeal to
			<lb />
			our sense of reason, that when dealing with a bail plea in an appeal
			<lb />
			under section 21 of the NIA Act, the High Court would be bereft of its
			<lb />
			own powers under section 439 Cr.P.C., or absent even those powers,
			<lb />
			would be unable to act ex debito justitiae in exercise of its inherent
			<lb />
			powers under section 482 Cr.P.C. In our view therefore, regardless of
			<lb />
			the fact that the present case arises as an appeal under section 21 of the
			<lb />
			NIA Act, since the additional constraints of section 43D(5) of UAPA do
			<lb />
			not apply, this court would be entitled to consider the matter of bail on
			<lb />
			the touchstone of the provisions of section 439 Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			70. In this behalf, we remind ourselves of the following precepts laid down
			<lb />
			by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court for grant or denial of bail.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			General Principles of Bail
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			71. A quick conspectus of the general principles for considering a bail plea
			<lb />
			would not be out of place at this point. Outlining the considerations for
			<lb />
			bail, in Ash Mohammad vs. Shiv Raj Singh &amp; Anr. the Supreme
			<lb />
			35
			<lb />
			Court expressed itself as follows:
			<lb />
			(2012) 9 SCC 446
			<lb />
			35
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			&quot;8. In Ram Govind Upadhyay v. Sudarshan Singh , it has been
			<lb />
			36
			<lb />
			opined that the grant of bail though involves exercise of
			<lb />
			discretionary power of the Court, such exercise of discretion has to
			<lb />
			be made in a judicious manner and not as a matter of course. The
			<lb />
			heinous nature of the crime warrants more caution and there is
			<lb />
			greater chance of rejection of bail, though, however dependent on
			<lb />
			the factual matrix of the matter. In the said case the learned Judges
			<lb />
			referred to the decision in Prahlad Singh Bhati v. NCT, Delhi and
			<lb />
			stated as follows: (Ram Govind case, SCC p. 602, para 4)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;(a) While granting bail the court has to keep in mind not only
			<lb />
			the nature of the accusations, but the severity of the
			<lb />
			punishment, if the accusation entails a conviction and the
			<lb />
			nature of evidence in support of the accusations.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) Reasonable apprehensions of the witnesses being tampered
			<lb />
			with or the apprehension of there being a threat for the
			<lb />
			complainant should also weigh with the court in the matter of
			<lb />
			grant of bail.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) While it is not expected to have the entire evidence
			<lb />
			establishing the guilt of the accused beyond reasonable doubt
			<lb />
			but there ought always to be a prima facie satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			court in support of the charge.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d) Frivolity in prosecution should always be considered and it
			<lb />
			is only the element of genuineness that shall have to be
			<lb />
			considered in the matter of grant of bail, and in the event of
			<lb />
			there being some doubt as to the genuineness of the
			<lb />
			prosecution, in the normal course of events, the accused is
			<lb />
			entitled to an order of bail.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			&quot;9. In Chaman Lal v. State of U.P. this Court while dealing with an
			<lb />
			37
			<lb />
			application for bail has stated that certain factors are to be
			<lb />
			considered for grant of bail, they are: (SCC p. 525)
			<lb />
			(2002) 3 SCC 598
			<lb />
			36
			<lb />
			(2004) 7 SCC 525
			<lb />
			37
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;… (i) the nature of accusation and the severity of punishment
			<lb />
			in case of conviction and the nature of supporting evidence,
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(ii) reasonable apprehension of tampering with the witness or
			<lb />
			apprehension of threat to the complainant, and (iii) prima
			<lb />
			facie satisfaction of the court in support of the charge.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;10. In Masroor v. State of U.P. , while giving emphasis to
			<lb />
			38
			<lb />
			ascribing reasons for granting of bail, however, brief it may be, a
			<lb />
			two-Judge Bench observed that: (SCC p. 290, para 15)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;15. There is no denying the fact that the liberty of an
			<lb />
			individual is precious and is to be zealously protected by the
			<lb />
			courts. Nonetheless, such a protection cannot be absolute in
			<lb />
			every situation. The valuable right of liberty of an individual
			<lb />
			and the interest of the society in general has to be balanced.
			<lb />
			Liberty of a person accused of an offence would depend upon
			<lb />
			the exigencies of the case.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;11. In Prasanta Kumar Sarkar v. Ashis Chatterjee it has been
			<lb />
			39
			<lb />
			observed that (SCC p. 499, para 9) normally this Court does not
			<lb />
			interfere with an order passed by the High Court granting or
			<lb />
			rejecting the bail of the accused, however, it is equally incumbent
			<lb />
			upon the High Court to exercise its discretion judiciously, cautiously
			<lb />
			and strictly in compliance with the basic principles laid down in a
			<lb />
			plethora of decisions of this Court on the point.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;9. … among other circumstances, the factors [which are] to
			<lb />
			be borne in mind while considering an application for bail
			<lb />
			are:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i) whether there is any prima facie or reasonable ground to
			<lb />
			believe that the accused had committed the offence;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) nature and gravity of the accusation;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) severity of the punishment in the event of conviction;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(2009) 14 SCC 286
			<lb />
			38
			<lb />
			(2010) 14 SCC 496
			<lb />
			39
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iv) danger of the accused absconding or fleeing, if released
			<lb />
			on bail;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(v) character, behaviour, means, position and standing of the
			<lb />
			accused;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(vi) likelihood of the offence being repeated;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(vii) reasonable apprehension of the witnesses being
			<lb />
			influenced; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(viii) danger, of course, of justice being thwarted by grant of
			<lb />
			bail.&quot;
			<lb />
			* * * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;20. Having said about the sanctity of liberty and the restrictions
			<lb />
			imposed by law and the necessity of collective security, we may
			<lb />
			proceed to state as to what is the connotative concept of bail. In
			<lb />
			Halsbury&apos;s Laws of England it has been stated thus:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;166. Effect of bail.-The effect of granting bail is not to set
			<lb />
			the defendant [(accused) at liberty], but to release him from
			<lb />
			the custody of the law and to entrust him to the custody of his
			<lb />
			sureties, who are bound to produce him to appear at his trial
			<lb />
			at a specified time and place. The sureties may seize their
			<lb />
			principal at any time and may discharge themselves by
			<lb />
			handing him over to the custody of law, and he will then be
			<lb />
			imprisoned….&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;21. In Sunil Fulchand Shah v. Union of India Dr A.S. Anand,
			<lb />
			40
			<lb />
			learned Chief Justice, in his concurring opinion, observed: (SCC pp.
			<lb />
			429-30, para 24)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;24. … Bail is well understood in criminal jurisprudence and
			<lb />
			Chapter 33 of the Code of Criminal Procedure contains
			<lb />
			elaborate provisions relating to grant of bail. Bail is granted
			<lb />
			to a person who has been arrested in a non-bailable offence or
			<lb />
			has been convicted of an offence after trial. The effect of
			<lb />
			(2000) 3 SCC 409
			<lb />
			40
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			granting bail is to release the accused from internment though
			<lb />
			the court would still retain constructive control over him
			<lb />
			through the sureties. In case the accused is released on his
			<lb />
			own bond such constructive control could still be exercised
			<lb />
			through the conditions of the bond secured from him. The
			<lb />
			literal meaning of the word &apos;bail&apos; is surety.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			72. In a recent decision in Sanjay Chandra vs. CBI the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			41
			<lb />
			has held that :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;21. In bail applications, generally, it has been laid down from the
			<lb />
			earliest times that the object of bail is to secure the appearance of
			<lb />
			the accused person at his trial by reasonable amount of bail. The
			<lb />
			object of bail is neither punitive nor preventative. Deprivation of
			<lb />
			liberty must be considered a punishment, unless it is required to
			<lb />
			ensure that an accused person will stand his trial when called upon.
			<lb />
			The courts owe more than verbal respect to the principle that
			<lb />
			punishment begins after conviction, and that every man is deemed
			<lb />
			to be innocent until duly tried and duly found guilty.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;22. From the earliest times, it was appreciated that detention in
			<lb />
			custody pending completion of trial could be a cause of great
			<lb />
			hardship. From time to time, necessity demands that some
			<lb />
			unconvicted persons should be held in custody pending trial to
			<lb />
			secure their attendance at the trial but in such cases, &quot;necessity&quot; is
			<lb />
			the operative test. In this country, it would be quite contrary to the
			<lb />
			concept of personal liberty enshrined in the Constitution that any
			<lb />
			person should be punished in respect of any matter, upon which, he
			<lb />
			has not been convicted or that in any circumstances, he should be
			<lb />
			deprived of his liberty upon only the belief that he will tamper with
			<lb />
			the witnesses if left at liberty, save in the most extraordinary
			<lb />
			circumstances.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2012) 1 SCC 40
			<lb />
			41
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			&quot;23. Apart from the question of prevention being the object of
			<lb />
			refusal of bail, one must not lose sight of the fact that any
			<lb />
			imprisonment before conviction has a substantial punitive content
			<lb />
			and it would be improper for any court to refuse bail as a mark of
			<lb />
			disapproval of former conduct whether the accused has been
			<lb />
			convicted for it or not or to refuse bail to an unconvicted person
			<lb />
			for the purpose of giving him a taste of imprisonment as a lesson.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;24. In the instant case, we have already noticed that the &quot;pointing
			<lb />
			finger of accusation&quot; against the appellants is &quot;the seriousness of
			<lb />
			the charge&quot;. The offences alleged are economic offences which have
			<lb />
			resulted in loss to the State exchequer. Though, they contend that
			<lb />
			there is a possibility of the appellants tampering with the witnesses,
			<lb />
			they have not placed any material in support of the allegation. In
			<lb />
			our view, seriousness of the charge is, no doubt, one of the relevant
			<lb />
			considerations while considering bail applications but that is not
			<lb />
			the only test or the factor: the other factor that also requires to be
			<lb />
			taken note of is the punishment that could be imposed after trial and
			<lb />
			conviction, both under the Penal Code and the Prevention of
			<lb />
			Corruption Act. Otherwise, if the former is the only test, we would
			<lb />
			not be balancing the constitutional rights but rather &quot;recalibrating
			<lb />
			the scales of justice&quot;.&quot;
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;39. Coming back to the facts of the present case, both the courts
			<lb />
			have refused the request for grant of bail on two grounds: the
			<lb />
			primary ground is that the offence alleged against the accused
			<lb />
			persons is very serious involving deep-rooted planning in which,
			<lb />
			huge financial loss is caused to the State exchequer; the secondary
			<lb />
			ground is that of the possibility of the accused persons tampering
			<lb />
			with the witnesses. In the present case, the charge is that of cheating
			<lb />
			and dishonestly inducing delivery of property and forgery for the
			<lb />
			purpose of cheating using as genuine a forged document. The
			<lb />
			punishment for the offence is imprisonment for a term which may
			<lb />
			extend to seven years. It is, no doubt, true that the nature of the
			<lb />
			charge may be relevant, but at the same time, the punishment to
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			which the party may be liable, if convicted, also bears upon the
			<lb />
			issue. Therefore, in determining whether to grant bail, both the
			<lb />
			seriousness of the charge and the severity of the punishment should
			<lb />
			be taken into consideration.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;46. We are conscious of the fact that the accused are charged with
			<lb />
			economic offences of huge magnitude. We are also conscious of the
			<lb />
			fact that the offences alleged, if proved, may jeopardise the economy
			<lb />
			of the country. At the same time, we cannot lose sight of the fact that
			<lb />
			the investigating agency has already completed investigation and
			<lb />
			the charge-sheet is already filed before the Special Judge, CBI,
			<lb />
			New Delhi. Therefore, their presence in the custody may not be
			<lb />
			necessary for further investigation. We are of the view that the
			<lb />
			appellants are entitled to the grant of bail pending trial on stringent
			<lb />
			conditions in order to ally the apprehension expressed by CBI.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			73. Most recently, in P. Chidambaram vs. CBI the Supreme Court has
			<lb />
			42
			<lb />
			held :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;22. The jurisdiction to grant bail has to be exercised on the basis
			<lb />
			of the well-settled principles having regard to the facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances of each case. The following factors are to be taken
			<lb />
			into consideration while considering an application for bail:-(i) the
			<lb />
			nature of accusation and the severity of the punishment in the case
			<lb />
			of conviction and the nature of the materials relied upon by the
			<lb />
			prosecution; (ii) reasonable apprehension of tampering with the
			<lb />
			witnesses or apprehension of threat to the complainant or the
			<lb />
			witnesses; (iii) reasonable possibility of securing the presence of the
			<lb />
			accused at the time of trial or the likelihood of his abscondence;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iv) character behaviour and standing of the accused and the
			<lb />
			circumstances which are peculiar to the accused; (v) larger interest
			<lb />
			2019 SCC OnLine SC 1380
			<lb />
			42
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			of the public or the State and similar other considerations (vide
			<lb />
			Prahlad Singh Bhati v. NCT, Delhi). There is no hard and fast rule
			<lb />
			regarding grant or refusal to grant bail. Each case has to be
			<lb />
			considered on the facts and circumstances of each case and on its
			<lb />
			own merits. The discretion of the court has to be exercised
			<lb />
			judiciously and not in an arbitrary manner. .....&quot;
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;33. The appellant is not a &quot;flight risk&quot; and in view of the
			<lb />
			conditions imposed, there is no possibility of his abscondence from
			<lb />
			the trial. Statement of the prosecution that the appellant has
			<lb />
			influenced the witnesses and there is likelihood of his further
			<lb />
			influencing the witnesses cannot be the ground to deny bail to the
			<lb />
			appellant particularly, when there is no such whisper in the six
			<lb />
			remand applications filed by the prosecution. The charge-sheet has
			<lb />
			been filed against the appellant and other co-accused on
			<lb />
			18.10.2019. The appellant is in custody from 21.08.2019 for about
			<lb />
			two months. The co-accused were already granted bail. The
			<lb />
			appellant is said to be aged 74 years and is also said to be suffering
			<lb />
			from age related health problems. Considering the above factors
			<lb />
			and the facts and circumstances of the case, we are of the view that
			<lb />
			the appellant is entitled to be granted bail.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			74. Furthermore in P. Chidambaram vs. Directorate of Enforcement , the
			<lb />
			43
			<lb />
			Supreme Court has explained the concept and application of &apos;gravity&apos;
			<lb />
			of an offence in the following way :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;12. …. The gravity can only beget the length of sentence provided
			<lb />
			in law and by asserting that the offence is grave, the grant of bail
			<lb />
			cannot be thwarted. The respondent cannot contend as if the
			<lb />
			appellant should remain in custody till the trial is over.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			* * * * * *
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			2019 SCC OnLine SC 1549
			<lb />
			43
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			&quot;23. …. Keeping in view the consequences that would befall on the
			<lb />
			society in cases of financial irregularities, it has been held that even
			<lb />
			economic offences would fall under the category of &quot;grave offence&quot;
			<lb />
			and in such circumstance while considering the application for bail
			<lb />
			in such matters, the Court will have to deal with the same, being
			<lb />
			sensitive to the nature of allegation made against the accused. One
			<lb />
			of the circumstances to consider the gravity of the offence is also the
			<lb />
			term of sentence that is prescribed for the offence the accused is
			<lb />
			alleged to have committed. Such consideration with regard to the
			<lb />
			gravity of offence is a factor which is in addition to the triple test or
			<lb />
			the tripod test that would be normally applied. In that regard what is
			<lb />
			also to be kept in perspective is that even if the allegation is one of
			<lb />
			grave economic offence, it is not a rule that bail should be denied in
			<lb />
			every case since there is no such bar created in the relevant
			<lb />
			enactment passed by the legislature nor does the bail jurisprudence
			<lb />
			provides so. Therefore, the underlining conclusion is that
			<lb />
			irrespective of the nature and gravity of charge, the precedent of
			<lb />
			another case alone will not be the basis for either grant or refusal of
			<lb />
			bail though it may have a bearing on principle. But ultimately the
			<lb />
			consideration will have to be on case to case basis on the facts
			<lb />
			involved therein and securing the presence of the accused to stand
			<lb />
			trial.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			75. Commenting on the consequences of pre-trial detention, in Moti Ram
			<lb />
			vs. State of M.P. the Supreme Court said :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			44
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;14. The consequences of pre-trial detention are grave. Defendants
			<lb />
			presumed innocent are subjected to the psychological and physical
			<lb />
			deprivations of jail life, usually under more onerous conditions than
			<lb />
			are imposed on convicted defendants. The jailed defendant loses his
			<lb />
			job if he has one and is prevented from contributing to the
			<lb />
			preparation of his defence. Equally important, the burden of his
			<lb />
			(1978) 4 SCC 47
			<lb />
			44
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			detention frequently falls heavily on the innocent members of his
			<lb />
			family.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			76. In Babu Singh vs. State of U.P. the Supreme Court observed :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			45
			<lb />
			&quot;18. We must weigh the contrary factors to answer the test of
			<lb />
			reasonableness, subject to the need for securing the presence of the
			<lb />
			bail applicant. It makes sense to assume that a man on bail has a
			<lb />
			better chance to prepare or present his case than one remanded in
			<lb />
			custody. And if public justice is to be promoted, mechanical
			<lb />
			detention should be demoted. ......... The considerable public expense
			<lb />
			in keeping in custody where no danger of disappearance or
			<lb />
			disturbance can arise, is not a negligible consideration. Equally
			<lb />
			important is the deplorable condition, verging on the inhuman, of
			<lb />
			our sub-jails, that the unrewarding cruelty and expensive custody of
			<lb />
			avoidable incarceration makes refusal of bail unreasonable and a
			<lb />
			policy favouring release justly sensible.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Conclusions
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			77. Upon a conspectus of the general law relating to bail and applying
			<lb />
			these well-worn principles to the present case, in our view, though
			<lb />
			during trial the State will no doubt attempt to marshal evidence and
			<lb />
			make good the allegations made against the appellant, as we speak now
			<lb />
			these are mere allegations and, as discussed above, we are not
			<lb />
			convinced prima facie of the veracity of the allegations so made.
			<lb />
			Charge-sheet dated 16.09.2020 has already been filed in the matter.
			<lb />
			Some 740 witnesses have been cited in the subject charge-sheet. Trial is
			<lb />
			yet to commence. In view of the truncated functioning of courts by
			<lb />
			(1978) 1 SCC 579
			<lb />
			45
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			reason of the prevailing second wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, it is
			<lb />
			unlikely that trial will commence anytime soon.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			78. That apart, the appellant has already been admitted to bail in case
			<lb />
			F.I.R. No. 298/2019 dated 16.12.2019 vidé order dated 28.05.2020
			<lb />
			made by the learned Sessions Court; and in our view there also appears
			<lb />
			to be an overlap between the so-called larger conspiracy, acts and
			<lb />
			omissions alleged against the appellant in the said other FIR and in the
			<lb />
			subject FIR from which the present appeal arises. While the presence of
			<lb />
			the appellant for purposes of trial must be secured, there is no material
			<lb />
			or basis to suspect; nor is there any reasonable apprehension that the
			<lb />
			appellant will tamper with evidence or intimidate witnesses. As very
			<lb />
			pithily put by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in P. Chidambaram (supra)
			<lb />
			the gravity of the offence alleged would beget the length of sentence, as
			<lb />
			may be awarded upon conclusion of trial; but an assertion as to the
			<lb />
			gravity of the offence cannot thwart the grant of bail. On the other
			<lb />
			hand, apart from militating against the presumption of innocence, pre-
			<lb />
			trial detention would lead to needless psychological and physical
			<lb />
			deprivations; and above all, would seriously hamper the appellant from
			<lb />
			participating in and contributing to the preparation of his defence at the
			<lb />
			trial. The three cardinal concerns against grant of bail pending trial,
			<lb />
			namely of evidence tampering, witness intimidation and abscondence,
			<lb />
			can be addressed by imposition of requisite conditions on grant of bail.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			79. In view of the above considerations and discussion, we are inclined to
			<lb />
			allow the appeal.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			80. We accordingly set-aside impugned order dated 26.10.2020 made by
			<lb />
			the learned Special Court in the case arising from F.I.R. No. 59/2020
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page ! of !
			<lb />
			dated 06.03.2020 registered at P.S.: Crime Branch; and admit the
			<lb />
			appellant to regular bail until conclusion of trial, subject to the
			<lb />
			following conditions:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall furnish a personal bond in the sum of Rs.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			50,000/-(Rs. Fifty Thousand Only) with 02 local sureties in
			<lb />
			the like amount, to the satisfaction of the learned Trial Court;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			(b)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall furnish to the Investigating Officer/
			<lb />
			S.H.O. a cellphone number on which the appellant may be
			<lb />
			contacted at any time and shall ensure that the number is kept
			<lb />
			active and switched-on at all times;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(c)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall ordinarily reside at his place of residence
			<lb />
			as per prison records and shall inform the Investigating
			<lb />
			Officer if he changes his usual place of residence;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(d)
			<lb />
			If the appellant has a passport, he shall surrender the same to
			<lb />
			the learned Trial Court and shall not travel out of the country
			<lb />
			without prior permission of the learned Trial Court;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(e)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall not contact, nor visit, nor offer any
			<lb />
			inducement, threat or promise to any of the prosecution
			<lb />
			witnesses or other persons acquainted with the facts of case.
			<lb />
			The appellant shall not tamper with evidence nor otherwise
			<lb />
			indulge in any act or omission that is unlawful or that would
			<lb />
			prejudice the proceedings in the pending trial.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			81. For clarity, this judgment supersedes the interim custody bail granted to
			<lb />
			the appellant vidé order dated 04.06.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			82. Nothing in this order shall be construed as an expression on the merits
			<lb />
			of the pending trial.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			83. A copy of this order be sent to the concerned Jail Superintendent.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			84. The appeal stands disposed of in the above terms.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			85. Pending applications, if any, are also disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			SIDDHARTH MRIDUL, J
			<lb />
			ANUP JAIRAM BHAMBHANI, J
			<lb />
			JUNE 15, 2021
			<lb />
			uj/Ne/ds
			<lb />
			CRL.A. 39/2021
			<lb />
			Page !
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			of
		</p>
		<p>
			!
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			ANNEXURE-A
			<lb />
			COMPARISON TABLE OF PROVISIONS
			<lb />
		</head>
		<figure type="table">
			NDPS
			<lb />
			TADA
			<lb />
			MCOCA, 1999
			<lb />
			POTA
			<lb />
			UAPA
			<lb />
			Narcotic Drugs and
			<lb />
			Psychotropic
			<lb />
			Substances Act, 1985
			<lb />
			Terrorist and
			<lb />
			Disruptive Activities
			<lb />
			(Prevention) Act, 1987
			<lb />
			Maharashtra Control of
			<lb />
			Organised
			<lb />
			Crime Act, 1999
			<lb />
			Prevention of
			<lb />
			Terrorism Act, 2002
			<lb />
			Unlawful Activities
			<lb />
			(Prevention) Act, 1967
			<lb />
			S. 37(1)
			<lb />
			S. 20(8)
			<lb />
			S. 21(4)
			<lb />
			S. 49(6)-(7)
			<lb />
			S. 43-D(5)
			<lb />
			37. Offences to be
			<lb />
			cognizable and non-
			<lb />
			bailable.-(1)
			<lb />
			Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1973 (2 of
			<lb />
			1974),-
			<lb />
			…
			<lb />
			(b) no person accused
			<lb />
			of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable for offences
			<lb />
			under Section 19 or
			<lb />
			Section 24 or Section
			<lb />
			27-A and also for
			<lb />
			offences involving
			<lb />
			commercial quantity
			<lb />
			shall be released on
			<lb />
			bail or on his own bond
			<lb />
			unless-
			<lb />
			(i) the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor has been
			<lb />
			given an opportunity to
			<lb />
			oppose the application
			<lb />
			for such release, and
			<lb />
			(ii) where the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor opposes the
			<lb />
			application, the court is
			<lb />
			satisfied that there are
			<lb />
			reasonable grounds
			<lb />
			for believing that he is
			<lb />
			not guilty of such
			<lb />
			offence and that he is
			<lb />
			not likely to commit
			<lb />
			any offence while on
			<lb />
			bail.
			<lb />
			20. Modified
			<lb />
			application of certain
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code.
			<lb />
			-…
			<lb />
			(8) Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code, no person
			<lb />
			accused of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under this
			<lb />
			Act or any rule made
			<lb />
			thereunder shall if in
			<lb />
			custody, be released
			<lb />
			on bail or on his own
			<lb />
			bond unless-
			<lb />
			(a) the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor has been
			<lb />
			given an opportunity to
			<lb />
			oppose the application
			<lb />
			for such release, and
			<lb />
			(b) where the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor opposes the
			<lb />
			application, the court is
			<lb />
			satisfied that there are
			<lb />
			reasonable grounds
			<lb />
			for believing that he is
			<lb />
			not guilty of such
			<lb />
			offence and that he is
			<lb />
			not likely to commit
			<lb />
			any offence while on
			<lb />
			bail.
			<lb />
			21. Modified
			<lb />
			application of certain
			<lb />
			provisions of the code
			<lb />
			…
			<lb />
			4) Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code, no person
			<lb />
			accused of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under this
			<lb />
			Act shall, if in
			<lb />
			custody, be
			<lb />
			released on bail or on
			<lb />
			his own bond, unless
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			(a) the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor has been
			<lb />
			given an opportunity to
			<lb />
			oppose the application
			<lb />
			of such release; and
			<lb />
			(b) where the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor opposes the
			<lb />
			application, the Court
			<lb />
			is satisfied that there
			<lb />
			are reasonable
			<lb />
			grounds for believing
			<lb />
			that he is not guilty of
			<lb />
			such offence and that
			<lb />
			he is not likely to
			<lb />
			commit any offence
			<lb />
			while on bail.
			<lb />
			49. Modified
			<lb />
			application of certain
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code.
			<lb />
			-…
			<lb />
			(6) Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code, no person
			<lb />
			accused of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under this
			<lb />
			Act shall, if in
			<lb />
			custody, be released
			<lb />
			on bail or on his own
			<lb />
			bond unless the court
			<lb />
			gives the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor an
			<lb />
			opportunity of being
			<lb />
			heard.
			<lb />
			(7) Where the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor opposes the
			<lb />
			application of the
			<lb />
			accused to release on
			<lb />
			bail, no person
			<lb />
			accused of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under this
			<lb />
			Act or any rule made
			<lb />
			thereunder shall be
			<lb />
			released on bail until
			<lb />
			the court is satisfied
			<lb />
			that there are grounds
			<lb />
			for believing that he is
			<lb />
			not guilty of
			<lb />
			committing such
			<lb />
			offence:
			<lb />
			Provided that after the
			<lb />
			expiry of a period of
			<lb />
			one year from the date
			<lb />
			of detention of the
			<lb />
			accused for an offence
			<lb />
			under this Act, the
			<lb />
			provisions of sub-
			<lb />
			section (6) of this
			<lb />
			section shall apply.
			<lb />
			43-D. Modified
			<lb />
			application of certain
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code.
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			…
			<lb />
			(5) Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in
			<lb />
			the Code, no person
			<lb />
			accused of an offence
			<lb />
			punishable under
			<lb />
			Chapters IV and VI
			<lb />
			of this Act shall, if in
			<lb />
			custody, be released
			<lb />
			on bail or on his own
			<lb />
			bond unless the Public
			<lb />
			Prosecutor has been
			<lb />
			given an opportunity of
			<lb />
			being heard on the
			<lb />
			application for such
			<lb />
			release:
			<lb />
			Provided that such
			<lb />
			accused person shall
			<lb />
			not be released on bail
			<lb />
			or on his own bond if
			<lb />
			the Court, on a perusal
			<lb />
			of the case diary or the
			<lb />
			report made under
			<lb />
			Section 173 of the
			<lb />
			Code is of the opinion
			<lb />
			that there are
			<lb />
			reasonable grounds
			<lb />
			for believing that the
			<lb />
			accusation against
			<lb />
			such person is prima
			<lb />
			facie true.
			<lb />
		</table>
	</text>
</tei>
