<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>C O M M O N J U D G M E N T<lb/> These criminal appeals are directed against the judgment and order<lb/> dated 15.12.2014 passed by the VI Additional Sessions Judge, Chennai in S.C.<lb/> No.394 of 2007.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.It is the case of the prosecution that the police had intelligence<lb/> that some persons were fabricating R.C. books in Agathiar Nagar, Villivakkam<lb/> and hence, they mounted surveillance in that area on 22.06.2001. Around<lb/></p>

			<p>10.30 am, they saw a person moving suspiciously and they intercepted him,<lb/> questioned him and learnt that his name is Murali (A1). From Murali (A1), the<lb/> police seized 10 nos. of 100 rupee currency notes bearing the same serial<lb/> number under the cover of mahazar Ex.P2.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.On a complaint lodged by G. Ramachandran (P.W.1), Inspector<lb/> of Police, Crime Branch, V-5 Thirumangalam Police Station, an F.I.R. was<lb/> 2/32<lb/> registered on 22.06.2001 in Cr. No.822 of 2001 against Murali (A.1) for the<lb/> offences under Sections 489-B and 489-C IPC.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.Based on the information provided by Murali (A1), further<lb/> investigation was conducted and the police arrested Venkat (A2), G.Kumar<lb/> (A3), M.Kanniappan (A4), Panneerselvam (A5), Thangamani (A6), Balaji (A7)<lb/> and Loganathan (A8) and effected seizures of counterfeit currency notes,<lb/> degree certificates, S.S.L.C. (Secondary School Leaving Certificate), caste<lb/> certificates, rubber stamps and seals of various Government offices, etc.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.After completing the investigation, the police filed a final report<lb/> against the aforesaid 8 persons in P.R.C.No.174 of 2005 before the Additional<lb/> Chief Metropolitan Magistrate, Egmore, Chennai, for the offences under<lb/> Sections 489-B, 489-C, 465, 466, 472 read with 467, 467 read with 471 and<lb/> 109 IPC.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.On appearance of the accused, the provisions of Section 207<lb/> Cr.P.C were complied with and the case was committed to the Court of<lb/> Session in S.C.No.394 of 2007 and was made over to the VI Additional<lb/> District and Sessions Court, Chennai, for trial.<lb/></p>

			<p>3/32<lb/></p>

			<p>7.The trial Court framed charges against the accused for the<lb/> aforesaid offences and when questioned, they pleaded &quot;not guilty&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.To prove the case, the prosecution examined 15 witnesses and<lb/> marked 43 exhibits and 36 material objects.<lb/></p>

			<p>9.When the accused were questioned under Section 313 Cr.P.C on<lb/> the incriminating circumstances appearing against them, they denied the<lb/> same. On behalf of the accused, no witness was examined nor was any<lb/> document marked.<lb/></p>

			<p>10.After considering the evidence on record and hearing either<lb/> side, the trial Court, by a judgment and order dated 15.12.2014 in<lb/> S.C.No.394 of 2007, acquitted Panneerselvam (A5), Thangamani (A6), Balaji<lb/> (A7) and Loganathan (A8), but, convicted and sentenced Murali (A1), Venkat<lb/> (A2), Kumar (A3) and Kanniappan (A4) as follows:<lb/></p>

			<item>Name of the<lb/> accused<lb/> Provision under which<lb/> convicted<lb/> Sentence<lb/> Murali (A1)<lb/> Section 489-B IPC<lb/> Three years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.5,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/></item>

			<item>Section 489-C<lb/> Two years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/></item>

			<item>4/32<lb/> Name of the<lb/> accused<lb/> Provision under which<lb/> convicted<lb/> Sentence<lb/> Section 466 IPC<lb/> Two years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/></item>

			<item>Sections 472 r/w.467 IPC Two years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/> Sections 467 r/w.471 IPC<lb/> and 109 IPC<lb/> Three years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.5,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/> Venkat (A2)<lb/> Section 465 IPC<lb/> One year simple imprisonment<lb/> Section 466 IPC<lb/> Two years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/> Sections 467 r/w.471 IPC Three years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/> Sections 472 r/w.467 and<lb/> 109 IPC<lb/> Two years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo<lb/> 6 months<lb/> simple imprisonment<lb/> Kumar (A3)<lb/> Section 489 r/w.109 IPC<lb/> Three years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.5,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/></item>

			<item>M.Kanniappan<lb/> (A4)<lb/> Section 465 IPC<lb/> One year simple imprisonment<lb/> Sections 472 r/w.467 IPC Two years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/> Sections 467 r/w.471 and<lb/> 109 IPC<lb/> Three years simple imprisonment<lb/> and fine of Rs.2,000/-, in default<lb/> to undergo 6 months simple<lb/> imprisonment<lb/></item>

			<item>5/32<lb/></item>

			<p>The aforesaid sentences were ordered to run concurrently. Challenging the<lb/> said conviction and sentences, Murali (A1) has filed C.A.No.23 of 2015,<lb/> Venkat (A2) has filed C.A.No.17 of 2015, Kumar (A3) has filed C.A.No.18 of<lb/> 2015 and Kanniappan (A4) has filed C.A.No.22 of 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>11.It is seen that Murali (A1) and Kanniappan (A4) had engaged<lb/> Mr.Arunprasad and Ms.K.Jayachitra for filing appeals in C.A.Nos.23 of 2015<lb/> and 22 of 2015 before this Court. They have also obtained suspension of<lb/> sentence and bail. When the matter was posted for final hearing on<lb/> 18.09.2019, there was no representation for them. However, Mr.Sunder<lb/> Mohan, learned counsel for Kumar (A3) made his submissions. Therefore,<lb/> this Court made their names appear in the display board and the Court<lb/> Officer contacted the counsel in his mobile number and informed him of the<lb/> case. The counsel never turned up for arguments. Hence, this Court<lb/> appointed Mr.Kumar Tarejaa, Advocate (Enrolment No.463/1988) of more<lb/> than 20 years standing in the criminal bar, as amicus curiae for the appellants<lb/> Murali/A1 (C.A.No.23 of 2015) and Kanniappan/A4 (C.A.No.22 of 2015) and<lb/> furnished him with a typed set of papers. The matter was adjourned to<lb/> various dates and in the cause list, the names of Mr.Arunprasad and<lb/> Ms.Jayachitra were printed along with the name of Mr.Kumar Tarejaa.<lb/></p>

			<p>6/32<lb/></p>

			<p>12.The matter was heard on 19.09.2019 and 24.09.2019.<lb/> Mrs.P.Kritika Kamal, learned Government Advocate (Crl. Side) submitted that<lb/> Kanniappan (A4) has died, but, the police did not produce the death<lb/> certificate and therefore, this Court was unable to act merely on the<lb/> representation of the learned Government Advocate (Crl. Side). Hence, this<lb/> Court proceeded to hear Mr.Kumar Tarejaa, as if Kanniappan (A4) was alive.<lb/> Mr.V.Gopinath, learned Senior Counsel representing Mr.Suresh, learned<lb/> counsel on record for Venkat (A2) in C.A.No.17 of 2015, made his<lb/> submissions. Mr.Sunder Mohan, learned counsel made his submissions for<lb/> Kumar (A3) in C.A.No.18 of 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>13.G.Ramachandran (P.W.1), in his evidence, has stated that when<lb/> he was working as Inspector of Police (Crimes), V-5 Thirumangalam Police<lb/> Station, the police had intelligence that some persons are printing fake<lb/> registration certificates for two-wheelers in Agathiar Nagar, Villivakkam area<lb/> and therefore, he constituted a team comprising Head Constables and<lb/> Constables and mounted surveillance on 22.06.2001 near Wheels India area;<lb/> around 10.30 a.m., he saw a person moving around suspiciously and he<lb/> intercepted him and questioned him; the said person gave evasive replies and<lb/> was not giving his name properly; on thorough enquiry, that person said that<lb/> he is Murali, S/o.Balakrishnan and a resident of Block No.23, 40 th Street,<lb/> Agathiar Nagar, Villivakkam; on searching him, a black purse was found, in<lb/> 7/32<lb/> which, 10 nos. of 100 rupee notes, all bearing serial No.3BK047664 (M.O.1<lb/> series) were available; therefore, he (P.W.1) seized the purse under Mahazar<lb/> (Ex.P2) in the presence of witnesses Mani (P.W.11) and one Kannan (not<lb/> examined); he arrested Murali (A1), brought him along with the seized<lb/> counterfeit notes (M.O.1) to the police station and registered a case in Crime<lb/> No.822 of 2001; he recorded the confession statement of Murali (A1), pursuant<lb/> to which, the house of Murali (A1) was searched and from there, the following<lb/> items were recovered under mahazar (Ex.P4), in the presence of witnesses<lb/> Mani (PW11) and Kannan (not examined):<lb/></p>

			<item>i. 59 nos. of 100 rupee notes, all bearing same serial No.3BK047664<lb/> (M.O.2);<lb/></item>

			<item>ii. Old Tin box (M.O.3);<lb/></item>

			<item>iii. Fake H.S.C. Certificate in the name of S.Shanmugasundaram (M.O.4);<lb/></item>

			<item>iv. Fake Madras University B.Sc. mark sheet bearing Serial No.260844 in the<lb/> name of Senthil Kumar (M.O.5);<lb/></item>

			<item>v. Fake Mark Sheet in the name of R.Senthilkumar of University of Madras<lb/> bearing Serial No.069415 (M.O.6);<lb/></item>

			<item>vi. Fake M.C.A. Mark Sheet in the name of Rajesh Jawahar of University of<lb/> Madras bearing Serial No.335496 (M.O.7);<lb/></item>

			<item>vii. Fake B.Tech. Mark Sheet of University of Madras in the name of Kishore<lb/> bearing serial No.8190 (M.O.8);<lb/></item>

			<item>viii. Fake S.S.L.C. Mark sheet without name -93 nos. (M.O.9);<lb/></item>

			<item>ix. Fake and blank H.S.C. Mark sheets without names -32 nos. (M.O.10);<lb/></item>

			<item>x. Fake and blank H.S.C. Certificates without names -676 nos. (M.O.11 );<lb/></item>

			<item>xi. Fake and blank Transfer Certificates -90 nos. (M.O.12);<lb/></item>

			<item>8/32<lb/> xii. Fake and blank Madras University Degree certificates without names -65<lb/> nos. (M.O.13);<lb/></item>

			<item>xiii. Fake Transfer Certificates of Maruti Vidya Mandir, Minjur without names -<lb/>30 nos. (M.O.14);<lb/></item>

			<item>xiv. Fake blank B.A. Provisional Certificate of University of Madras -110 nos.<lb/> (M.O.15);<lb/></item>

			<item>xv. Forged Residency Certificates with the seal of the Tahsildar, Perambur-<lb/>Purasawalkam -3 nos. (M.O.16);<lb/></item>

			<item>xvi. Forged Transfer Certificate of Government Arts College, Tiruttani -4 nos.<lb/> (M.O.17);<lb/></item>

			<item>xvii.Forged blank Transfer Certificates of Annamalai University -2 nos.<lb/> (M.O.18);<lb/></item>

			<item>xviii.Forged blank Science degree certificate of Madras University -1 no.<lb/> (M.O.19);<lb/></item>

			<item>xix. Forged blank University of Madras Mark Sheet -9 nos. (M.O.20);<lb/></item>

			<item>xx. Forged blank community certificates with the signature of Tahsildar and<lb/> Government Seal -2 nos. (M.O.21);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxi. Forged Community Certificates of various castes -10 nos. (M.O.22);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxii.Forged Community Certificate with the Government Seal and signature of<lb/> Tahsildar, Purasaiwalkam -1 no. (M.O.23);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxiii.Forged Community Certificate with the Government Seal and signature<lb/> of Tahsildar, Ambattur -1 no. (M.O.24);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxiv.Forged Scheduled Caste Certificate with the Government Seal and<lb/> signature of Tahsildar, Ponneri -1 no. (M.O.25);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxv.Rubber Stamps of various universities and colleges -74 nos. (M.O.26);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxvi.Metal seals of various colleges and universities -39 nos. (M.O.27);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxvii.Dyes for the purpose of printing the fake certificates weighing 34<lb/> kilograms (M.O.28);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxviii.Special papers for manufacturing the certificates -2 bundles (M.O.29);<lb/></item>

			<item>xxix.Black colour ink in a polythene bag (M.O.30); and<lb/> 9/32<lb/> xxx.Typewriter -1no. (M.O.31).<lb/></item>

			<p>14.G.Ramachandran (P.W.1), has further stated that, on the<lb/> showing of Murali (A1), Venkat (A2), S/o.Lakshmanasamy, residing at No.31/8,<lb/> Abdul Aziz Street, T.Nagar, was arrested on 22.06.2001 at 15.00 hours and his<lb/> confession statement was recorded; the admissible portion of the confession<lb/> statement was marked as Ex.P5; based on the disclosure, he (P.W.1) searched<lb/> the house of Venkat (A2) and seized the following items under the cover of<lb/> Mahazar (Ex.P6):<lb/></p>

			<item>i. Cement colour Aristocrat suitcase;<lb/></item>

			<item>ii. Community Certificate with the Government seal and sign of<lb/> Tahsildar, Perambur-Purasawalkam in the name of Subba<lb/> Rao S/o.Baskara Rao;<lb/></item>

			<item>iii. Community Certificate with the Government seal and sign of<lb/> Tahsildar, Ponneri in the name of Komma Sriram<lb/> S/o.K.S.Venkateswara Rao;<lb/></item>

			<item>iv. Community Certificate with the Government seal and sign of<lb/> Tahsildar in the name of Pasala Srinivasa Rao, S/o.Rama<lb/> Rao;<lb/></item>

			<item>v. Fake and blank Community Certificate with the Government<lb/> Seal and signature of Tahsildar, Purasawalkam;<lb/></item>

			<item>vi. Fake and blank Community Certificate with the Government<lb/> Seal and signature of Tahsildar, Ponneri;<lb/></item>

			<item>vii. Fake Community Certificate with the seal and signature of<lb/> Tahsildar, Mambalam-Guindy;<lb/></item>

			<item>viii. 15 nos. of blank residency certificates with the signature and<lb/> seal of Tahsildar, Perambur-Purasaiwalkam; and<lb/></item>

			<item>10/32<lb/> ix. Fake and blank residency certificate with the signature and<lb/> seal of Tahsildar, Ponneri.<lb/> The aforesaid items were marked as M.O.32 series.<lb/></item>

			<p>15.Ramachandran (P.W.1), has also stated that, on the information<lb/> provided by Murali (A1), the police arrested Kumar (A3) and seized a colour<lb/> photocopier and a stabilizer (M.O.33) under mahazar Ex.P8; on the information<lb/> provided by Murali (A1), he arrested M.Kanniappan (A4) on 22.06.2001 at<lb/> 17.05 hours and recorded his confession statement, based on which, he<lb/> recovered the following items from Kanniappan&apos;s (A4&apos;s) residence at 4/12, First<lb/> Street, Tikasa Road, Pulianthope:<lb/></p>

			<p>i) Blank Community Certificate (2 Nos.);<lb/></p>

			<p>ii) Blank H.S.C. Certificate Mark Sheet (3 Nos.);<lb/></p>

			<p>iii) Blank S.S.L.C. Mark Sheet (1 No.);<lb/></p>

			<p>iv) Blank H.S.C. Certificate Mark Sheet (3 Nos.);<lb/> vi) Blank St. Mary&apos;s Matric Higher Secondary School Transfer<lb/> Certificate (1No.) and<lb/> vii) Blue Colour file<lb/> All of the aforesaid items were marked as Ex.P11 Series.<lb/></p>

			<p>16.Ramachandran (P.W.1), has further testified about the arrest of<lb/> 11/32<lb/> and seizure from Panneerselvam (A5), Thangamani (A6), Balaji (A7) and<lb/> Loganathan (A8). Since A5 to A8 have been acquitted and the State has not<lb/> preferred any appeal against their acquittal, this Court is not adverting to<lb/> Ramachandran&apos;s (P.W.1&apos;s) testimony in this regard. Ramachandran (P.W.1)<lb/> was cross-examined by the accused on 15.12.2010, 24.01.2011 and<lb/> 25.03.2011. The defence strenuously attacked the seizure, but to no avail.<lb/> The evidence of Ramachandran (P.W.1) has been substantially corroborated by<lb/> Stephen (P.W.2), Head Constable and Ravindran (P.W.3), Head Constable.<lb/></p>

			<p>17.In order to satisfy the judicial conscience, this Court called for the<lb/> original records and material objects from the trial Court and placed the same<lb/> in the open Court for perusal of the defence counsel and the learned<lb/> Government Advocate. For a clear understanding of the nature of the seized<lb/> documents, this Court is giving herein below, one sample each of the various<lb/> documents that were recovered from each of the accused. A decade ago,<lb/> when we were using only manual typewriters, it would not have been possible<lb/> to extract such images in the body of the judgment. Now, however, with the<lb/> advent of the state-of-the-art technology, this Court wants to make the best<lb/> use of the same that is available for making this judgment complete.<lb/></p>

			<p>12/32<lb/> ii. Community Certificate (unfilled certificate)<lb/> (Serial No.5 of M.O.32 Series -2 nos.)<lb/></p>

			<item>iii. Nativity/Residence Certificate (unfilled certificate)<lb/> (Serial No.9 of M.O.32 Series)<lb/></item>

			<item>17/32<lb/> Seized from the residence of Kanniappan (A4)<lb/> i. Community Certificate<lb/> ii. Higher Secondary Course (H.S.C) Certificate<lb/> This Court was unable to scan the aforesaid documents as they are intimately<lb/> stitched to the trial Court records.<lb/></item>

			<p>18.Mr.Kumar Tarejaa submitted that there should be some evidence<lb/> to show that the certificates were forged, inasmuch as the police should have<lb/> obtained the opinion of an expert, who should have compared the original<lb/> certificates with the forged certificates. This argument will apply in a case,<lb/> where &apos;A&apos; has the original of a sale deed and &apos;B&apos; has the forged sale deed. In<lb/> such a case, the police can send the original and the forged one to the expert<lb/> and get their opinion.<lb/></p>

			<p>19.Mr.V.Gopinath submitted that the prosecution had failed to prove<lb/> the exact place from where, the seizures were effected from Venkat (A2). In<lb/> this regard, he drew the attention of this Court to the evidence of<lb/> Ramachandran (P.W.1), who has stated that, for searching in all the places, he<lb/> had taken only the same witnesses, viz., Mani (P.W.11) and Kannan (not<lb/> examined) and did not call other persons from the local area to stand as<lb/> witnesses. In this case, after arresting Murali (A1), the police had to<lb/> continuously conduct search at various places and in those circumstances, they<lb/> had taken these two witnesses with them. This cannot be faulted in the facts<lb/> and circumstances of the present case.<lb/></p>

			<p>18/32<lb/> 20.Mr.V.Gopinath further submitted that there are contradictions in<lb/> the evidence of Ramachandran (P.W.1), Stephen (P.W.2) and Mani (P.W.11),<lb/> with regard to the exact place from where, the seizure was effected in the<lb/> house of Venkat (A2). According to him, Ramachandran (P.W.1) has stated in<lb/> the cross-examination that Venkat (A2) was standing in front of his house in a<lb/> lane, whereas, Stephen (P.W.2), has stated that, they went inside Venkat&apos;s<lb/> (A2&apos;s) house, which is in a lane. He took this Court through the evidence of<lb/> Mani (P.W.11), who has stated that Venkat&apos;s (A2&apos;s) house was opened and he<lb/> was living in the ground floor, whereas, Stephen (P.W.2), has stated that,<lb/> Venkat&apos;s (A2&apos;s) house was in the first floor. As stated above, the seizures in<lb/> this case were effected in June 2001 and Mani (P.W.11) was examined in<lb/> February 2013 and other witnesses were examined subsequently, nearly a<lb/> decade later. The witnesses cannot be expected to remember accurately,<lb/> which is the exact place Mani (P.W.11) was standing, when the police came to<lb/> his house or in which floor, he was living with his family. In the opinion of this<lb/> Court, these are trivial discrepancies and the evidence of witnesses should be<lb/> appreciated, bearing in mind that they are not robots or recording machines to<lb/> give parrot-like versions.<lb/></p>

			<p>21.Mr.V.Gopinath submitted that, out of 9 classes of documents<lb/> allegedly recovered from the house of Venkat (A2), the police had sent three<lb/> 19/32<lb/> blank community certificates to the Office of the Tahsildar, Perambur-<lb/>Purasawalkam Taluk, for opinion. Jayapandian (P.W.5), Tahsildar, Perambur-<lb/>Purasawalkam Taluk, has given his opinion (Ex.P15), wherein, he has stated<lb/> that the three community certificates bearing Nos.477291, 477293 and<lb/> 4800105 were not issued by his office. However, Mr.V.Gopinath contended<lb/> that in the cross-examination, Jayapandian (P.W.5) has stated that he had<lb/> given the opinion, based on the file noting of the Junior Assistant and thus, the<lb/> evidence of Jayapandian (P.W.5) deserves to be rejected.<lb/></p>

			<p>22.To appreciate the contention of Mr.V.Gopinath, it may be relevant<lb/> to state here that 9 classes of documents were recovered from the residence of<lb/> Venkat (A2) and they have been exhibited in paragraph 14 supra. Out of them,<lb/> 3 community certificates were sent to the Office of the Tahsildar, Perambur-<lb/>Purasawalkam Taluk, for opinion. A bare perusal of the said 3 certificates<lb/> shows that they bear the signature of Vijayakumar. A copy of the sample of<lb/> the certificate is given in paragraph 17 supra. A mere perusal of these<lb/> certificates shows that they have the seal of the Taluk office and the person<lb/> who has signed as Tahsildar is one Vijayakumar.<lb/></p>

			<p>23.Jayapandian (P.W.5), in his evidence, has clearly stated that no<lb/> one by name Vijayakumar had ever worked as Tahsildar in Perambur-<lb/>Purasawalkam Taluk. In the cross-examination, this has not been denied.<lb/> 20/32<lb/> When a certificate is sent to an institution like Taluk office or Collectorate, we<lb/> cannot expect the Tahsildar or the Collector to examine the old records and<lb/> give a report himself. He would seek the aid of his staff member working<lb/> under him to examine the request of the police and prepare a note file. The<lb/> staff member will examine the old records and find out whether the certificate<lb/> in question was issued by their office and thereafter, put up a note to the head<lb/> of the office. Therefore, the answer of Jayapandian (P.W.5) that he acted on<lb/> the note put up by his clerk, cannot be a reason to hold that these certificates<lb/> are genuine in nature.<lb/></p>

			<p>24.What surprises this Court is, as to how Venkat (A2) is connected<lb/> to the Revenue Department. It is not known as to why, he had so many<lb/> numbers of Community Certificates, both filled and unfilled, of various<lb/> Tahsildars and residence certificates in huge quantities. As stated above, the<lb/> bogus certificates bear the signature of one Vijayakumar, which is clearly<lb/> visible to the naked eye and the evidence of Jayapandian (P.W.5) that no one<lb/> by name Vijayakumar had worked as Tahsildar of Perambur-Purasawalkam<lb/> Taluk, is sufficient, in the opinion of this Court, to hold that the documents<lb/> were forged ones.<lb/></p>

			<p>25.Mr.V.Gopinath and Mr.Kumar Tarejaa contended that the<lb/> independent witness Ezhumalai (P.W.4) turned hostile and therefore, the<lb/> alleged seizures of the incriminating materials have not been satisfactorily<lb/> 21/32<lb/> proved. It is true that Ezhumalai (P.W.4), the independent witness for the<lb/> seizure of counterfeit currency from Murali (A1) turned hostile, for which, there<lb/> may be several reasons. In this case, the seizures were of the year 2001 and<lb/> the trial began only in the year 2010 and therefore, it is obvious that much<lb/> water would have flown under the bridge.<lb/></p>

			<p>26.Be that as it may, in Rameshbhai Mohanbhai Koli Vs. State of<lb/> Gurajat [2011 (3) SCC (Crl.) 102], the Surpeme Court has held as follows:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;35. This Court has held in large number of cases that<lb/> merely because the panch witnesses have turned hostile is no ground to<lb/> reject the evidence if the same is based on the testimony of the<lb/> Investigating Officer alone.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>27.As alluded to above, the evidence of Ramachandran (P.W.1) does<lb/> inspire the confidence of this Court. There is no reason for Ramachandran<lb/> (P.W.1) or the police to foist a case of such a gargantuan nature on the<lb/> accused.<lb/> Seizure of counterfeit currency notes, fake educational and<lb/> community certificates and rubber stamps of all hues from the residences of<lb/> the accused speak for themselves. The prosecution has examined, the officials<lb/> from the Revenue Department, University of Madras and respective institutions,<lb/> viz., K.Jeyapandian (P.W.5), Tahsildar (Retd.), A.S.Karunanidhi (P.W.6) from<lb/> Madras University, Stanly Charly (P.W.7), Principal, St. Mary&apos;s Boys High<lb/> School, Stalin (P.W.8), Principal, Kamaraj Matriculation Higher Secondary<lb/> School, Vasantha (P.W.9), Principal, Velankanni Matriculation Higher Secondary<lb/> 22/32<lb/> School and Santha Bella (P.W.10), from Corporation School, Nungambakkam,<lb/> to prove that the seized certificates were not issued by their respective<lb/> institutions.<lb/></p>

			<p>28.Mr.Kumar Tarejaa, learned counsel for Murali (A1) and<lb/> Kanniappan (A4) contended that the F.I.R. in this case was registered on the<lb/> complaint of Ramachandran (P.W.1) and hence, he ought not to have been the<lb/> Investigating Officer. In support of this contention, the defence placed strong<lb/> reliance on the judgment of the Supreme Court in Mohan Lal Vs. State of<lb/> Punjab [(2018) 17 SCC 627].<lb/></p>

			<p>29.However, Mrs.P.Kritika Kamal, learned Government Advocate<lb/> (Crl. Side) brought to the notice of this Court, the judgment of the Supreme<lb/> Court in Varinder Kumar Vs. State of Himachal Pradesh (2019 SCC OnLine SC<lb/></p>

			<p>170), wherein, in paragraph 18, it is held as follows :<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;18.The criminal justice delivery system, cannot be allowed to<lb/> veer exclusively to the benefit of the offender making it uni-directional<lb/> exercise. A proper administration of the criminal justice delivery system,<lb/> therefore requires balancing the rights of the accused and the<lb/> prosecution, so that the law laid down in Mohan Lal Vs. State of Punjab<lb/> [(2018) 17 SCC 627] is not allowed to become a springboard for<lb/> acquittal in prosecutions prior to the same, irrespective of all other<lb/> considerations. We therefore hold that all pending criminal prosecutions,<lb/> trials and appeals prior to the law laid down in Mohan Lal (supra) shall<lb/> continue to be governed by the individual facts of the case.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>30.In this case, Ramachandran (P.W.1) intercepted Murali (A1) on<lb/> 23/32<lb/> suspicion and recovered counterfeit currency notes from him. Thereafter, on<lb/> the disclosure statement of Murali (A1), other seizures were effected, without<lb/> giving much time for the accused to destroy the evidence. However,<lb/> investigation was done by the C.B.C.I.D and charge sheet was filed by<lb/> A.Udhayakumar (P.W.15), Inspector of Police (C.B.C.I.D). Therefore, on facts,<lb/> the aforesaid ruling relied upon by the defence may not have any application to<lb/> the facts of the case at hand.<lb/></p>

			<p>31.Mr.Sunder Mohan, learned counsel for Kumar (A3) strenuously<lb/> contended that except the seizure of a photocopier and a stabilizer from the<lb/> shop of Kumar (A3), there is absolutely no material to link him in the offence.<lb/> There appears to be sufficient force in the contention of the learned counsel.<lb/> It is true that apart from seizure of a colour photocopier (M.O.33) from the<lb/> shop of Kumar (A3), there is no other material to fasten criminal liability on<lb/> him. Had there been seizure of certificates or currency notes from the shop of<lb/> Kumar (A3), then one can link them with the other seizures effected from the<lb/> residences of the other accused. The photocopier has not been seized from<lb/> the residence of Kumar (A3), but, from Jamuna Xerox that was run by Kumar<lb/> (A3). Of course, Kumar (A3) is not as innocent as a lamb. But, we have only<lb/> his police confession and the police confession of the co-accused against<lb/> Kumar and nothing more. Therefore, in the absence of any legal evidence<lb/> against Kumar (A3), the conviction and sentence of Kumar (A3) deserves to be<lb/> 24/32<lb/> set aside.<lb/></p>

			<p>32.Mr.V.Gopinath took this Court through Sections 463, 464, 465,<lb/> 466 and 471 IPC and submitted that even if the evidence adduced by the<lb/> prosecution finds acceptance by this Court, yet, there is no material to show<lb/> that it was Venkat (A2), who had made, signed, sealed or executed the<lb/> documents in question. He contended that, at the most, the evidence would<lb/> show that Venkat (A2) was in possession of forged documents and nothing<lb/> more. From the residence of Venkat (A2), 9 Community Certificates, out of<lb/> which, 3 certificates have been filled up and the rest are unfilled, but, which<lb/> bear the signature of Vijayakumar and seal of Tahsildar, Perambur-<lb/>Purasawalkam Taluk, were seized. Similarly, 15 unfilled Nativity/Residence<lb/> Certificates bearing the signature of Vijayakumar and seal of Tahsildar,<lb/> Perambur-Purasawalkam Taluk were also seized.<lb/></p>

			<p>33.It is true that there is no direct evidence to show that Venkat<lb/> (A2) made these documents. One cannot expect the accused to manufacture<lb/> such certificates with witnesses around. Such manufacture will take place only<lb/> clandestinely and therefore, seldom will there be direct evidence to show that<lb/> the accused had manufactured the documents. In a case, where the accused<lb/> is found to be possessed of a single forged document, then, he can possibly<lb/> argue that he had not manufactured the document himself and that, he was<lb/> 25/32<lb/> only in possession of it. In this case, out of 9 Community Certificates, 3 of<lb/> them are filled and they bear the name of the recipients and the rest are blank.<lb/> Similarly, the name of the recipients has not been filled in 15 Nativity<lb/> Certificates. This shows that Venkat (A2) is ready to fill up the name of the<lb/> recipient, as and when he is approached. Thus, the evidence, cumulatively<lb/> viewed, unmistakably show that these documents were manufactured by<lb/> Venkat (A2) for sale to prospective customers. The possession of these mass<lb/> quantities of certificates has remained unexplained. The onus was clearly on<lb/> Venkat (A2) to lead some evidence to establish the nature of his possession,<lb/> regard being had to the provisions of Section 106 of the Evidence Act.<lb/></p>

			<p>34.The above submission of Mr.V.Gopinath can also be analysed<lb/> from yet another dimension.<lb/></p>

			<p>35.The charge that was framed against Venkat (A2) in Tamil reads<lb/> thus: &quot;On 22.06.2001, around 14.30 hours, you (A2) was in possession of 25<lb/> nos. of forged Community Certificates and Nativity Certificates in your<lb/> residence at No.318, Abdul Aziz Street, T.Nagar, Chennai-17 and thereby, you<lb/> are punishable under Sections 465, 466, 467 read with 471 and 472 read with<lb/> 467 and 109 IPC.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>26/32<lb/> 36.Section 474 IPC reads as under :<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot; 474.Having possession of document described in<lb/> section 466 or 467, knowing it to be forged and intending to use<lb/> it as genuine -Whoever has in his possession any document or<lb/> electronic record, knowing the same to be forged and intending<lb/> that the same shall fraudulently or dishonestly be used as<lb/> genuine, shall, if the document or electronic record is one of the<lb/> description mentioned in section 466 of this Code, be punished<lb/> with imprisonment of either description for a term which may<lb/> extend to seven years, and shall also be liable to fine; and if the<lb/> document is one of the description mentioned in section 467,<lb/> shall be punished with imprisonment for life, or with<lb/> imprisonment of either description, for a term which may extend<lb/> to seven years, and shall also be liable to fine.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The Community Certificates and Nativity Certificates would fall within the<lb/> meaning of Section 466 IPC, as they are certificates purported to have been<lb/> made by a public servant in his official capacity. At this juncture, it may be<lb/> apposite to extract illustration (b) of Section 14 of the Evidence Act, 1872 :<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;A is accused of fraudulently delivering to another<lb/> person a counterfeit coin which, at the time when he delivered it,<lb/> he knew to be counterfeit.<lb/> That fact that, at the time of its delivery, A was<lb/> possessed of a number of other pieces of counterfeit is relevant.<lb/> The fact that A had been previously convicted of<lb/> delivering to another person as genuine a counterfeit coin<lb/> knowing it to be counterfeit is relevant.&quot;<lb/> As stated above, 3 Community Certificates seized from Venkat (A2) bear the<lb/> name of the recipients and they are (i) G.Subba Rao, S/o.Baskar Rao, (ii)<lb/> Komma Sriram, S/o.Gangeswara Rao and (iii) Pasala Srinivasa Rao, S/o.Rama<lb/> Rao. These 3 certificates were ready for delivery to the recipients named<lb/> 27/32<lb/> therein and before that, Venkat (A2) was caught.<lb/></p>

			<p>37.The possession of other certificates becomes relevant to show<lb/> the existence of his state of mind. Though there is no specific charge under<lb/> Section 474 IPC, the substance of the imputation extracted above, clearly<lb/> encompasses the ingredients of Section 474 IPC. Therefore, the failure to refer<lb/> to Section 474 IPC in the charge, cannot have the effect of vitiating the<lb/> prosecution case, especially in the light of Section 464 Cr.P.C. The maximum<lb/> punishment for the offence under Section 466 IPC and 474 IPC in respect of a<lb/> document, which is not a valuable security or will, is only 7 years<lb/> imprisonment. In this case, Venkat (A2) has been awarded 3 years rigorous<lb/> imprisonment. There is absolutely no material to show that failure of justice<lb/> had occasioned by non-framing of a charge under Section 474 IPC. Section<lb/> 466 IPC will apply, if a person had manufactured the document and Section<lb/> 474 IPC will apply, if a person is in possession of a forged document.<lb/></p>

			<p>38.As explained above, the circumstantial evidence shows that<lb/> Venkat (A2) had manufactured the impugned documents, whereas, direct<lb/> evidence shows that Venkat (A2) was in possession of the impugned<lb/> documents. Even if Venkat (A2) escapes from the frying pan of Section 466<lb/> IPC, he will fall into the fire of Section 474 IPC.<lb/></p>

			<p>28/32<lb/></p>

			<p>39.Coming to the case of Kanniappan (A4), two blank Community<lb/> Certificates, six blank Higher Secondary Course Certificates, one Secondary<lb/> School Leaving Certificate and one Transfer Certificate of St. Mary&apos;s<lb/> Matriculation Higher Secondary School were recovered. Stanly Charly (P.W.7),<lb/> Principal of St. Mary&apos;s Matriculation Higher Secondary School, in his testimony,<lb/> has stated that the blank Transfer Certificate form was not printed by his<lb/> school and he has given reasons for it.<lb/> From the possession of Murali (A1),<lb/> 74 nos. of rubber stamps of various Government offices, colleges, schools and<lb/> universities were recovered and they were marked as M.O.26. He was also in<lb/> possession of metal seals numbering 39 with Mahatma Gandhi&apos;s figure<lb/> embossed and they have been marked as M.O.27. The recovery of these seals<lb/> and the certificates clearly shows that he was running a full-fledged<lb/> manufacturing unit, from where he was churning out all sorts of certificates.<lb/></p>

			<p>40.Therefore, this Court has no reason to disbelieve the prosecution<lb/> version for acquitting the appellants. It is indeed very sad that the police have<lb/> not been able to find out the clientele of these appellants, who, with the forged<lb/> certificates obtained from them, may now be occupying various positions in<lb/> public offices.<lb/></p>

			<p>41. Before parting, this Court is recalling an interesting counterfeit<lb/> coin case mentioned in the book &quot;Crime in India&quot; by S.M. Edwardes published<lb/> by Printwell, London (1924):<lb/></p>

			<item>29/32<lb/> &quot;A remarkable case of false coining occurred in Nagpur. The<lb/> official staff of the Central Jail suddenly became aware that one of their<lb/> prisoners was gaily counterfeiting four-anna and two-anna pieces<lb/> inside the jail. He was promptly prosectued and was sentenced to a<lb/> term of rigorous imprisonment; but on appeal the Sessions Judge<lb/> quashed the conviction, as he found it impossible to believe that the<lb/> prisoner could have counterfeited coin in the presence of so many<lb/> prisoners and under the nose of the jail staff. Against the aquittal of<lb/> the prisoner by the Sessions Judge, the Local Government made a<lb/> further appeal, which resulted in the original finding and sentence being<lb/> restored. One can hardly imagine the possibility of a long-term convict<lb/> in, say, Maidstone Jail calmly counterfeiting sixpenny and threepenny<lb/> bits, and it seems possible that jail supervision and discipline in India<lb/> are sometimes of a more dolce far niente type than is usual in England.<lb/> If the average Indian peasant and small trader were less gullible and<lb/> more alert, a good deal of false coining and note-forgery would<lb/> automatically cease.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>41.In the result:<lb/></p>

			<p>➢ Crl.A.No.18 of 2015 filed by Kumar (A3) is allowed. The judgment of<lb/> conviction and sentence passed by the Trial Court in S.C.No.394 of 2007<lb/> qua Kumar (A3) are set aside. Bail bond executed by him will stand<lb/> discharged. Fine amount, if any, paid by him shall be refunded.<lb/></p>

			<p>➢ Crl.A.No.17 of 2015 preferred by Venkat (A2), Crl.A.No.23 of 2015<lb/> preferred by Murali (A1) and Crl.A.No.22 of 2015 preferred by<lb/> Kanniappan (A4) are dismissed as being devoid of merits. The trial<lb/> Court is directed to take Murali (A1), Venkat (A2) and Kanniappan (A4)<lb/> into custody, for them to serve out the remaining period of sentence.<lb/></p>

			<p>30/32<lb/> objects and bogus certificates, including Ex.P11 series, are completely<lb/> destroyed under his direct supervision, so that they do not find their way<lb/> into the system and send a report to this Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>➢ The Registry is directed to send the original records and the material<lb/> objects through a special messenger to the trial Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>42. The Tamil Nadu State Legal Services Authority, Chennai, is<lb/> directed to pay a sum of Rs.10,000/-as remuneration to Mr. Kumar Tarejaa,<lb/> Amicus Curiae.<lb/> To sum up:<lb/> i. Crl.A.No.18 of 2015 filed by Kumar (A3) is allowed.<lb/> ii. Crl.A.No.17 of 2015 filed by Venkat (A2), Crl.A.No.22 of 2015<lb/> filed by Kanniappan (A4) and Crl.A.No.23 of 2015 filed by<lb/> Murali (A1) are dismissed as being devoid of merits.<lb/></p>

			<p>04.10.2019<lb/> gya/gpa<lb/> P.N.PRAKASH, J.<lb/> 31/32<lb/> gpa/gya<lb/> To<lb/> 1.The VI Additional Sessions Judge,<lb/> Chennai.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.The Inspector of Police,<lb/> Prevention of Counterfeit Currency Wing,<lb/> C.B.C.I.D.,<lb/> V-5 Thirumangalam Police Station,<lb/> Chennai.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.The Deputy Registrar,<lb/> Criminal Side,<lb/> High Court,<lb/> Madras.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.The Public Prosecutor,<lb/> High Court,<lb/> Madras.<lb/></p>

			<p>5. The Member Secretary<lb/> Tamil Nadu State Legal Services Authority<lb/> High Court Buildings<lb/> Chennai 600 104<lb/> Criminal Appeal Nos.17, 18, 22<lb/> and 23 of 2015<lb/> 04.10.2019<lb/> 32/32</p>


	</text>
</tei>
