<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			2013 (for short the 2013 Act), which was confirmed by the National
			<lb />
			Company Law Appellate Tribunal on appeals, the company in
			<lb />
			liquidation, namely, Devas Multimedia Private Limited, through its
			<lb />
			exDirector has come up with an appeal in Civil Appeal No.5766 of
			<lb />
			2021 and one of the shareholders of the company in liquidation,
			<lb />
			namely, Devas Employees Mauritius Private Limited (hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as DEMPL) has come up with another appeal in CA
			<lb />
			No.5906 of 2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			We have heard Shri Mukul Rohtagi, learned senior counsel
			<lb />
			appearing for the company in liquidation, Shri Arvind P. Datar,
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel appearing for the shareholderappellant,
			<lb />
			Shri N. Venkataraman, learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			appearing for Respondent No. 1 herein, which is the company which
			<lb />
			moved the Tribunal for winding up the company in liquidation and
			<lb />
			Shri Balbir Singh, learned Additional Solicitor General appearing for
			<lb />
			the Union of India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Brief Background
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			3.1
			<lb />
			The first respondent in these appeals, namely, Antrix
			<lb />
			Corporation Limited (hereinafter referred to as Antrix), incorporated
			<lb />
			on 28.09.1992 under the Companies Act, 1956, is the commercial
			<lb />
			arm of the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO for short)
			<lb />
			which is wholly owned by the Government of India and coming
			<lb />
			under the administrative control of the Department of Space.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.2
			<lb />
			On 28.07.2003, Antrix entered into a Memorandum of
			<lb />
			Understanding with Forge Advisors, LLC, a Virginia Corporation.
			<lb />
			The intent, as spelt out in the MOU, was to make both parties
			<lb />
			become &quot;strong and vital partners in evaluating and implementing
			<lb />
			major new satellite applications across diverse sectors including
			<lb />
			agriculture, education, media and telecommunications&quot;. Apart from
			<lb />
			other things, the MOU contemplated Forge Advisors to provide a
			<lb />
			broad array of advisory services that included nearterm tactical
			<lb />
			projects in the areas of sales, marketing, business development,
			<lb />
			strategic partnership negotiations and other related business areas
			<lb />
			and long term projects in the areas of corporate strategy, market
			<lb />
			opportunity assessment, business case development for new
			<lb />
			services, launch of new application services etc.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.3
			<lb />
			On 22.03.2004, Forge Advisors made a presentation
			<lb />
			proposing an Indian joint venture, to launch what came to be known
			<lb />
			as &quot;DEVAS&quot; (Digitally Enhanced Video and Audio Services). It was
			<lb />
			projected in the said proposal that DEVAS platform will be capable
			<lb />
			of delivering multimedia and information services via satellite to
			<lb />
			mobile devices tailored to the needs of various market segments
			<lb />
			such as (i) consumer segment, comprising of entertainment and
			<lb />
			information services to digital multimedia consoles in cars and
			<lb />
			vehicles;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) commercial segment, comprising of high value
			<lb />
			information services to Commercial Information Devices in
			<lb />
			commercial transport vehicles; and (iii) social segment, comprising
			<lb />
			of Developmental Information Services to Rural Information kiosks
			<lb />
			in underserved areas.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.4
			<lb />
			The presentation dated 22.03.2004 was followed by a
			<lb />
			proposal dated 15.04.2004. The proposal was to form &quot;a strategic
			<lb />
			partnership to launch DEVAS, a new service that delivers video,
			<lb />
			multimedia and information services via satellite to mobile receivers in
			<lb />
			vehicles and mobile phones across India&quot;. The proposal dated
			<lb />
			15.04.2004 indicated that DEVAS was conceived as a new National
			<lb />
			Service, expected to be launched by the end of 2006, that would
			<lb />
			deliver video, multimedia and information services via satellite to
			<lb />
			mobile receivers in vehicles and mobile phones across India 1 . The
			<lb />
			proposal contemplated the formation of a joint venture and an
			<lb />
			obligation on the part of ISRO and Antrix to invest in one
			<lb />
			operational SBand satellite with a ground space segment to be
			<lb />
			leased to the joint venture. In return, ISRO and Antrix were to
			<lb />
			receive lease payments of USD 11 million annually for a period of 15
			<lb />
			years.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.5
			<lb />
			The concept of DEVAS, as indicated in the penultimate
			<lb />
			paragraph of the Executive Summary of the proposal dated
			<lb />
			15.04.2004, was based upon the evolution and performance of
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			Paragraph 1 of the Executive Summary of the Proposal dated 15.04.2004
			<lb />
			similar services in other markets such as XM Radio and Sirius Radio
			<lb />
			in the United States and Mobile Broadcasting Corporation&apos;s
			<lb />
			multimedia services via satellite in Korea and Japan.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.6
			<lb />
			It appears that pursuant to the aforesaid proposal, several
			<lb />
			meetings were held between the representatives of Forge and
			<lb />
			ISRO/Antrix and a Committee headed by one Dr. K.N. Shankara,
			<lb />
			Director of SAC (Space Application Centre) was constituted to
			<lb />
			examine the proposal.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.7
			<lb />
			On 17.12.2004 Devas Multimedia Private Limited,
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as &apos;Devas&apos; or the &apos;company in liquidation&apos;)
			<lb />
			was incorporated as a private company under the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			1956. Immediately thereafter, Antrix entered into an Agreement with
			<lb />
			the said company on 28.01.2005. The Agreement was titled as
			<lb />
			&quot;Agreement for the lease of space segment capacity on ISRO/Antrix S
			<lb />
			Band spacecraft by DEVAS&quot;. The preamble of the Agreement stated
			<lb />
			that Devas was developing a platform capable of delivering
			<lb />
			multimedia and information services via satellite and terrestrial
			<lb />
			system to mobile receivers, tailored to the needs of various market
			<lb />
			segments and that Devas had, therefore, requested Antrix, space
			<lb />
			segment capacity for the purpose of offering SDMB service, a new
			<lb />
			digital multimedia and information service, including but not limited
			<lb />
			to audio and video content and information interactive services,
			<lb />
			across India that will be delivered via satellite and terrestrial system
			<lb />
			via fixed, portable mobile receivers including mobile phones, mobile
			<lb />
			video/audio receivers for vehicles etc.. What was to be leased out by
			<lb />
			Antrix to Devas was 5 numbers of C X S transponders each of 8.1
			<lb />
			MHz capacity and 5 numbers of S X C transponders each of 2.7 MHz
			<lb />
			capacity on the Primary Satellite 1 (PS1). The leased capacity was
			<lb />
			agreed to be delivered by Antrix to Devas from a fully operational
			<lb />
			and ready PS1 within 30 months of the agreement, with a further
			<lb />
			grace period of six months.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.8
			<lb />
			Article 7 of the Agreement contained provisions for the
			<lb />
			termination of the Agreement by either of the parties, with certain
			<lb />
			consequences to one or the other, depending upon the
			<lb />
			circumstances under which termination was made.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.9
			<lb />
			It appears that Devas obtained approvals from Foreign
			<lb />
			Investment Promotion Board (FIPB) during the period May 2006 to
			<lb />
			September 2009. Pursuant to those approvals, Devas actually
			<lb />
			brought into India, an investment of about INR 579 crores.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.10
			<lb />
			Devas also obtained an Internet Service Provider (ISP)
			<lb />
			License from the Department of Telecommunications on 02.05.2008.
			<lb />
			Devas then obtained permission from the Department of
			<lb />
			Telecommunications on 31.03.2009 for providing Internet Protocol
			<lb />
			Television (IPTV) Services within the scope of the terms and
			<lb />
			conditions of ISP license. Devas claims to have conducted
			<lb />
			experiments on the emerging technologies for satellite and terrestrial
			<lb />
			system in September 2009.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.11
			<lb />
			However the Agreement dated 28.01.2005 was terminated
			<lb />
			by Antrix by a Communication dated 25.02.2011, in accordance
			<lb />
			with Article 7(c) of the Agreement, which provides for termination on
			<lb />
			the ground of force majeure. It was stated in the said letter that the
			<lb />
			Government of India had taken a policy decision not to provide
			<lb />
			orbital slots in SBand for commercial activities.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.12
			<lb />
			This termination led to Devas initiating a commercial
			<lb />
			arbitration in India before the ICC Arbitral Tribunal. Independently,
			<lb />
			the Mauritius investors initiated a BIT arbitration under the India
			<lb />
			Mauritius Bilateral Investment Treaty and the German Company by
			<lb />
			name Deutsche Telecom, initiated a BIT arbitration under the India
			<lb />
			Germany BIT. ICC Arbitral Tribunal passed an Award on 14.09.2015
			<lb />
			directing Antrix to pay Devas, a sum of USD 562.5 million with
			<lb />
			simple interest @ 18% p.a. The Government of India suffered similar
			<lb />
			awards in the other 2 BIT Arbitral proceedings also.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.13
			<lb />
			In the meantime, the Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI)
			<lb />
			filed a First Information Report on 16.03.2015, against the company
			<lb />
			in liquidation namely Devas, as well as the officers of Devas and
			<lb />
			Antrix, for offences under Section 420 read with Section 120B of IPC
			<lb />
			and Section 13(1)(d) read with Section 13(2) of the Prevention of
			<lb />
			Corruption Act, 1988. It was followed by a chargesheet filed on
			<lb />
			11.08.2016 and a supplementary chargesheet on 08.01.2019.
			<lb />
			Similarly the Enforcement Directorate filed a report in ECIR
			<lb />
			No.12/BGZO/2015.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.14
			<lb />
			Therefore, Antrix made a request to the Ministry of
			<lb />
			Corporate Affairs, Government of India, on 14.01.2021 seeking
			<lb />
			authorization to initiate proceedings under Section 271(c) of the
			<lb />
			2013 Act for winding up Devas. Authorisation was given on
			<lb />
			18.01.2021, on the basis of which Antrix filed a petition before the
			<lb />
			National Company Law Tribunal, Bengaluru Bench on 18.01.2021
			<lb />
			for the winding up of Devas.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.15
			<lb />
			On 19.01.2021, NCLT passed a reasoned order, after
			<lb />
			hearing the counsel for Devas, admitting the company petition and
			<lb />
			appointing the Official Liquidator attached to the High Court of
			<lb />
			Karnataka at Bangalore, as the provisional liquidator.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.16
			<lb />
			Against the said order of NCLT admitting the company
			<lb />
			petition, DEMPL filed an appeal, but the same was disposed of by
			<lb />
			the NCLAT with a direction to DEMPL to seek impleadment before
			<lb />
			NCLT and raise all objections.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.17
			<lb />
			DEMPL simultaneously filed a writ petition in W.P. No.
			<lb />
			6191 of 2021 before the Karnataka High Court challenging the
			<lb />
			constitutional validity of Section 272(1)(e) of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013 and praying for quashing the authorization dated 18.01.2021
			<lb />
			granted by the Ministry of Corporate Affairs to Antrix to initiate
			<lb />
			proceedings for winding up Devas. The High Court dismissed the
			<lb />
			Writ Petition on 28.04.2021 and also imposed costs of Rs.5,00,000/
			<lb />
			on DEMPL on the ground that they were guilty of abuse of process of
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.18
			<lb />
			By a final order dated 25.05.2021, NCLT directed the
			<lb />
			winding up of Devas. Aggrieved by the order of winding up, Devas
			<lb />
			filed one appeal and the shareholderDEMPL filed another appeal
			<lb />
			before NCLAT. These appeals having been dismissed by NCLAT by
			<lb />
			an Order dated 08.09.2021, the exDirector of the company as well
			<lb />
			as the shareholder are on appeal before us.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Grounds of Attack:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.1
			<lb />
			The Company in liquidation, which is the appellant in one
			<lb />
			appeal, assails the impugned orders of NCLT and NCLAT broadly on
			<lb />
			the following grounds:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			breach of the mandatory requirement of advertisement
			<lb />
			before ordering winding up;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) winding up petition barred by limitation;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) Antrix estopped from pleading fraud;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iv) violation of the principles of natural justice due to the
			<lb />
			denial of permission for cross examination.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(v) erroneous findings of fact;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(vi) application of incorrect standard of proof on the question
			<lb />
			of fraud;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(vii) erroneous conclusions regarding the consequences of
			<lb />
			fraud, assuming that fraud was established;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4.2 DEMPL, which is the appellant in the second appeal before us
			<lb />
			and which holds 3.48% of the issued equity share capital of the
			<lb />
			Company in liquidation, assails the impugned orders broadly on the
			<lb />
			following grounds:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			The question of locus of a small shareholder to oppose
			<lb />
			winding up has been decided by both Tribunals contrary
			<lb />
			to law;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) Findings recorded against shareholders on the question of
			<lb />
			fraud, have been so recorded without making them a
			<lb />
			party and without giving them an opportunity of hearing;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) Inapplicability of the theory of useless formality to
			<lb />
			mandatory requirements such as advertisements before
			<lb />
			ordering winding up.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			5
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Defence
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.1
			<lb />
			The impugned orders are sought to be defended by Shri N.
			<lb />
			Venkataraman, learned Additional Solicitor General appearing for
			<lb />
			Antrix, broadly on the following grounds:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			Detailed findings recorded by the Tribunal on 8 different
			<lb />
			types of fraud committed by Devas, both in the formation
			<lb />
			of the Company and in the manner in which the affairs of
			<lb />
			the Company were carried out, which cannot be assailed
			<lb />
			in an appeal under Section 423 of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			The Agreement dated 28.01.2005 entered into between
			<lb />
			Antrix and Devas spoke about three components, namely,
			<lb />
			DEVAS 2 Technology, DEVAS services and DEVAS device,
			<lb />
			none of which existed either on the date of formation of
			<lb />
			Devas or on the date of execution of the Agreement or on
			<lb />
			the date of termination of the Agreement and not even on
			<lb />
			the date of winding up of the company.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) Violation of SATCOM policy, manipulation of minutes of
			<lb />
			meetings and the misleading Cabinet Note.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iv) Shocking nature of the financial fraud.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			5.2
			<lb />
			Shri Balbir Singh, learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			appearing for the Union of India defended the impugned orders
			<lb />
			broadly on the following grounds:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			The requirement of an advertisement before winding up is
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			2 Wherever there is a reference to the company in liquidation, we have used the lowercase of the
			<lb />
			letters in the word &apos;Devas&apos; and wherever there is a reference to the technology and services
			<lb />
			offered by Devas, we have used the capital letters in the word &apos;DEVAS&apos;
			<lb />
			redundant in a petition under Section 271(c).
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii) The question of fraud has to be addressed from the broad
			<lb />
			parameters laid down, not only in Section 17 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Contract Act, 1872, but also in Section 447 read with
			<lb />
			Section 7 of the Companies Act, 2013 and keeping in
			<lb />
			mind the distinction between fraud, fraudulent manner,
			<lb />
			fraudulent purpose and unlawful purpose.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) The attempt of Devas to challenge the constitutional
			<lb />
			validity of Section 271(c) and its failure.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iv) The case on hand not falling under the category of cases
			<lb />
			where crossexamination was necessary.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Fraud as a ground for winding up and the difference
			<lb />
			between 1956 Act and 2013 Act
			<lb />
			Before we proceed to consider the specific grounds of challenge
			<lb />
			to the impugned order, it is necessary to see the contours of Section
			<lb />
			271 (c) of the Companies Act, 2013, as it is stated by the learned
			<lb />
			counsel on both sides (i) that this is a new addition to the Compa
			<lb />
			nies Act; and (ii) that this is the first case of winding up on the
			<lb />
			ground of fraud. Therefore, a comparison of the provisions of 2013
			<lb />
			Act with those of the 1956 Act may serve us better.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.1
			<lb />
			The Companies Act, 1956 spoke about two categories of
			<lb />
			winding up, namely, (i) winding up by the Tribunal; and
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) voluntary winding up. The circumstances in which a company
			<lb />
			could be wound up by the Court, were enlisted in Section 433 of the
			<lb />
			1956 Act. This Section contained a list of nine circumstances in
			<lb />
			which a company may be wound up. Fraud (i) either in the forma
			<lb />
			tion of the company or (ii) in the conduct of affairs of the com
			<lb />
			pany or (iii) on the part of persons concerned in the formation
			<lb />
			of or the management of its affairs, was not one of the circum
			<lb />
			stances stipulated in Section 433 of 1956 Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.2
			<lb />
			Though Section 433 of the 1956 Act did not include fraud
			<lb />
			as one of the circumstances in which a company may be wound up,
			<lb />
			there was still an indirect reference to fraud. Section 439(1) of the
			<lb />
			1956 Act provided a list of seven persons who were entitled to file an
			<lb />
			application for the winding up of a company. Under clause (f) of sub
			<lb />
			section (1) of Section 439, an application for winding up shall be
			<lb />
			presented by &quot;any person authorized by the Central Government in
			<lb />
			their behalf&quot; in a case falling under Section 243.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.3
			<lb />
			Section 243 of the 1956 Act empowered the Central
			<lb />
			Government to cause a petition for winding up to be presented, in
			<lb />
			cases covered by subclause (i) or sub clause (ii) of Clause (b) of
			<lb />
			Section 237. Section 243 of the 1956 Act read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;243. Application for winding up of company or an order
			<lb />
			under section 397 or 398. If any such company or other
			<lb />
			body corporate is liable to be wound up under this Act and it
			<lb />
			appears to the Central Government from any such report as
			<lb />
			aforesaid that it is expedient so to do by reason of any such
			<lb />
			circumstances as are referred to in subclause (i) or (ii) of
			<lb />
			clause (b) of section 237, the Central Government may,
			<lb />
			unless the company, or body corporate is already being
			<lb />
			wound up by the Tribunal, cause to be presented to the
			<lb />
			Tribunal by any person authorised by the Central
			<lb />
			Government in this behalf -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			a petition for the winding up of the company, or body
			<lb />
			corporate on the ground that it is just and equitable
			<lb />
			that it should be wound up ;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			an application for an order under section 397 or 398,
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			both a petition and an application as aforesaid.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			6.4
			<lb />
			Section 243 forms part of a set of provisions from Sections
			<lb />
			235 to 251 in Chapter I of Part VI of the Act. This cluster of provi
			<lb />
			sions from Sections 235 to 251 is grouped under the Heading &quot;In
			<lb />
			vestigation&quot;. Section 235(1) empowers the Central Government to or
			<lb />
			der an investigation into the affairs of the company whenever a Re
			<lb />
			port has been made by the Registrar under Section 234. Indepen
			<lb />
			dent of Section 235(1), Central Government is empowered also
			<lb />
			under Section 237 to order an investigation, if, in its opinion
			<lb />
			or in the opinion of the Company Law Board (i) the business of
			<lb />
			the company is being conducted for a fraudulent or unlawful
			<lb />
			purpose or (ii) the company was formed for any fraudulent or
			<lb />
			unlawful purpose or (iii) persons concerned in the formation of
			<lb />
			the company or the management of its affairs have in connec
			<lb />
			tion therewith, are guilty of fraud. Section 237 of the 1956 Act
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;237. Investigation of company&apos;s affairs in other cases.
			<lb />
			Without prejudice to its powers under section 235, the
			<lb />
			Central Government -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			shall appoint one or more competent persons as
			<lb />
			inspectors to investigate the affairs of a company and
			<lb />
			to report thereon in such manner as the Central
			<lb />
			Government may direct, if -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			the company, by special resolution ; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			the Court, by order,
			<lb />
			declares that the affairs of the company ought to be
			<lb />
			investigated by an inspector appointed by the Central
			<lb />
			Government ; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			may do so in its opinion or in the opinion of the
			<lb />
			Tribunal, there are circumstances suggesting -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			that the business of the company is being
			<lb />
			conducted with intent to defraud its creditors,
			<lb />
			members or any other persons, or otherwise for a
			<lb />
			fraudulent or unlawful purpose or in a manner
			<lb />
			oppressive of any of its members, or that the
			<lb />
			company was formed for any fraudulent or
			<lb />
			unlawful purpose;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			that persons concerned in the formation of the
			<lb />
			company or the management of its affairs have in
			<lb />
			connection therewith been guilty of fraud,
			<lb />
			misfeasance or other misconduct towards the
			<lb />
			company or towards any of its members ; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			that the members of the company have not been
			<lb />
			given all the information with respect to its
			<lb />
			affairs which they might reasonably expect,
			<lb />
			including information relating to the calculation
			<lb />
			of the commission payable to a managing or
			<lb />
			other director, or the manager, of the company.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			6.5
			<lb />
			Thus a combined reading of Sections 439(1)(f), 243 and
			<lb />
			237(b) of the 1956 Act shows that, (i) fraud in the formation of the
			<lb />
			company; (ii) fraud in the conduct of affairs of the company; and
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii) fraud on the part of the persons engaged in the formation or
			<lb />
			conduct of the affairs of the company, though not listed as some of
			<lb />
			the circumstances under Section 433 of the 1956 Act, were still
			<lb />
			available for the winding up of the company, even under the 1956
			<lb />
			Act. But there were 3 requirements to be satisfied. They are: (i) the
			<lb />
			perpetration of one or the other types of fraud mentioned above are
			<lb />
			reflected in a report of investigation; (ii) the petition under these
			<lb />
			provisions is to be filed only by a person authorised by the Central
			<lb />
			Government; and (iii) the petition should be premised on the ground
			<lb />
			that it is just and equitable to wind up the company.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.6
			<lb />
			What is interesting to observe from section 243 (a) is that
			<lb />
			a petition for winding up in terms of Section 439(1)(f) of the
			<lb />
			1956 Act, read with Section 237(b)(i) and (ii), has to be on &quot;just
			<lb />
			and equitable&quot; ground. Clause (a) of Section 243 of the 1956 Act,
			<lb />
			enabled the Central Government (if upon receipt of a report about
			<lb />
			the existence of the circumstances referred to in Section 237(b)(i)
			<lb />
			and (ii), it appears to the Central Government that it is expedient to
			<lb />
			do so), to authorize any person to present a petition for the winding
			<lb />
			up of a company, not directly on the ground of fraud but actually on
			<lb />
			the ground that it is just and equitable that the company should be
			<lb />
			wound up.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.7
			<lb />
			It must be noted that just and equitable clause has
			<lb />
			several facets. The origin of just and equitable clause in Company
			<lb />
			law, is traceable to the law of partnership, which developed &quot;the
			<lb />
			conceptions of probity, good faith and mutual confidence 3 &quot;. The
			<lb />
			principle behind just and equitable clause, in the words of the
			<lb />
			House of Lords is that &quot;equity always does enable the Court to
			<lb />
			subject the exercise of legal rights to equitable considerations&quot;. In
			<lb />
			other words, equitable considerations get superimposed on
			<lb />
			statutorily governed legal rights under this clause.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.8
			<lb />
			It is well settled that the words &quot;just and equitable&quot; in the
			<lb />
			legislation specifying the grounds for winding up by the Court, are
			<lb />
			not to be read as being ejusdem generis with the preceding words of
			<lb />
			the enactment. They are not to be cut down by the formation of
			<lb />
			categories or headings under which cases must be brought if the
			<lb />
			enactment is to apply 4 . But apart from cases, (i) where there is
			<lb />
			something in the history of the company or in the relationship
			<lb />
			between the shareholders; or (ii) where there is functional deadlock
			<lb />
			of a paralysing kind; or (iii) where there is justifiable lack of
			<lb />
			confidence, which may give rise to a petition for winding up on just
			<lb />
			and equitable clause, there have also been other cases at least
			<lb />
			before the Courts in England, some of which are listed in paragraph
			<lb />
			360 of Volume 16 of the Fifth Edition (2017) of the Halsbury&apos;s Laws
			<lb />
			of England. Two of them are (i) where the company is a bubble
			<lb />
			company; and (ii) where the company is fraudulent in its inception
			<lb />
			and carries on at a loss without a capital of its own.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.9
			<lb />
			But traditionally, fraud committed by a company on
			<lb />
			outsiders or the fact that the company acted dishonestly to
			<lb />
			outsiders, was not a ground for winding up in English Law. A useful
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			Para 359, Vol. XVI, Fifth Edition (2017) of Halsbury&apos;s Laws of England.
			<lb />
			reference may be made in this regard to Re Medical Battery Co. 5 ,
			<lb />
			where a question relating to investigation through public
			<lb />
			examination came up. It was held therein that the relevant provision
			<lb />
			was not intended to apply to a case where the charges were about
			<lb />
			the commitment of fraud in the course of business with the outside
			<lb />
			world and not connected in any way with the promotion or formation
			<lb />
			of the company.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.10
			<lb />
			But the law has not remained static even in England. The
			<lb />
			Insolvency Act, 1986 was amended in England through the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 1989 to incorporate Section 124A. Under Section
			<lb />
			124A of the Insolvency Act, 1986, (i) the Secretary of State may
			<lb />
			seek the winding up of a company if he thinks that it is
			<lb />
			expedient in the public interest to wind up the company and
			<lb />
			(ii) if the court thinks it just and equitable to do so. Such
			<lb />
			winding up may be based upon, (i) the reports of some investigations
			<lb />
			under the Companies Act itself; or (ii) a report under the Financial
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(1894) 1 Ch. 444
			<lb />
			Services and Markets Act; or (iii) any information under the
			<lb />
			Criminal Justice Act, 1987.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.11
			<lb />
			In Re Walter L. Jacob &amp; Co. Ltd. 6 , the Court of Appeal
			<lb />
			(Civil Division) was concerned with a case, where the Secretary of
			<lb />
			State, after examining the books of the company in question, formed
			<lb />
			an opinion that the company should be wound up in public interest.
			<lb />
			Therefore, he filed a petition under Section 447 of the Companies
			<lb />
			Act, 1985 for winding up on just and equitable ground under
			<lb />
			Section 122(1)(g) of the Insolvency Act, 1986. The High Court
			<lb />
			dismissed the petition. While reversing the decision and ordering the
			<lb />
			winding up, the Court of Appeal held that the Court&apos;s task in the
			<lb />
			case of petitions for winding up in public interest, is to carry out a
			<lb />
			balancing exercise, having regard to all the circumstances as
			<lb />
			disclosed by the totality of the evidence. One of the arguments raised
			<lb />
			in that case was that the company sought to be wound up did well
			<lb />
			and that all clients to whom the company owed money except one,
			<lb />
			had settled the matter with the company. While rejecting the said
			<lb />
			argument, the Court of Appeal emphasised that the Parliament had
			<lb />
			recognised the need for the general public to be protected against
			<lb />
			the activities of unscrupulous persons who deal in securities.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.12
			<lb />
			Thus, there was a shift even in the English Law, from the
			<lb />
			conservative view that fraud committed by the company upon
			<lb />
			outsiders was not available as a ground for winding up. However,
			<lb />
			winding up on the ground of public interest was also linked to just
			<lb />
			and equitable clause in England. This is perhaps why the law even
			<lb />
			in India, for the winding up of a company on the ground of fraud,
			<lb />
			was also linked to just and equitable clause under the 1956 Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.13
			<lb />
			But the mandate of Section 243 (a) of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			1956 to take recourse, in cases of fraud, to just and equitable
			<lb />
			ground, was little incongruous. This is due to the reason that under
			<lb />
			Section 443(2), the court may refuse to make an order of winding
			<lb />
			up, on just and equitable ground, if some other remedy was
			<lb />
			available to the persons seeking winding up. Section 443(2) of the
			<lb />
			1956 Act reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;443. Powers of tribunal on hearing petition
			<lb />
			xxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) Where the petition is presented on the ground that it is
			<lb />
			just and equitable that the company should be wound up,
			<lb />
			the Tribunal may refuse to make an order of winding up, if it
			<lb />
			is of the opinion that some other remedy is available to the
			<lb />
			petitioners and that they are acting unreasonably in seeking
			<lb />
			to have the company wound up instead of pursuing that
			<lb />
			other remedy.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			Therefore, despite the fact that fraud was available, albeit
			<lb />
			indirectly, as a circumstance for the winding up of a company,
			<lb />
			even under the 1956 Act, its link to just and equitable clause
			<lb />
			was little problematic because of section 443(2).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.14
			<lb />
			Coming to the 2013 Act, provisions similar to subclauses
			<lb />
			(i) and (ii) of clause (b) of section 237 of the 1956 Act, are to be
			<lb />
			found in subclauses (i) and (ii) of clause (b) of section 213 of the
			<lb />
			2013 Act. They employ the same language for the purpose of
			<lb />
			ordering an investigation into the affairs of a company. But under
			<lb />
			section 237 of the 1956 Act, the power to order investigation was
			<lb />
			with the central Government, while it is with the Tribunal under
			<lb />
			Section 213 of the 2013 Act. Section 224 (2) of the 2013 Act is
			<lb />
			similar to Section 243 of the 1956 Act as it enables the Central
			<lb />
			Government to authorize any person to file a petition for winding up,
			<lb />
			on the basis of the report of any investigation. Here again, the
			<lb />
			petition for winding up on the basis of the report of such
			<lb />
			investigation, is to be on just and equitable ground by virtue of
			<lb />
			clause (a) of subsection (2) of Section 224, which is similar to
			<lb />
			clause (a) of Section 243.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.15
			<lb />
			The main departure of the 2013 Act from the statutory
			<lb />
			regime of the 1956 Act, is the specific inclusion of fraud, directly as
			<lb />
			one of the circumstances in which a company could be wound up.
			<lb />
			Section 271 of the 2013 Act lists out the circumstances in which a
			<lb />
			company may be wound up. What were clauses (a), (g), (h) and (i) of
			<lb />
			Section 433 of 1956 Act have now become clauses (a), (b), (d) and (e)
			<lb />
			of Section 271 of the 2013 Act, though not in the same order. In
			<lb />
			addition, (i) conduct of the affairs of the company in a fraudulent
			<lb />
			manner; (ii) formation of the company for fraudulent or unlawful
			<lb />
			purpose; and (iii) persons concerned in the formation or
			<lb />
			management of its affairs being guilty of fraud, misfeasance or
			<lb />
			misconduct, have now been included in clause (c) of Section 271, as
			<lb />
			some of the circumstances in which a company could be wound up.
			<lb />
			In other words, fraud has now directly become (under the 2013
			<lb />
			regime), one of the circumstances in which a company could be
			<lb />
			wound up, though it also continues to be a ground indirectly, under
			<lb />
			section 224(2) read with section 213 [as it was under Section 439(1)
			<lb />
			(f) read with sections 243 and 237(b) of the 1956 Act] .
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.16
			<lb />
			As a matter of fact, Section 271(1) of the 2013 Act, as it
			<lb />
			was originally enacted, included the inability of a company to pay its
			<lb />
			debts as one of the grounds for winding up. Therefore, the deeming
			<lb />
			provision which was there in Section 434 of the 1956 Act found a
			<lb />
			place as subsection (2) of Section 271 of the 2013 Act. But by the
			<lb />
			Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code, 2016 (Act 31 of 2016), &quot;inability to
			<lb />
			pay debts&quot; has been deleted from Section 271. As a consequence,
			<lb />
			the deeming provision in subsection (2) of Section 271 also stands
			<lb />
			deleted. In fact, section 271 of the 2013 Act (along with sections 270
			<lb />
			and 272) got amended even before they were notified under
			<lb />
			Section 1 (3) of the Act to come into force.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.17
			<lb />
			In other words, Section 271 as it originally stood in the
			<lb />
			2013 Act, listed six circumstances in which a company may be
			<lb />
			wound up. Inability to pay debts was one of those six circumstances.
			<lb />
			But by Act 31 of 2016, &apos;inability to pay debts&apos; got deleted from the
			<lb />
			list of circumstances 7 . Section 271 of the 2013 Act, as it now stands
			<lb />
			after 2016, reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;271. Circumstances in which company may be wound
			<lb />
			up by Tribunal A company may, on a petition under sec
			<lb />
			tion 272, be wound up by the Tribunal,
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			if the company has, by special resolution, resolved
			<lb />
			that the company be wound up by the Tribunal;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			if the company has acted against the interests of the
			<lb />
			sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the
			<lb />
			State, friendly relations with foreign States, public or
			<lb />
			der, decency or morality;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			if on an application made by the Registrar or any other
			<lb />
			person authorised by the Central Government by noti
			<lb />
			fication under this Act, the Tribunal is of the opinion
			<lb />
			that the affairs of the company have been conducted in
			<lb />
			a fraudulent manner or the company was formed for
			<lb />
			fraudulent and unlawful purpose or the persons con
			<lb />
			cerned in the formation or management of its affairs
			<lb />
			have been guilty of fraud, misfeasance or misconduct
			<lb />
			in connection therewith and that it is proper that the
			<lb />
			company be wound up;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d)
			<lb />
			if the company has made a default in filing with the
			<lb />
			Registrar its financial statements or annual returns for
			<lb />
			immediately preceding five consecutive financial years;
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e)
			<lb />
			if the Tribunal is of the opinion that it is just and
			<lb />
			equitable that the company should be wound up.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			6.18
			<lb />
			Just as Section 439(1) of the 1956 Act provided a list of
			<lb />
			persons by whom an application for winding up may be filed,
			<lb />
			Section 272(1) of the 2013 Act also provides a list of persons by
			<lb />
			whom a petition for winding up may be filed. What is common to
			<lb />
			both Section 439(1) of the 1956 Act and Section 272(1) of the 2013
			<lb />
			Act, is that a petition for winding up may be filed by: (i) the
			<lb />
			company; (ii) any contributory; (iii) the Registrar; and (iv) any
			<lb />
			person authorized by the Central Government in that behalf.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.19
			<lb />
			Both Section 439(1) of the 1956 Act and Section 272(1) of
			<lb />
			the 2013 Act use two important expressions, in relation to the
			<lb />
			persons competent to file a petition for winding up and the
			<lb />
			procedure to be followed. They are, (i) authorization; and (ii)
			<lb />
			sanction. The circumstances in which an &apos;authorization&apos; has to be
			<lb />
			granted and the circumstances in which a sanction has to be
			<lb />
			granted, are different. Similarly, the grant of sanction should be
			<lb />
			preceded by an opportunity of hearing, but the issue of
			<lb />
			authorization does not require any prior opportunity to the company
			<lb />
			to make a representation. Sub-sections (5) and (6) of section 439 of the 1956 Act and
			<lb />
			sub-section (3) of section 272 of the 2013 Act are presented in a table for easy reference:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			439. Provisions as to applica
			<lb />
			tions for winding up
			<lb />
			(1) ………….
			<lb />
			(2) ………….
			<lb />
			(3) ………….
			<lb />
			(4) ………….
			<lb />
			(5 ) Except in the case where he
			<lb />
			is authorised in pursuance of
			<lb />
			clause (f) of sub section (1), the
			<lb />
			Registrar shall be entitled to pre
			<lb />
			sent a petition for winding up a
			<lb />
			company only on the grounds
			<lb />
			specified in clauses (b), (c), (d), (e)
			<lb />
			and (f)] of section 433:
			<lb />
			Provided that the Registrar shall
			<lb />
			not present a petition on the
			<lb />
			ground specified in clause (e)
			<lb />
			aforesaid, unless it appears to
			<lb />
			him either from the financial
			<lb />
			condition of the company as dis
			<lb />
			closed in its balance sheet or
			<lb />
			from the report of a special audi
			<lb />
			tor appointed under section
			<lb />
			233A or an inspector] appointed
			<lb />
			under section 235 or 237, that
			<lb />
			the company is unable to pay its
			<lb />
			debts:
			<lb />
			Provided further that the Reg
			<lb />
			istrar shall obtain the previous
			<lb />
			272. Petition for winding up
			<lb />
			(1) ………..
			<lb />
			(2) ………..
			<lb />
			(3) The Registrar shall be enti
			<lb />
			tled to present a petition for
			<lb />
			winding up under section 271,
			<lb />
			except on the grounds specified
			<lb />
			in clause (a) of that section:
			<lb />
			Provided that the Registrar shall
			<lb />
			obtain the previous sanction of
			<lb />
			the Central Government to the
			<lb />
			presentation of a petition:
			<lb />
			Provided
			<lb />
			further
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Central Government shall not
			<lb />
			accord its sanction unless the
			<lb />
			company has been given a
			<lb />
			reasonable
			<lb />
			opportunity
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			making representations.
			<lb />
			sanction of the Central Gov
			<lb />
			ernment to the presentation of
			<lb />
			the petition on any of the
			<lb />
			grounds aforesaid.
			<lb />
			(6) The Central Government shall
			<lb />
			not accord its sanction in pur
			<lb />
			suance of the foregoing proviso,
			<lb />
			unless the company has first
			<lb />
			been afforded an opportunity
			<lb />
			of making its representations,
			<lb />
			if any.
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			6.20
			<lb />
			It may be seen from the above table that the second
			<lb />
			proviso to subsection (5) of section 439 of the 1956 Act became the
			<lb />
			first proviso to subsection (3) of Section 272 of the 2013 Act and
			<lb />
			subsection (6) of Section 439 became the second proviso to sub
			<lb />
			section (3) of Section 272. They respectively prescribe, (i) that for
			<lb />
			presenting a petition for winding up, the Registrar requires previous
			<lb />
			sanction of the Central Government; and (ii) that before granting
			<lb />
			sanction, the Central Government should give a reasonable
			<lb />
			opportunity to the company to make a representation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.21
			<lb />
			Thus, in effect, the distinction between the procedure to
			<lb />
			be followed by the Registrar and the procedure to be followed by
			<lb />
			&quot;any other person authorised by the Central Government&quot;, for
			<lb />
			presenting a petition for winding up, is maintained as such. If the
			<lb />
			petition is to be filed by the Registrar, it should be preceded by 2
			<lb />
			things namely, (i) a sanction; and (ii) an opportunity to the company
			<lb />
			to object. If the petition is to be filed by &quot;any other person&quot;, there is
			<lb />
			only one requirement namely that of authorization by the Central
			<lb />
			Government by notification.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.22
			<lb />
			The above discussion would show that in contrast to the
			<lb />
			1956 Act, the 2013 Act provides 2 different routes for the winding
			<lb />
			up of a company on the ground of fraud. They are:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i) winding up under clause (c) of Section 271 (directly on the
			<lb />
			ground of fraud) by any person authorised by the Central
			<lb />
			Government by notification; or
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) winding up under clause (e) of Section 271 (on the ground
			<lb />
			that it is just and equitable to wind up) in terms of Section
			<lb />
			224(2)(a) on the basis of a report of investigation under Section
			<lb />
			213(b).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.23
			<lb />
			If the second route is taken, then the power of the
			<lb />
			Tribunal to order winding up, may perhaps stand circumscribed by
			<lb />
			subsection (2) of Section 273 which states that where a petition is
			<lb />
			presented on just and equitable ground, the Tribunal may refuse to
			<lb />
			make an order of winding up, if it is of the opinion that some other
			<lb />
			remedy is available to the petitioners and that they are acting
			<lb />
			unreasonably in seeking to have the company wound up instead of
			<lb />
			pursuing the other remedy. But the question whether such a
			<lb />
			restriction could be applied to cases of fraud, established by reports
			<lb />
			of investigation, may have to be tested in appropriate cases.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.24
			<lb />
			Having seen the distinguishing features between the 1956
			<lb />
			Act and the 2013 Act, with regard to the question of availability of
			<lb />
			fraud as a ground for the winding up of a company, let us now take
			<lb />
			up for consideration, the grounds of attack to the impugned orders
			<lb />
			one after another.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Advertisement of the Company Petition
			<lb />
			Admittedly, the petition for winding up, in this case, was
			<lb />
			never advertised nor even ordered to be advertised, either upon the
			<lb />
			admission of the petition or anytime thereafter. It is therefore
			<lb />
			contended by the appellants that the failure to comply with this
			<lb />
			requirement which is mandatory, vitiates the whole proceedings.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.1
			<lb />
			Under the 1956 Act regime, the mode of proceedings to be
			<lb />
			held for winding up of a company, was prescribed by the Companies
			<lb />
			(Court) Rules, 1959 issued in exercise of the powers conferred by
			<lb />
			subsections (1) and (2) of Section 643 of the 1956 Act. Rule 10 of
			<lb />
			these 1959 Rules prescribed that all applications under the Act,
			<lb />
			unless otherwise provided by the Rules or permitted by the Judge,
			<lb />
			shall be made (i) either by a petition; or (ii) by a Judge&apos;s summons.
			<lb />
			Rule 11(a) contains a list of about 23 types of applications under the
			<lb />
			Act, which shall be made by way of petition. Rule 11(b) states that
			<lb />
			all applications other than those covered by Rule 11(a), shall be
			<lb />
			made by a Judge&apos;s summons.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.2
			<lb />
			After making a distinction between (i) applications to be
			<lb />
			made by way of a petition; and (ii) applications to be made by way of
			<lb />
			a Judge&apos;s summons in Rule 11, the Companies (Court) Rules, 1959
			<lb />
			speaks about advertisement in Rules 23 and 24. Rules 23 and 24 of
			<lb />
			the Companies (Court) Rules, 1959 read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;23. Summons for direction (a) Where a petition is
			<lb />
			presented under paragraphs (1), (3), (4), (22) and (23) of Rule
			<lb />
			11, an application shall, in every case, be made by summons
			<lb />
			to the Judge in Chambers for directions as to the
			<lb />
			advertisement of the petition, the notices to be served and
			<lb />
			the proceedings to be taken. Except where, in any particular
			<lb />
			case, a different form is prescribed by these rules, such
			<lb />
			summons shall be in Form No. 4. (b) The summons shall be
			<lb />
			posted for hearing before the Judge in Chambers at the next
			<lb />
			Chamber sittings, and the Judge may make such orders
			<lb />
			thereon and may give such directions as may seem to him
			<lb />
			appropriate. (c) No summons for directions shall be
			<lb />
			necessary in the case of other petitions, but the petition
			<lb />
			shall, upon admission, be placed before the Judge in
			<lb />
			Chambers for fixing the date of hearing and directions as to
			<lb />
			the advertisement of the petition and the notices to be
			<lb />
			served, and such other directions as may be necessary.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			24. Advertisement of petition (1) Where any petition is
			<lb />
			required to be advertised, it shall, unless the Judge
			<lb />
			otherwise orders, or these rules otherwise provide, be
			<lb />
			advertised not less than fourteen days before the date fixed
			<lb />
			for hearing, in one issue of the Official Gazette of the State or
			<lb />
			the Union Territory concerned, and in one issue each of a
			<lb />
			daily newspaper in the English language and a daily
			<lb />
			newspaper in the regional language circulating in the State
			<lb />
			or the Union Territory concerned, as may be fixed by the
			<lb />
			Judge. (2) Except in the case of a petition to windup a
			<lb />
			company the Judge may, if he thinks fit, dispense with any
			<lb />
			advertisement required by these rules.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.3
			<lb />
			As could be seen from Rule 23, the summons for
			<lb />
			directions as to advertisement of the petition, dealt with by Rule 23,
			<lb />
			correlates only to 5 out of the 23 items listed in Rule 11(a). These 5
			<lb />
			items mentioned in Rule 23, are those found in serial Nos.1, 3, 4, 22
			<lb />
			and 23 of Rule 11(a). A petition for winding up falls under item
			<lb />
			No.15 of Rule 11(a). Therefore, Rule 23 has no application to a
			<lb />
			petition for winding up.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.4
			<lb />
			Rule 24 deals with advertisement of a petition. But Rule
			<lb />
			24(1) begins with the words &quot;where any petition is required to be
			<lb />
			advertised&quot;. Therefore, Rule 24 will also have no application unless
			<lb />
			there is any provision in the Act or the Rules which require the
			<lb />
			petition to be advertised.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.5
			<lb />
			Part III of the 1959 Rules contains special provisions
			<lb />
			relating to proceedings for winding up. This part comprises of Rules
			<lb />
			95 to 338. Rule 95 requires a petition for winding up to be in Form
			<lb />
			No.45, 46 or 47. Rule 96 speaks about admission of petition and
			<lb />
			directions as to advertisement. It reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;96. Admission of petition and directions as to
			<lb />
			advertisement Upon the filing of the petition, it shall be
			<lb />
			posted before the Judge in Chambers for admission of the
			<lb />
			petition and fixing a date for the hearing thereof and for
			<lb />
			directions as to the advertisements to be published and the
			<lb />
			persons, if any, upon whom copies of the petition are to be
			<lb />
			served. The Judge may, if he thinks fit, direct notice to be
			<lb />
			given to the company before giving directions as to the
			<lb />
			advertisement of the petition.&quot;
			<lb />
			Rule 99 deals with advertisement and it reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;99. Advertisement of petition Subject to any directions
			<lb />
			of the Court, the petition shall be advertised within the time
			<lb />
			and in the manner provided by rule 24 of these rules. The
			<lb />
			advertisement shall be in Form No. 48.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.6
			<lb />
			It must be remembered that Chapter II of Part VII of the
			<lb />
			1956 Act, did not contain a provision in itself, requiring the
			<lb />
			advertisement of a petition for winding up. But Section 643(1) read
			<lb />
			with Clause (i) of Subsection (2) of Section 643 of the 1956 Act
			<lb />
			delegated to the Rule making power of the Central Government, the
			<lb />
			power to prescribe the mode of proceedings to be held for the
			<lb />
			winding up of a company by the Court. Therefore it is the Rules that
			<lb />
			speak about advertisement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.7
			<lb />
			Coming to the rules framed under the 2013 Act, Subsec
			<lb />
			tions (1) and (2) of Section 468 of the 2013 Act empower the Central
			<lb />
			Government to make Rules providing for all matters relating to
			<lb />
			winding up of companies. In exercise of the powers so conferred, the
			<lb />
			Central Government has issued a set of Rules known as the Compa
			<lb />
			nies (Winding up) Rules, 2020. Rules 5 and 7 of these Rules speak
			<lb />
			about advertisement. These Rules read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;5. Admission of petitioner and directions as to
			<lb />
			advertisement. Upon filing of the petition, it shall be
			<lb />
			posted before the Tribunal for admission of the petition and
			<lb />
			fixing a date for the hearing thereof and for appropriate
			<lb />
			directions as to the advertisements to be published and the
			<lb />
			persons, if any, upon whom copies of the petition are to be
			<lb />
			served, and where the petition has been filed by a person
			<lb />
			other than the company, the Tribunal may, if it thinks fit,
			<lb />
			direct notice to be given to the company and give an
			<lb />
			opportunity of being heard, before giving directions as to the
			<lb />
			advertisement of the petition, if any, and the petitioner shall
			<lb />
			bear all costs of the advertisement.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			7.
			<lb />
			Advertisement of petition. Subject to any directions
			<lb />
			of the Tribunal, notice of the petition shall be advertised not
			<lb />
			less than fourteen days before the date fixed for hearing in
			<lb />
			any daily newspaper in English and vernacular language
			<lb />
			widely circulated in the State or Union territory in which the
			<lb />
			registered office of the company is situated, and the
			<lb />
			advertisement shall be in Form WIN 6.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.8
			<lb />
			In view of the language employed in Rule 7 of the 2020
			<lb />
			Rules, it is contended by Shri Arvind P. Datar, learned senior
			<lb />
			counsel appearing for DEMPL, that there is no option available to
			<lb />
			NCLT but to order the advertisement of the petition. Rule 7 begins
			<lb />
			with the words &quot;subject to any directions of the Tribunal, notice of the
			<lb />
			petition shall be advertised&quot;. These words, in the contention of the
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel for DEMPL, indicate the availability of a
			<lb />
			limited elbow space to the Tribunal to issue directions about the
			<lb />
			newspaper in which the advertisement is to be issued and the
			<lb />
			particular edition (State, Regional or National Edition) in which the
			<lb />
			advertisement shall be published. In other words, his contention is
			<lb />
			that ordering the publication of an advertisement is mandatory, but
			<lb />
			smaller things such as the particular newspaper, particular edition
			<lb />
			etc., are left to the discretion of the Tribunal to be exercised in the
			<lb />
			form of directions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.9
			<lb />
			Before we test the correctness of the above argument, it
			<lb />
			may be necessary to look at the anatomy of Rule 5 which prescribes
			<lb />
			the procedure to be followed by the Tribunal, upon the filing of a
			<lb />
			petition for winding up. The stepbystep procedure prescribed in
			<lb />
			Rule 5 is as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(1) The petition should first be posted before the Tribunal for
			<lb />
			admission.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(2) The purpose of posting the petition for admission is three
			<lb />
			fold, namely, (i) fixing a date for hearing of the petition;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) issuing appropriate directions as to the advertisement to be
			<lb />
			published; and (iii) indicating the persons upon whom the
			<lb />
			copies of the petition are to be served.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(3) On the date when the petition is posted for admission, the
			<lb />
			Tribunal may direct notice to be given to the company
			<lb />
			and also provide an opportunity of being heard before
			<lb />
			giving directions as to the advertisement of the petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.10
			<lb />
			The essence of Rule 5 is to provide an opportunity of being
			<lb />
			heard to the company sought to be wound up, even before directions
			<lb />
			as to the advertisement of the petition are given. The last limb of
			<lb />
			Rule 5 speaks about the discretion vested in the Tribunal to direct
			<lb />
			notice to be given to the company and to give an opportunity of
			<lb />
			being heard before giving any directions as to the advertisement of
			<lb />
			the petition. This last limb of Rule 5 provides the clue about the
			<lb />
			purpose of advertisement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.11
			<lb />
			One way of looking at the requirement of an advertisement
			<lb />
			is that it provides an opportunity to all the stakeholders such as
			<lb />
			(i) creditors; (ii) workers; (iii) suppliers; (iv) customers; and (v) the
			<lb />
			general public, either to support or oppose the proceedings for
			<lb />
			winding up. There is also another way of looking at the object of
			<lb />
			issuing an advertisement of the petition for winding up. The
			<lb />
			advertisement serves as a warning/notice or red alert to all those
			<lb />
			dealing with the company so that they know that there could be an
			<lb />
			element of risk in dealing with the company.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.12
			<lb />
			After all, the winding up of a company is like the
			<lb />
			insolvency of an individual. The advertisement of the petition for
			<lb />
			winding up, not merely serves as an opportunity to support or
			<lb />
			oppose winding up, but also harms the reputation of the company
			<lb />
			and sends shock waves in the stock market, if it is a listed company
			<lb />
			or among the stakeholders who have dealings with the company.
			<lb />
			This is why an opportunity of being heard is contemplated in Rule 5,
			<lb />
			before ordering the advertisement of the petition. This is exactly the
			<lb />
			reason why this Court held in National Conduits (P) Ltd. vs. S.S.
			<lb />
			Arora 8 as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;xxxxx
			<lb />
			xxxxx
			<lb />
			xxxxx
			<lb />
			The view taken by the High Court that the Court must, as
			<lb />
			soon as the petition is admitted, advertise the petition is
			<lb />
			contrary to the plain terms of Rule 96. Such a view, if
			<lb />
			accepted, would make the Court an instrument, in
			<lb />
			possible cases, of harassment and even of blackmail, for
			<lb />
			once a petition is advertised, the business of the
			<lb />
			Company is bound to suffer serious loss and injury.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.13
			<lb />
			The decision is National Conduits (P) Ltd. (supra) was
			<lb />
			followed in Cotton Corporation of India Limited vs. United
			<lb />
			Industrial Bank Ltd. &amp; Ors. 9 In fact, the argument of the
			<lb />
			companies sought to be wound up in Cotton Corporation of India
			<lb />
			Limited (supra) was that &quot;the presentation of winding up petition
			<lb />
			coupled with advertisement thereof in newspapers, has certain
			<lb />
			serious consequences on the status, standing, financial
			<lb />
			viability and stability and operational efficiency of the
			<lb />
			company.&quot; While dispelling the apprehensions so expressed, this
			<lb />
			Court relied upon the decision in National Conduits (P) Ltd.
			<lb />
			(supra) to say that the apprehensions stood removed by taking a
			<lb />
			view that advertisement is not automatic.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.14
			<lb />
			Therefore, the way in which the requirement of
			<lb />
			advertisement has been viewed by Courts is that advertisement
			<lb />
			causes more harm to the company than the benefit that it brings to
			<lb />
			the company. Hence the argument of the appellant in this case that
			<lb />
			the failure to advertise the petition was prejudicial to their interest,
			<lb />
			goes contrary to one of the important purposes of the advertisement
			<lb />
			and the chilling effect that it is supposed to have on the company.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.15
			<lb />
			It is no doubt true that in National Conduits, this Court
			<lb />
			was concerned with an appeal arising out of an order of the Delhi
			<lb />
			High Court, holding that once a petition is admitted to file, the Court
			<lb />
			is bound forthwith to advertise the petition. Interestingly, such an
			<lb />
			order was challenged by the Company itself on the ground that
			<lb />
			advertisement was prejudicial to them. While considering the
			<lb />
			challenge, in terms of Rule 24(2), this Court held in National
			<lb />
			Conduits (in paragraph 4) that a petition for winding up cannot be
			<lb />
			placed for hearing before the Court, unless the petition is advertised.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.16
			<lb />
			In IDBI Bank Ltd. vs. the Official Liquidator 10 ,
			<lb />
			authored by one of us (VRS, J.) as a Company Judge in the High
			<lb />
			Court of Judicature at Madras, it was held that Rule 99 of the 1959
			<lb />
			Rules makes it mandatory for an advertisement to be issued and
			<lb />
			that Rule 24(2) does not confer any power even upon the Company
			<lb />
			Court to dispense with any advertisement, in the proceedings for
			<lb />
			winding up. It was also pointed out in IDBI Bank Ltd. (supra) that
			<lb />
			Rule 100(2) which prohibits the withdrawal of a winding up petition
			<lb />
			before the date fixed in the advertisement for the hearing of the
			<lb />
			parties, also provided a clue about the mandatory nature of the
			<lb />
			requirement to advertise. In the aforesaid decision, Rule 101 which
			<lb />
			provides for the substitution of a creditor or contributory in the
			<lb />
			place of the original petitioner, upon his failure to advertise, was
			<lb />
			also taken note of. Rule 101 of the Companies (Court) Rules, 1959
			<lb />
			reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Rule 101. Substitution of creditor or contributory for
			<lb />
			original petitioner. -Where a petitioner. -
			<lb />
			(1)
			<lb />
			is not entitled to present a petition, or
			<lb />
			(2)
			<lb />
			fails to advertise his petition within the time prescribed
			<lb />
			by these rules or by order of court or such extended time as
			<lb />
			the court may allow, or
			<lb />
			(3)
			<lb />
			consents to withdraw the petition, or to allow it to be
			<lb />
			dismissed, or the hearing to be adjourned or fails to appear
			<lb />
			in support of his petition when it is called on in court on the
			<lb />
			day originally fixed for the hearing thereof, or any day to
			<lb />
			which the hearing has been adjourned, or
			<lb />
			(4)
			<lb />
			if appearing, does not apply for an order in terms of the
			<lb />
			prayer of his petition
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			where in the opinion of the court there is other sufficient
			<lb />
			cause for an order being made under this rule, the court
			<lb />
			may, upon such terms as it may think just, substitute as pe
			<lb />
			titioner any creditor or contributory who, in the opinion of
			<lb />
			the court, would have a right to present a petition, and who
			<lb />
			is desirous of prosecuting the petition.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.17
			<lb />
			In the light of the aforesaid Rule 101 also, it was held in
			<lb />
			IDBI Bank Ltd., that the requirement of advertisement was
			<lb />
			mandatory. While coming to the said conclusion, the Madras High
			<lb />
			Court also took note of the difference of opinion in this regard
			<lb />
			between the High Courts of Allahabad and Gujarat on the one hand
			<lb />
			and the High Court of Delhi on the other hand, with respect to the
			<lb />
			power of the Court to dispense with the publication of advertisement
			<lb />
			in the official Gazette. Paragraphs 53 to 55 of the decision of the
			<lb />
			Madras High Court in IDBI Bank Ltd. is reproduced for easy
			<lb />
			reference as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;53. In U.P. Twiga Fiberglass Ltd vs. Parekh Marketing Pvt.
			<lb />
			Ltd {1986 (59) CC 886}, a Division Bench of the Allahabad
			<lb />
			High Court considered on appeal, a question, among others,
			<lb />
			as to whether the nonpublication of the advertisement in
			<lb />
			the Gazette would be violative of Rule 24. In that case, the
			<lb />
			Company Judge ordered the publication of advertisements in
			<lb />
			one English Daily and one Vernacular Daily, but not in the
			<lb />
			Gazette. The Division Bench of the Allahabad High Court
			<lb />
			held that Rule 24(1) contains a rider &quot;unless the Judge oth
			<lb />
			erwise orders&quot; and that Rule 99 also speaks about &quot;subject
			<lb />
			to any directions of the Court&quot;. A similar view with regard to
			<lb />
			the power of the Company Court to dispense with the publi
			<lb />
			cation of advertisement in the Government Gazette was
			<lb />
			taken by a Division Bench of the Gujarat High Court in Plas
			<lb />
			tisac P. Ltd vs. Gujarat Lease Finance Ltd {2000 (101) CC
			<lb />
			334 (Guj.)}. But a Division Bench of the Delhi High Court
			<lb />
			disagreed with the views expressed by the Allahabad and
			<lb />
			Gujarat High Courts, with regard to the power of the Com
			<lb />
			pany Court to dispense with the publication of advertisement
			<lb />
			in the Official Gazette. In Lt. Col. R.K.Saxena vs. Imperial
			<lb />
			Forestry Corporation {2001 (107) CC 401 (Del.)}, a Division
			<lb />
			Bench of the Delhi High Court, after a careful consideration
			<lb />
			of Rules 96, 99 and 24 held that &quot;the publication of the ad
			<lb />
			vertisement of a petition for winding up is mandatory, even
			<lb />
			in respect of the Official Gazette&quot;. On the scope of the discre
			<lb />
			tion conferred by Rule 99, the Delhi High Court held that the
			<lb />
			discretion is limited only to the extent of deciding at what
			<lb />
			stage the petition is to be advertised. The contention that the
			<lb />
			Company Court has inherent powers by virtue of Rule 9 even
			<lb />
			to dispense with the requirement of Rule 24, was also re
			<lb />
			jected by the Delhi High Court on the ground that &quot;if a
			<lb />
			statute requires a thing to be done in a particular manner, it
			<lb />
			shall be done in that manner or not at all&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			54. Though there was a difference of opinion between the Al
			<lb />
			lahabad and Gujarat High Courts on the one hand and the
			<lb />
			Delhi High Court on the other hand, with regard to the
			<lb />
			power to dispense with the publication of advertisement in
			<lb />
			the Official Gazette, all these Courts were unanimous in
			<lb />
			their opinion at least with regard to the mandatory nature of
			<lb />
			the requirement of publication of advertisements, in one
			<lb />
			English Daily and one Vernacular Daily as ordered by the
			<lb />
			Company Judge. Therefore, it is clear that publication of ad
			<lb />
			vertisements is mandatory. Irrespective of whether the Court
			<lb />
			has any discretion to dispense with the publication in the
			<lb />
			Gazette or not, the publication of advertisements at least in
			<lb />
			newspapers is mandatory and the failure of the petitioning
			<lb />
			creditor to comply with this requirement despite a positive
			<lb />
			order to that effect, is fatal to his petition.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			55. In Falcon Gulf Ceramics Ltd vs. Industrial Designs Bu
			<lb />
			reau {1996 (86) CC 207 (Raj.)}, a Division Bench of the Ra
			<lb />
			jasthan High Court set aside an order of winding up passed
			<lb />
			by the Company Court, on the sole ground that the winding
			<lb />
			up order was not preceded by an advertisement. The Divi
			<lb />
			sion Bench of the Rajasthan High Court held in that case
			<lb />
			that advertisement of a petition was imperative in view of the
			<lb />
			provisions of Rule 96 read with Rule 99. For holding so, the
			<lb />
			Division Bench of the Rajasthan High Court relied upon
			<lb />
			paragraph 1463 of Halsbury&apos;s Laws of England (4th Edition),
			<lb />
			which stated that noncompliance with these provisions is a
			<lb />
			ground on which the Court shall reject the petition. After cit
			<lb />
			ing the relevant passage from the decision of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in National Conduits, the Division Bench held in para
			<lb />
			16 of its decision that in the absence of advertisement and
			<lb />
			admission, the petition for winding up was bound to be re
			<lb />
			jected.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.18
			<lb />
			However, when the decision of the Company Judge in
			<lb />
			IDBI Bank Ltd. was assailed in an intracourt appeal, the Division
			<lb />
			bench of the Madras High Court held in Pradeep D. Kothari vs.
			<lb />
			IDBI Bank Ltd. 11 as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;31. Therefore, to our minds, two aspects would arise for
			<lb />
			consideration given the fact and circumstances obtaining in
			<lb />
			the instant case. First, if, winding up is not advertised, by
			<lb />
			the original petitioner as directed, can the Court direct the
			<lb />
			PL to advertise the petition, having regard to the fact that the
			<lb />
			proceedings are inter alia for the benefit of creditors at large
			<lb />
			and not one single creditor ?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			31.1. The answer to this poser, to our minds, has to be in af
			<lb />
			firmative as there is no bar in the Rules which prohibits a PL
			<lb />
			from advertising the Company Petition in such like circum
			<lb />
			stances, though, ordinarily, in practice, Company Petitions
			<lb />
			are advertised by the petitioner who institutes the action. As
			<lb />
			alluded to above, the Rules do not bar the Company Court
			<lb />
			from directing the PL to advertise the petition. The reason,
			<lb />
			why we hold this view is plainly this, that, while, adver
			<lb />
			tisement of the petition is compulsory as winding up
			<lb />
			proceedings are proceedings in rem and therefore should
			<lb />
			receive the widest of publicity enabling all stakeholders
			<lb />
			to have notice of the proceedings, there is no such stipu
			<lb />
			lation in the Rules that once, the winding up petition is
			<lb />
			admitted by a Court, it can in no circumstances move
			<lb />
			forward, unless an advertisement is taken out by the
			<lb />
			original petitioner or a suitable substituent who fulfills
			<lb />
			the qualifications provided in Rule 101(4).&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.19
			<lb />
			But the Judgment of the Company Judge of the Madras
			<lb />
			High Court in IDBI Bank Ltd. and the Judgment of the Division
			<lb />
			Bench in Pradeep D. Kothari, arose out of proceedings for winding
			<lb />
			up, in which a specific order directing the publication of the
			<lb />
			advertisement had been made by the Company Court at the time of
			<lb />
			admission. However, the said direction was omitted to be complied
			<lb />
			with, by the petitioning creditor. Therefore, the crucial question that
			<lb />
			fell for consideration in that case was as to how a company Judge
			<lb />
			should proceed, in circumstances where the petitioning creditor
			<lb />
			loses interest in prosecuting the petition further and abandons the
			<lb />
			proceedings without carrying out the advertisement. This question
			<lb />
			assumed significance in the light of the fact that the failure of one
			<lb />
			petitioning creditor cannot result in serious prejudice to a whole
			<lb />
			body of creditors, in a proceedings in rem.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.20
			<lb />
			The above decision of the Division Bench of the Madras
			<lb />
			High Court in Pradeep D. Kothari was assailed before this Court.
			<lb />
			While upholding the decision of the Division Bench, in its decision in
			<lb />
			IDBI Bank Ltd. vs. the Official Liquidator 12 , this Court held as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;14.3.
			<lb />
			Against this backdrop, the crucial question that
			<lb />
			arises for our consideration is whether a winding up petition
			<lb />
			can be dismissed solely on the ground lack of a prosecuting
			<lb />
			creditor under Rule 101, or whether the Company Court has
			<lb />
			the power to direct the publication of an advertisement by
			<lb />
			the Liquidator of the company, especially in cases where
			<lb />
			other unsatisfied creditors still remain. For answering this
			<lb />
			question, it is important to bear in mind that winding
			<lb />
			proceedings are proceedings in rem and have an impact
			<lb />
			on the rights of people, in general. Thus, it is mandatory
			<lb />
			to advertise such proceedings so as to ensure that they
			<lb />
			receive the widest possible publicity and all relevant
			<lb />
			stakeholders have adequate notice. This implies that in a
			<lb />
			situation where the petitioning creditor fails to advertise the
			<lb />
			petition and no other creditor or contributory comes forward
			<lb />
			to prosecute it, Rule 101 should not be read in a manner
			<lb />
			that absolutely bars the continuation of a winding up
			<lb />
			petition. This is particularly so when there are unsatisfied
			<lb />
			creditors who should have been given an opportunity to
			<lb />
			prosecute the petition, but were deprived of the same due to
			<lb />
			the failure to advertise. Indeed, Rule 101 is only limited to
			<lb />
			instances where the petitioning creditor fails to advertise the
			<lb />
			petition. However, there is nothing in the language of Rule
			<lb />
			24, 96 or 99 to indicate that only such petitioning creditor
			<lb />
			can advertise the petition. In our considered opinion, given
			<lb />
			the absence of a specific provision mandating that the
			<lb />
			petition can only be advertised by the petitioning creditor,
			<lb />
			the Company Court has the discretion to direct the
			<lb />
			publishing of an advertisement to secure the interest of other
			<lb />
			creditors. In such situations, the winding up proceedings
			<lb />
			cannot be dismissed, as it would frustrate the very objective
			<lb />
			of securing the interest of all creditors.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			14.4.
			<lb />
			In the light of this discussion, we find that it
			<lb />
			would be unjust to dismiss the winding up petition in the
			<lb />
			instant case solely on the ground that there is no other
			<lb />
			person willing to substitute the original creditor in terms of
			<lb />
			Rule 101. Here, due to the lack of advertisement of the
			<lb />
			winding petitions, it appears that the secured creditors of
			<lb />
			KOFL were constrained to approach the DRT for recovery of
			<lb />
			their dues by filling OAs Nos. 139 of 2001, 978 of 2000 and
			<lb />
			14 of 2002. Further, upon learning of the decision of the
			<lb />
			Company Judge dated 04.10.2013, dismissing the winding
			<lb />
			up petition, one of the secured creditors (SBI) also
			<lb />
			approached the DRT to secure its interest. Based on this,
			<lb />
			vide order dated 13.12.2013, the DRT had directed that the
			<lb />
			amount to be returned to KOFL be attached so that the
			<lb />
			banks have an opportunity to recover their dues from KOFL.
			<lb />
			This clearly goes on to show that the secured creditors of
			<lb />
			KOFL were relevant stakeholders who were affected by the
			<lb />
			nonadvertising of the windingup petition. They should
			<lb />
			have been called upon to indicate whether they would want
			<lb />
			to step into the shoes of the petitioning creditors as per Rule
			<lb />
			101.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.21
			<lb />
			Thus even in a case where the Court took a view that
			<lb />
			advertisement is mandatory, not only in view of the prescription
			<lb />
			contained in the Rules, but also in view of the specific order passed
			<lb />
			by the Company Court at the time of admission, directing the
			<lb />
			publication of the advertisement in specified newspapers, this Court
			<lb />
			did not see the failure to publish an advertisement as something
			<lb />
			that would lead to the automatic dismissal of the petition for
			<lb />
			winding up. This is for the reason that the advertisement of a
			<lb />
			petition for winding up is perceived to be something that worked at
			<lb />
			cross purposes, sometimes beneficial to several stakeholders as it
			<lb />
			provides an opportunity of hearing to them and sometimes as a
			<lb />
			measure of harassment of the company. There are cases where the
			<lb />
			companies themselves have opposed the advertisement of the
			<lb />
			petition on the ground that the same would harm their reputation
			<lb />
			and cripple their commercial activities. There are also cases where
			<lb />
			the failure to advertise has led to some of the creditors not having
			<lb />
			any notice of the proceedings and thereby suffering prejudice. This
			<lb />
			is why another Bench of the Madras High Court held in
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			T. Narayanan vs. the Official Liquidator 13 , after taking note of
			<lb />
			the decision in National Conduits, as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;38. Assuming that the mandatory requirement was not
			<lb />
			complied with, the question falling for consideration is, can
			<lb />
			the noncompliance of procedural mandatory requirement
			<lb />
			would ipso facto vitiate the winding up order and stall fur
			<lb />
			ther proceedings?. The next question falling for considera
			<lb />
			tion is &apos;can the noncompliance of a procedural manda
			<lb />
			tory requirement be a ground to set aside the winding up
			<lb />
			order after three years, especially when the appellant
			<lb />
			had the opportunity of fighting out the litigation in the
			<lb />
			earlier round?&apos;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			39. The purpose of advertisement is to give an opportunity to
			<lb />
			the creditors/debtors/Company to put forth their case be
			<lb />
			fore the Court. Assuming that the procedural mandatory
			<lb />
			requirement was not complied with, in our considered
			<lb />
			view, it cannot be a ground to set aside the winding up
			<lb />
			order after three years. As rightly contended by the
			<lb />
			learned Senior Counsel for the Official Liquidator, to sus
			<lb />
			tain the allegations of violation of principles of natural
			<lb />
			justice, one must establish prejudice. When fairness is
			<lb />
			shown and if the facts and circumstances indicate that
			<lb />
			the Company/contributory were put on notice and that
			<lb />
			no prejudice was caused to them, the Company/contrib
			<lb />
			utory cannot complain of any procedural irregularity.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.22
			<lb />
			We may also have to take note of one more aspect. The
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 2013 mandates the constitution of a National
			<lb />
			Company Law Tribunal and a National Company Law Appellate
			<lb />
			Tribunal to exercise and discharge such powers and functions as
			<lb />
			may be conferred upon it by or under the Act. Section 424(1) makes
			<lb />
			it clear (i) that the Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall not be
			<lb />
			bound by the procedure laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure,
			<lb />
			1908, but shall be guided by the principles of natural justice; and
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) that subject to the other provisions of the Act and of any rules
			<lb />
			made thereunder, the Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall
			<lb />
			have power to regulate their own procedure.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.23
			<lb />
			While Section 468(1) of the 2013 Act empowers the
			<lb />
			Central Government to make Rules consistent with the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure, providing for all matters relating to winding up, Section
			<lb />
			469(1) empowers the Central Government generally to make Rules
			<lb />
			for carrying out the provisions of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.24
			<lb />
			In exercise of the powers conferred by Sections 468 and
			<lb />
			469, the Central Government issued the Companies (Winding Up)
			<lb />
			Rules 2020. Similarly, the Central Government issued another set of
			<lb />
			Rules called the National Company Law Tribunal Rules, 2016 (for
			<lb />
			short &quot;NCLT Rules 2016&quot;) in exercise of the powers conferred by
			<lb />
			Section 469.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.25
			<lb />
			Rule 35 of the National Company Law Tribunal Rules,
			<lb />
			2016 deals with advertisement of petitions. It reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;35. Advertisement detailing petition. (1) Where any
			<lb />
			application, petition or reference is required to be advertised,
			<lb />
			it shall, unless the Tribunal otherwise orders, or these rules
			<lb />
			otherwise provide, be advertised in Form NCLT3A, not less
			<lb />
			than fourteen days before the date fixed for hearing, at least
			<lb />
			once in a vernacular newspaper in the principal vernacular
			<lb />
			language of the district in which the registered office of the
			<lb />
			company is situate, and at least once in English language in
			<lb />
			an English newspaper circulating in that district.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) Every such advertisement shall state;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			the date on which the application, petition or reference
			<lb />
			was presented;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			the name and address of the applicant, petitioner and
			<lb />
			his authorised representative, if any;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			the nature and substance of application, petition or
			<lb />
			reference;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d)
			<lb />
			the date fixed for hearing;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e)
			<lb />
			a statement to the effect that any person whose
			<lb />
			interest is likely to be affected by the proposed petition
			<lb />
			or who intends either to oppose or support the petition
			<lb />
			or reference at the hearing shall send a notice of his
			<lb />
			intention to the concerned Bench and the petitioner or
			<lb />
			his authorised representative, if any, indicating the
			<lb />
			nature of interest and grounds of opposition so as to
			<lb />
			reach him not later than two days previous to the day
			<lb />
			fixed for hearing.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(3) Where the advertisement is being given by the company,
			<lb />
			then the same may also be placed on the website of the
			<lb />
			company, if any.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(4) An affidavit shall be filed to the Tribunal, not less than
			<lb />
			three days before the date fixed for hearing, stating whether
			<lb />
			the petition has been advertised in accordance with this rule
			<lb />
			and whether the notices, if any, have been duly served upon
			<lb />
			the persons required to be served:
			<lb />
			Provided that the affidavit shall be accompanied with
			<lb />
			such proof of advertisement or of the service, as may be
			<lb />
			available.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(5) Where the requirements of this rule or the direction of the
			<lb />
			Tribunal, as regards the advertisement and service of
			<lb />
			petition, are not complied with, the Tribunal may either
			<lb />
			dismiss the petition or give such further directions as it
			<lb />
			thinks fit.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(6) The Tribunal may, if it thinks fit, and upon an application
			<lb />
			being made by the party, may dispense with any
			<lb />
			advertisement required to be published under this rule.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.26
			<lb />
			It may be seen from Subrule (1) of Rule 35 that the
			<lb />
			procedure laid down in Rule 35 is applicable to cases &quot;where any
			<lb />
			application, petition or reference is required to be advertised.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.27
			<lb />
			The requirement to advertise a petition for winding up
			<lb />
			does not flow out of the statute, but flows out of the Rules. Since the
			<lb />
			requirement to advertise a petition for winding up is stipulated in
			<lb />
			Rules 5 and 7 of the Companies (Winding up) Rules, 2020, what is
			<lb />
			prescribed in Rule 35 would cover even petitions for winding up.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.28
			<lb />
			If so understood, Subrules (5) and (6) of Rule 35 of the
			<lb />
			NCLT Rules 2016 would throw light upon the controversy on hand.
			<lb />
			Subrule (5) makes it clear that even in cases where the direction of
			<lb />
			the Tribunal as regards advertisement has not been complied with,
			<lb />
			the Tribunal has an option (i) either to dismiss the petition; or (ii) to
			<lb />
			give such further directions as it may think fit. Subrule (6) confers
			<lb />
			power upon the Tribunal even to dispense with any advertisement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.29
			<lb />
			In other words, what was not specifically available in
			<lb />
			black and white, under the 1956 statutory regime, namely the power
			<lb />
			to dispense with any advertisement, is now made available
			<lb />
			specifically under the statutory regime of 2013.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.30
			<lb />
			In the case on hand, the company in liquidation was
			<lb />
			incorporated on 17.12.2004, the Memorandum of Association of the
			<lb />
			Company was subscribed to by two persons by name D. Venugopal
			<lb />
			and M. Umesh. They subscribed to 9000 equity shares and 1000
			<lb />
			equity shares respectively @ Rs.10 per share. Subsequently six
			<lb />
			individuals by name Ramachandran Vishwanathan, Paresh Shah
			<lb />
			Natwarlal, James Fox, MG Chandrasekar, Abhishek Jain and L
			<lb />
			Clarence Irving were issued with equity shares on 31.12.2005.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, two corporate entities, namely, Columbus Capital Devas
			<lb />
			(Mauritius) Ltd. and the Telecom Devas Mauritius Ltd., were issued
			<lb />
			Optionally Convertible Preference Shares and equity shares.
			<lb />
			Subsequently, two other companies by name Deutsche Telecom Asia
			<lb />
			Plc. Ltd. and Devas Employees Mauritius Pvt. Ltd. were issued with
			<lb />
			equity shares. All these shareholders are aware of the winding up
			<lb />
			proceedings and the proceedings are fought tooth and nail by one
			<lb />
			shareholder DEMPL through Mr. Ramachandran Vishwanathan who
			<lb />
			was also a shareholder. Another individual shareholder by name MG
			<lb />
			Chandrasekar has filed one of the above appeals as the exdirector
			<lb />
			of the company in liquidation. Admittedly, the company in
			<lb />
			liquidation does not have any creditors or customers who have
			<lb />
			dealings with the company. In other words, there are no
			<lb />
			stakeholders who are prejudiced by the failure of NCLT to order the
			<lb />
			publication of advertisement of the petition. Though technically the
			<lb />
			Tribunal may not be correct in invoking &quot;useless formality theory&quot; in
			<lb />
			cases of this nature, we can certainly apply the test of prejudice,
			<lb />
			especially in the light of the serious nature of the allegations of
			<lb />
			fraud, on the basis of which the company is sought to be wound up.
			<lb />
			This is not a case where the company is sought to be wound up on
			<lb />
			the ground of inability to pay debts or on just and equitable ground.
			<lb />
			This is a case of fraud and all stakeholders are fully aware of the
			<lb />
			proceedings and they have even shown extreme urgency in enforcing
			<lb />
			an ICC Arbitration award and 2 BIT awards, before the conclusion of
			<lb />
			the winding up proceedings. Therefore, we are unable to sustain the
			<lb />
			argument that the failure of the Tribunal to order the publication of
			<lb />
			an advertisement rendered the entire proceedings unlawful.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.31
			<lb />
			The Companies (Winding Up) Rules, 2020 contain a list of
			<lb />
			Forms in which all the proceedings before the Tribunal are to be
			<lb />
			couched. While FORM WIN 1 prescribes the format of a petition for
			<lb />
			winding up by a person other than the company and Forms WIN 2,
			<lb />
			WIN 3 etc., prescribe the formats of certain other things, FORM WIN
			<lb />
			11 prescribes the format of a winding up order. The National
			<lb />
			Company Law Tribunal is obliged under Rule 17(1) of the
			<lb />
			Companies (Winding Up) Rules 2020, to prepare the order for
			<lb />
			winding up in FORM WIN 11 with such variations as may be
			<lb />
			necessary. On the basis of the contents of FORM WIN 11, it was
			<lb />
			argued by the learned counsel for the appellants that paper
			<lb />
			publication of the advertisement of the winding up petition is
			<lb />
			mandatory.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.32
			<lb />
			FORM WIN 11 reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			FORM WIN 11
			<lb />
			[See rule 17(1)]
			<lb />
			Before The National Company Law Tribunal
			<lb />
			Bench At……………………………
			<lb />
			In The Matter ofLtd (Give The Name of The Company)
			<lb />
			(Company incorporated under Companies Act,……………….. )
			<lb />
			Company Petition No…../20……..
			<lb />
			……………….&apos;Petitioner
			<lb />
			Before the Hon&apos;ble Mr.
			<lb />
			Dated…………
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Winding up Order
			<lb />
			Upon the petition of…………….. presented on the day
			<lb />
			of……… .20 , upon hearing Shri ……………representative for
			<lb />
			the petitioner Shri representative for the creditors (or
			<lb />
			contributors)
			<lb />
			supporting
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			petition,
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Shri……………………….. representative for the creditors (or
			<lb />
			contributors) opposing the petition, and Shri…………………
			<lb />
			representative for the company, upon reading the said
			<lb />
			petition, the affidavit of A.B., filed the ………………….day
			<lb />
			of……………... 20 verifying the said petition, the affidavit of
			<lb />
			x.y., filed the ....... day of…………… 20 ..... the (state or
			<lb />
			union territory) paper publication of the advertisement of
			<lb />
			the said petition this Tribunal doth order:
			<lb />
			*(1) That the said company be wound up by this Tribunal
			<lb />
			under the provisions of the Companies Act, 2013; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) That the provisional liquidator or Company Liquidator as
			<lb />
			the case may be as liquidator of the company aforesaid
			<lb />
			forthwith take charge of all the property effects actionable
			<lb />
			claims and books and papers of the said company;
			<lb />
			**(3) That the provisional liquidator or Company Liquidator
			<lb />
			shall cause a sealed copy of this order to be served on the
			<lb />
			company by pre&apos;paid registered post;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(4) That the petitioner do advertise within fourteen days
			<lb />
			from this date a notice in the prescribed form of the
			<lb />
			making of this order in one issue (each) of. .. (here enter
			<lb />
			the newspaper or newspapers in which the order is to be
			<lb />
			advertised);
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(5) That the said petitioner do serve a certified copy of this
			<lb />
			order on the Registrar of Companies not later than one
			<lb />
			month from this date; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(6) That the cost of the said petition shall be paid out of the
			<lb />
			assets of the said company.
			<lb />
			Dated this …...... day ….... 20.
			<lb />
			(By the Tribunal)
			<lb />
			Registrar
			<lb />
			*Where the company ordered to be wound up is a Banking
			<lb />
			Company or an Insurance Company add at the end of clause
			<lb />
			(1) &quot;and the Banking Companies Act, 1949&apos; or &apos;and the
			<lb />
			Insurance Act 1938&quot; as the case may be.
			<lb />
			** To be inserted only where the company is not the
			<lb />
			petitioner.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.33
			<lb />
			The above FORM WIN 11 contains a reference to
			<lb />
			advertisement, in two places. In the first place, it is found in the
			<lb />
			preamble portion of the format, beginning with the words &quot;upon the
			<lb />
			petition…..&quot;. In the second place, a reference to advertisement is
			<lb />
			found in paragraph 4 of FORM WIN 11. While the advertisement
			<lb />
			referred to in the preamble of FORM WIN 11, obviously relates to the
			<lb />
			advertisement of the petition, the advertisement referred to in
			<lb />
			paragraph 4 of WIN 11 relates to the advertisement of the making of
			<lb />
			the order of winding up. It is needless to say that the advertisement
			<lb />
			of the petition for winding up is different from the advertisement of
			<lb />
			an order of winding up.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.34
			<lb />
			In so far as the advertisement of the order of winding up is
			<lb />
			concerned, Rules 19 and 20 occupy the field. Rules 19 and 20 of the
			<lb />
			Companies (Winding Up) Rules, 2020 read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;19. Directions on making winding up order. At the time
			<lb />
			of making the winding up order or at any time thereafter the
			<lb />
			Tribunal shall give directions to the petitioner as to the
			<lb />
			advertisement of the order and the persons if any on whom
			<lb />
			the order shall be served and the persons if any to whom
			<lb />
			notice shall be given of the further proceedings in the
			<lb />
			liquidation and such further directions as may be necessary.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			20. Advertisement of order. Save as otherwise ordered by
			<lb />
			the Tribunal the order for the winding up of a company by
			<lb />
			the Tribunal shall within fourteen days of the date of the
			<lb />
			order be advertised by the petitioner in a newspaper in the
			<lb />
			English language and a newspaper in vernacular language
			<lb />
			widely circulating in the State or the Union territory where
			<lb />
			the registered office of the company is situated and shall be
			<lb />
			served by the petitioner upon such person if any and in such
			<lb />
			manner as the Tribunal may direct and the advertisement
			<lb />
			shall be in Form WIN 14&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			7.35
			<lb />
			Rule 19 mandates the Tribunal, at the time of making
			<lb />
			of the winding up order or any time thereafter to give directions
			<lb />
			to the petitioner as to the advertisement of the order. This is why
			<lb />
			paragraph 4 of FORM WIN 11 forms part of the operative portion of
			<lb />
			the FORM.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.36
			<lb />
			In so far as the reference to advertisement contained in
			<lb />
			the preamble of FORM WIN 11 is concerned, it is merely one of the
			<lb />
			several items that the Tribunal may take into account for passing a
			<lb />
			winding up order. The items mentioned in the preamble of FORM
			<lb />
			WIN 11 are, (i) the petition for winding up; (ii) the hearing of the
			<lb />
			representative for the petitioner; (iii) the hearing of the
			<lb />
			representative for the creditors or contributories supporting the
			<lb />
			petition; (iv) the hearing of the representative for the creditors or
			<lb />
			contributories opposing the petition; (v) the hearing of the
			<lb />
			representative of the company; (vi) the affidavits; and (vii) the paper
			<lb />
			publication of the advertisement of the petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.37
			<lb />
			Thus the preamble merely contains a list of several
			<lb />
			matters that may be taken into account by the Tribunal before
			<lb />
			passing an order of winding up. All those items need not necessarily
			<lb />
			be present in all cases. For instance, there may be cases where the
			<lb />
			petition may not be supported by all creditors or contributories.
			<lb />
			There may also be cases where the petition may not be opposed by
			<lb />
			all creditors or contributories. However, there is a mention in the
			<lb />
			preamble about the hearing of the representatives of creditors
			<lb />
			supporting or opposing the winding up petition. Therefore, we
			<lb />
			cannot hold that merely because something is mentioned in the
			<lb />
			preamble of Form WIN11, it becomes mandatory.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			LIMITATION
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.1
			<lb />
			The second ground on which the impugned orders are
			<lb />
			assailed, is that the petition under Section 271(c) was hopelessly
			<lb />
			barred by limitation. Section 433 of the Companies Act, 2013 makes
			<lb />
			the provisions of the Limitation Act, 1963 applicable to proceedings
			<lb />
			or appeals before the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal as the case
			<lb />
			may be. Therefore, it is the contention of the learned senior counsel
			<lb />
			for the appellants that Article 137 of the Schedule to the Limitation
			<lb />
			Act, which prescribes a period of limitation of 3 years for any
			<lb />
			application for which no period is prescribed elsewhere, is applicable
			<lb />
			to the case on hand. The period of 3 years so prescribed, according
			<lb />
			to the learned Senior Counsel for the appellants, in cases of fraud,
			<lb />
			would start running from the date stipulated in Section 17 of the
			<lb />
			Limitation Act, 1963. Section 17 reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;17. Effect of fraud or mistake.-(1) Where, in the case of
			<lb />
			any suit or application for which a period of limitation is pre
			<lb />
			scribed by this Act,-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			the suit or application is based upon the fraud of
			<lb />
			the defendant or respondent or his agent; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) the knowledge of the right or title on which a suit or
			<lb />
			application is founded is concealed by the fraud of any
			<lb />
			such person as aforesaid;
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) the suit or application is for relief from the conse
			<lb />
			quences of a mistake; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d) where any document necessary to establish the right
			<lb />
			of the plaintiff or applicant has been fraudulently con
			<lb />
			cealed from him,
			<lb />
			the period of limitation shall not begin to run until plaintiff
			<lb />
			or applicant has discovered the fraud or the mistake or
			<lb />
			could, with reasonable diligence, have discovered it; or in the
			<lb />
			case of a concealed document, until the plaintiff or the appli
			<lb />
			cant first had the means of producing the concealed docu
			<lb />
			ment or compelling its production:
			<lb />
			Provided that nothing in this section shall enable any
			<lb />
			suit to be instituted or application to be made to recover or
			<lb />
			enforce any charge against, or set aside any transaction af
			<lb />
			fecting, any property which-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i) in the case of fraud, has been purchased for valuable
			<lb />
			consideration by a person who was not a party to the
			<lb />
			fraud and did not at the time of the purchase know, or
			<lb />
			have reason to believe, that any fraud had been com
			<lb />
			mitted, or
			<lb />
			(ii) in the case of mistake, has been purchased for valu
			<lb />
			able consideration subsequently to the transaction in
			<lb />
			which the mistake was made, by a person who did not
			<lb />
			know, or have reason to believe, that the mistake had
			<lb />
			been made, or
			<lb />
			(iii) in the case of a concealed document, has been pur
			<lb />
			chased for valuable consideration by a person who was
			<lb />
			not a party to the concealment and, did not at the time
			<lb />
			of purchase know, or have reason to believe, that the
			<lb />
			document had been concealed.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2)
			<lb />
			Where a judgmentdebtor has, by fraud or force, pre
			<lb />
			vented the execution of a decree or order within the period of
			<lb />
			limitation, the court may, on the application of the judg
			<lb />
			mentcreditor made after the expiry of the said period extend
			<lb />
			the period for execution of the decree or order: Provided that
			<lb />
			such application is made within one year from the date of
			<lb />
			the discovery of the fraud or the cessation of force, as the
			<lb />
			case may be.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			8.2
			<lb />
			The argument of Shri Mukul Rohatgi, learned Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel for the appellant is that even assuming that the so called
			<lb />
			fraud was incapable of being discovered with due diligence,
			<lb />
			limitation would start running at least from the date of actual
			<lb />
			discovery of the fraud. The date of actual discovery of fraud cannot
			<lb />
			be postponed beyond 11.08.2016, which was the date on which a
			<lb />
			charge sheet was filed in the criminal case, by the CBI before the
			<lb />
			Special Court. Therefore, it is the contention of the learned senior
			<lb />
			counsel for the appellants that the petition for winding up ought to
			<lb />
			have been filed at least on or before 10.08.2019. However, Antrix
			<lb />
			applied to the Government of India only on 14.01.2021 for the grant
			<lb />
			of authorisation. The authorisation was issued on 18.01.2021 and
			<lb />
			the petition for winding up was filed on 18.01.2021 (the same day).
			<lb />
			Therefore, placing heavy reliance upon the decision of the three
			<lb />
			member Bench of this Court in Jignesh Shah and Anr. vs. Union
			<lb />
			of India and Anr. 14 , it is contended on behalf of the appellant that
			<lb />
			the petition for winding up should have been thrown out on the
			<lb />
			ground of limitation, even if we take the date of filing of the charge
			<lb />
			sheet alone as the date of knowledge of the alleged fraud.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.3
			<lb />
			Before
			<lb />
			we
			<lb />
			consider
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			aforesaid
			<lb />
			contentions
			<lb />
			independently, it will be useful to take note of the manner in which
			<lb />
			the National Company Law Appellate Tribunal dealt with the
			<lb />
			question of limitation and decided the same against the appellants.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.4
			<lb />
			The Member (Technical) of NCLAT, in his separate but
			<lb />
			concurring opinion, dealt with the question of limitation, from
			<lb />
			paragraphs 2 to 13. In sum and substance, the Member (T) of
			<lb />
			NCLAT held (i) that the fraud alleged by Antrix was not a singular
			<lb />
			act which was transactionspecific; (ii) that the petition for winding
			<lb />
			up was based upon a series of acts of fraud, unearthed over a long
			<lb />
			period of time; (iii) that though the CBI filed a first chargesheet on
			<lb />
			11.08.2016, a supplementary chargesheet was filed on 8.01.2019;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iv) that a complaint was lodged under the Prevention of Money
			<lb />
			Laundering Act, 2002 alleging financial frauds, only on 24.12.2018;
			<lb />
			and (v) that in cases of this nature, the date of discovery of the first
			<lb />
			act of fraud among a series of acts of fraud, cannot be taken to be
			<lb />
			the date on which the right to apply accrued in terms of Article 137
			<lb />
			of the Schedule to the Limitation Act, 1963.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.5
			<lb />
			The above view taken by NCLAT is a plausible view and
			<lb />
			does not suffer from any perversity. The above view cannot be said
			<lb />
			to be completely contrary to law. However, we will independently
			<lb />
			deal with this issue, so that the myth of limitation is demystified.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8
		</p>
		<p>
			.
		</p>
		<p>
			6
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			The various provisions of the Companies Act, 2013,
			<lb />
			unfortunately came into force on various dates, in view of the
			<lb />
			leverage granted under Section 1(3) to the Central Government to
			<lb />
			appoint different dates for different provisions to come into force.
			<lb />
			Section 270 providing for the winding up by the Tribunal, Section
			<lb />
			271 prescribing the circumstances in which a company may be
			<lb />
			wound up by the Tribunal and Section 272 stipulating the
			<lb />
			requirements of a petition for winding up, as they were originally
			<lb />
			enacted in the Companies Act, 2013, never came into force, since no
			<lb />
			notification under Section 1(3) of the Act was issued in respect of
			<lb />
			these three provisions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.7
			<lb />
			However, the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code, 2016 (Act
			<lb />
			31 of 2016) received the assent of the President on 28.05.2016.
			<lb />
			Section 255 of this Code declared that the Companies Act, 2013
			<lb />
			shall stand amended in the manner specified in the 11 th Schedule to
			<lb />
			the Code. The existing provisions of Sections 270 to 272 of the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 2013 were replaced by the 11 th Schedule read with
			<lb />
			Section 255 of IBC. Section 255 of IBC came into force on
			<lb />
			15.11.2016 vide S.O 3453(E) dated 15.11.2016. Consequently the
			<lb />
			11 th Schedule containing amendments to the Companies Act, 2013
			<lb />
			also came into force on 15.11.2016. Sections 270, 271 and 272 as
			<lb />
			they stand today, resultantly came into force on 15.11.2016.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.8
			<lb />
			In contrast, the provisions of Sections 4 to 32 of IBC came
			<lb />
			into force on 1.12.2016 vide S.O 3594(E) dated 30.11.2016. The
			<lb />
			provisions relating to Corporate Insolvency Resolution Process are
			<lb />
			found in Sections 6 to 32 of IBC 2016. Sections 7, 9 and 10 of IBC
			<lb />
			2016 provide for the initiation of Corporate Insolvency Resolution
			<lb />
			Process, respectively by the financial creditor, the operational
			<lb />
			creditor and the corporate applicant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.9
			<lb />
			Section 434 of the Companies Act, 2013, as it was
			<lb />
			originally enacted, provided for transfer of certain proceedings
			<lb />
			pending before various forums on the date of coming into force of
			<lb />
			the Act. Clause (c) of Subsection (1) of Section 434 provided for the
			<lb />
			transfer of the winding up proceedings to the Tribunal, with a
			<lb />
			mandate to the Tribunal to proceed to deal with those proceedings
			<lb />
			from the stage before their transfer. IBC 2016, through the 11 th
			<lb />
			Schedule, substituted a new provision in Section 434. Though the
			<lb />
			newly incorporated Section 434 also provided under Clause (c) of
			<lb />
			Subsection (1) for the transfer of winding up proceedings from the
			<lb />
			High Court to the Tribunal, such transfer was made subject to
			<lb />
			certain restrictions. One of those restrictions was that only those
			<lb />
			proceedings relating to winding up which are at a stage as may be
			<lb />
			prescribed by the Central Government, which may be transferred to
			<lb />
			the Tribunal. This restriction is found in the first proviso to Section
			<lb />
			434(1).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.10
			<lb />
			Therefore, the Central Government issued a set of Rules
			<lb />
			known as the Companies (Transfer of Pending Proceedings) Rules,
			<lb />
			2016. These Rules (except Rule 4 which relates to voluntary winding
			<lb />
			up) came into force with effect from 15.12.2016. Rule 5 of these
			<lb />
			Rules prescribes the stage at which alone, a petition for winding up
			<lb />
			under Section 433(e) of the 1956 Act could be transferred to NCLT.
			<lb />
			Similarly Rule 6 prescribes the stage at which the petitions for
			<lb />
			winding up filed under Clauses (a) and (f) of Section 433 of the 1956
			<lb />
			Act could be transferred.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.11
			<lb />
			What is important to note from the above discussion is
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i)
			<lb />
			that while Sections 270 to 272 of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013 came into force on 15.11.2016, Sections 7, 9
			<lb />
			and 10 of IBC came into force on 1.12.2016 and the
			<lb />
			Rules relating to transfer proceedings came into
			<lb />
			force on 15.12.2016; and
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) what is provided for under the Companies (Transfer
			<lb />
			of Pending Proceedings) Rules, 2016 read with
			<lb />
			Section 434 of the Companies Act, 2013 and Section
			<lb />
			239 of the IBC 2016 is the transfer of only three
			<lb />
			categories of petitions for winding up, namely, those
			<lb />
			that fall under clauses (a), (e) and (f) of Section 433
			<lb />
			of the 1956 Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.12
			<lb />
			Keeping in mind the above statutory scheme, let us now
			<lb />
			see what happened in Jignesh Shah (supra), on which heavy
			<lb />
			reliance is placed. In Jignesh Shah, a suit for specific performance
			<lb />
			of an agreement with an alternative claim for damages, was filed by
			<lb />
			IL&amp;FS, on 19.06.2013, on the ground that the cause of action,
			<lb />
			namely, the refusal to honour the commitment under the agreement
			<lb />
			arose on 16.08.2012. After more than two years of the date of the
			<lb />
			institution of the suit and after more than three years of the date
			<lb />
			mentioned in the plaint as the date of arising of the cause of action,
			<lb />
			the plaintiff in the suit issued a statutory notice under Sections 433
			<lb />
			and 434 of the 1956 Act, on 3.11.2015. After receipt of the reply
			<lb />
			from the defendant, a petition for winding up was filed by the
			<lb />
			plaintiff in the suit, against the defendant, on 21.10.2016 before the
			<lb />
			Bombay High Court under Section 433(e) of the 1956 Act. This
			<lb />
			petition for winding up was transferred by the High Court of Bombay
			<lb />
			to the NCLT, by an order dated 1.02.2017, in terms of Section 434 of
			<lb />
			the Companies Act, 2013 read with Rule 5 of the Companies
			<lb />
			(Transfer of Pending proceedings) Rules, 2016. NCLT treated the
			<lb />
			petition for winding up as a petition for corporate insolvency
			<lb />
			resolution under Section 7 of IBC by a financial creditor and ordered
			<lb />
			the admission of the petition. The order of admission was
			<lb />
			unsuccessfully challenged before the NCLAT, whereafter, the matter
			<lb />
			landed up before this Court. The view taken by NCLAT was that
			<lb />
			since Section 7 of IBC 2016 came into force on 1.12.2016, the
			<lb />
			winding up petition was within the period of limitation. It was this
			<lb />
			view of NCLAT which was put to test before this Court in Jignesh
			<lb />
			Shah.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.13
			<lb />
			In essence, Jignesh Shah was one under Section 433(e)
			<lb />
			of the 1956 Act which related to inability of a company to pay its
			<lb />
			debts. Therefore, unless the debt was a legally recoverable debt, on
			<lb />
			the date on which a petition for winding up was filed, no petition for
			<lb />
			winding up was maintainable. If a suit for recovery of such a debt
			<lb />
			was already time barred, it is incongruous to say that a petition for
			<lb />
			winding up was maintainable in respect of such a debt. Therefore,
			<lb />
			the test applied in Jignesh Shah was not new but what was so
			<lb />
			obvious. In fact, on the date on which a petition for winding up was
			<lb />
			filed on the file of the Bombay High Court in Jignesh Shah, the civil
			<lb />
			suit for enforcement of the contract with an alternative claim for
			<lb />
			damages was pending. If the plaintiff had waited for a decree in the
			<lb />
			suit and thereafter moved a petition for winding up on the basis of
			<lb />
			the decree, Section 434(1)(b) of the Companies Act, 1956 would have
			<lb />
			come into play and the winding up petition could not have been held
			<lb />
			in Jignesh Shah to have been time barred. Since the plaintiff in the
			<lb />
			suit moved an application for winding up even during the pendency
			<lb />
			of the suit, limitation had to be naturally counted on the basis of the
			<lb />
			original cause of action mentioned in the civil suit, with reference to
			<lb />
			Section 434(1)(a).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.14
			<lb />
			As we have seen earlier, Section 434 of the 2013 Act read
			<lb />
			with the Companies (Transfer of Pending Proceedings) Rules, 2016
			<lb />
			apply only in respect of three types of proceedings for winding up,
			<lb />
			namely, (i) proceedings on the ground of inability to pay the debts,
			<lb />
			covered by Clause (e) of Section 433 of the 1956 Act; (ii) proceedings
			<lb />
			initiated by the company itself by a special resolution covered by
			<lb />
			Clause (a) of Section 433; and (iii) proceedings on just and equitable
			<lb />
			ground covered by clause (f) of Section 433.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.15
			<lb />
			As we have seen in Chapter 6 above, fraud was not
			<lb />
			included in Section 433 of the 1956 Act as one of the nine
			<lb />
			circumstances in which a company may be wound up. Under the
			<lb />
			1956 statutory regime, a petition for winding up, even if triggered on
			<lb />
			the basis of an investigation report under section 237(b) read with
			<lb />
			section 243 and Section 439(1)(f), was required to be only on just
			<lb />
			and equitable ground under Section 433(f). Therefore, on the date on
			<lb />
			which IBC came into force, if a petition for winding up was pending
			<lb />
			under section 433 (e) or (f), it was liable to be transferred to NCLT by
			<lb />
			virtue of Section 434 of the 2013 Act read with the Companies
			<lb />
			(Transfer of Pending Proceedings) Rules, 2016.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.16
			<lb />
			But under the Companies Act, 2013, three different types
			<lb />
			of fraud are included in Section 271(c), as the circumstances for
			<lb />
			winding up a company. Such a winding up is independent of just
			<lb />
			and equitable ground. Therefore, the parameters applicable to
			<lb />
			winding up on the ground of inability to pay debts or on just and
			<lb />
			equitable ground may not be applied blind fold to a case of fraud.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.17
			<lb />
			Antrix, which initiated the proceedings for winding up, is
			<lb />
			neither a financial creditor nor an operational creditor nor a
			<lb />
			corporate applicant. This is why Antrix have not and could not have
			<lb />
			gone for insolvency resolution process, under the IBC, but taken
			<lb />
			recourse to Section 271(c) of the Companies Act, 2013. Hence the
			<lb />
			ratio in Jignesh Shah, as applicable to debts, whose recovery in
			<lb />
			any case should not have been time barred on the date of initiation
			<lb />
			of the proceedings for winding up/insolvency resolution process,
			<lb />
			cannot have any application to the case on hand.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.18
			<lb />
			It is fundamental to the law of limitation that limitation
			<lb />
			extinguishes the remedy and not the right. If the remedy of filing a
			<lb />
			civil suit for the recovery of a debt stands extinguished by the Law of
			<lb />
			Limitation, the creditor cannot make use of Section 433(e) of the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 1956. This is the premise on which this Court
			<lb />
			decided Jignesh Shah.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.19
			<lb />
			After Jignesh Shah, this court was concerned with the
			<lb />
			application of sections 14 and 18 of the Limitation Act, 1963 in
			<lb />
			different cases. In Sesh Nath Singh v. Baidyabati Sheoraphuli
			<lb />
			Cooperative Bank Ltd 15 , this Court held that Sections 14 and 18
			<lb />
			will apply to cases filed under section 7 or 9 of IBC. Again in Laxmi
			<lb />
			Pat Surana vs Union Bank of India 16 , this Court held :&quot;Section 18
			<lb />
			of the Limitation Act would come into play every time when the
			<lb />
			principal borrower and/or the corporate guarantor (corporate debtor),
			<lb />
			as the case may be, acknowledge their liability to pay the debt. Such
			<lb />
			acknowledgement, however, must be before the expiration of the
			<lb />
			prescribed period of limitation including the fresh period of limitation
			<lb />
			due to acknowledgement of the debt, from time to time, for institution
			<lb />
			of the proceedings under Section 7 of the Code.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.20
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the question whether the entries made in the
			<lb />
			balance sheets of a corporate debtor would amount to
			<lb />
			acknowledgement of a liability under section 18 of the Limitation Act
			<lb />
			came up for consideration in Asset Reconstruction company vs
			<lb />
			Bishal Jaiswal 17 . After referring to the judgment of the Calcutta
			<lb />
			High Court in Bengal Silk Mills Co. v. Ismail Golam Hossain Ariff 18 ,
			<lb />
			this Court held in Bishal Jaiswal (i) that &quot;though the filing of a
			<lb />
			balance sheet is by compulsion of law, the acknowledgement
			<lb />
			of a debt is not necessarily so; and (ii) that the entries made in
			<lb />
			the balance sheets would amount to acknowledgement of
			<lb />
			liability depending upon whether such an entry qua any
			<lb />
			particular creditor is unequivocal or has been entered into
			<lb />
			with caveats in the form of notes that are annexed to or
			<lb />
			forming part of such financial statements&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.21
			<lb />
			The above decisions show that limitation is not always
			<lb />
			akin to a lighted matchstick to a train of gun powder. The date of
			<lb />
			commencement of the period need not necessarily be static. The
			<lb />
			date of commencement may keep changing depending upon the acts
			<lb />
			of omission and commission on the part of the party against whom
			<lb />
			the action is initiated. These acts of omission and commission
			<lb />
			constitute the bundle of facts, which determine the question
			<lb />
			whether an action is barred by limitation or not.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.22
			<lb />
			As we have pointed out elsewhere, the contours of fraud
			<lb />
			as delineated in Section 271(c) of the Companies Act, 2013 cover
			<lb />
			three aspects namely, (i) the affairs of the company being conducted
			<lb />
			in a fraudulent manner; (ii) the company was formed for fraudulent
			<lb />
			and unlawful purpose; and (iii) the persons concerned in the
			<lb />
			formation and management of its affairs have been guilty of fraud,
			<lb />
			misfeasance or misconduct in connection therewith. As rightly
			<lb />
			pointed out by the Tribunal, a singular act of omission or
			<lb />
			commission may constitute fraud and even a series of acts may
			<lb />
			constitute fraud. A fraudulent act may be different from the
			<lb />
			fraudulent manner in which an act is performed. The words &quot;the
			<lb />
			conduct of the affairs of a company in a fraudulent manner&quot; indicate
			<lb />
			that the process was a continuing one. If the conduct of the affairs of
			<lb />
			the company in a fraudulent manner is a continuing process, the
			<lb />
			right to apply becomes recurring.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.23
			<lb />
			We must keep in mind the fact that apart from the
			<lb />
			persons in charge of the management of the affairs of the company
			<lb />
			in liquidation, the officials of Antrix as well as the officials of the
			<lb />
			Department of Space are now facing prosecution not only for
			<lb />
			offences under Section 420 read with Section 120B of the Indian
			<lb />
			Penal Code, but also for offences under the Prevention of Corruption
			<lb />
			Act, 1988 and the Prevention of Money Laundering Act. The
			<lb />
			termination of the Contract on 25.02.2011, was not triggered by an
			<lb />
			allegation of fraud and corruption. Fraud and corruption were
			<lb />
			discovered only later and by the time the discovery was made, the
			<lb />
			attempts to reap the fruits of fraud had reached the pinnacle. These
			<lb />
			attempts continue even till date and this falls squarely within
			<lb />
			Section 271(c). Therefore, the contention that the petition was
			<lb />
			barred by limitation was rightly rejected by the Tribunal and we
			<lb />
			have no reason to take a different view.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			ESTOPPEL
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.1
			<lb />
			The next ground of attack to the impugned orders is that
			<lb />
			Antrix is estopped from pleading fraud and seeking winding up of
			<lb />
			Devas, in view of the fact, (i) that the letter of termination dated
			<lb />
			25.02.2011, of the Agreement dated 28.01.2005 was not on the
			<lb />
			ground of fraud but by invoking the force majeure clause; (ii) that in
			<lb />
			the proceedings before the arbitral Tribunals, no allegation of fraud
			<lb />
			was ever raised; and (iii) that the Auditor&apos;s reports of Antrix for all
			<lb />
			these years, contained a statement that no fraud was committed on
			<lb />
			Antrix.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.2
			<lb />
			The contention of the appellants is that under Section 19
			<lb />
			of the Indian Contract Act, 1872, an agreement vitiated by fraud is
			<lb />
			not void but only voidable at the option of the party who is a victim
			<lb />
			and that therefore the failure of Antrix, (i) to terminate the contract
			<lb />
			on the ground of fraud and/or (ii) to set up fraud as a defence to the
			<lb />
			arbitral proceedings operated as estoppel. In addition, the Auditor&apos;s
			<lb />
			statements in the Annual Reports, that no fraud was committed on
			<lb />
			Antrix, would give rise to a valid plea of estoppel.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.3
			<lb />
			Factually, the appellants are right in pointing out that the
			<lb />
			Agreement dated 28.01.2005 was terminated by a letter dated
			<lb />
			25.02.2011 only by invoking the force majeure clause and that fraud
			<lb />
			was not set up as a defence in the arbitral proceedings. The
			<lb />
			appellants are also factually correct in pointing out from the
			<lb />
			Auditor&apos;s reports of Antrix dated 15.09.2012, 19.07.2016,
			<lb />
			24.07.2017, 19.06.2020 etc., that there was a certification by the
			<lb />
			auditors to the effect that no fraud on or by the company has been
			<lb />
			noticed or reported during the course of the audit. In the Annexure
			<lb />
			to the Auditor&apos;s report dated 15.09.2012, the Auditors have stated:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;According to the information and explanations given to us
			<lb />
			in the course of our audit, we report that no fraud on or by
			<lb />
			the Company has been noticed or reported during the course
			<lb />
			of our audit.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			9.4
			<lb />
			Similarly, in the Annual Report dated 19.07.2016, for
			<lb />
			201516, it was reported by the Auditors as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;To the best of our knowledge and belief and according to the
			<lb />
			information and explanations given to us, we report that no
			<lb />
			case of fraud has been committed on or by the Company or
			<lb />
			by its officers or employees during the year.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			9.5
			<lb />
			A statement similar to the one extracted above, also finds
			<lb />
			a place in the Auditor&apos;s report dated 24.07.2017, forming part of the
			<lb />
			Annual Report 201617.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.6
			<lb />
			Even in AnnexureB Report dated 19.06.2020, the
			<lb />
			Auditors have given a statement as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Fraud by company or its officers and employees
			<lb />
			According to the information and explanation given to us,
			<lb />
			there are no frauds reported by the company or any fraud
			<lb />
			has been noticed or reported during the year. Accordingly,
			<lb />
			the provisions of clause 3(x) of the said order are not
			<lb />
			applicable.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			9.7
			<lb />
			Under Clause (xxi) of paragraph 4 of the Companies
			<lb />
			(Auditor&apos;s Report) Order, 2003, issued in exercise of the powers
			<lb />
			conferred by Section 227 (4A) of the Companies Act, 1956, there is a
			<lb />
			prescription that the Auditor&apos;s Report should contain a statement as
			<lb />
			to whether any fraud on or by the company has been noticed or
			<lb />
			reported during the year and if so, the nature and the amount
			<lb />
			involved.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.8
			<lb />
			But the question is as to whether all the above would lead
			<lb />
			to an inference of estoppel against Antrix. The fact that the
			<lb />
			Agreement dated 28.01.2005 was not terminated on the ground of
			<lb />
			fraud, through the letter dated 25.02.2011, cannot take the
			<lb />
			appellants anywhere. The earliest First Information Report for the
			<lb />
			offences under Section 420 read with Section 120B of the IPC was
			<lb />
			filed by the CBI only on 16.03.2015. The officers of Antrix as well as
			<lb />
			officials of the Government were also implicated in the FIR for
			<lb />
			offences under the Prevention of Corruption act, 1988. Therefore,
			<lb />
			the appellants cannot set up a plea of estoppel on the ground that
			<lb />
			the termination of the Agreement in the year 2011 was not on the
			<lb />
			ground of fraud, when the discovery of fraud itself was many years
			<lb />
			later.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.9
			<lb />
			For the very same reason, the failure of Antrix to plead
			<lb />
			fraud in the ICC arbitration proceedings, cannot also operate as
			<lb />
			estoppel. The arbitral proceedings commenced in the year 2013 and
			<lb />
			the award itself was passed on 14.09.2015. Antrix cannot be
			<lb />
			expected to plead fraud in the arbitral proceedings, even before the
			<lb />
			discovery of fraud.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.10
			<lb />
			The Chartered Accountants/Auditors are not experts
			<lb />
			either in Criminal Law or in the technology that formed the subject
			<lb />
			matter of the Agreement between Antrix and Devas. The statement
			<lb />
			of Chartered Accountants are always qualified with certain riders
			<lb />
			such as &quot;according to the information and explanations given to us in
			<lb />
			the course of our audit&quot; or &quot;to the best of our knowledge and belief
			<lb />
			and according to the information and explanations given to us&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.11
			<lb />
			In fact, the Companies (Auditor&apos;s Report) Order, 2015
			<lb />
			which was superseded by another order in 2016 was issued by the
			<lb />
			Central Government in exercise of the power conferred by Section
			<lb />
			143(11) of the Companies Act, 2013. Section 143(12) obliges the
			<lb />
			Auditor to report to the Central Government, if he has reason to
			<lb />
			believe that an offence of fraud of a particular dimension was being
			<lb />
			committed in the company by its officers or employees. Subsection
			<lb />
			(13) of Section 143 also provides immunity to the Auditors for
			<lb />
			furnishing a report to the Central Government, if it is done in good
			<lb />
			faith. Subsection (12) &amp; (13) of Section 143 read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;143.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<head>
			Powers and duties of auditors and auditing
			<lb />
			standards
		</head>
		<p>
			.
			<lb />
			xxxx
			<lb />
			xxxx
			<lb />
			xxxx
			<lb />
			(12) Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, if
			<lb />
			an auditor of a company in the course of the performance of
			<lb />
			his duties as auditor, has reason to believe that an offence of
			<lb />
			fraud involving such amount or amounts as may be
			<lb />
			prescribed, is being or has been committed in the company
			<lb />
			by its officers or employees, the auditor shall report the
			<lb />
			matter to the Central Government within such time and in
			<lb />
			such manner as may be prescribed:
			<lb />
			Provided that in case of a fraud involving lesser than
			<lb />
			the specified amount, the auditor shall report the matter to
			<lb />
			the audit committee constituted under section 177 or to
			<lb />
			the Board in other cases within such time and in such man
			<lb />
			ner as may be prescribed:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Provided further that the companies, whose auditors
			<lb />
			have reported frauds under this subsection to the audit
			<lb />
			committee or the Board but not reported to the Central Gov
			<lb />
			ernment, shall disclose the details about such frauds in the
			<lb />
			Board&apos;s report in such manner as may be prescribed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(13) No duty to which an auditor of a company may be
			<lb />
			subject to shall be regarded as having been contravened by
			<lb />
			reason of his reporting the matter referred to in subsection
			<lb />
			(12) if it is done in good faith.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			9.12
			<lb />
			If the auditors of a company fail to make a report in terms
			<lb />
			of Section 143(12), despite having knowledge about the fraud, they
			<lb />
			may become liable for penal consequences under Section 448 read
			<lb />
			with Section 447 of the Companies Act, 2013. But the failure of the
			<lb />
			auditors to make a report as required by Section 143(12) or as
			<lb />
			required by the order issued under Section 143(11), cannot operate
			<lb />
			as estoppel against the company. The auditor&apos;s report can neither be
			<lb />
			taken as gospel truth nor act as estoppel against the company. The
			<lb />
			statement in the auditor&apos;s report, is as per the information given to
			<lb />
			them or as per the information culled out to the best of their ability.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.13
			<lb />
			The reliance placed upon Section 19 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Contract Act, 1872 to raise the plea of estoppel may not wholly be
			<lb />
			correct. Section 19 of the Indian Contract Act, deals with only one
			<lb />
			type of fraud namely, a fraud perpetrated on a party to secure his
			<lb />
			consent to an agreement. Section 19 begins with the words &quot;when
			<lb />
			consent to an agreement is caused by coercion, fraud…..&quot;. Frauds
			<lb />
			other than those used to induce the consent of a party to an
			<lb />
			agreement, are not covered by Section 19. In fact, the definition of
			<lb />
			fraud under Section 17 is also confined only to certain acts
			<lb />
			committed by a party to a contract. There are cases where a party
			<lb />
			may perpetrate a fraud either upon noncontracting parties or upon
			<lb />
			the Government or even upon the courts. The principle that fraud
			<lb />
			vitiates all solemn acts, will itself be rendered nugatory, if the
			<lb />
			understanding of fraud is confined only to the realm of contract.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.14
			<lb />
			In the case on hand, the fraud alleged by Antrix is not
			<lb />
			solely on the ground that their consent to the Agreement dated
			<lb />
			28.01.2005 was vitiated by fraud. What is alleged in the petition for
			<lb />
			winding up are, (i) formation of the company for fraudulent or
			<lb />
			unlawful purpose; (ii) fraud in the conduct of the affairs of the
			<lb />
			company; and (iii) fraud on the part of the persons who were
			<lb />
			involved in the formation and/or in the management of affairs of the
			<lb />
			company. The fraud relatable to the agreement, is only one facet of
			<lb />
			the whole scheme of things. Therefore, we have to go beyond section
			<lb />
			19 of the Contract Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.15
			<lb />
			In fact, the Explanation (i) under Section 447 of the
			<lb />
			companies Act, 2013 also defines fraud, but for the purposes of
			<lb />
			Section 447. What is covered by Section 271(c) of the Companies
			<lb />
			Act, 2013 is a fraud that goes beyond what lies in the realm of
			<lb />
			contract or in the realm of the penal provisions of the Companies
			<lb />
			Act, 2013. Hence the contention that Antrix was estopped from
			<lb />
			pleading fraud, was rightly rejected by the Tribunal and we see no
			<lb />
			reason to taken a different view.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			Refusal to permit crossexamination
			<lb />
			10.1
			<lb />
			Another ground of attack by the appellants to the
			<lb />
			impugned orders is that the foundation for the allegation of fraud
			<lb />
			was the averment that Devas offered to provide goods and services
			<lb />
			which were nonexistent both on the date of execution of the
			<lb />
			agreement and on the date of its termination and that Devas was
			<lb />
			also incapable and did not have the necessary permission/approvals
			<lb />
			to provide such device/services. Contending that the question of
			<lb />
			existence/availability of the technology has become a contentious
			<lb />
			issue with both parties filing several affidavits, Devas filed an
			<lb />
			application before NCLT seeking permission to crossexamine the
			<lb />
			officials of Antrix. This application was taken up along with the main
			<lb />
			company petition. While ordering winding up, by a final Order dated
			<lb />
			25.05.2021, NCLT justified its action by holding that the case did
			<lb />
			not require any oral evidence. Therefore, in the memorandum of
			<lb />
			grounds of appeal before NCLAT, the appellants raised a specific
			<lb />
			ground that the omission on the part of the Tribunal to afford an
			<lb />
			opportunity of crossexamination, vitiated the final outcome. But
			<lb />
			NCLAT upheld the view taken by NCLT.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.2
			<lb />
			Therefore, it is contended on behalf of the appellants that
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i) allegations of fraud, as a rule, warrant a fullfledged trial and
			<lb />
			proof; (ii) that in the light of the specific bar of jurisdiction of Civil
			<lb />
			Courts under Section 430 of the Companies Act, 2013, NCLT was
			<lb />
			obliged to scan the allegations of fraud very carefully, by allowing
			<lb />
			parties to lead evidence and crossexamine the witnesses; (iii) that
			<lb />
			the Tribunal is conferred with the same powers as are vested in a
			<lb />
			Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, in respect of the
			<lb />
			summoning and enforcing of the attendance of any person and
			<lb />
			examining him on oath, under Section 424(2) of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013; (iv) that Rules 52 and 135 of the National Company Law
			<lb />
			Tribunal Rules, 2016 make it clear that the Tribunal has the power
			<lb />
			to summon the appearance of any witness, crossexamine him on
			<lb />
			oath and even issue commission for the examination of witnesses;
			<lb />
			and (v) that the Tribunals committed a gross error of law in
			<lb />
			recording findings on serious allegation of frauds, solely on the basis
			<lb />
			of affidavits and documents. Reliance is placed in this regard by the
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel for the appellants, on the decisions of this
			<lb />
			Court in Standard Chartered Bank vs. Andhra Bank Financial
			<lb />
			Services Ltd. and Ors. 19 ; Svenska Handelsbanken vs. Indian
			<lb />
			Charge Chrome and Ors. 20 and V. Ravi Kumar vs. State, Rep. by
			<lb />
			Inspector of Police, District Crime Branch, Salem &amp; Ors. 21
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.3
			<lb />
			At the outset we should point out that the decision in
			<lb />
			Svenska Handelsbanken (supra) arose out of an interim order of
			<lb />
			injunction granted in a civil suit. The principle of law laid down in
			<lb />
			the said decision that mere pleadings cannot make out a case of
			<lb />
			fraud, is an offshoot of the time tested principle that pleadings
			<lb />
			cannot take the place of proof. Insofar as the decision in Standard
			<lb />
			Chartered Bank (supra) is concerned, the same arose out of
			<lb />
			proceedings before the special Court. One of those proceedings was
			<lb />
			under Section 111 of the Companies Act, 1956 which was
			<lb />
			&quot;somewhat summary in nature&quot;. Therefore it was in that context that
			<lb />
			this Court held that when a seriously disputed question of title
			<lb />
			arises, the Company Court should relegate the parties to a civil suit.
			<lb />
			But having admitted that under Section 430 of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			the jurisdiction of the Civil Court is barred, it is not open to the
			<lb />
			appellants to rely upon this decision to say that the parties could be
			<lb />
			relegated to a civil court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.4
			<lb />
			Similarly the decision in V. Ravi Kumar (supra), arose
			<lb />
			out of criminal proceedings under Section 482 Cr.P.C for quashing
			<lb />
			the second complaint, after the withdrawal of the first complaint.
			<lb />
			The High Court quashed the criminal complaint and while setting
			<lb />
			aside the order of the High Court, this Court held that the
			<lb />
			allegations of fraud and cheating, which prima facie constitute
			<lb />
			offences under Section 420 IPC, have to be established through
			<lb />
			evidence at the time of trial.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.5
			<lb />
			Thus the decisions relied upon by the appellants to drive
			<lb />
			home the point that the Tribunal must have permitted cross
			<lb />
			examination, have no relevance to the case on hand. However,
			<lb />
			dehors those decisions relied upon by the appellants, let us see
			<lb />
			whether the omission of NCLT to permit crossexamination was
			<lb />
			fatal.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.6
			<lb />
			The Tribunal classified the allegations made by Antrix into
			<lb />
			eight categories. In sum and substance, they revolve around, (i) the
			<lb />
			offer of a nonexistent technology; (ii) misrepresentation about the
			<lb />
			possession of intellectual property rights over a device; (iii) violation
			<lb />
			of SATCOM policy; (iv) securing of an experimental licence
			<lb />
			fraudulently; (v) manipulation of the minutes; and (vi) the trail of
			<lb />
			money brought in through FIPB approvals.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.7
			<lb />
			All the averments forming the foundation of the
			<lb />
			allegations of fraud, from the point of view of the Indian Evidence
			<lb />
			Act, would fall under only two categories, namely, (i) positive
			<lb />
			assertions requiring persons making those assertions to prove them;
			<lb />
			and (ii) negative assertions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.8
			<lb />
			A party alleging the nonexistence of something, cannot be
			<lb />
			called upon to prove the nonexistence. It is the party who asserts
			<lb />
			the existence or who challenges the assertion of non existence, who
			<lb />
			is liable to prove the existence of the same.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.9
			<lb />
			In the case on hand, Antrix asserted that Devas offered
			<lb />
			services which were nonexistent, through a device which was not
			<lb />
			available and that even the socalled intellectual property rights over
			<lb />
			the device were not available. Therefore, obviously Antrix cannot
			<lb />
			lead evidence to show the nonexistence or nonavailability of those
			<lb />
			things, either by oral evidence or by subjecting their officials to
			<lb />
			crossexamination by Devas. Devas never produced before the
			<lb />
			Tribunals any device nor did they demonstrate the availability to
			<lb />
			Devas services. All that Devas wanted was, the crossexamination of
			<lb />
			the officials of Antrix. Any amount of crossexamination of the
			<lb />
			officials of Antrix could not have established the existence of
			<lb />
			something that was disputed by Antrix.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.10
			<lb />
			It is also interesting to note that the application for cross
			<lb />
			examination was moved by Devas on 5.5.2021, after arguments in
			<lb />
			the main petition itself had commenced on 30.04.2021 and
			<lb />
			concluded on 3.05.2021 on the side of Antrix. The list of dates filed
			<lb />
			by Shri N. Venkataraman, Additional Solicitor General shows that
			<lb />
			on 19.01.2021, NCLT ordered the admission of the company petition
			<lb />
			and appointed a provisional liquidator. In fact this order was passed
			<lb />
			after hearing objections of the company. As against the order of
			<lb />
			admission, DEMPL filed an appeal before NCLAT. But the same was
			<lb />
			dismissed by NCLAT on 11.02.2021, with liberty to the DEMPL to
			<lb />
			file an application for impleadment. DEMPL filed an application for
			<lb />
			impleadment on 2.03.3021. They also filed a writ petition before the
			<lb />
			High Court of Karnataka challenging the authorisation given by
			<lb />
			Central Government to Antrix, as well as the constitutional validity
			<lb />
			of Section 272(1)(e) read with Section 272(3) of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013. After hearing extensive arguments over several dates, the High
			<lb />
			Court of Karnataka dismissed the writ petition by an Order dated
			<lb />
			28.04.2021 with costs of Rs.5,00,000/ for abuse of process of law.
			<lb />
			It was only thereafter that the company petition was taken up by
			<lb />
			NCLT and arguments on behalf of Antrix was heard and concluded
			<lb />
			on 30.04.2021 and 3.05.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.11
			<lb />
			When the company petition was adjourned to 5.05.2021
			<lb />
			for arguments on behalf of Devas, a twopronged strategy was
			<lb />
			adopted by Devas. The first was to make DEMPL file a writ appeal
			<lb />
			before the Division Bench of the High Court of Karnataka against
			<lb />
			the order of the learned Single Judge upholding the constitutional
			<lb />
			validity of the aforesaid provisions. Simultaneously, Devas filed an
			<lb />
			application on 5.05.2021 to crossexamine the Managing Director
			<lb />
			and Finance Director of Antrix. However, Devas also continued their
			<lb />
			arguments in the main company petition and concluded the same
			<lb />
			on 10.05.2021. On 10.05.2021, NCLT reserved the judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.12
			<lb />
			Incidentally, it must be pointed out that the writ appeal
			<lb />
			filed by the DEMPL came up for hearing before the Division Bench of
			<lb />
			the High Court of Karnataka on 12.05.2021. The Division Bench
			<lb />
			directed the matter to be listed on 19.05.2021 with a condition that
			<lb />
			the costs as awarded by the learned Single Judge should be paid on
			<lb />
			or before the said date.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.13
			<lb />
			On 25.05.2021, the NCLT passed final orders, after which
			<lb />
			DEMPL withdrew the writ appeal on 27.05.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.14
			<lb />
			It is clear from the above timeline of events that the
			<lb />
			application for crossexamination was moved by Devas after
			<lb />
			conclusion of the arguments on the side of Antrix in the main
			<lb />
			petition itself, and that too after the unsuccessful attempt made by
			<lb />
			one of its shareholders to assail the constitutional validity of the
			<lb />
			statutory provisions. Therefore, the Tribunal was right in rejecting
			<lb />
			the request for crossexamination.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			LOCUS STANDI OF THE SHAREHOLDERS
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.1
			<lb />
			The next ground of attack to the impugned orders is that
			<lb />
			despite the petition for winding up containing specific allegations of
			<lb />
			fraud as against the shareholders of Devas, NCLT did not give any
			<lb />
			opportunity to the shareholders. Even the application for
			<lb />
			impleadment filed by DEMPL which is one of the shareholders,
			<lb />
			pursuant to the leave granted by NCLAT, was taken up along with
			<lb />
			the main company petition and eventually rejected along with the
			<lb />
			main company petition. Therefore, DEMPL filed an independent
			<lb />
			appeal before NCLAT. Unfortunately, the Member (Judicial) of
			<lb />
			NCLAT dismissed the appeal, as not maintainable, on the ground
			<lb />
			(i) that the rights of the shareholders are confined to the election of
			<lb />
			Directors, voting in the meetings of the company, distribution of
			<lb />
			dividends and the distribution of surplus upon liquidation; and
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) that the company in liquidation itself, through its exDirector,
			<lb />
			has independently filed an appeal as an aggrieved person.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.2
			<lb />
			Therefore, relying upon the decision of this Court in
			<lb />
			National Textile Workers&apos; Union vs. P.R. Ramakrishnan &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors. 22 , it is contended that it would be contrary to every recognised
			<lb />
			principle of fair judicial procedure and violative of the rule of audi
			<lb />
			alteram partem which constitutes one of the basic principles of
			<lb />
			natural justice, to deny to the shareholders, the right to be heard
			<lb />
			before an order prejudicially affecting their interest was passed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.3
			<lb />
			It is true that the petition for winding up was filed under
			<lb />
			Section 271(c) alleging (i) that the affairs of the company have been
			<lb />
			conducted in a fraudulent manner; (ii) that the company was formed
			<lb />
			for fraudulent and unlawful purpose; and (iii) that the persons
			<lb />
			concerned in the formation or management of its affairs have been
			<lb />
			guilty of fraud. But there is no scope either in the Act or in the Rules
			<lb />
			for the impleadment of any shareholder as a respondent to the
			<lb />
			petition for winding up. Rule 3(1) of Companies (Winding Up) Rules
			<lb />
			2020 requires a petition for winding up to be in Form WIN 1 or Form
			<lb />
			WIN 2. A look at these forms would indicate that there is no
			<lb />
			provision for making any one, as the respondent in the petition.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the question of impleading any shareholder at the time
			<lb />
			when the petition for winding up was filed, did not arise.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.4
			<lb />
			Interestingly, Antrix sought the authorisation under
			<lb />
			Section 272(1)(e) on 14.01.2021 and the Central Government
			<lb />
			granted authorisation on 18.01.2021. On the very same day, the
			<lb />
			petition for winding up was filed. When the petition was taken up by
			<lb />
			NCLT on 19.01.2021 for the first time, Devas Multimedia Private
			<lb />
			Limited, which is the company in liquidation appeared through
			<lb />
			counsel and opposed the petition and also sought sufficient time to
			<lb />
			file reply. Therefore, NCLT did not have to go through the formality
			<lb />
			of ordering notice before admission, as a battery of counsel appeared
			<lb />
			for Devas, raised preliminary objections and also sought time to file
			<lb />
			response. The Tribunal passed a detailed order dated 19.01.2021
			<lb />
			admitting the company petition and appointing a provisional
			<lb />
			liquidator even while granting time to the company to file its reply.
			<lb />
			In paragraph 5 of the detailed order dated 19.01.2021, the
			<lb />
			preliminary submissions made by the company in liquidation
			<lb />
			against the admission of the company petition, are recorded.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.5
			<lb />
			The order dated 19.01.2021 admitting the company
			<lb />
			petition became the subject matter of an appeal before NCLAT at the
			<lb />
			instance of the company in liquidation. Therefore, on 8.02.2021
			<lb />
			when the company petition came up for hearing, it was adjourned to
			<lb />
			16.02.2021 and, thereafter, to 2.03.2021. On 2.03.2021, DEMPL
			<lb />
			which is a shareholder filed a petition for impleadment. It is true
			<lb />
			that this application was not independently dealt with and disposed
			<lb />
			of at that stage. However, the objections of DEMPL to the main
			<lb />
			company petition were just the same as the objections of the
			<lb />
			company in liquidation. Despite the fact that a provisional liquidator
			<lb />
			has been appointed on 19.02.2021 itself, the exDirector of the
			<lb />
			company in liquidation was permitted to file objections to the main
			<lb />
			company petition and also argue the same fully.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.6
			<lb />
			After the conclusion of the arguments on the part of
			<lb />
			Antrix to the main company petition, DEMPL even moved a writ
			<lb />
			petition challenging the constitutional validity of Section 272(1)(e)
			<lb />
			and the authorisation issued to Antrix. The writ petition was
			<lb />
			dismissed with costs and the writ appeal was withdrawn.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.7
			<lb />
			It will be clear from the above sequence of events that (i)
			<lb />
			despite NCLT not disposing of the impleadment petition before
			<lb />
			passing final orders; and (ii) despite NCLT dismissing the
			<lb />
			impleadment petition along with the main company petition, their
			<lb />
			objections to the main company petition have been dealt, along with
			<lb />
			the objections of the exDirector of the company in liquidation. In
			<lb />
			other words, the objecting shareholder had an effective hearing
			<lb />
			before NCLT. Though their appeal was rejected by NCLAT on the
			<lb />
			ground of maintainability, their arguments for opposing the winding
			<lb />
			up, which were just the same as that of the company, have been
			<lb />
			considered. Therefore, the objection that an opportunity was not
			<lb />
			given to the shareholders, is just theoretical, when in fact they were
			<lb />
			heard.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.8
			<lb />
			It is true that in National Textile Workers&apos; Union
			<lb />
			(supra), this Court took the law relating to locus standi by a leap
			<lb />
			forward. But as seen from the facts of the said case, the petition for
			<lb />
			winding up was triggered by one group of shareholders, both on the
			<lb />
			ground that company was unable to pay its debts and on the ground
			<lb />
			that it is just and equitable to wind up the company. The company
			<lb />
			Judge before whom the winding up petition came up, granted an ex
			<lb />
			parte injunction restraining company from borrowing any moneys
			<lb />
			and from alienating and/or creating any charge or encumbrance
			<lb />
			over any of the assets of the company. As a consequence, the
			<lb />
			Employees&apos; Cooperative Stores, stopped issuing any provisions or
			<lb />
			supplies to the workmen. The workmen were also prevented from
			<lb />
			enjoying the benefits under the ESI scheme. The wages payable for
			<lb />
			the following month itself became doubtful. Faced with the sudden
			<lb />
			threat to their livelihood, the workers&apos; Unions sought to implead
			<lb />
			themselves as party to the winding up proceeding. Therefore, the
			<lb />
			decision rendered in National Textile Workers&apos; Union&apos;s case has
			<lb />
			to be understood in the context in which it was rendered.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.9
			<lb />
			It is true that the dismissal of the appeal filed by DEMPL,
			<lb />
			by NCLAT on the ground of maintainability may not be correct.
			<lb />
			Section 421(1) of the Companies Act, 2013 enables &quot;any person
			<lb />
			aggrieved by an order of the Tribunal&quot;, to file an appeal. To say that
			<lb />
			DEMPL cannot be taken to be a person aggrieved, may be far
			<lb />
			fetched. But on that sole ground, the impugned order cannot be set
			<lb />
			aside.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.10
			<lb />
			We have seen from the memorandum of grounds of appeal
			<lb />
			filed by DEMPL before NCLAT and the memorandum of grounds of
			<lb />
			appeal filed by DEMPL before this Court that their objections to the
			<lb />
			petition for winding up are just the same as those of the exDirector
			<lb />
			of the company in liquidation. In fact, before us, the exDirector of
			<lb />
			the company in liquidation was represented by Shri Mukul Rohtagi,
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel and DEMPL was represented by Shri Arvind
			<lb />
			P. Datar, learned senior counsel. While the learned senior counsel
			<lb />
			for the company in liquidation occupied the crease only for limited
			<lb />
			number of overs, the learned senior counsel appearing for DEMPL
			<lb />
			took the entire responsibility on his shoulders and played a very
			<lb />
			long innings. Therefore, it is not possible for us to set aside the order
			<lb />
			of winding up, on the sole ground that the shareholders application
			<lb />
			for impleadment as well as the appeal were rejected wrongly.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.11
			<lb />
			Before leaving the discussion on this ground of attack, we
			<lb />
			must also take note of one submission made by Shri N.
			<lb />
			Venkataraman, learned Additional Solicitor General. According to
			<lb />
			him, all the shareholders of Devas are arrayed as accused by the
			<lb />
			CBI in the criminal cases. But the CBI has not even been able to
			<lb />
			serve summons on them. Therefore, persons who are ducking/
			<lb />
			avoiding summons in the criminal prosecution, cannot be heard to
			<lb />
			contend that they must have been heard in the petition for winding
			<lb />
			up. Taking advantage of their citizenship/residence abroad, these
			<lb />
			shareholders are prosecuting proceedings for the enforcement of (i)
			<lb />
			ICC Arbitral Tribunal Award in India; and (ii) BIT Awards overseas,
			<lb />
			even while making it impossible for CBI to serve summons on them
			<lb />
			for the past five years. It is not open to such persons to raise the
			<lb />
			bogey of failure to afford an opportunity.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			FINDINGS
			<lb />
			ERRONEOUS
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			PERVERSE
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			THE STANDARD OF PROOF APPLIED INCORRECT
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.1
			<lb />
			The next ground of attack to the impugned orders is that
			<lb />
			the findings recorded by the NCLT which were approved by NCLAT
			<lb />
			were completely perverse and erroneous and that the Tribunals
			<lb />
			applied a completely incorrect standard of proof. In any case, the
			<lb />
			findings were recorded to be only prima facie, which is not sufficient
			<lb />
			to order the winding up of the company.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.2
			<lb />
			In order to test the correctness of the above contention, it
			<lb />
			is necessary to take note of the averments on which Antrix built
			<lb />
			their case for winding up, the response of Devas to the averments,
			<lb />
			the findings recorded by NCLT and the findings recorded by NCLAT.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.3
			<lb />
			Briefly stated, the averments made by Antrix in their
			<lb />
			petition for winding up were, (i) that Devas was incorporated as a
			<lb />
			private limited company, on 17.12.2004, with an authorised share
			<lb />
			capital of Rs.1,00,000/ divided into 10,000 equity shares of Rs.10/
			<lb />
			each; (ii) that within a few weeks of incorporation, an Agreement
			<lb />
			dated 28.01.2005 was entered into between the company and
			<lb />
			Antrix, as a result of a fraudulent and criminal conspiracy between
			<lb />
			the persons in management of the affairs of the company and the
			<lb />
			officials of Antrix/Government of India, to award a lease of scarce
			<lb />
			and valuable Sband spectrum, without obtaining necessary
			<lb />
			approvals and without following applicable norms and procedures;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii) that the persons incharge of the formation as well as the
			<lb />
			management of the affairs of Devas did not possess the necessary
			<lb />
			technical knowhow or the intellectual property rights for the
			<lb />
			provision of what was claimed as &quot;Devas Services&quot;, either at the time
			<lb />
			of signing of the agreement or even till date; (iv) that despite not
			<lb />
			being in possession of either the technology or the device, the
			<lb />
			company was pushing Antrix and the Government of India to launch
			<lb />
			the satellite; (v) that as part of the conspiracy, the Agreement dated
			<lb />
			28.01.2005 was terminated by Antrix by a letter dated 25.02.2011
			<lb />
			by invoking the force majeure clause; (vi) that it made things easy for
			<lb />
			Devas to initiate an arbitration before the ICC Arbitral Tribunal,
			<lb />
			apart from the initiation of the two BIT Arbitrations by the
			<lb />
			shareholders of Devas, (vii) that when the criminal conspiracy, fraud
			<lb />
			and corrupt practices came to light, an FIR was lodged by the CBI
			<lb />
			on 16.03.2015; (viii) that a chargesheet was filed by CBI on
			<lb />
			11.08.2016, both against the persons responsible for the formation
			<lb />
			and management of the affairs of the company in liquidation, as well
			<lb />
			as the officials of Antrix and Government of India; (ix) that a
			<lb />
			supplementary chargesheet was filed on 08.01.2019; (x) that a
			<lb />
			complaint was also registered under the Prevention of Money
			<lb />
			Laundering Act, 2002 on 24.12.2018; (xi) that the company which
			<lb />
			was formed with an authorized share capital Rs. 1,00,000/ in
			<lb />
			December, 2004, managed to secure a contract for a stated
			<lb />
			consideration of an &quot;upfront capacity reservation fee&quot; in the region
			<lb />
			of US, $ 20 million per satellite, apart from annual license fee of
			<lb />
			around US $ 9 million per satellite; (xii) that the execution of such a
			<lb />
			contract and the award of a public largesse of such a huge
			<lb />
			magnitude was not through any public auction but by private
			<lb />
			negotiations held by the officials of Antrix with Forge Advisors of
			<lb />
			USA, (xiii) that after securing the contract, the company was able to
			<lb />
			sell its equity shares as well as OCP shares at a huge premium to
			<lb />
			foreign investors; (xiv) that equity shares of a face value of Rs. 10/
			<lb />
			were sold at the rate of Rs. 1.26 lakhs per share; (xv) that
			<lb />
			interestingly, DT Germany which invested Rs. 430 crores through
			<lb />
			DT Asia obtained only 19% share holding, while four Mauritius
			<lb />
			investors obtained 37% share holding by investing Rs. 150 crores;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xvi) that experimental licences were obtained by Devas by
			<lb />
			manipulating the minutes of the meetings; (xvii) that FIPB approvals
			<lb />
			were secured for the stated purpose of providing Internet services,
			<lb />
			though the agreement was for rendering a hybrid service known as
			<lb />
			Satellite based Digital Multimedia Broadcasting Services (SDMB
			<lb />
			Services, for short); (xviii) that the fact that such a hybrid
			<lb />
			technology was not in existence at that time was suppressed from
			<lb />
			FIPB as well as other authorities; (xix) that after showcasing the
			<lb />
			inflow into India, of investment to the tune of Rs. 579 crores, the
			<lb />
			company siphoned out of India, a sum of Rs. 75 crores for creating a
			<lb />
			wholly owned subsidiary in USA, a sum of Rs. 180 crores towards
			<lb />
			payment for business support services and sum of Rs. 233 crores
			<lb />
			toward litigation services; (xx) that a sum of Rs. 92 crores alone was
			<lb />
			kept in India out of which Rs. 21 crores was by way of Fixed
			<lb />
			Deposits and a sum of Rs. 59 crores was paid to Antrix towards up
			<lb />
			front capacity fee; (xxi) that some of the then officials of Antrix and
			<lb />
			the Government of India were parties to the fraudulent and unlawful
			<lb />
			purpose for which Devas was created and the fraudulent manner in
			<lb />
			which the affairs of the company had been conducted; (xxii) that the
			<lb />
			persons including investors and the shareholders concerned in the
			<lb />
			formation and the management of its affairs have been guilty of
			<lb />
			fraud, corrupt practices and money laundering and that therefore
			<lb />
			the company was liable to be wound up.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.4
			<lb />
			On the basis of the pleadings, the documents produced
			<lb />
			and the submissions made, NCLT recorded the following findings
			<lb />
			namely, (i) that the incorporation of Devas was with fraudulent
			<lb />
			intention to grab the prestigious contract in question, in connivance
			<lb />
			and collusion with the then officials of Antrix; (ii) that it is not in
			<lb />
			dispute that at the time of entering into the contract, Devas did not
			<lb />
			have the technology, infrastructure or experience to perform their
			<lb />
			obligations under the Agreement; (iii) that one of the subscribers to
			<lb />
			the Memorandum of Association of the company in liquidation was
			<lb />
			an Auditor by name Shri M. Umesh, whose Article Clerk by name
			<lb />
			Gururaj was the one signed the Agreement; (iv) that the Executive
			<lb />
			Director of Antrix who signed the Agreement of behalf of Antrix is
			<lb />
			one of accused in the criminal cases; (v) that the incorporation of
			<lb />
			Devas was with fraudulent motive and unlawful object, to bring
			<lb />
			money into India and divert it by dubious methods; (vi) that even
			<lb />
			after the termination of the Agreement, Devas was not carrying on
			<lb />
			any business operations; (vii) that the objective of Devas was hardly
			<lb />
			to do any business except grabbing Primary SatelliteI (PSI) and
			<lb />
			Primary SatelliteII (PSII), and that therefore the requirements of
			<lb />
			Section 271(c) stand satisfied.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.5
			<lb />
			The order of the Appellate Tribunal is in two parts; the first
			<lb />
			authored by Member (Judicial), and the second authored by Member
			<lb />
			(Technical). The Member (Judicial) noted, (i) that the company in
			<lb />
			liquidation failed to establish either the existence of technology or
			<lb />
			the ownership of intellectual property rights over the stated
			<lb />
			technology; (ii) that even according to the affidavit of Shri M. G.
			<lb />
			Chandrashekar, Devas had ample time to develop Devas Technology,
			<lb />
			meaning thereby that its nonexistence at that time was admitted;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii) that the company did not have a single approval, permission or
			<lb />
			licence to render Devas services utilising Devas technology; (iv) that
			<lb />
			the approval of the Space Commission for building a satellite for
			<lb />
			Devas, was secured only after finalisation of commercial terms but
			<lb />
			without apprising the Space Commission of the same; (v) that even
			<lb />
			in the cabinet note, prepared by the Department of Space on
			<lb />
			17.11.2005 a full picture was not recorded; (vi) that there was a
			<lb />
			contravention of the SATCOM Policy; (vii) that though the original
			<lb />
			minutes of the meeting required Devas to secure a spectrum licence
			<lb />
			from Wireless Planning Committee (WPC), after appearing before the
			<lb />
			apex committee with requisite technical details, the minutes of the
			<lb />
			meetings were manipulated later as though the company was
			<lb />
			exempted from the requirement; (viii) that after objections about the
			<lb />
			manipulations, the original minutes of the meeting came to be
			<lb />
			restored, on 20.11.2009, but this happened only after the grant of
			<lb />
			experimental licence on 07.05.2009; (ix) that in any case the
			<lb />
			experimental licence was to establish Wireless Telegraph Station in
			<lb />
			India under the India Telegraph Act, 1885, without which
			<lb />
			experimental trials could not have been conducted; (x) that Devas
			<lb />
			obtained IPTV licence as part of ISP licence, which has nothing to do
			<lb />
			with what was offered as DEVAS services; (xi) that the agreement
			<lb />
			dated 28.01.2005 made no reference of IPTV; (xii) that undeniably,
			<lb />
			Devas services cannot be provided with ISP licences; (xiii) that after
			<lb />
			bringing an amount of Rs 579 crores into India, a major portion was
			<lb />
			taken out of India; (xiv) that the only business activity carried on by
			<lb />
			Devas was to provide ISP services in a particular locality in
			<lb />
			Bangalore for a few residents and that too for a short duration,
			<lb />
			which made Devas earn a revenue of Rs. 80,000/; (xv) that the
			<lb />
			diversion of Rs. 489 crores and Rs. 58 crores for non ISP purposes is
			<lb />
			violative of ISP licence, which comes squarely within the ambit of
			<lb />
			Section 271(c); (xvi) that Devas fraudulently approached FIPB
			<lb />
			through the ISP route to avoid scrutiny by Department of Space;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xvii) that the investors of Devas actually became shareholders and
			<lb />
			they also had their nominees on the Board of Devas; (xviii) that
			<lb />
			therefore these persons were also guilty of the conduct of the affairs
			<lb />
			of Devas in the manner stated; (xix) that the Share Subscription
			<lb />
			Agreement dated 06.03.2006 entered into with the investors
			<lb />
			contains a recital as though appropriate licences have been validly
			<lb />
			issued or assigned to the company, though in fact the only licence
			<lb />
			namely ISP licence was obtained much later on 02.05.2008 and (xx)
			<lb />
			that therefore the formation of the company and the conduct of the
			<lb />
			affairs of the company were fraudulent and the persons concerned
			<lb />
			therewith were also guilty of fraud.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.6
			<lb />
			In his independent but concurrent opinion the Member
			<lb />
			(Technical) of NCLAT classified the items of fraud into eight
			<lb />
			categories. He first found that the company was formed and the
			<lb />
			Agreement was entered into with the stated object of providing a
			<lb />
			bouquet of services, which were nonexistent. The second category of
			<lb />
			fraud dealt with by the Member (Technical) related to the
			<lb />
			misrepresentation in the Agreement. The third category of fraud
			<lb />
			concerned the violation of SATCOM Policy. The fourth category was
			<lb />
			actually an extension of the third category which related to SATCOM
			<lb />
			Policy. The fifth category was about suppression and
			<lb />
			misrepresentation in obtaining the approval of the cabinet. The sixth
			<lb />
			category of fraud revolved around the ISP licence dated 02.05.2008,
			<lb />
			of which IPTV licence was a part, but which had nothing to do with
			<lb />
			Devas Services. The seventh category related to the fraudulent
			<lb />
			manner in which experimental licence was obtained and the eighth
			<lb />
			category related to FIPB approvals and money trail. The Member
			<lb />
			(Technical) found the formation of company, the conduct of the
			<lb />
			affairs of the company and those persons concerned in the formation
			<lb />
			and conduct of management of its affairs to be guilty of fraud.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.7
			<lb />
			Technically speaking, the appeal before us which is
			<lb />
			under Section 423 of the Companies Act, 2013, is only on a question
			<lb />
			of law. When two forums namely NCLT and NCLAT have recorded
			<lb />
			concurrent findings on facts, it is not open to this Court to re
			<lb />
			appreciate evidence. Realising this constraint, the learned Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel for the Appellant sought to project the case as one of
			<lb />
			perversity of findings. But we do not find any perversity in the
			<lb />
			findings recorded by both the Tribunals. These findings are actually
			<lb />
			borne out by documents, none of which is challenged as fabricated
			<lb />
			or inadmissible. Though it is sufficient for us to stop at this, let us
			<lb />
			go a little deeper to find out whether there was any perversity in the
			<lb />
			findings recorded by the Tribunals and whether such findings could
			<lb />
			not have been reached by any reasonable standards.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.8
			<lb />
			The following undisputed facts emerge from the
			<lb />
			documents placed before the Tribunal. The authenticity of these
			<lb />
			documents were never in question or denied:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(i)
			<lb />
			An agreement of a huge magnitude, for leasing out five
			<lb />
			numbers of C X S transponders each of 8.1 MHz capacity
			<lb />
			and five numbers of S X C transponders each of 2.7 MHz
			<lb />
			capacity on the Primary SatelliteI (PSI), was surprisingly
			<lb />
			and shockingly entered into by Antrix with Devas, without
			<lb />
			same being preceded by any auction/tender process. It
			<lb />
			appears from the letter dated 27.09.2004 sent by DEVAS
			<lb />
			LLC, USA to Shri K.R. Sridhara Murty, Executive Director
			<lb />
			of Antrix with copies to Dr. G. Madhavan Nair, Chairman,
			<lb />
			ISRO and others that Shri Ramachandran Viswanathan,
			<lb />
			met the then Chairman of ISRO and other officials in
			<lb />
			Bangalore in April2003 and they met once again in
			<lb />
			Washington D.C. during the visit of the then Chairman of
			<lb />
			ISRO. These meetings, which were not preceded by any
			<lb />
			invitation to the public for any Expression of Interest,
			<lb />
			culminated in a Memorandum of Understanding dated
			<lb />
			28.07.2003. Though it is not clear where the MoU was
			<lb />
			signed, there are indications that it was signed overseas;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii) It must be noted here that a one man Committee
			<lb />
			comprising of Dr. B.N. Suresh, former Member of the
			<lb />
			Space Commission and Director of Indian Institute of
			<lb />
			Space Science and Technology, was constituted on
			<lb />
			8.12.2009, long after the commencement of the
			<lb />
			commercial relationship, to look comprehensively into all
			<lb />
			aspects of the contract, both commercial and technical.
			<lb />
			According to the Report submitted by him in May2010, it
			<lb />
			was Forge Advisors, USA which made a presentation in
			<lb />
			March2003, on technology aspects of digital multimedia
			<lb />
			services to Antrix/ISRO, followed by a presentation in
			<lb />
			May2003 purportedly to the top management of Antrix/
			<lb />
			ISRO. The MoU was signed thereafter;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii) But the documents filed by the appellants themselves
			<lb />
			show that a power point presentation was made by Forge
			<lb />
			LLC on 22.03.2004, proposing an Indian joint venture to
			<lb />
			launch what came to be known as DEVAS (which perhaps
			<lb />
			ultimately turned out to be ASURAS 23 ). It was claimed in
			<lb />
			the said proposal that DEVAS platform will be capable of
			<lb />
			delivering multimedia and information services via
			<lb />
			satellite to mobile devices tailored to the needs of various
			<lb />
			market segments such as consumer segment, commercial
			<lb />
			segment and social segment. This presentation dated
			<lb />
			22.03.2004 was followed by a proposal dated 15.04.2004,
			<lb />
			about which we have made a brief mention in paragraph
			<lb />
			3.4 above. This proposal obliged ISRO/Antrix to invest in
			<lb />
			one operational Sband Satellite with a ground space
			<lb />
			segment to be leased to a joint venture between Forge and
			<lb />
			23 According to Hindu Mythology, Devas are demigods and Asuras are demons
			<lb />
			Antrix. What was to be reserved for the joint venture was
			<lb />
			97% of the space. The consideration receivable by ISRO/
			<lb />
			Antrix upon such a lease, was to be US $ 11 million
			<lb />
			annually for a period of 15 years. At least at this stage the
			<lb />
			proposal to invest in an operational Sband satellite and
			<lb />
			the lease of nearly the entire space of such satellite to a
			<lb />
			joint venture, should have come to the public domain, to
			<lb />
			see, (a) if the technology existed; and (b) if the proposal
			<lb />
			was commercially viable. But it was not done;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iv) On 14.05.2004, a Committee headed by one Dr. K.N.
			<lb />
			Shankara, Director, Space Applications Centre was
			<lb />
			constituted purportedly to examine the technical
			<lb />
			feasibility, risk management including possibilities of
			<lb />
			alternate uses of space segment, financial and market
			<lb />
			aspects and time schedule. According to the Report
			<lb />
			submitted by this Committee, DEVAS was conceived as a
			<lb />
			new national service expected to be launched by the end
			<lb />
			of 2006 that would deliver video, multimedia and
			<lb />
			information services via high powered satellite to mobile
			<lb />
			receivers in vehicles and mobile phones across India. The
			<lb />
			catch here lies in the fact that while it was possible to
			<lb />
			deliver some of these services via terrestrial mode, it was
			<lb />
			not possible at that point of time to provide this bouquet
			<lb />
			of services via satellite. Even today satellite phones are
			<lb />
			beyond the reach of a common man. Mobile receivers or
			<lb />
			devices which can simply receive audio and video content
			<lb />
			are different from mobile phones, which are capable of
			<lb />
			providing a two way communication. The technology for
			<lb />
			providing the services through mobile phones was not in
			<lb />
			existence at that time, which is why the proposal made by
			<lb />
			Forge Advisors included an expectation that such a
			<lb />
			service may be launched by the end of 2006. It was with
			<lb />
			this expectation/promise that an Agreement was entered
			<lb />
			into on 28.01.2005 but this socalled new national service
			<lb />
			was never launched as promised in 2006. The launch of
			<lb />
			the services was not linked to the provision of a Sband
			<lb />
			satellite by Antrix, at least at the time when negotiations
			<lb />
			took place;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(v)
			<lb />
			Admittedly, FIPB (Foreign Investment Promotion Board)
			<lb />
			approvals taken by Devas during the period May2006 to
			<lb />
			September2009 were on the basis of the ISP (Internet
			<lb />
			Service Provider) license secured from the Department of
			<lb />
			Telecommunications on 02.05.2008 and IPTV (Internet
			<lb />
			Protocol Television) services license obtained on
			<lb />
			31.03.2009;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vi) Therefore, the finding of the Tribunal, (a) that a public
			<lb />
			largesse was doled out in favour of Devas, in
			<lb />
			contravention of the public policy in India; (b) that Devas
			<lb />
			enticed Antrix/ISRO to enter into an MoU followed by an
			<lb />
			Agreement by promising to provide something that was
			<lb />
			not in existence at that time and which did not come into
			<lb />
			existence even later; (c) that the licenses and approvals
			<lb />
			were for completely different services; and (d) that the
			<lb />
			services offered were not within the scope of SATCOM
			<lb />
			Policy etc. are actually borne out by records;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vii) There is no denial of the fact that Devas offered a bouquet
			<lb />
			of services known as (a) Devas Services through a device
			<lb />
			called (b) Devas device in a hybrid mode of transmission,
			<lb />
			which is a combination of satellite and terrestrial
			<lb />
			transmissions, and which is called (c) Devas Technology
			<lb />
			but none of which existed at the relevant point of time or
			<lb />
			even thereafter;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(viii) Devas did not even hold necessary intellectual property
			<lb />
			rights in this regard though they claimed to have applied;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ix) That the formation of the company, namely, Devas
			<lb />
			Multimedia Private Limited was for a fraudulent and
			<lb />
			unlawful purpose is borne out by the fact that the
			<lb />
			company was incorporated in December2004, as a result
			<lb />
			of preliminary meetings held at Bangalore in March2003
			<lb />
			and in USA in May2003, followed by the signing of the
			<lb />
			MoU on 28.07.2003, the presentation made on
			<lb />
			22.03.2004 and the discussions held thereafter. The
			<lb />
			ground work was clearly done during the period from
			<lb />
			March2003 to December2004 before the company was
			<lb />
			formally incorporated. Immediately after incorporation,
			<lb />
			the Agreement dated 28.01.2005 was signed. Therefore,
			<lb />
			the first ingredient of Section 271(c) of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013, namely, the formation of the company for a
			<lb />
			fraudulent and unlawful purpose was clearly made out;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(x) The kind of licenses obtained such as ISP and IPTV
			<lb />
			licenses and the object for which FIPB approvals were
			<lb />
			taken but showcased as those sufficient for fulfilling the
			<lb />
			obligations under the Agreement dated 28.01.2005
			<lb />
			demonstrated that the affairs of the company were
			<lb />
			conducted in a fraudulent manner. This is fortified by the
			<lb />
			fact that a total amount of Rs.579 crores was brought in,
			<lb />
			but almost 85% of the said amount was siphoned out of
			<lb />
			India, partly towards establishment of a subsidiary in the
			<lb />
			US, partly towards business support services and partly
			<lb />
			towards litigation expenses. We do not know if the
			<lb />
			amount of Rs.233 crores taken out of India towards
			<lb />
			litigation services, also became a part of the investment in
			<lb />
			a more productive venture, namely, arbitration. The
			<lb />
			manner in which a misleading note was put to the cabinet
			<lb />
			and the manner in which the minutes of the meeting of
			<lb />
			TAG subcommittee were manipulated, highlighted by the
			<lb />
			Tribunal, also shows that the affairs of the company were
			<lb />
			conducted in a fraudulent manner. Thus, the second limb
			<lb />
			of Section 271(c), namely, the conduct of the affairs of the
			<lb />
			company in a fraudulent manner, also stood established.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xi) SATCOM Policy perceived telecommunication and
			<lb />
			broadcasting services to be independent of each other and
			<lb />
			also mutually exclusive. Therefore, a combination of both
			<lb />
			was not permitted by law. It is especially so since no
			<lb />
			deliberation took place with the Ministry of Information
			<lb />
			and Broadcasting. Moreover, unless ICC allocates space
			<lb />
			segment, to a private player, the same becomes unlawful.
			<lb />
			This is why the conduct of the affairs of the company
			<lb />
			became unlawful;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xii) That the officials of the Department of Space and Antrix
			<lb />
			were in collusion and that it was a case of fence eating the
			<lb />
			crop (and also allowing others to eat the crop), by joining
			<lb />
			hands with third parties, is borne out by the fact that the
			<lb />
			Note of the 104 th Space Commission did not contain a
			<lb />
			reference to the Agreement. The Cabinet Note dated
			<lb />
			17.11.2005 prepared after ten months of signing of the
			<lb />
			Agreement, did not make a mention about Devas or the
			<lb />
			Agreement, but proceeded on the basis as though ISRO
			<lb />
			received several Expressions of Interest. These materials
			<lb />
			show the complicity of the officials to allow Devas to have
			<lb />
			unjust enrichment;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xiii) It is on record that the minutes of the meeting of the Sub
			<lb />
			Committee dated 06.01.2009 were manipulated and the
			<lb />
			experimental licence was granted on 07.05.2009. Only
			<lb />
			thereafter, the original minutes were restored on
			<lb />
			20.11.2009 and that too after protest.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xiv) Admittedly, every one of the investors procured shares of
			<lb />
			the company in liquidation and each shareholder had a
			<lb />
			representative in the board of directors. Since the board
			<lb />
			controlled the company, the directors were guilty of the
			<lb />
			conduct of the affairs of the company in a fraudulent
			<lb />
			manner. Since each shareholder had a representative in
			<lb />
			the board, the shareholders had to take the blame for the
			<lb />
			misdeeds of the directors;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xv) Additionally, the shareholders were fully aware of the fact
			<lb />
			that the application for approval dated 02.02.2006 to the
			<lb />
			FIPB was for ISP services. But they entered into a Share
			<lb />
			Subscription Agreement on 06.03.2006 for Devas
			<lb />
			services. The Share Subscription Agreement discloses that
			<lb />
			they were aware of the false statements contained in the
			<lb />
			Agreement dated 28.01.2005. Therefore, the shareholders,
			<lb />
			who now want to reap the fruits of a tree, fraudulently
			<lb />
			planted and unlawfully nurtured, cannot feign ignorance
			<lb />
			and escape the allegations of fraud.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.9
			<lb />
			An argument was advanced by the learned senior counsel
			<lb />
			for the appellants, on the basis of a statement contained in the order
			<lb />
			of NCLAT that the allegations are prima facie made out, that a
			<lb />
			company cannot be ordered to be wound up on the basis of prima
			<lb />
			facie findings. The standard of proof required for winding up of a
			<lb />
			company cannot be prima facie.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.10
			<lb />
			But we do not think that the appellants can take
			<lb />
			advantage of the use of an inappropriate expression by NCLAT. The
			<lb />
			detailed findings recorded by the Tribunal show that they are final
			<lb />
			and not prima facie. Merely because NCLAT used an erroneous
			<lb />
			expression those findings cannot become prima facie.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			Miscellenous Grounds
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.1
			<lb />
			Apart from the above main grounds of attack, which we
			<lb />
			have dealt in extenso, the learned senior counsel for the appellants
			<lb />
			also made a few supplementary submissions. One of them was that
			<lb />
			a lis between two private parties cannot become the subject matter
			<lb />
			of a petition under Section 271(c). But this argument is to be
			<lb />
			rejected outright, in view of the fact that the claims of Devas and its
			<lb />
			shareholders are also on the property of the Government of India.
			<lb />
			The space segment in the satellite proposed to be launched by the
			<lb />
			Government of India, is the property of the Government of India. In
			<lb />
			fact, the shareholders have secured two awards against the Republic
			<lb />
			of India under BIT. Therefore, it is neither a lis between two private
			<lb />
			parties nor a private lis between a private party and a public
			<lb />
			authority. It is a case of fraud of a huge magnitude which cannot be
			<lb />
			brushed under the carpet, as a private lis.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.2
			<lb />
			Another contention raised on behalf of the appellants is
			<lb />
			that the petition under Section 271(c) should have been preceded, at
			<lb />
			least by a report from the Serious Fraud Investigation Office, which
			<lb />
			has now gained statutory status under Section 211 of the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 2013. But this contention is unacceptable, in view
			<lb />
			of the fact that under the 2013 Act there are two different routes for
			<lb />
			winding up of a company on allegations of fraud. One is under
			<lb />
			Section 271(c) and the other is under the just and equitable clause
			<lb />
			in Section 271(e), read with Section 224(2) and Section 213(b).
			<lb />
			What was Section 439(1)(f) read with Section 243 and Section 237(b)
			<lb />
			of the 1956 Act, have now taken a new avatar under Section 224(2)
			<lb />
			read with Section 213(b). It is only in the second category of cases
			<lb />
			that the report of the investigation should precede a petition for
			<lb />
			winding up.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.3
			<lb />
			Yet another contention raised on behalf of the appellants
			<lb />
			is that the criminal complaint filed for the offences punishable under
			<lb />
			Section 420 read with Section 120B IPC, has not yet been taken to
			<lb />
			its logical end. Therefore, it is contended that in case the officials of
			<lb />
			Antrix and shareholders of Devas are acquitted after trial, the clock
			<lb />
			cannot be put back, if the company is now wound up. Attractive as
			<lb />
			it may seem at first blush, this contention cannot hold water, if
			<lb />
			scrutinised a little deeper. The standard of proof required in a
			<lb />
			criminal case is different from the standard of proof required in the
			<lb />
			proceedings before NCLT. The outcome of one need not depend upon
			<lb />
			the outcome of the other, as the consequences are civil under the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 2013 and penal in the criminal proceedings.
			<lb />
			Moreover, this argument can be reversed like the handle of a dagger.
			<lb />
			What if the company is allowed to continue to exist and also enforce
			<lb />
			the arbitration awards for amounts totalling to tens of thousands of
			<lb />
			crores of Indian Rupees (The ICC award is stated to be for INR
			<lb />
			10,000 crores and the 2 BIT awards are stated to be for INR 5,000
			<lb />
			crores) and eventually the Criminal Court finds all shareholders
			<lb />
			guilty of fraud? The answer to this question would be abhorring.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.4
			<lb />
			Lastly, it was contended that the actual motive behind
			<lb />
			Antrix seeking the winding up of Devas, is to deprive Devas, of the
			<lb />
			benefits of an unanimous award passed by the ICC Arbitral tribunal
			<lb />
			presided over by a former Chief Justice of India and the two BIT
			<lb />
			awards and that such attempts on the part of a corporate entity
			<lb />
			wholly owned by the Government of India would send a wrong
			<lb />
			message to international investors.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.5
			<lb />
			We do not find any merit in the above submission. If as a
			<lb />
			matter of fact, fraud as projected by Antrix, stands established, the
			<lb />
			motive behind the victim of fraud, coming up with a petition for
			<lb />
			winding up, is of no relevance. If the seeds of the commercial
			<lb />
			relationship between Antrix and Devas were a product of fraud
			<lb />
			perpetrated by Devas, every part of the plant that grew out of those
			<lb />
			seeds, such as the Agreement, the disputes, arbitral awards etc., are
			<lb />
			all infected with the poison of fraud. A product of fraud is in conflict
			<lb />
			with the public policy of any country including India. The basic
			<lb />
			notions of morality and justice are always in conflict with fraud and
			<lb />
			hence the motive behind the action brought by the victim of fraud
			<lb />
			can never stand as an impediment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.6
			<lb />
			We do not know if the action of Antrix in seeking the
			<lb />
			winding up of Devas may send a wrong message, to the community
			<lb />
			of investors. But allowing Devas and its shareholders to reap the
			<lb />
			benefits of their fraudulent action, may nevertheless send another
			<lb />
			wrong message namely that by adopting fraudulent means and by
			<lb />
			bringing into India an investment in a sum of INR 579 crores, the
			<lb />
			investors can hope to get tens of thousands of crores of rupees, even
			<lb />
			after siphoning off INR 488 crores.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Conclusion
			<lb />
			Therefore, in fine, we find all the grounds of attack to the
			<lb />
			concurrent orders of the NCLT and NCLAT to be unsustainable.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the appeals are dismissed. However, without any order
			<lb />
			as to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			…..…………....................J.
			<lb />
			(Hemant Gupta)
			<lb />
			.…..………......................J.
			<lb />
			(V. Ramasubramanian)
			<lb />
			NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			JANUARY 17, 2022
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
