<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			MANMOHAN SINGH, J.
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			By this order, I propose to dispose of IA No.7774/2011
			<lb />
			filed by plaintiff under Order XXXIX Rules 1 and 2 Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure,1908 and IA No.10124/2011 filed under order XXXIX Rule
			<lb />
			4 CPC seeking vacation of interim order passed on 03.06.2011.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The brief factual matrix of the matter can be enunciated as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			The Plaintiff no 1 is stated to be a company incorporated under
			<lb />
			the laws of Korea. The plaintiff No. 2 is stated to be company
			<lb />
			incorporated under the Indian Companies Act. Both the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			collectively stated to be a part of Samsung Group of Companies
			<lb />
			having 14 listed companies and 285 worldwide operations.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			It is stated that the plaintiffs are engaged in the business of
			<lb />
			manufacturing and trading in electronic goods such colour
			<lb />
			televisions of all types, home appliances, washing machines,
			<lb />
			microwaves, air conditions, computers, printers and cartridges
			<lb />
			etc.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have stated to earn revenues for the year 2009
			<lb />
			around US$ 172.5 Billion and the net income was around US$
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.8 Billion. The asset of the plaintiffs were valued as USD
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			294.5 Billion for the year 2004-2005.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs inform that it is one of leading companies in the
			<lb />
			electronic goods segment across the globe and its products are of
			<lb />
			world class quality goods. The plaintiffs have also informed
			<lb />
			about their business in India which was initiated since 1995
			<lb />
			when the plaintiff No. 2 was formed. The plaintiff No. 2 enjoys
			<lb />
			a turnover of US 1 Billion in just over a decade of operations in
			<lb />
			India. All this has been done under the brand name and corporate
			<lb />
			of the plaintiffs namely SAMSUNG.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have also informed about the extensive promotions
			<lb />
			carried out in promoting and popularizing the brand name
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG by them and due to the same and their worldwide
			<lb />
			nature of operation, the trade mark SAMSUNG as per the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs is the well known or famous trade mark.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			f)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have registered the following the trade marks in
			<lb />
			India under the mark SAMSUNG:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Sl
			<lb />
			No.
			<lb />
			TRADEMARK
			<lb />
			CLASS
			<lb />
			REGISTRATION
			<lb />
			NO.
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			Samsung
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			591127
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			1055554
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			Samsung
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
			591128
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
			1055555
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			Samsung
			<lb />
			11
			<lb />
			591126
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG
			<lb />
			11
			<lb />
			1055556
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG
			<lb />
			7,9,11
			<lb />
			1240403
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			The Plaintiff No. 1 has licensed the use of Samsung
			<lb />
			trademark in India to Plaintiff No.2 vide a trademark agreement
			<lb />
			dated 8 th July 2003. The said agreement has also been filed with
			<lb />
			the Trade Mark&quot;s Registry for registration.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			g)
			<lb />
			The grievance of the plaintiffs in the present case relates to the
			<lb />
			important business of manufacturing, selling and distribution of
			<lb />
			wide range of printers under the mark SAMSUNG by them and
			<lb />
			rampant problem of parallel importation especially carried out by
			<lb />
			the defendant No. 1 and 2 whereby the plaintiffs are deprived to
			<lb />
			carry out their legitimate business under the mark SAMSUNG.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			h)
			<lb />
			The plaintiff explains the said business of printers which includes
			<lb />
			wide range of varieties of printers costing from Rs.5299/-to
			<lb />
			Rs.1,39,999/-. All these printers cater to diversified needs of the
			<lb />
			consumers across the India. The plaintiffs have stated that the
			<lb />
			printers sold in India by them are sold through the authorized
			<lb />
			channel of resellers and partners of the plaintiff No.2. Any third
			<lb />
			party who is not authorized by the plaintiff cannot legitimately
			<lb />
			sell, advertise the Samsung products in India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			i)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have also mentioned in the plaint that the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			are selling and advertising their products through website namely
			<lb />
			Samsung.com/in through which they intend to educate the
			<lb />
			customers of their varied range of products etc.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			j)
			<lb />
			The defendant No. 2 is stated to be a company engaged in
			<lb />
			distributing, retailing and selling various types of computer
			<lb />
			hardware as well as periphericals. The defendant No. 3 appears
			<lb />
			to be retail outlet of the defendant No. 2. The defendant No. 1 is
			<lb />
			added as the managing director for the defendant No. 2
			<lb />
			k)
			<lb />
			The grievance as stated in the plaint is that in the month of
			<lb />
			March 2011, the plaintiffs received an information from market
			<lb />
			sources that the defendants were distributing, retailing and
			<lb />
			selling grey market printers of the plaintiffs in the market and not
			<lb />
			the ones supplied by the plaintiff No. 2. As per the said
			<lb />
			information gathered from the market sources, the plaintiff
			<lb />
			learned that the said printers as being sold by the defendants
			<lb />
			were without the proper Maximum Retail Price stickers and were
			<lb />
			not earmarked to be sold in the Indian market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			l)
			<lb />
			It is averred that the defendants are neither the authorized sellers
			<lb />
			of the Samsung products nor they have the permission or the
			<lb />
			authorization from the plaintiff to sell their products in India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			m)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have averred in the plaint that on 18 th March 2011,
			<lb />
			the advertisement was published in the weekly The DQ week by
			<lb />
			the defendant No. 2 offering SAMSUNG printers for sale. The
			<lb />
			plaintiff also complained that the said advertisement used the
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG mark along with slanted device. The said
			<lb />
			advertisement quoted the price much below than the price of the
			<lb />
			printers ordinarily sold in the market as per the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			n)
			<lb />
			The Defendant also operates a website whereby the defendant
			<lb />
			offers for sale a varied range of the printers under the mark
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG at the prices much lower than offered by the
			<lb />
			plaintiff. The defendants use the technique of deep hyperlinking
			<lb />
			whereby the defendant is also able establish a connect between
			<lb />
			his website with that of the plaintiff when it comes to displaying
			<lb />
			the product to the consumer. All this is done to confuse the
			<lb />
			consumer so as to believe that the products are emanated from
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs authorized representatives when the defendants are
			<lb />
			not so.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			o)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have also informed that the defendants&quot; premises
			<lb />
			were also inspected by the plaintiffs through their investigator
			<lb />
			whereby the following models of the printers were discovered
			<lb />
			when the plaintiffs asked to purchase the printers:
			<lb />
			1. ML-160 which should be rather ML-1666 for India.
			<lb />
			2. SCX-3200 instead of SCX 3201 and
			<lb />
			3. SCX -4623F instead of SCX -4623 FN
			<lb />
			The defendant representative assured the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			representative that these printers have exactly the same features
			<lb />
			which they are looking for in the printers asked for. The prices
			<lb />
			were also quoted as :
			<lb />
			1. ML-1666 -Rs. 3300
			<lb />
			2. SCX -3200 -Rs 6500
			<lb />
			3. SCX-4623 F -Rs. 9500
			<lb />
			It is mentioned that the plaintiffs&quot; representative has thus
			<lb />
			purchased the said products from the defendant&quot;s representative
			<lb />
			and along with the same was given the card and the invoice
			<lb />
			issued by the defendant. All this has been averred in the plaint to
			<lb />
			show the cause of action wherein the products which as per the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs are meant for Indian markets are sold by the defendants
			<lb />
			at the price lower than the MRP of the said products sold by the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			p)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have further stated that the said printers purchased
			<lb />
			by the plaintiffs from the defendants were then examined by the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs and it was discovered the said printers from materially
			<lb />
			different from that of the products sold by the plaintiffs in Indian
			<lb />
			market. The said differences have been highlighted by the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs product model wise as under:
			<lb />
			A-ML-1660/ XSG (Impugned product No. 1)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			S. No
			<lb />
			Point
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			difference
			<lb />
			Impugned product Product sold in
			<lb />
			India
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			MRP Label
			<lb />
			Incorrect
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			missing details
			<lb />
			Correct
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			complete details
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Model number ML-1660/ XSG
			<lb />
			ML-1666/ XIP
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			MRP
			<lb />
			Rs. 3300
			<lb />
			Rs. 6299
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Size of the
			<lb />
			Box
			<lb />
			Smaller.
			<lb />
			Not
			<lb />
			conforming with
			<lb />
			the packaging laws
			<lb />
			of India
			<lb />
			A little larger
			<lb />
			confirming
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			laws of India
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Warranty
			<lb />
			a. Warranty
			<lb />
			applicable
			<lb />
			only in Gulf
			<lb />
			Region (will
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			honored in
			<lb />
			India)
			<lb />
			b. No extended
			<lb />
			warranty
			<lb />
			c. Does
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			offer on site
			<lb />
			warranty
			<lb />
			a. Warranty
			<lb />
			applicable
			<lb />
			only in India
			<lb />
			b. Offers
			<lb />
			an
			<lb />
			extended
			<lb />
			warranty 1 +
			<lb />
			2 years
			<lb />
			c. Offers
			<lb />
			on
			<lb />
			site warranty
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Colour
			<lb />
			Has dual tone -
			<lb />
			Black and white
			<lb />
			Has a monotone -
			<lb />
			only black, Dual
			<lb />
			tone printers are
			<lb />
			not sold in India
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Model No. of
			<lb />
			toner
			<lb />
			1042
			<lb />
			1043
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Capacity
			<lb />
			700 prints
			<lb />
			1500 Prints
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			USB Cable
			<lb />
			Not provided
			<lb />
			Provided
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			Plug
			<lb />
			2 Pin (without
			<lb />
			earthing)
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			Pin
			<lb />
			(with
			<lb />
			earthing)
			<lb />
		</table>
		<item>
			Likewise for respective models SCX-3200 XSG and SCX-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4623/ XSA, the differences on similar lines have been
			<lb />
			highlighted in para 32 of the plaint.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			q)
			<lb />
			Additionally, it is stated that the packaging of the said printers is
			<lb />
			violative of the provisions of The Standards of Weights and
			<lb />
			Measurement Act, 1976 and the rules made therein. Thus, the
			<lb />
			said act of the parallel importation by the defendants is also
			<lb />
			violative of other laws for the time being in force.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			3.
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs by showing the above acts of the defendants
			<lb />
			allege that the defendants are guilty of the following infringement:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			By way of parallel imports, the defendants are infringing
			<lb />
			the trade mark SAMSUNG of the plaintiffs in as much as
			<lb />
			the importation has been caused without the consent or
			<lb />
			permission of the registered proprietor and thus the
			<lb />
			defendants acts are infringement in view of Section 29 of
			<lb />
			the Trade Marks Act.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			By way of doing meta tagging and deep hyperlinking, the
			<lb />
			defendants are guilty of the infringement of trade mark
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG as the defendants are using the mark in
			<lb />
			relation to the advertisement and the use of the same is
			<lb />
			treated to be use for the purposes of infringement and thus
			<lb />
			the defendants are violating Section 29(1) read with
			<lb />
			Section 29 (6) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			The defendants are passing off the goods which are not
			<lb />
			meant for Indian market giving the impression that the
			<lb />
			same are emanating from the plaintiffs when the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			have not given any such authorization or permission to the
			<lb />
			defendants to undertake such activities. All this is being
			<lb />
			done to the detriment of the plaintiffs is clear act of
			<lb />
			misrepresentation as well as deceit to the general public.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			The defendants are also tarnishing the reputation of the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs well known trade mark SAMSUNG by providing
			<lb />
			the goods which are actually not intended to be served to
			<lb />
			the Indian public. Any element of dissatisfaction would
			<lb />
			then clearly attack or reflect on the reputation of the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs mark SAMSUNG.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			For all these reason, the plaintiffs have raised the complaint
			<lb />
			before this court by preferring a suit for infringement of the trade mark
			<lb />
			and passing off. Along with the same, the plaintiffs have preferred an
			<lb />
			IA No.7774/2011 under Order XXXIX Rule 1 and 2 CPC which came
			<lb />
			up for hearing on admission on 11.05.2011 and then on 03.06.2011
			<lb />
			when this court has passed the order to the following effect:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;The Defendants, their partners, directors, principal officers,
			<lb />
			servants, agents and all others acting for and on their behalf are
			<lb />
			restrained from importing, exporting distributing, selling, offering
			<lb />
			for sale, advertising, directly or indirectly dealing in the grey
			<lb />
			market ink cartridges/toners, or any other products of the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs under the mark SAMSUNG or any mark as may be
			<lb />
			deceptively similar to the plaintiffs trade marks amounting to
			<lb />
			infringement of the plaintiffs registered trade marks.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The defendants were served in the suit and in the
			<lb />
			application and pursuant to the same, the defendants have filed written
			<lb />
			statement and an application which is IA No.10124/2011 under Order
			<lb />
			XXXIX Rule 4 read with Section 151 CPC seeking vacation of interim
			<lb />
			order passed on June 3, 2011. The following are the main contentions
			<lb />
			and defences raised in the application and written statement:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs are guilty of concealment of material facts and
			<lb />
			have not come before this court with clean hands. The
			<lb />
			defendants have been portrayed as infringers in the plaint
			<lb />
			however, the plaintiffs have not disclosed the following facts:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have suppressed a material fact that the
			<lb />
			applicants/ defendants are importing and selling the
			<lb />
			genuine, original unaltered SAMSUNG printers which
			<lb />
			have been purchased and imported through the legitimate
			<lb />
			channels. These printers have been sold in the market by
			<lb />
			the plaintiff No. 1 and the same are being imported into
			<lb />
			India and sold in the same condition as they were first
			<lb />
			sold by the plaintiff. All the relevant import documents for
			<lb />
			each of the printers listed in the suit are being filed with
			<lb />
			these present proceedings along with the import licence
			<lb />
			issued to the defendant No.2 and their central sales tax
			<lb />
			registration.
			<lb />
			 Plaintiffs have falsely claimed that they have received
			<lb />
			information that the defendants were distributing, retailing
			<lb />
			and selling grey market printers of the plaintiffs in the
			<lb />
			market in the month of the March 2011. The plaintiffs
			<lb />
			have deliberately chosen to suppress the fact that the
			<lb />
			defendant No. 3 has been erstwhile brand shop which is
			<lb />
			authorized retail outlet of the plaintiff No. 2 from the year
			<lb />
			2000 to 2004, the only IT brand ship of the plaintiff No. 2
			<lb />
			in India at the time. Documents demonstrating the
			<lb />
			commercial relationship between the plaintiff No. 2 and
			<lb />
			defendants No. 1 and 3 are filed with the court.
			<lb />
			 It is submitted that even when the defendant No. 3 was
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs authorized outlet, it was importing and
			<lb />
			selling openly on its premises, parallel imported products
			<lb />
			that were not purchased from plaintiffs No. 2 or Indian
			<lb />
			distributors and the same were stocked with the defendant
			<lb />
			No. 3&quot;s premises and the consumers had the option of
			<lb />
			buying either of them. The only difference was price
			<lb />
			differentiation and warranty which is emanated from
			<lb />
			Indian entity of the plaintiffs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The business model of the defendants of selling parallel
			<lb />
			imported product existed from as far back as 1998 and
			<lb />
			was well known to the plaintiff No. 2 even at the time
			<lb />
			when the agreement was entered into between the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs and the defendants and no objection was raised
			<lb />
			during the currency of the relationship between the
			<lb />
			parties.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The plaintiffs have not disclosed that the plaintiff No. 2
			<lb />
			itself imports products from other territories and sells
			<lb />
			them in India in the exact same manner as the defendants
			<lb />
			and their averment in the plaint that there are separate
			<lb />
			earmarked products for India is untrue.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The plaintiffs have suppressed the relationship between
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs and the defendants and there are some
			<lb />
			commercial relationships between the plaintiffs and the
			<lb />
			defendants whereby the plaintiffs have failed to pay the
			<lb />
			rent to the defendants and the present suit is a counter
			<lb />
			blast to the said grievance which is also pending before
			<lb />
			this court in form of CS(OS) 357 of 2007 Dimension
			<lb />
			Next Infocom vs. Samsung India Electronics Ltd.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The defendants have again attempted to falsify the
			<lb />
			statements in the plaint by urging the model numbers of
			<lb />
			the printers stated in the plaint are not relating to the ones
			<lb />
			which are earmarked for India and the said statement is
			<lb />
			untrue. It is stated that the products are actually available
			<lb />
			in various countries including India and thus the said
			<lb />
			stand of the plaintiff in the plaint is incorrect.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The defendants have again stated that the investigator
			<lb />
			story mentioned in the plaint is not properly worded and
			<lb />
			the defendants never stated that the printers which were
			<lb />
			asked for are out of stock etc, the said story is
			<lb />
			misrepresented before this court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 Plaintiffs are themselves guilty of defrauding the
			<lb />
			exchequer by selling the printers after importation at the
			<lb />
			higher prices. The plaintiffs have also not shown to the
			<lb />
			court as to how and why their own products are imported
			<lb />
			at the lower prices are shown to be at the higher prices on
			<lb />
			paper.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			The allegations in the plaint relating to warranty are also
			<lb />
			incorrect as the defendants are themselves offering carrying in
			<lb />
			warranty to their customers and in the cases of the faulty
			<lb />
			products, replacing the parts with the original ones. It is
			<lb />
			submitted that there is recognition in the law of about the
			<lb />
			different kinds of warranties. The uniform commercial code in
			<lb />
			USA recognizes the seller&quot;s warranty obligations. The
			<lb />
			defendants are thus well within their right to provide warranty to
			<lb />
			their own customers independent to that of the plaintiffs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			It is a settled law that the import, sale and/ or resale of the
			<lb />
			genuine printers by the defendants does not amount and indeed
			<lb />
			cannot amount to infringement, dilution and passing off. The
			<lb />
			plaintiffs cannot impose restriction on sale or resale of genuine
			<lb />
			products originating from the plaintiffs. The present suit is an
			<lb />
			attempt to thwart competition from original goods which are
			<lb />
			available in the market at substantially lesser price. The present
			<lb />
			acts of the defendants are permissible under Section 30 of the
			<lb />
			Act of 1999.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have admitted in the para 37 of the plaint that the
			<lb />
			goods appear to be genuine ones. Thus, the said sale of the
			<lb />
			products by the plaintiffs done internationally, the plaintiffs are
			<lb />
			estopped from challenging the subsequent sales by way clear
			<lb />
			application of exhaustion rule envisaged under Section 30 of the
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			Article 6 of TRIPS convention gives the option to the member
			<lb />
			state including India to opt for the exhaustion principle and
			<lb />
			pursuant to the same, India has followed the principle of
			<lb />
			international exhaustion of rights by introducing Section 30
			<lb />
			under the Act of 1999. This fact has been reflected under the
			<lb />
			notes on clauses which are filed with the proceedings
			<lb />
			f)
			<lb />
			The trade marks act does not provide recognize or provide any
			<lb />
			protection to market segmentation or division on the basis of the
			<lb />
			territories in order to enable the trade mark proprietor to engage
			<lb />
			in price differentiation on the basis of the territories. The mere
			<lb />
			act of loss of sales or erosion of the market of the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			cannot be categorized as infringement when there are only
			<lb />
			genuine products which are available in the market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			g)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs&quot; permission or consent for further sale of the
			<lb />
			products which have already sold by the plaintiffs in the
			<lb />
			international market is not required. The contention of the
			<lb />
			contravention of the other laws by the defendants is also
			<lb />
			incorrect.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			h)
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs have wrongly stated that there are alterations in
			<lb />
			order to invoke the exception under Section 30 (4) when actually
			<lb />
			there are no alteration or changes of the products after
			<lb />
			importation.
			<lb />
			By averring the above mentioned defences in the
			<lb />
			application, the defendants pressed for the vacation of the
			<lb />
			injunction. Both the applications came up for hearing before this
			<lb />
			court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Hearing the parties on 8.7.2011, this court was pleased to
			<lb />
			pass an order partially modifying the order dated 3.6.2011 passed in the
			<lb />
			local commissioner application and the goods were released to the
			<lb />
			defendants with few directions. The defendants also filed an affidavit in
			<lb />
			Undertaking along with the photographs on 25.7.2011. A demand draft
			<lb />
			for a value of 3% of the sale price of the printer was also filed.
			<lb />
			The said order was modified by order dated 17.11.2011 in
			<lb />
			view of the statement made by the counsel for the plaintiff that the
			<lb />
			present case is of infringement of trade mark SAMSUNG only in
			<lb />
			relation to printers and its cartridges/toners and is not in respect of any
			<lb />
			other products.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs and the defendants on the other hand pressed
			<lb />
			their respective IAs which have been eventually heard by this court.
			<lb />
			This court has heard the submissions of Mr. Parveen Anand, learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the plaintiff and Mr. Neeraj Kishan Kaul senior advocate
			<lb />
			along with Mr. Saikrishna Rajagopal appearing on behalf of the
			<lb />
			defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Mr. Parveen Anand, learned counsel appearing on behalf of
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs has made his submissions which can be crystallized to the
			<lb />
			following terms:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Firstly, Mr. Anand, learned counsel submitted that the
			<lb />
			defendants acts of importing the printers bearing the trade mark
			<lb />
			Samsung without the permission of the plaintiffs to India
			<lb />
			amounts to infringement of the trade mark within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 29 of the Trade Marks Act, 1999.
			<lb />
			In this context, Mr. Anand has read and relied on Section 29
			<lb />
			of the Trade Marks Act, 1999 and argued that the acts of the
			<lb />
			defendants are without the permission of the registered
			<lb />
			proprietor and also the defendants are not the registered
			<lb />
			proprietor of the trade mark. Further Section 29 (6) provides for
			<lb />
			the definition of use wherein the import of the goods as well as
			<lb />
			selling the goods amounts to use of the trade mark. Thus, as per
			<lb />
			the learned counsel of the plaintiff, the collective reading of
			<lb />
			Section 29 (1) read with Section 29 (6) of the Act would
			<lb />
			squarely cover the defendant&quot;s acts whereby the defendants
			<lb />
			import the goods under the identical mark and sell the same
			<lb />
			within the market without the permission of the owner of the
			<lb />
			registered trade mark.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			Secondly, Mr. Anand has also explained the case of the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			for additional infringements carried out by the defendants by
			<lb />
			adding and using the name Samsung on their website by way of
			<lb />
			meta tagging and deep hyperlinking. By doing all this, the
			<lb />
			defendants are projecting themselves to be associated with the
			<lb />
			plaintiff by offering for sale the products of the plaintiff in the
			<lb />
			advertisements online for sale of the said products. This as per
			<lb />
			the plaintiff&quot;s counsel is an infringement within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 29 (8) as contemplated under the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			Thirdly, Mr. Anand has vociferously argued in refutation to the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s contentions on the principle of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion that Trade Mark Act, 1999 recognizes the principle
			<lb />
			of national exhaustion unlike international exhaustion. Learned
			<lb />
			counsel relied on Section 30 (3) of the Act in this context and
			<lb />
			also drawn the aid from European Union Trade marks Directives
			<lb />
			and provisions of the UK Act 1994 as existing in UK wherein
			<lb />
			the principles of national exhaustion are followed. It is argued
			<lb />
			that the provisions as existing in UK and in Indian Act are more
			<lb />
			or less similarly worded and rather pari materia and therefore,
			<lb />
			the departure from the views expressed by the UK courts under
			<lb />
			similar provisions would not be the correct construction of
			<lb />
			Section 30(3) of the Trade Mark Act and rather this court should
			<lb />
			adopt the views expressed by UK courts and follow the
			<lb />
			principles of national exhaustion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			Fourthly, learned counsel for the plaintiffs has also commented
			<lb />
			on the admission made by the plaintiffs in the replication that
			<lb />
			India follows international exhaustion rule. He says that it was
			<lb />
			made due to oversight while drafting of replication by junior
			<lb />
			counsel. Learned counsel urged before this court that admission
			<lb />
			of the legal principle by the plaintiff or parties to the proceeding
			<lb />
			will not confer any duty on the court to interpret of the provision
			<lb />
			of Act on the basis of the said admission and neither this court
			<lb />
			will not render the same interpretation on the basis of the
			<lb />
			admission if the same can be interpreted otherwise. Thus, it is
			<lb />
			the court to decide what is purely a legal issue and the consent or
			<lb />
			dissent of the parties is immaterial.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			Fifthly, learned counsel has argued that even otherwise still the
			<lb />
			right of the proprietor to oppose further dealings remains under
			<lb />
			Section 30 (4) and the plaintiffs case thus falls within the ambit
			<lb />
			of Section 30 (4).
			<lb />
			This has been explained by Mr. Anand by reading Section
			<lb />
			30 (4) of the Act. By placing reliance on Section 30 (4) of the
			<lb />
			Act, Mr. Anand correlated the applicability of the section with
			<lb />
			the present case by pointing out the following differences or
			<lb />
			changes in the products of the plaintiff vis a vis that of the
			<lb />
			defendants which according to plaintiffs&quot; counsel are material
			<lb />
			changes or impairments enabling the plaintiffs to oppose the
			<lb />
			further dealings in the market. The said differences are outlined
			<lb />
			in the following manner:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			1.
			<lb />
			Incorrect or missing MRP labels mandatory under the
			<lb />
			legal Metrology Act, 2009
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Model numbers
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Price
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Size of the box.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The warranty is not applicable in India, but only in the
			<lb />
			country where the goods have been imported from.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Colour
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Model number of the toner, which is not interchangeable.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Capacity of the toner
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			There is no USB cable provided in the printers sold by the
			<lb />
			defendants
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			10. Different plugs
			<lb />
			11. Different language
			<lb />
			In view of the above as per Mr. Anand, learned counsel for
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs, the case of the plaintiffs is not governed by any
			<lb />
			principle of exhaustion be it national or international provided
			<lb />
			under Section 30 (3) and rather it falls within purview of Section
			<lb />
			30 (4) which is an exception to Section 30 (3) and the defendants
			<lb />
			are selling the products which are not meant for Indian markets
			<lb />
			with the marked changes or impairments without the consent of
			<lb />
			the proprietor which leads to doing something which falls within
			<lb />
			the domain of the proprietor to decide whether he actually
			<lb />
			intends to market such products in the country specific which in
			<lb />
			the instant case is India. Therefore, the plaintiff being the
			<lb />
			proprietor can very well object against the further dealings or
			<lb />
			selling of those goods in India.
			<lb />
			f)
			<lb />
			Sixthly, learned counsel for the plaintiffs has argued that the
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 30 (4) is also applicable where there are
			<lb />
			legitimate reasons for the proprietor to oppose the further
			<lb />
			dealings of the products or the goods. The said legitimate
			<lb />
			reasons as per Mr. Anand in the instance case are manifold and
			<lb />
			the same can be highlighted in the following manner:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			 Material Differences/ Impairment of the goods.
			<lb />
			 Likelihood of consumer confusion
			<lb />
			 Dilution of the trade mark
			<lb />
			 Dissatisfied consumers leading to loss of goodwill and
			<lb />
			reputation
			<lb />
			 Disruption of Authorized distribution channels
			<lb />
			 Possible liability under the Legal Metrology Act
			<lb />
			 Possible Liability under the Consumer Protection Act
			<lb />
			 Misrepresentation through the advertisements, deep hyper
			<lb />
			linking and metatagging.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			All these as per the learned counsel for the plaintiffs are the
			<lb />
			legitimate reasons entitling the proprietor to oppose the further dealings
			<lb />
			of the goods imported by the defendant in addition to the fact that the
			<lb />
			conditions of the goods are changed and impaired. Therefore, the
			<lb />
			concerns or legitimate reasons of the plaintiff allows the opposition of
			<lb />
			dealings in the goods under Section 30 (4) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			This has been further explained by Mr. Anand by urging
			<lb />
			that the section uses the expression &quot;legitimate reasons&quot; which may or
			<lb />
			may not include the change and impairment of the goods and thus the
			<lb />
			said legitimate reasons can be any reason which is legally permissible
			<lb />
			to the proprietor to oppose the dealings in the goods. Mr. Anand has
			<lb />
			argued that the courts in European countries have interpreted the term
			<lb />
			legitimate reasons to subsume the following reasons:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			When the use of the identical trade mark seriously damages the
			<lb />
			reputation of that mark.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			When use is carried out in such a way as to give an impression
			<lb />
			that there is commercial link between the trade mark proprietor
			<lb />
			and third party.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			When the use is carried out in such a way so as to the give the
			<lb />
			impression to the third party is affiliated to the proprietor&quot;s
			<lb />
			distribution network or that there is a special relationship
			<lb />
			between the two persons.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			All these reasons have been included by the courts by
			<lb />
			interpreting the term legitimate reasons. It has been urged that the said
			<lb />
			reasons are satisfied in the present case too in as much as the
			<lb />
			defendants are selling the products which are material changed or
			<lb />
			impaired and thus causing the damage to the reputation of the plaintiffs&quot;
			<lb />
			mark. Furthermore, the defendants are purporting to establish the
			<lb />
			commercial link by using the identical brand name of internet or by
			<lb />
			hyper linking, by advertising in newspapers etc. Therefore, the present
			<lb />
			legitimate reasons must be accepted by this court entitling the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			to prohibit the dealings in the goods.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			Mr. Anand also relied upon the following judgments to
			<lb />
			support his submissions:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			SKF USA v. International Trade Commission, 423F, 3d, 1037
			<lb />
			wherein the court has held that material difference doctrine will
			<lb />
			include physical as well as non physical differences.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			PepsiCo v. Martin Ryes, 70 F.Supp, 2d 1057(1999), wherein the
			<lb />
			court has considered non compliance of labeling requirement as
			<lb />
			material differences and also considered the aspect marketing
			<lb />
			techniques adopted by the importer which is different from that
			<lb />
			of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			Societie Des Product Nestle v. Casa Helvetia, 982 F. 2d 633
			<lb />
			(1992) wherein the court has held that the difference in the
			<lb />
			proprietors goods and grey market good is sufficient to cause
			<lb />
			confusion and the court answered the question in affirmative.
			<lb />
			The court has also considered lack of warranty and after sale
			<lb />
			service as a factor which may also cause consumer confusion.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			Gamut Trading co v. International Trade Commission, 200 F.3d
			<lb />
			(Fed Cir) 1999 wherein the court has held that the rule of
			<lb />
			international exhaustion is not applied incase there are material
			<lb />
			difference between the foreign grey goods and the authorized
			<lb />
			domestic goods.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			Osawa &amp; Co v. B&amp; H Photo 589 F, Supp 1163 (1984) where the
			<lb />
			guarantee and post sale service was held to be material
			<lb />
			difference entitling the proprietor to oppose such sales.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			Ferrero USA Inc v. Ozak Trading Inc, 753 F. Supp 1240 (1991)
			<lb />
			wherein the court has stated that non compliance of the statutory
			<lb />
			requirement amounts to difference or changes which may entitle
			<lb />
			the proprietor to oppose such imports or dealings.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			Original Appalachian Artword Inc. Granada Electronics Inc, 816
			<lb />
			F.2d 68 76 (1987) wherein the court has held about the material
			<lb />
			differences.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			
			<lb />
			General Electric Company v. Mr. Altamas Khan, an order passed
			<lb />
			in CS(OS) No. 1283 of 2006 which is an interim order passed
			<lb />
			exparte.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			Bose Corporation v. Mr. S Mehta &amp; Anr, an exparte order
			<lb />
			passed in CS(OS) No. 337 of 2006.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			Samsung Electronics Company Ltd &amp; Anr v. Mr. Adwani &amp;
			<lb />
			Anr, an exparte order passed in CS(OS) No. 1583 of 2006.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			Samsung Electronics Company Ltd &amp; Anr v. Mr. M. Borana &amp;
			<lb />
			Anr, an exparte order passed in CS(OS) No. 1582 of 2006.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			Zino Davidoff v. A &amp; G Imports Ltd, (2002) RPC 20 wherein
			<lb />
			the European court has evolved the tests relating to consent of
			<lb />
			the proprietor and how the same has to be proved. Further it was
			<lb />
			held that the lack of knowledge of the importer as to the
			<lb />
			objection to resale is immaterial as regards the exhaustion. It is
			<lb />
			also immaterial if the authorized retailers failed to impose a
			<lb />
			contractual reservation on subsequent purchasers.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			In view of the aforementioned submissions and case laws
			<lb />
			relied upon, Mr. Anand concluded his arguments by stating that the
			<lb />
			present case thus warrants the grant of interim injunction as the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs have the prima facie case of established infringement, the
			<lb />
			balance of the convenience also lies in favour of the plaintiffs as the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs would be inconvenienced if the defendants are allowed to
			<lb />
			tarnish the reputation and goodwill of the plaintiff. The irreparable
			<lb />
			injury shall also result to the plaintiffs if the parallel markets are
			<lb />
			allowed to be made by the defendants without the consent of the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs. Therefore, the interim injunction as per the plaintiffs&quot; counsel
			<lb />
			must follow in the present case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Per contra Mr. Neeraj Kishan Kaul, learned Senior counsel
			<lb />
			and Mr. Saikrishna Rajagopal and Ms. Shwetasree Majumdar, learned
			<lb />
			counsel appearing on behalf of the defendants have made their
			<lb />
			submissions which can be outlined in the following terms:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Firstly Mr. Kaul attempted to explain the case of the defendants
			<lb />
			by stating that the defendants are importing and selling the
			<lb />
			genuine, original and unaltered SAMSUNG printers which have
			<lb />
			been purchased and imported through the legitimate channels.
			<lb />
			The printers have been sold in the world market by the plaintiff
			<lb />
			No. 1 and the same are being imported and sold in India in the
			<lb />
			same condition as they were first sold much in the same way as
			<lb />
			the plaintiff No. 2 itself imports products from other territories
			<lb />
			and sells them in India. Thus, as per learned senior counsel, the
			<lb />
			defendants acts of importation of the printers amounts to
			<lb />
			&quot;acquisition from the lawful channels&quot; and also the concept of
			<lb />
			&quot;world market&quot; must be brought into picture wherein there is a
			<lb />
			free world market operating without any barriers. It is thus the
			<lb />
			submission of the defendant&quot;s counsel that there is no prohibition
			<lb />
			thereafter and nor the proprietor is entitled to control the dealings
			<lb />
			in the goods once the goods are lawfully acquired from the world
			<lb />
			market.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul has explained and it has been urged by him that it
			<lb />
			is nobody&quot;s case that the defendants are importing the printers
			<lb />
			from the countries which are so alien to the conditions in India so
			<lb />
			as to categorize Indian market as superior market and imported
			<lb />
			products are inferior. Rather, the imports of the printers made by
			<lb />
			the defendants are emerging from Gulf territories and china
			<lb />
			which are more or less the same territories from where the
			<lb />
			plaintiff No. 2 is also importing the printers. Therefore the
			<lb />
			complaint of the plaintiff is frivolous and meritless.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			Secondly, Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel for the defendants
			<lb />
			has argued that the defendants cannot be held guilty of parallel
			<lb />
			importation in view of the applicability of principle of
			<lb />
			international exhaustion envisaged under Section 30 (3) of the
			<lb />
			Act. Mr. Kaul has specifically urged that India has followed the
			<lb />
			principle of international exhaustion of the goods in respect of
			<lb />
			Trade mark law whereby if the goods are sold once by the
			<lb />
			proprietor under the trade mark worldwide, the proprietor is
			<lb />
			estopped from further questioning or challenging the further
			<lb />
			dealings of the products unless the strong case of Section 30(4)
			<lb />
			of the Act is made out by the plaintiff with evidence.
			<lb />
			This has been explained by Mr. Kaul by citing the Article 6
			<lb />
			of TRIPS convention wherein Members states are given liberty
			<lb />
			to choose the manner of exhaustion principle which they intend
			<lb />
			to adopt. By placing reliance on the said article 6, it has been
			<lb />
			contended by Mr. Kaul that India followed the principle of
			<lb />
			international exhaustion of trade marks by exercising its
			<lb />
			discretion in view of the said Article 6. This has been engrafted
			<lb />
			in the form of Section 30 (3) of the Act as per Mr. Kaul which
			<lb />
			speaks for itself that it is case of the international exhaustion.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel for the defendant in order to
			<lb />
			amplify his argument on India&quot;s take on international exhaustion
			<lb />
			has also relied upon the statement of objects and reasons of
			<lb />
			Clause 30 of the Trade Marks Bill, 1999 which reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;Sub clause (3) and (4) recognize the principle of
			<lb />
			&quot;exhaustion of rights&quot; by preventing the trade mark owner
			<lb />
			from prohibiting on ground of trade mark rights, the
			<lb />
			marketing of goods in any geographical area, once the
			<lb />
			goods under the registered trade mark are lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired by a person. However, when the conditions of
			<lb />
			goods are changed or impaired after they have been put on
			<lb />
			the market, the provision will not apply&quot;
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul also relied upon 227 th Report on Copyright
			<lb />
			Amendment Bill, 2010 which reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;Indian law is quite liberal in permitting Parallel Imports
			<lb />
			of genuine goods bearing the registered trade marks
			<lb />
			provided such goods have not been materially altered after
			<lb />
			they have been put in the market…. The general rule is
			<lb />
			that once trademarked goods are released anywhere in the
			<lb />
			market by or with the consent of trade mark proprietor, the
			<lb />
			proprietor cannot assert its trademarks rights to prevent
			<lb />
			imports of such goods into India, provided that such goods
			<lb />
			are not materially altered&quot;
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul relied upon the case of Xerox Corporation v.
			<lb />
			Puneet Suri which is case wherein while passing an interim
			<lb />
			arrangement by the learned single judge, there are some
			<lb />
			observation to the effect of the rights of proprietor to oppose the
			<lb />
			dealings in relation to second hand goods.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul relied upon some write up on Standards and
			<lb />
			Principles Concerning the Availability, scope and use of Trade
			<lb />
			related Intellectual Property Rights-Communication from India,
			<lb />
			10 th July, 1989 wherein similar observation of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion are made.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul further placed reliance upon some write up or
			<lb />
			Map demonstrating regimes followed by various countries issued
			<lb />
			by International Trade Mark Association which again pinpoints
			<lb />
			the adoption of international exhaustion.
			<lb />
			As per Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel for the defendants,
			<lb />
			the aforementioned statement of objects, reports, write ups,
			<lb />
			views and judgment passed by a single Judge are nothing but a
			<lb />
			strong indicators to the effect that the prevalent position
			<lb />
			governing in India in law of trademarks when it comes to
			<lb />
			importation of genuine goods is international exhaustion and not
			<lb />
			regional exhaustion. Thus, this court should vacate the interim
			<lb />
			order passed on 03.06.2011 with immediate effect as the case of
			<lb />
			defendants is squarely governed by the provisions of Section 30
			<lb />
			(3) of the Act of 1999.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			Thirdly, Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel also argued that the
			<lb />
			plaintiff also admits that India follows the regime of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion in the Replication filed by the plaintiff wherein there
			<lb />
			is categorical admission made by the plaintiff. Therefore, it is all
			<lb />
			the more clear that Section 30 (3) shall be applicable on
			<lb />
			international exhaustion basis.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			Fourthly, Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel for the defendant has
			<lb />
			submitted that Section 30 (4) on which the plaintiff is placing its
			<lb />
			reliance is an exception to the rule of international exhaustion
			<lb />
			and therefore the said exception must be narrowly construed. It
			<lb />
			is argued that the term &quot;legitimate reasons&quot; cannot be given a
			<lb />
			wider import so as to include any legal reason which may make
			<lb />
			the provisions of Section 30 (3) as dead letters. Both Section 30
			<lb />
			(3) and 30 (4) are to be interpreted together holistically so as to
			<lb />
			make them workable together and not one overpowering the
			<lb />
			other.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul propounded that the Section 30 (4) acts as a
			<lb />
			proviso to Section 30 (3) and has placed reliance upon the
			<lb />
			treatise on Interpretation of Statutes by Justice Guru Prasanna
			<lb />
			Singh (G.P. Singh) to urge that the provisos are construed
			<lb />
			narrowly.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul has argued that even otherwise the case of the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			does not fall under Section 30 (4) as the material alterations
			<lb />
			pointed out by the plaintiffs are merely artificial in nature and the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs have not been able to point out any significant changes
			<lb />
			or impairments entitling them to oppose such dealings. It is
			<lb />
			argued that the changes like plug difference is not merely
			<lb />
			artificial but actually there is no such change exists, further,
			<lb />
			model numbers changes are also artificial, guarantee change does
			<lb />
			not make any difference as it is not only the prerogative of the
			<lb />
			proprietor to give such warrantee or guarantee. Therefore, all the
			<lb />
			changes as alleged and responded and other changes whatsoever
			<lb />
			pointed by the plaintiffs are nothing but an artificial changes
			<lb />
			which cannot be accepted as material alterations or impairment
			<lb />
			so that the plaintiff can restrain the defendants from dealing with
			<lb />
			the genuine products of the plaintiff itself.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			f)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul has further argued that the provisions of Section 30 (4)
			<lb />
			are not in pari materia with EU directives are there are
			<lb />
			differences in the wordings and therefore the judgments rendered
			<lb />
			in the relation to &quot;legitimate reasons&quot; cannot be pressed into
			<lb />
			service while dealing with Section 30 (4).
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul has read both the provisions and for the sake of
			<lb />
			brevity only article 7 of the EU Directive is reproduced:
			<lb />
			Article 7 : Exhaustion of the Rights conferred by a trade mark
			<lb />
			(1) The trade mark shall not entitle the proprietor to prohibit
			<lb />
			its use in relation to goods which have been put on the
			<lb />
			market in the community under that trade mark by the
			<lb />
			proprietor or with his consent.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(2) Paragraph 1 shall not apply where there exist legitimate
			<lb />
			reasons for the proprietor to oppose further
			<lb />
			commercialization of the goods, especially where the
			<lb />
			condition of the goods is changed or impaired after they
			<lb />
			have been put on the market&quot;
			<lb />
			By reading the above provisions, Mr. Kaul has pointed out
			<lb />
			the following differences in the language:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Article 7(2) uses the term &quot;further commercialization&quot; as
			<lb />
			against Indian provision which uses the term &quot;further
			<lb />
			dealings&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			Article 7 (2) uses the term &quot;goods especially where….&quot;
			<lb />
			Whereas section 30 (4) uses the term &quot;goods in particular,
			<lb />
			where..&quot; ( The comma occurs after &quot;in particular&quot; in
			<lb />
			Indian section before &quot;especially&quot; in EU Directive)
			<lb />
			The aforementioned two point difference as per Mr. Kaul
			<lb />
			makes the section distinct from Indian provision and therefore
			<lb />
			the section and the directive cannot be said to be pari materia to
			<lb />
			each other. Resultantly, the judgments cannot be relied upon
			<lb />
			relating to legitimate reasons.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			g)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul submitted that even otherwise the term &quot;legitimate
			<lb />
			reasons&quot; is connected with the guarantee of identity of origin of
			<lb />
			the goods and therefore there should be some identity crises from
			<lb />
			where the goods are emanated and not otherwise wherein such
			<lb />
			legitimate reasons can be pressed into service. Accordingly, the
			<lb />
			reasons which are enlisted by the plaintiffs relating to
			<lb />
			disturbance in the distribution channels, etc are artificial and
			<lb />
			cannot be counted as legitimate reasons for opposing the further
			<lb />
			dealings.
			<lb />
			The reliance is placed on the judgment of The Wellcome
			<lb />
			Foundation v. Paranova Pharmazeutika Handels, (2008) ECR
			<lb />
			I-10479 where in the court has said &quot; the right to oppose the use
			<lb />
			of the trade mark once the goods have been put on the market
			<lb />
			only arises where such use is liable to impair the guarantee of
			<lb />
			identity of origin of the goods.&quot;
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul, additionally has taken the objection that the
			<lb />
			plaintiff has not taken the recourse of Section 30 (4) in the
			<lb />
			pleadings and it is only in the reply to the Order XXXIX Rule 4
			<lb />
			application such stand has been taken which also debars the
			<lb />
			plaintiff to take such stand of exception.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			h)
			<lb />
			It is the contention of Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel for the
			<lb />
			defendants that the concept of material alteration is distinct from
			<lb />
			the concept of material differences as enunciated by the US
			<lb />
			courts. It is submitted that the plaintiffs have only pointed out the
			<lb />
			material differences and at no point of time have pointed out any
			<lb />
			material alterative which is statutorily entitles the plaintiffs to
			<lb />
			take such recourse to the exception. The Defendants have relied
			<lb />
			upon the following case laws of US courts wherein the US courts
			<lb />
			despite being lower test of material differences have negated the
			<lb />
			claim of infringements as against the material alteration which is
			<lb />
			stringent test to pass. The case laws relied upon are as follows:
			<lb />
			1. Matrix Essentials Inc v. Emporium Drug Mart Inc of
			<lb />
			Lafayette decided US Court of Appeals (fifth Circuit) no-
			<lb />
			91-4457 which holds that the importation of identical genuine
			<lb />
			products does not per se deceive consumers and thus no
			<lb />
			infringement of trade mark liability can be found.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. American Circuit Breaker Corporation v. Oregon Breakers
			<lb />
			Inc, (406 F.3d 577) (9 th circuit), where the court holds that
			<lb />
			the differences between the products proved so minimal that
			<lb />
			the consumers who purchase the alleged infringer&quot;s goods get
			<lb />
			precise what they believed that they were purchasing. …..
			<lb />
			Territorial protection kicks in under the Lanham Act where
			<lb />
			two merchants sell physically different products in the same
			<lb />
			market and the same name….
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. Zip International Group LLC v. Trilini Imports Inc decided
			<lb />
			by New York Eastern District Court on May 24, 2011
			<lb />
			wherein the court holds : Trademark Law does not reach the
			<lb />
			sale of genuine goods bearing a true mark even though the
			<lb />
			sale is not authorized by the mark owner for there is no
			<lb />
			possibility of confusion.
			<lb />
			By placing reliance on the aforementioned provisions, Mr.
			<lb />
			Kaul contended that the goods which are not physically different
			<lb />
			cannot be opposed by the proprietor while enforcing the right
			<lb />
			under Section 30 (4) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			i)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul has argued that the plaintiff No. 2 is not the only entity
			<lb />
			authorized to import Samsung printers and periphericals in India
			<lb />
			and not even the plaintiffs admit so. It is argued that even the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs admit that the arrangement between the plaintiff No. 1
			<lb />
			and the plaintiff No. 2 is commercial in nature and the same
			<lb />
			cannot come in the way of prohibiting imports by any third party.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul further argued that by private arrangement
			<lb />
			between the parties, the same cannot contract out the law of the
			<lb />
			land if it is otherwise permissible in law. It is argued by the
			<lb />
			private covenant wherein the defendants are not privy to the
			<lb />
			same cannot be used to the detriment of the defendants if the law
			<lb />
			permits them to import such goods under Section 30 (3).
			<lb />
			The judgment passed in the case of Universal
			<lb />
			Petrochemicals Ltd Vs. RSEB; AIR 2001 Cal 110 is relied
			<lb />
			upon to contend that a private commercial arrangement cannot
			<lb />
			override a statutory provision.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul argued further to support his principal submission
			<lb />
			that the market segmentation by way private arrangement cannot
			<lb />
			defeat the legal provision by urging that the law when it enacts
			<lb />
			the exhaustion principle is actually acting against such market
			<lb />
			segmentation principle. For the purposes of the said proposition
			<lb />
			Judgment passed in Matrix Essentials Inc v. Emporium Drug
			<lb />
			Mart Inc. of US court of Appeals is relied upon wherein the
			<lb />
			court has said &quot;Thus Matrix use of professional hair care salons
			<lb />
			as its exclusive trade distribution channel seems more marketing
			<lb />
			related than quality related&quot;.
			<lb />
			Similarly in NEC Electronics v. Cal Circuit Abco, (810
			<lb />
			F.2d 1506) (9 th Circuit) has been relied upon to urge that if the
			<lb />
			plaintiff chooses to sell abroad at the lower prices than those it
			<lb />
			could obtain for identical products here that is its business. In
			<lb />
			doing so, it cannot look into US Trade Marks law to insulate
			<lb />
			American Market or to violate the effects of international trade.
			<lb />
			In Zip International Group LLC v. Trilini Imports Inc again
			<lb />
			US court holds the similar proposition by holding against
			<lb />
			consumer confusion on the same lines.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul propounded that the purpose of such importation
			<lb />
			is immaterial so long as the right to importation exists under
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3). The alleged motive of the importer is of no
			<lb />
			consequence whatsoever. If India followed a principle of
			<lb />
			national exhaustion as incorrectly advocated by the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			then the mere act of importing the products would render them
			<lb />
			infringing. It would not be open to the plaintiff to justify some
			<lb />
			imports and arbitrarily deem others infringing the same. Thus, as
			<lb />
			per Mr. Kaul importation is no prohibition under the trade mark
			<lb />
			law as also contended in point 3 sub point (viii) in the written
			<lb />
			submissions as well.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			j)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul has painstakingly pointed out some admissions which
			<lb />
			as per the learned counsel for the defendants, the plaintiffs have
			<lb />
			made. The said admissions are enlisted as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			Admission in Paragraph 37 of the plaint wherein the
			<lb />
			plaintiff avers &quot;Although the printers as being sold by the
			<lb />
			defendants appear to be genuine products of the plaintiffs,
			<lb />
			the same are illegally imported into India by the
			<lb />
			defendants and are part of &quot;grey market&quot; goods&quot;.
			<lb />
			It is argued that it is thus admitted case that the
			<lb />
			defendants imported goods are genuine ones and by the
			<lb />
			plain reading of Section 30 (3), the said goods cannot be
			<lb />
			categorized as infringing goods. As per the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the defendants, the law precludes the
			<lb />
			proprietor of a trade mark from preventing the sale or
			<lb />
			resale of the goods which have been lawfully acquired by
			<lb />
			a person unless they fall within the exception provided
			<lb />
			under Section 30 (4).
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			Para 2-8 at page 11 of the replication which according the
			<lb />
			defendants, the plaintiff has conceded that it is well laid
			<lb />
			down principle that material change and/ or impairment of
			<lb />
			goods is an exception to the doctrine of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion&quot;.
			<lb />
			As the defendants counsel, the whole argument
			<lb />
			of the plaintiffs relating to national exhaustion and
			<lb />
			physical differences becomes redundant and thus the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs are estopped by urging what has been admitted
			<lb />
			case of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			
			<lb />
			Admission by the plaintiffs in paragraph 17 of the
			<lb />
			replication that India follows the principle of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion of rights under Section 30 (3) of the Trade
			<lb />
			Marks Act, 1999.
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			Admission by the plaintiff in paragraph 11 of the
			<lb />
			replication that the models of the plaintiff No. SCX 4623
			<lb />
			F and the imported one by the defendant bearing No.
			<lb />
			SCX-4623 FN are materially different although they are
			<lb />
			close equivalents. This as per the defendants counsel is
			<lb />
			again an admission which binds the plaintiff from urging
			<lb />
			that there is material difference between the competing
			<lb />
			models.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			k)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel has argued that the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			have made misrepresentation in the plaint as to the status and the
			<lb />
			extent of operation of the defendants. It is argued that the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs have averred that they have received the information
			<lb />
			that the defendants are selling, distributing the gray market
			<lb />
			printers of the plaintiffs in the month of March 2011, on the
			<lb />
			contrary, as per the defendants, they have been an erstwhile
			<lb />
			brand shop/ authorized retail outlet of plaintiff No. 2 from the
			<lb />
			year 2000-2004, the only IT brand shop of the plaintiff No. 2 in
			<lb />
			India.
			<lb />
			It is argued that even when defendant No. 3 was the plaintiff
			<lb />
			No. 2&quot;s authorized outlet, it was importing and selling openly on
			<lb />
			its premises, parallel imported products that were not purchased
			<lb />
			from the plaintiff No. 2 or its distribution channels. Thus, it is not
			<lb />
			newly that the defendants have started this business but it was
			<lb />
			within the knowledge of the plaintiffs at the earlier occasions
			<lb />
			too. Thus, the plaintiffs are guilty of mispresentation and thus the
			<lb />
			interim order ought to vacated on account of misrepresentations.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			l)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul, learned Senior counsel for the defendants have also
			<lb />
			refuted the contentions of the plaintiff relating to meta tagging by
			<lb />
			submitted that the defendants are selling the products which are
			<lb />
			genuine products of the plaintiffs, thus they are entitle to promote
			<lb />
			themselves as the ones selling the plaintiffs products and the way
			<lb />
			that can be described is a fair use defence and cannot be
			<lb />
			categorized as infringement under Section 29 of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			This has been explained by placing reliance on the following
			<lb />
			judgments:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Playboy Enterprises Inc v. Welles, 279 F.3d 796 (9 th Circuit)
			<lb />
			wherein the court said that with regard to headlines and banner
			<lb />
			advertisements has no practical way of describing herself without
			<lb />
			using the trademarked terms……. Forcing (Welles) to use
			<lb />
			absurd turns of phrase in their metatags such as those necessary
			<lb />
			to identify (Welles) would be particularly damaging in the
			<lb />
			internet search context. Searchers would have a much more
			<lb />
			difficult time locating the relevant websites if they could do so
			<lb />
			only by correctly guessing the long phrases necessary to
			<lb />
			substitute for trademarks&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			New Kids on Block v. News America Publishing Inc, 971 F.2d
			<lb />
			302 (9 th Circuit) wherein the court has held that such a
			<lb />
			normative use of a mark-where the only word reasonably
			<lb />
			available to describe a particular thing is pressed into service-
			<lb />
			lies outside the strictures.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			Mr. Kaul thus contended that the defendants cannot be held
			<lb />
			guilty of meta tagging as the plaintiff products under the mark
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG can be described in the manner done by the defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			By making the aforesaid submission, Mr. Kaul concluded
			<lb />
			his arguments by submitting that the interim order passed on
			<lb />
			03.06.2011 is liable to be vacated as there is no prima facie case in
			<lb />
			view of the clear legal position relating to exhaustion of rights, and
			<lb />
			balance of convenience is also in favour of the defendants as the
			<lb />
			defendant should be permitted what is legally permissible and the
			<lb />
			irreparable damage will result to the defendants for the very same
			<lb />
			reason.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			I have gone through the plaint, written statement, replication
			<lb />
			and documents filed by the parties and have also given careful
			<lb />
			consideration to the submissions made at the bar as enlisted above.
			<lb />
			Before dealing with the submissions of the parties, I deem it
			<lb />
			appropriate to first discuss the law on the subject.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			IMPORTATION OF GOODS UNDER THE MARK AS AN
			<lb />
			INFRINGEMENT OF THE TRADE MARK
			<lb />
			The first question which according to me falls for
			<lb />
			consideration is as to whether the provisions of Trade Mark Act, 1999
			<lb />
			provides for the import of goods as an infringement and if so whether it
			<lb />
			can be said to include genuine products emanating from the proprietor
			<lb />
			from international market although it may not be with the consent of the
			<lb />
			proprietor. Therefore, I shall first examine the aspect of infringement.
			<lb />
			For the sake of convenience, the provisions of the trade
			<lb />
			marks act are reproduced hereinafter:
			<lb />
			Section 29 (1) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999 provides for
			<lb />
			registered trademark, which reads as under:-
			<lb />
			Section 29(1) : &quot;A registered trade mark is infringed by a person
			<lb />
			who, not being a registered proprietor or a person using by way
			<lb />
			of permitted use, uses in the course of trade, a mark which is
			<lb />
			identical with, or deceptively similar to, the trade mark in
			<lb />
			relation to goods or services in respect of which the trade mark is
			<lb />
			registered and in such manner as to render the use of the mark
			<lb />
			likely to be taken as being used as a trade mark.&quot;
			<lb />
			…………
			<lb />
			Section 29(6) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999 reads as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;for the purposes of this section, a person uses a registered mark,
			<lb />
			if, in particular, he -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) affixes it to goods or the packaging thereof;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) offers or exposes goods for sale, puts them on the market,
			<lb />
			or stocks them for those purposes under the registered
			<lb />
			trade mark, or offers or supplies services under the
			<lb />
			registered trade mark;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) imports or exports goods under the mark; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d) uses the registered trade mark on business papers or in
			<lb />
			advertising.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			19.
			<lb />
			On conjoint reading of Section 29(1) along with Section
			<lb />
			29(6), it becomes amply clear that for the purposes of Section 29, a
			<lb />
			person uses a registered trade mark if in particular, he imports or
			<lb />
			exports the goods under the mark which means that the act of
			<lb />
			importing or exporting goods under the mark is treated to be as use of a
			<lb />
			registered trademark for the purposes of Section 29, and therefore,
			<lb />
			importation is in clear and explicit terms of Section 29(6)(c) read with
			<lb />
			Section 29(1) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999, is an infringement of the
			<lb />
			trademark.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			20.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, Section 29(1) has following essential
			<lb />
			ingredients:-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			a) a registered trademark is infringed by a person;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			b) who not being a registered proprietor;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			c) or, a person by way of permitted use;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			d) Uses in the course of a trade;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			e) A mark which is identical or deceptively similar to;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			f) A trademark in relation to goods or services in respect of which
			<lb />
			the trademark is registered;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			g) In such a manner to render use of trademark likely to be used as
			<lb />
			a trademark.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			These are some essential ingredients for attracting
			<lb />
			infringement u/s 29(1). In this perspective, one can easily gauge the
			<lb />
			legal position which is that if a person who neither being a registered
			<lb />
			proprietor nor a person using by way of permitted use, uses in the
			<lb />
			course of trade a mark which is identical to the trademark in relation to
			<lb />
			the goods in respect of which the mark is registered in such a manner
			<lb />
			so as to render, but use of the mark likely to be taken being use of a
			<lb />
			trademark, then the said act is an infringement u/s 29(1).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			Applying the act of importation as use as mentioned in
			<lb />
			Section 29(6) to Section 29(1), it can be discerned that any importer
			<lb />
			who is not a registered proprietor or permissive right holder, if imports
			<lb />
			the goods under the mark which is identical or similar to a trademark in
			<lb />
			relation to the goods in respect of which the trademark is registered so
			<lb />
			as to render the use of the mark likely to be taken as a trademark, then
			<lb />
			the said act of importation amounts to infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			A logical corollary which follows from the plain wordings
			<lb />
			of Section 29 (1) and Section 29 (6) is that either the importer must be
			<lb />
			permitted or permissive right holder from the proprietor or must be a
			<lb />
			registered proprietor so as not fall within the purview of Section 29 as
			<lb />
			otherwise the rigors of Section 29(1) shall apply strictly.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24.
			<lb />
			It is well settled law that when the plain reading of section
			<lb />
			itself is clear, then no departure is permissible from the plain rule of
			<lb />
			construction.( Kindly see judgment passed in This has been followed in
			<lb />
			Association for Development vs. Union of India &amp; Others, 2010
			<lb />
			(115) DRJ 277 wherein this court approved the literal rule and
			<lb />
			observed that -it is not the duty of the court to enlarge the scope of
			<lb />
			the legislation when the language of the provision is plain and
			<lb />
			unambiguous).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25.
			<lb />
			In the present case, once Section 29(1) and Section 29(6)
			<lb />
			are read conjointly, it becomes unambiguous in view of explicit terms
			<lb />
			of 29(6) (which clearly equates the export or import with the use for the
			<lb />
			purposes of entire Section 29), that the act of importation amounts to
			<lb />
			the infringement, if the said importer is not registered proprietor or
			<lb />
			permissive right holder.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26.
			<lb />
			Thus, in law it cannot be said that there is an unfettered
			<lb />
			right of importation of goods under the mark. On the other hand, in the
			<lb />
			normal course, the act of importation without the consent of the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor amounts to an infringement. This also negates the
			<lb />
			concept of free flow of goods in the world market as the Section 29
			<lb />
			clearly put barriers on importation and had there been such a legislative
			<lb />
			intent to remove barriers on imports or exports and to promote free
			<lb />
			commerce under the goods of identical trade marks, Section 29 (6)
			<lb />
			ought not to have provided for the acts of importation or exportation as
			<lb />
			a use of the mark for the purposes of Section 29.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27.
			<lb />
			Plainly and clearly, there is no such unfettered right of
			<lb />
			importing and there are restrictions imposed on the rights of
			<lb />
			importation by specifically prescribing it as an infringement and also
			<lb />
			other incidental remedies under the trade marks Act and Custom laws.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28.
			<lb />
			It is however still to be looked into as to whether the said
			<lb />
			fettered right of importation can subsume to the genuine goods as it can
			<lb />
			be argued that it is doubtful as to how the importation of genuine goods
			<lb />
			can be termed as infringement of the owners registered trademark.
			<lb />
			This can be seen again if one reads Section 29(1) plainly, it does not
			<lb />
			distinguish between a person either importing a genuine goods or non
			<lb />
			genuine goods for the purposes of attracting the provisions of
			<lb />
			infringement which is a statutory indicator to the effect that there is no
			<lb />
			such distinction.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, there is no legislative provision which carves
			<lb />
			out any such exception u/s 29 for the purposes of genuine or non
			<lb />
			genuine goods.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			29.
			<lb />
			There is no proviso to Section 29 (6) (c) which excludes the
			<lb />
			genuine products from the acts of import or exports nor there is any
			<lb />
			explanation appended to Section 29 (6) (c) clarifying the aspect of
			<lb />
			importing or exporting .This at least holds good plainly by reading of
			<lb />
			Section 29.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30.
			<lb />
			In the absence of the any such legislative provision or
			<lb />
			exception under the principle provision of infringement under Section
			<lb />
			29, it cannot be assumed on a priori basis that there is any such
			<lb />
			exception exists under the law exempting importation of genuine goods
			<lb />
			from rigors of infringement when the said act amounts to use of
			<lb />
			identical mark on the identical goods and when the importer is not
			<lb />
			registered proprietor or permissive user uses the same in the course of
			<lb />
			the trade clearly falls within Section 29 (1). (On a separate note I shall
			<lb />
			examine Section 30 separately under the next head which according to
			<lb />
			me operates differently as the discussion at present is confined to
			<lb />
			Section 29 only.)
			<lb />
			This view also gains strength in view of the well settled
			<lb />
			principles of law that the courts are not add words or delete words from
			<lb />
			the statute so as to enlarge or limit the scope of the sections. The courts
			<lb />
			are rather to interpret the law as it exists in the statute book on the plain
			<lb />
			reading and not to put to qualifications which are not legislatively
			<lb />
			engrafted.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31.
			<lb />
			The only line of demarcation which seems to be logical in
			<lb />
			the absence of legislative exception is that if the said importer is either
			<lb />
			a registered proprietor and in that case he will be protected by
			<lb />
			applicability of Section 28(3) or 30(2)(e) wherein the suit for
			<lb />
			infringement against the registered proprietor is not maintainable or if
			<lb />
			he is permissive right holder which will attract the proprietor&quot;s consent
			<lb />
			in the form of permissive right to the said importation, the said importer
			<lb />
			can escape the liability of infringement and not otherwise.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32.
			<lb />
			Further, the permissive right is a right which must emanate
			<lb />
			from the registered proprietor by way of permitted use in the manner
			<lb />
			prescribed under the Act and cannot be said to be an implied one on the
			<lb />
			basis of proprietor&quot;s throwing the goods in the market. This kind of
			<lb />
			assumption is only feasible if there is a legislative provision to this
			<lb />
			effect speaking clearly about the same but I find in the later part of the
			<lb />
			discussion that the import of Section 30 (3) on the plain reading as well
			<lb />
			as contextual reading does not inform the same. Thus, in the absence of
			<lb />
			any deeming fiction or presumption, the permissive right mentioned
			<lb />
			under Section 29 cannot be equated with the implied consent of the
			<lb />
			proprietor by way of registered proprietor&quot;s putting the goods in any
			<lb />
			market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			33.
			<lb />
			In view of the above discussion, it can be said that in the
			<lb />
			absence of any other line of demarcation or difference between genuine
			<lb />
			or non genuine goods for all practical purposes, the rigors of law u/s 29
			<lb />
			(1) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999 for the purposes of infringement will
			<lb />
			be applicable to the fullest extent except what has been provided as an
			<lb />
			exceptions within the section itself which is use either being a
			<lb />
			registered proprietor or a permissive right holder. Therefore, a fortiori
			<lb />
			it follows that act of importation of the goods bearing the mark of the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor without the importer being a registered proprietor
			<lb />
			or permissive right holder is statutorily engrafted infringement u/s 29 of
			<lb />
			the Trade Marks Act, 1999.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34.
			<lb />
			Thus, It cannot be contended that there is a free market
			<lb />
			economy worldwide which permits any such inflow of goods by way of
			<lb />
			importation without any barriers and there is no infringement if the
			<lb />
			goods bearing the mark are imported in the country especially in India
			<lb />
			when the said Section 29(1) read with Section 29(6) (c) explicitly and
			<lb />
			in clear terms provide so.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35.
			<lb />
			Thus, the fettered right of imports or exports amounting to
			<lb />
			infringement further gets restricted in the sense that in whatever manner
			<lb />
			the said imports under the mark (be the genuine or counterfeit) are
			<lb />
			carried out, the said acts if not done by the registered proprietor or the
			<lb />
			permissive right holder straightaway amounts to infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36.
			<lb />
			The controversy as to whether import of genuine products
			<lb />
			an infringement or not, is sought to be resolved by answering the same
			<lb />
			in affirmative by the authority on trademark law, namely, Modern Law
			<lb />
			on Trade Marks, 3 rd Edition (2008) by Morcom, Roughton &amp; Malynicz
			<lb />
			-LexisNexis, wherein the learned author very minutely observed and
			<lb />
			finds that even the imports of genuine product is an infringement in
			<lb />
			context of UK law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;16.3 -The legal analysis arises as follows. Trade Marks are
			<lb />
			territorial. A United Kingdom trade mark covers the United
			<lb />
			Kingdom. A Community trade mark covers the Community.
			<lb />
			Both the Trade Marks Directive and Community Trade Mark
			<lb />
			Regulation (CTMR) cite the act of importation as an example of
			<lb />
			an infringing act. Because a parallel import of a genuine
			<lb />
			product amounts to the use of an identical mark on identical
			<lb />
			goods, the importation of such goods is treated in some
			<lb />
			senses
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			very
			<lb />
			straightforward
			<lb />
			infringement…..&quot;[Emphasis Supplied]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			37.
			<lb />
			I fully endorse the view expressed by the learned author and
			<lb />
			this observation of the learned author is only by reading that it amounts
			<lb />
			to use of the identical mark on identical goods. There is no reason why
			<lb />
			the above analysis cannot hold good in the Indian context when Section
			<lb />
			29 (1) provides for the said infringement and Section 29 (6) further
			<lb />
			makes the same position again clear in unequivocal terms.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the import of genuine goods is an equal
			<lb />
			infringement as that of the counterfeit goods in the absence of the any
			<lb />
			legislative measure distinguishing the two and also by virtue of plain
			<lb />
			reading of Section 29 and more so when the authorities on trade mark
			<lb />
			law also provides for the same view. This answers the residual
			<lb />
			proposition framed above which is that the import of even genuine
			<lb />
			products can attract the infringement under Section 29.
			<lb />
			At this stage, I would like to also clarify that for all practical
			<lb />
			reasons the provision of Section 29 (1) as well as the discussion done
			<lb />
			above cannot be misconstrued to mean that there are barriers to imports
			<lb />
			of the goods under the trade mark by anyone for any purpose. It is only
			<lb />
			the cases which shall strictly fall within the provisions of Section 29
			<lb />
			wherein there is an import of goods under the mark by the person
			<lb />
			which has been further put to use &quot;in the course of trade&quot; as mentioned
			<lb />
			under Section 29 shall be called as an infringement and not all other
			<lb />
			cases.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39.
			<lb />
			After analyzing the import of Section 29 which provides for
			<lb />
			infringement of trade marks, it is for me to now discuss the nature and
			<lb />
			the scope of Section 30 of the Trade Marks Act more particularly
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			NATURE AND SCOPE OF SECTION 30(3) OF THE
			<lb />
			TRADEMARKS ACT, 1999: IT ACTS AS A MATTER OF
			<lb />
			DEFENCE OR EXCEPTION
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			40.
			<lb />
			Section 30(3) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999 acts as an
			<lb />
			exception to the infringement of registered trade marks as the head note
			<lb />
			of Section 30 itself speaks for itself which says limits on the effects of
			<lb />
			registered trademark and the wordings of Section 30 (3) in particular
			<lb />
			also states that the selling of goods in the market or otherwise
			<lb />
			dealing in those goods is not an infringement of trademark.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41.
			<lb />
			All these wordings mentioned in the Section 30 (3) coupled
			<lb />
			with its head note make it clear that the present section acts as an
			<lb />
			exception to the rule of infringement which presupposes that absenting
			<lb />
			the said provision which is Section 30, the acts mentioned therein shall
			<lb />
			be an infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			42.
			<lb />
			For the purpose of convenience, the Section concerning the
			<lb />
			present case is reproduced herein :
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) Where the goods bearing a registered trade mark
			<lb />
			are lawfully acquired by a person, the sale of the goods in the
			<lb />
			market or otherwise dealing in those goods by that person or by
			<lb />
			a person claiming under or through him is not infringement of a
			<lb />
			trade by reason only of :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a) the registered trade mark having been assigned by the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor to some other person, after the
			<lb />
			acquisition of those goods; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) the goods having been put on the market under the
			<lb />
			registered trade mark by the proprietor or with his
			<lb />
			consent.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			43.
			<lb />
			The said Section 30 (3) is thus an exception to the rule of
			<lb />
			infringement as provided Section 29. The said exception operates in the
			<lb />
			nature of defence to an infringement wherein the person using the mark
			<lb />
			in a particular form or dealing otherwise in the goods under the mark
			<lb />
			can plead that the said goods are lawfully acquired from the market
			<lb />
			wherein the proprietor has also put the goods in the market or the
			<lb />
			proprietor has given consent to the effect of such dealings or usage. It
			<lb />
			is however another thing which I shall examine later that in what field
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) operates and whether it can be said to include within its
			<lb />
			purview the imports.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			44.
			<lb />
			At this stage, for understanding sake about the nature and
			<lb />
			scope of the provision, it is proper to state that is one of the exceptions
			<lb />
			to the infringements envisaged under Section 30 and more particularly
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) operates as an defence to an infringement. This
			<lb />
			discussion becomes necessary in order to understand the real scope of
			<lb />
			the provisions as number of submissions have been made at the bar that
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) provides some right to import genuine goods to the
			<lb />
			person acquiring the goods. Thus, it became incumbent and inevitable
			<lb />
			to examine whether the said Section 30 (3) is a right conferring section
			<lb />
			or merely acts a defence to the infringement. In this backdrop, I find
			<lb />
			that the rights of the proprietor of the registered trade mark are
			<lb />
			provided under Section 29 and other section relating to other remedies.
			<lb />
			Section 30 or for that matter Section 30 (3) just operates an exception
			<lb />
			by putting limits to the rights conferred upon the registered proprietor
			<lb />
			and cannot be equated the one giving some additional right to some
			<lb />
			other person to import the genuine goods from the international market.
			<lb />
			Of course, this cannot be intent and purpose of legislating any such
			<lb />
			limitation to the general rule of infringement of trade marks. The
			<lb />
			purpose is rather different which is to exclude the person from the
			<lb />
			purview of infringement if the conditions for applicability of Section 30
			<lb />
			(3) are satisfied. The limitation or exception will thus operate to that
			<lb />
			extent only for which it is enacted carving out an exception to the
			<lb />
			infringement and not beyond the same by giving any additional right to
			<lb />
			any such person incidentally.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45.
			<lb />
			The consent of the proprietor operates as a defense to the
			<lb />
			infringement of the trademark is also observed in the authority namely
			<lb />
			Modern Law on Trade Marks, 3 rd Edition (2008) by Morcom,
			<lb />
			Roughton &amp; Malynicz -LexisNexis, wherein it is said as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;16.4 -It is a complete defense in respect of any infringing
			<lb />
			act, including importation, to show that it has been done with
			<lb />
			the consent of the proprietor. This has led parallel importers
			<lb />
			to argue in the &quot;international exhaustion&quot; cases that the mere fact
			<lb />
			that goods have been put on the market somewhere in the world
			<lb />
			by the proprietor, or with his consent, can be taken to indicate
			<lb />
			that he has implicitly consented to their importation into the area
			<lb />
			of protection of the relevant national or Community trade mark.
			<lb />
			As we shall see below, this argument has essentially been
			<lb />
			rejected at the highest level, thus forcing parallel importers to try
			<lb />
			different arguments, mainly concerning the question of consent,
			<lb />
			some of which have been more successful than others.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			46.
			<lb />
			From the above, it is clear that the provision relating to
			<lb />
			exhaustion or proprietor&quot;s consent is a complete defense to an
			<lb />
			infringement act. However, the same can be seen depending upon the
			<lb />
			language of the legal provision in the form in which it is couched in
			<lb />
			order to discern whether it is national exhaustion or international
			<lb />
			exhaustion and the argument of parallel importers can be accepted or
			<lb />
			rejected depending upon the scheme of the Act and circumstances
			<lb />
			arising in view of the legal provisions existing under the law. At this
			<lb />
			stage, it is only necessary to examine the nature and scope of the
			<lb />
			provision which is the proprietor&quot;s consent is the defence to an
			<lb />
			infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			47.
			<lb />
			After this discussion, it can be safely said that the nature
			<lb />
			and the scope of Section 30 (3) is that it operates as a defence to the
			<lb />
			infringing act and cannot be said to giving any additional right beyond
			<lb />
			the same.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			PLAIN AND CONTEXTUAL INTERPRETATION OF
			<lb />
			SECTION 30 (3) AND 30 (4) OF TRADE MARKS ACT 1999
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			48.
			<lb />
			Now, let me evaluate what is the possible interpretation of
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) and Section 30 (4) of the Act on the basis of the plain
			<lb />
			reading of the enactment.
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) reads as : Where the goods bearing a registered
			<lb />
			trade mark are lawfully acquired by a person, the sale of the
			<lb />
			goods in the market or otherwise dealing in those goods by that
			<lb />
			person or by a person claiming under or through him is not
			<lb />
			infringement of a trade by reason only of-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a) the registered trade mark having been assigned by the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor to some other person, after the
			<lb />
			acquisition of those goods; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) the goods having been put on the market under the
			<lb />
			registered trade mark by the proprietor or with his
			<lb />
			consent.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			49.
			<lb />
			From the bare reading of aforesaid section, it becomes clear
			<lb />
			that Section 30 (3) has following essential ingredients:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Where the goods bearing registered trademark are lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired by a person.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			The sale of goods in the market or otherwise dealing in those
			<lb />
			goods by a person is not an infringement by only reason of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			registered trademark having been assigned by the registered
			<lb />
			proprietor to some other person, after the acquisition of those
			<lb />
			goods or
			<lb />
			d)
			<lb />
			goods having put on the market under the registered
			<lb />
			trademark by the proprietor or with his consent.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			50.
			<lb />
			These are essential ingredients for attracting Section 30(3)
			<lb />
			of the Act, which acts as complete defense to infringement of
			<lb />
			trademark. The opening words of the said section are important, need
			<lb />
			examination and deserve to be noticed, which say &quot; where goods
			<lb />
			bearing a registered trade mark are lawfully acquired by a person …&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			51.
			<lb />
			From the reading of these words in the statute book, it is not
			<lb />
			reflected as to from what source, the said goods bearing registered
			<lb />
			trademark are lawfully acquired by a person which enables the
			<lb />
			importers to argue that the goods purchased from foreign country
			<lb />
			although bears mark identical to registered trademark owned by a
			<lb />
			proprietor in India are lawfully acquired by them and therefore the said
			<lb />
			circulation of goods by those importers in the market should not be
			<lb />
			treated as infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			52.
			<lb />
			The use of the words &quot;where the goods bearing a registered
			<lb />
			trade mark are lawfully acquired by a person&quot; and the possible
			<lb />
			interpretation of Section 30 (3) so as to include import by reading
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) in isolation with sub clause (b) ignoring clause (a) will
			<lb />
			result in anomalous results or what can be termed as absurd results
			<lb />
			under the principles of interpretation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			53.
			<lb />
			It is well settled canon of interpretation that the courts must
			<lb />
			do their endeavors to read the provisions plainly so as to give harmony
			<lb />
			between the two provisions and interpretation which renders any
			<lb />
			provision otiose or redundant must be eschewed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			54.
			<lb />
			In High Court of Gujarat and Anr. v. Gujarat Kishan
			<lb />
			Mazdoor Panchayat and Ors., [2003] 2 SCR 799 , the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			held as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;35. The Court while interpreting the provision of a statute,
			<lb />
			although, is not entitled to rewrite the statute itself, is not
			<lb />
			debarred from &quot;ironing out the creases&quot;. The court should
			<lb />
			always make an attempt to uphold the rules and interpret
			<lb />
			the same in such a manner which would make it workable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36.
		</p>
		<head>
			It is also a well-settled principle of law that an attempt
			<lb />
			should be made to give effect to each and every word
			<lb />
			employed in a statute and such interpretation which would
			<lb />
			render a particular provision redundant or otiose should be
			<lb />
			avoided&quot;
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			55.
			<lb />
			This can be seen if one reads the opening words of the
			<lb />
			section &quot; where the goods bearing registered trade mark are lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired by a person&quot; with the sub clause (a) which is that the
			<lb />
			proprietor cannot oppose the further dealings of the said goods only by
			<lb />
			reason of the registered trade mark having been assigned by the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor to some other person, after the acquisition of those
			<lb />
			goods.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			56.
			<lb />
			The wordings in sub clause (a) &quot;the registered trademark
			<lb />
			has been assigned by the registered proprietor to another person after
			<lb />
			acquisition of the said goods&quot; controls the language of the opening
			<lb />
			words &quot; where the goods under the registered trade mark are lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired by the person&quot;. Reading of same along with the opening
			<lb />
			words makes it clear said lawful acquisition presupposes the existence
			<lb />
			of three persons, a person acquiring the goods, a person selling the
			<lb />
			goods which is the registered proprietor and third person to which the
			<lb />
			trademark has been assigned at the same place.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			57.
			<lb />
			Thus, the said acquisition for the purposes of the sub clause
			<lb />
			(a) must arise within the same market wherein there are three persons
			<lb />
			present, person acquiring the goods, registered proprietor and the
			<lb />
			assignee of the trade mark. This the reason why the said section 30(3)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(a) also says that the registered trademark having been assigned after
			<lb />
			the acquisition of those goods which means that the acquisition must
			<lb />
			emanate from the registered proprietor where the registered proprietor
			<lb />
			has the knowledge about the said acquisition and he assigns the
			<lb />
			trademark after the said acquisition.
			<lb />
			A clear and workable example of the said proposition
			<lb />
			mentioned in clause (a) would be that proprietor after selling the goods
			<lb />
			to the market or to the distribution channels, cannot turn around either
			<lb />
			by himself or his assignee in title of the trade mark within the same
			<lb />
			market to say that now the dealings in goods which he has parted with
			<lb />
			to the person or to the distribution channel, cannot be allowed because
			<lb />
			the trademark has been assigned by him to some other person which is
			<lb />
			a simple and precise meaning of the clause (a).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			58.
			<lb />
			But, this may not hold good if one adopts the interpretation
			<lb />
			of opening words to subsume imports in an international perspective.
			<lb />
			The said interpretation of the opening words &quot; where the goods under
			<lb />
			the registered trade mark…..&quot; if given wider interpretation to include
			<lb />
			imports will lead to absurd results and will render clause (a) otiose.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			59.
			<lb />
			This can be seen by looking at the instance by applying
			<lb />
			opening words to include imports. For instance, if the SAMSUNG
			<lb />
			good is taken from Hong Kong market and brought into the Indian
			<lb />
			market by way of import and however in the meanwhile during the
			<lb />
			course of acquisition from Hong Kong Market, the Indian entity of
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG sells the brand name SONY or to some other company for
			<lb />
			Indian Territory. Now, for applicability of clause (a), the registered
			<lb />
			proprietor must assign the mark to some other person after the
			<lb />
			acquisition of the goods and the said criterion is not met at all. This is
			<lb />
			due to the reason as to how the registered proprietor will come to know
			<lb />
			as to where and which part of the world such acquisition of the goods
			<lb />
			has taken place and if he incidentally assigns the mark to some third
			<lb />
			party, how the assignee will enforce his rights and how the person
			<lb />
			acquiring the good can be given liberty to invoke the defence at the
			<lb />
			places where not even registered proprietor nor assignee is aware of
			<lb />
			such transaction of acquisition at all. Further, the registered proprietor
			<lb />
			shall always remain in dark as to where can he or his assignee can
			<lb />
			oppose the market dealings of which products in case the said provision
			<lb />
			is allowed to be given such a wider import.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			60.
			<lb />
			This anomalous situation will create worldwide havoc as the
			<lb />
			proprietor cannot be said to be aware about whatever acquisition of his
			<lb />
			goods occurred worldwide in any market and the proprietor on that
			<lb />
			count cannot control the market at all and even if he assigns the
			<lb />
			trademark for one particular country, the assignee cannot control the
			<lb />
			inflow of goods even when both are not privy to such acquisition
			<lb />
			anywhere from the world. In short, this interpretation of opening words
			<lb />
			leads to absurd results and makes sub clause (a) redundant or
			<lb />
			unworkable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			61.
			<lb />
			This cannot be the import of the section and it cannot be
			<lb />
			that Indian Section 30 (3) (a) is so widely couched that it can give a
			<lb />
			licence for worldwide selling of the goods on both the grounds
			<lb />
			mentioned in Section 30(3) of the Act. Therefore, if one applies the
			<lb />
			interpretation where the goods are lawfully acquired by a person in a
			<lb />
			broader perspective then the clause (a) would become redundant or
			<lb />
			otiose. Further, the wider import of the opening words further leads to
			<lb />
			anomalous results in its applicability and the working and operation of
			<lb />
			clause (a) becomes questionable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			62.
			<lb />
			However, if one reads Section 30 (3) plainly and
			<lb />
			contextually, then it is possible to give the correct and precise meaning
			<lb />
			to the section and also it does not lead to any absurd results or renders
			<lb />
			any provision otiose. Rather, the contextual reading of the section in the
			<lb />
			present case makes the provisions workable in their respective fields
			<lb />
			and sets harmony between the provisions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			63.
			<lb />
			It is well settled principle of law of contextual interpretation
			<lb />
			that a general words may sometime receive a limited interpretation by
			<lb />
			reason of its context in respect of which it is used. The terms used in
			<lb />
			section may have a general meaning in a general sense, but can be
			<lb />
			controlled by the company they keep with the later part of the words in
			<lb />
			the section, and therefore, it becomes relevant to analyze in the context
			<lb />
			in which the said wordings/ terms are used so that the entire provision
			<lb />
			may become workable/operative and should also not lead to conflict
			<lb />
			between other provisions of the Act or making the other provisions
			<lb />
			otiose.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			64.
			<lb />
			It has been held in Bentley v. Rotherham (1876) 4 Ch D
			<lb />
			588 p. 592 (Jessel, MR) &quot;the rule is of general application as even
			<lb />
			plainest terms may be controlled by the context&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			65.
			<lb />
			Likewise, in the case of RBI v. Peerless General Finance
			<lb />
			and Investment Co. Ltd., (1987) 1 SCC 424, the Apex court has
			<lb />
			elucidated the rule of contextual interpretation by observing as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;Interpretation must depend on the text and the context.
			<lb />
			They are the bases of interpretation. One may well say if the
			<lb />
			text is the texture, context is what gives the colour. Neither
			<lb />
			can be ignored. Both are important. That interpretation is
			<lb />
			best which makes the textual interpretation match the
			<lb />
			contextual. A statute is best interpreted when the object and
			<lb />
			purpose of its enactment is known. With this knowledge, the
			<lb />
			statute must be read, first as a whole and then section by section,
			<lb />
			clause by clause, phrase by phrase and word by word. If a statute
			<lb />
			is looked at, in the context of its enactment, with the glasses of
			<lb />
			the statute maker, provided by such context its scheme, the
			<lb />
			sections, clauses, phrases and words may take colour and appear
			<lb />
			different than when the statute is looked at without the glasses
			<lb />
			provided by the context. With these glasses the court must
			<lb />
			look at the Act as a whole and discover what each section,
			<lb />
			each clause, each phrase and each word is meant and
			<lb />
			designed to say as to fit into the scheme of the entire Act. No
			<lb />
			part of a statute and no word of a statute can be construed in
			<lb />
			isolation. Statutes have to be construed so that every word
			<lb />
			has a place and everything is in its place.&quot;(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			66.
			<lb />
			While going through the above mentioned authorities and
			<lb />
			illuminating observations of Supreme Court in relation to contextual
			<lb />
			interpretation which has been followed consistently by Supreme Court
			<lb />
			as well as High Courts, it becomes amply clear that the rule of
			<lb />
			contextual interpretation is well recognized and in the case where there
			<lb />
			is an ambiguity where the terms are amenable for two meanings; one is
			<lb />
			wider and one is narrower, then the Court must give effect to the words
			<lb />
			by adopting recourse to the plain rule of construction and also see the
			<lb />
			context in which they are used.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			67.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the present Section 30 (3) and 30(4) of Trade
			<lb />
			Marks Act, 1999 are to be given interpretation of the words which are
			<lb />
			plainly existing in the Statute which if read in isolation without
			<lb />
			examining the context may in argumentation leave a room of doubt that
			<lb />
			they may have some wider meaning but if they are read with the glasses
			<lb />
			of the context in which they are used it becomes crystal-clear that they
			<lb />
			cannot have any other meaning at all in the context in which they are
			<lb />
			used in the Statute Book.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			68.
			<lb />
			Let me now evaluate the wordings of Section 30 (3) and
			<lb />
			Section 30 (4) with the glasses of the context in which they are used so
			<lb />
			as to discern the true colour of the enactments. The same can be seen in
			<lb />
			my analysis done below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			The import of opening words &quot;where the goods bearing
			<lb />
			registered trademark are lawfully acquired by a person&quot; is to be
			<lb />
			seen in the context in which they are used and further reading of
			<lb />
			the said section along with other ingredients of the section would
			<lb />
			make it clear that when the sub clause (a) speaks &quot;the registered
			<lb />
			trade mark having been assigned by the registered proprietor to
			<lb />
			some other person&quot;, then the same should emanate from the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor within the same market or a person lawfully
			<lb />
			represents to be proprietor within the market and not outside the
			<lb />
			same. This is due to the reason that the section uses the wordings
			<lb />
			in sub clause (a) that the registered trade mark having been
			<lb />
			assigned by the registered proprietor to some other person
			<lb />
			after the acquisition of those goods. This presupposes that the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor at the time of the assignment of the
			<lb />
			registered trade mark to some other person is aware of the lawful
			<lb />
			acquisition of the goods by a person. Resultantly, all of the
			<lb />
			persons must coexist within the same market and it cannot be
			<lb />
			said that the lawful acquisition takes place in international
			<lb />
			market and assignment of the registered trade mark takes place
			<lb />
			in some other market and thus the said provision may become
			<lb />
			inoperative or otiose and leads to absurd results.
			<lb />
			All this collectively and contextually means that if the goods
			<lb />
			are once acquired by a person through a registered proprietor
			<lb />
			within the same market or may be as a distributor of the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor within the same market, then the registered
			<lb />
			proprietor or his assignee cannot turn around and state that is an
			<lb />
			infringement of his trademark solely on the count that there is
			<lb />
			change of ownership by way of an assignment between the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor and some other person and seek prohibition
			<lb />
			on the dealings of the goods.
			<lb />
			The said interpretation makes it more meaningful and
			<lb />
			Section 30(3)(a) operates to the fullest extent as against in sharp
			<lb />
			contradistinction if the opening words are given wider
			<lb />
			interpretation to subsume that a person acquiring the goods from
			<lb />
			a foreign market or importing goods, then it becomes highly
			<lb />
			questionable and doubtful as to how Section 30(3)(a) stands in
			<lb />
			favour of the person acquiring goods from foreign market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			If the interpretation of the wordings &quot;where the goods bearing a
			<lb />
			registered trade mark are lawfully acquired by a person&quot; is
			<lb />
			controlled by the context for the purposes of applicability of
			<lb />
			clause (a) then it can be no different for the purposes of
			<lb />
			applicability of clause (b) as well, because the wordings are
			<lb />
			same for both the grounds and rather they are emerging from the
			<lb />
			same provision. Thus, different import cannot be given for the
			<lb />
			applicability of respective two grounds clause (a) and clause (b).
			<lb />
			This is another reason which is compelling to give limited and
			<lb />
			contextual interpretation of the opening words for the purposes
			<lb />
			of clause (b) as well.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			Thirdly, the opening words &quot;where the goods bearing a
			<lb />
			registered trade mark are lawfully acquired by a person&quot; are
			<lb />
			itself very clear by the mere reading of the same and implicit in
			<lb />
			the same is that the said acquisition is within the domestic
			<lb />
			market. This is due to the reason that the words say &quot;where the
			<lb />
			goods bearing a registered trade mark are lawfully acquired by
			<lb />
			a person&quot; . If the trademark is registered in one country, then
			<lb />
			the goods bearing the said registered trademark can be lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired from that country only. It cannot be the case that the
			<lb />
			goods under the registered trademark can be acquired from
			<lb />
			another country as otherwise it would be an infringement u/s 29
			<lb />
			(1) read with 29(6) of the Act which says import of goods under
			<lb />
			the identical mark amounts to use and thereby infringement.
			<lb />
			Thus, the plain reading of opening words itself are clear and
			<lb />
			unambiguous that the goods which are acquired bearing the
			<lb />
			registered trade mark and further qualification of &quot;lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired&quot; makes them unequivocal and clear that the said
			<lb />
			acquisition has to be originated from the domestic market itself
			<lb />
			where the trademark is registered and not from elsewhere.
			<lb />
			Thus, the interpretation of widest amplitude cannot be given
			<lb />
			to the opening words as otherwise it will lead to direct conflict
			<lb />
			between the opening words of Section 30(3) and that of Section
			<lb />
			29(6) (c) where the import of goods under the mark is an
			<lb />
			infringement and if anyone is permitted to acquire the goods
			<lb />
			anywhere from the world under the registered trademark, then
			<lb />
			Section 29(6) (c) and its applicability shall stand nugatory.
			<lb />
			It can be argued at this stage that the said Section 30 (3) is
			<lb />
			itself the exception and thus the goods bearing the registered
			<lb />
			trade mark and its lawful acquisition cannot be said to be
			<lb />
			infringement under Section 29 (6). There is inherent fallacy in
			<lb />
			the said argument as the Section 30 (3) permits as an exception
			<lb />
			only those goods which bears registered trade mark which are
			<lb />
			acquired lawfully. The word lawfully will also include operation
			<lb />
			of trade mark law for the time being in force. In absence of any
			<lb />
			exception under Section 29 or before beginning of Section 30 (3)
			<lb />
			excluding the imports under the identical mark as an
			<lb />
			infringement, it cannot be assumed that the wording lawful
			<lb />
			acquisition will exclude the rigors of Section 29 (1) read with
			<lb />
			Section 29 (6) and thus the said argument fails being
			<lb />
			fundamentally wrong.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			The opening words &quot;where the goods bearing a registered trade
			<lb />
			mark are lawfully acquired by a person&quot; are merely if at all silent
			<lb />
			about the lawful acquisition although it becomes clear if one
			<lb />
			reads the same plainly in view of point No. (c) above, must bear
			<lb />
			the registered trademark and therefore originate from the
			<lb />
			domestic market. At the best, it can be said that they are silent
			<lb />
			about the lawful acquisition.
			<lb />
			The said words do not say that the said lawful acquisition
			<lb />
			can be from anywhere or from any place and therefore it cannot
			<lb />
			be read into the express provisions of the statute to modify the
			<lb />
			words where the goods bearing the registered trademark are
			<lb />
			lawfully acquired by a person from any place as the
			<lb />
			interpretation which has been canvassed to use this terminology
			<lb />
			in the manner to give the same effect where it may subsume
			<lb />
			&quot;import&quot; would lead to adding the words from any place in the
			<lb />
			Statute when in fact none exists.
			<lb />
			It is well settled that the Courts are not to add the words in
			<lb />
			the Statute or omit in the Statute or enlarge of limit the scope of
			<lb />
			the wordings but they are to interpret the law as it stands.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, it would be lawful to confine the wordings of
			<lb />
			the section as where they stand in the Statute Book that adding
			<lb />
			any words may lead to enlargement the scope of the section.
			<lb />
			If one sees from that standpoint that the goods bearing the
			<lb />
			registered trademark are lawfully acquired makes it amply clear
			<lb />
			that they are originated from the same market or Indian market
			<lb />
			where the trademark is registered, rather than from &quot;any place&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			The wordings &quot;where the goods bearing a registered trade mark
			<lb />
			are lawfully acquired by a person&quot; also needs consideration as it
			<lb />
			has been discerned above that import of the goods under the
			<lb />
			mark is an infringement u/s 29(6) (c) of the Act. Therefore, it is
			<lb />
			doubtful as to how the &quot;import&quot; can be said to be lawful
			<lb />
			acquisition as the said import itself will contravene the
			<lb />
			provisions of Trade Mark Act only, which is Section 29(6) (c).
			<lb />
			Hence, it cannot be said that the said import of the goods is
			<lb />
			lawfully acquisition till the time Section 29(6) (c) stands in the
			<lb />
			way. Therefore, it is another compelling factor which militates
			<lb />
			against the possible interpretation of acquisition from any place
			<lb />
			rather than lawfully acquisition.
			<lb />
			The reading of clause (b) also needs to be considered in
			<lb />
			view of the fact that it is the bone of contention that once the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor has put the goods on the market, therefore,
			<lb />
			the market means &quot;any market&quot; or &quot;world market&quot; and the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor is estopped from objecting to the same on
			<lb />
			the counts of infringement.
			<lb />
			Again, there is an inherent fallacy in the said argument as it
			<lb />
			has been seen above that lawful acquisition of goods bearing the
			<lb />
			registered trademark has been from the domestic market as per
			<lb />
			the contextual reading done above. Thereafter, the sale of said
			<lb />
			goods in the market or otherwise dealing in the said goods has to
			<lb />
			be in the same market only and subsequently the registered
			<lb />
			proprietor has put the goods within the same market only and not
			<lb />
			in some other market.
			<lb />
			The simple and precise example of applicability of sub
			<lb />
			clause (b) would be again where the company supposedly
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG has given the goods to the distributor to supply in
			<lb />
			the market which can be said to be lawfully acquired by the
			<lb />
			distributor bearing the registered trade mark or to some other
			<lb />
			person for further selling. The said goods can be sold by him
			<lb />
			freely within the market without objection from the registered
			<lb />
			proprietor even if the registered proprietor has himself launched
			<lb />
			the goods in the market by putting himself the said goods or with
			<lb />
			his consent by someone else which means that by creating a
			<lb />
			competition amongst the persons who have lawfully acquired the
			<lb />
			goods, the proprietor cannot refrain the said lawful acquired
			<lb />
			goods by himself coming into the market either by himself or
			<lb />
			through someone else.
			<lb />
			Now, this may not hold good again in the international
			<lb />
			perspective. This is again due to the reason that lawful
			<lb />
			acquisition has to be originated from the same market/ domestic
			<lb />
			market as stated above in view of contextual reading and
			<lb />
			therefore the sale of goods by such person has to be in the same
			<lb />
			market from where the goods are originated and the reason of
			<lb />
			proprietor not objecting so by putting the goods himself in the
			<lb />
			market also has to be in the same market/ domestic market and
			<lb />
			not otherwise. Thus, the entire Section 30 (3) read with clause
			<lb />
			(b) is speaking about only one market which is Indian market
			<lb />
			and no separate connotation to the word &quot;market&quot; can be given
			<lb />
			within the same section. This is due to the following reasons:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			I.
			<lb />
			Once the lawful acquisition has been made from the
			<lb />
			domestic market then, the said Section 30 (3) when it
			<lb />
			speaks sale of goods or further dealings in the market
			<lb />
			has to be the same market from where the goods are
			<lb />
			acquired and the said section cannot give permission to
			<lb />
			the said acquirer to sell the goods to the worldwide
			<lb />
			market. It is to be remembered that one is concerned with
			<lb />
			Indian Trade Mark act wherein the section contemplates
			<lb />
			that goods bearing registered trademark are purchased by
			<lb />
			a person which according to the interpretation has to be
			<lb />
			from the domestic market then it is incomprehensible to
			<lb />
			assume by purchasing the goods from the Indian market,
			<lb />
			the law of the land is giving permission to sell to the goods
			<lb />
			worldwide which leads to anomalous situation and
			<lb />
			therefore the words &quot;in the market&quot; cannot be
			<lb />
			substituted/supplanted with the words &quot;any market&quot; which
			<lb />
			shows fallacy in the argument of the defendants.
			<lb />
			Thus, once the situation becomes clear about the import of
			<lb />
			the opening words of the section, then the said lawful
			<lb />
			acquisition due to the controlling words registered trademark
			<lb />
			must originate from the domestic market/ national market, and
			<lb />
			the subsequent wordings has to be also given contextual
			<lb />
			reading and the wider import of the same words &quot;in the
			<lb />
			market&quot; cannot be given to include &quot;worldwide market&quot;. Thus,
			<lb />
			it has to be confined to within the same market as otherwise it
			<lb />
			would lead to giving permission to sell anywhere in the world
			<lb />
			by purchasing from India which cannot be the purpose and
			<lb />
			intent of legislature while enacting such exception to
			<lb />
			infringement of Trade Mark in India in the Indian law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			II. The wordings which have been used in sub clause (3) of
			<lb />
			Section 30 are &quot;in the market&quot; and &quot;on the market&quot;, once in
			<lb />
			sub section (3) which is &quot;in the market&quot; and in sub clause (b)
			<lb />
			&quot;on the market&quot;. Now, the argument which is raised is that
			<lb />
			even if the goods are imported from anywhere in the world, the
			<lb />
			said goods can be circulated in any market by the said
			<lb />
			purchaser without any objection from the proprietor once he
			<lb />
			has put the goods in the market on the presupposition that the
			<lb />
			word &quot;market&quot; means &quot;any market&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			I am not inclined to accept this interpretation as it is not
			<lb />
			clearly emerging from the section. This is due to the reason
			<lb />
			which again makes its beginning from the opening words
			<lb />
			which is that the lawful acquisition has to be in the same
			<lb />
			market and thereafter the sale of goods has to be in the same
			<lb />
			market by the purchaser and as seen from the preceding point I
			<lb />
			above. It cannot be that the words &quot;in the market&quot; can be
			<lb />
			given a worldwide effect as otherwise it will give a licence to
			<lb />
			anyone to purchase the goods from Indian market and to sell
			<lb />
			anywhere in the worldwide market. Therefore, the words &quot;in
			<lb />
			the market&quot; in sub section (3) has to be domestic market.
			<lb />
			Now, the only question left for consideration is whether the
			<lb />
			goods having been &quot;put on the market&quot; is to be read in the
			<lb />
			context of some separate market or within the same market
			<lb />
			which is clause (b) and again the words goods having been put
			<lb />
			on the market necessarily and invariably have to be in the
			<lb />
			same market.
			<lb />
			This is due to the reason that the word &quot;market&quot; is not
			<lb />
			qualified by any other word either in clause (3) or sub clause
			<lb />
			(b). It is just mentioned &quot;in the market&quot; and &quot;on the market&quot;.
			<lb />
			Had there been a separate meaning ascribed to the word
			<lb />
			&quot;market&quot; in sub clause (3) and in (b), then there must have
			<lb />
			been a qualification before or after the word &quot;market&quot; in both
			<lb />
			the provisions which is not so present.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, once it is clear that lawful acquisition has to
			<lb />
			be from the domestic market, the permission to sell by the
			<lb />
			purchaser has to be in the domestic market, then how come the
			<lb />
			proprietor just having thrown the goods in international market
			<lb />
			can benefit the lawful purchaser from domestic market to sell
			<lb />
			goods in the domestic market. Therefore, the words &quot;on the
			<lb />
			market&quot; are and have to be relating to the same market. Thus,
			<lb />
			the word or words &quot;in the market&quot; or &quot;on the market&quot; has to
			<lb />
			be read in the context from where the lawful acquisition is
			<lb />
			made which is domestic market and cannot be ascribed any
			<lb />
			other meaning like that of international market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			III. The words used under Section 30 (3) and (b) are &quot;the market&quot;
			<lb />
			and not &quot;any market&quot;. Again reading of the same otherwise
			<lb />
			would lead to adding the words in the statute which is
			<lb />
			impermissible and the market has to be the specific market and
			<lb />
			not any market and has to be given grammatical, ordinary and
			<lb />
			plain meaning, rather than departing from the plain rule by
			<lb />
			giving the rule of any market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			IV. The words &quot;on the market&quot; are not merely used in Section
			<lb />
			30(3) (b) of the Act, but are also used in the similar context in
			<lb />
			Section 29((6) (b) of the Act wherein it contemplates that
			<lb />
			offering, exposing or putting the goods on the market is an
			<lb />
			infringement.
			<lb />
			Now, one has to understand that if the words &quot;on the
			<lb />
			market&quot; as stated in Section 29 (6) (b) are interpreted
			<lb />
			international market, then there cannot be any infringement as
			<lb />
			a trademark law of the registration extends only to the
			<lb />
			territorial bounds of India. Therefore, if anyone exposes the
			<lb />
			goods or put the goods on the market if that is the infringement
			<lb />
			then the said market invariably has to be domestic market and
			<lb />
			if that is so, then how the exception to an infringement u/s
			<lb />
			30(3) when it uses the words &quot;in the market&quot; or &quot;on the
			<lb />
			market&quot; can be given wider import extending it to international
			<lb />
			market when the principal section of infringement uses the
			<lb />
			identical words &quot;on the market&quot; which leads to the conclusion
			<lb />
			it is domestic market upon its contextual reading.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			V.
			<lb />
			Once the words &quot;on the market&quot; are used there both in
			<lb />
			Section 29 and Section 30 of the Act and there is no separate
			<lb />
			definition clause before the initiation of Section 30 for the
			<lb />
			words &quot;on the market&quot;, in the absence of the same, it is futile
			<lb />
			exercise to assume that the &quot;on the market&quot; or &quot;in the market&quot;
			<lb />
			can be given separate connotations for the purposes of
			<lb />
			applicability of Section 29 and 30 differently.
			<lb />
			It is well settled principle of law that when the legislature
			<lb />
			uses the same word in different parts of the same section or a
			<lb />
			Statute, there is a presumption that word is used in the same
			<lb />
			sense throughout. (Kindly see Bhogi Lal Chunni Lal Pandya
			<lb />
			Vs State of Bombay reported as AIR 1959 SC 356, p.357 and
			<lb />
			Raghubans Narayan Singh Vs Uttar Pradesh Government
			<lb />
			reported as AIR 1967 SC 465).
			<lb />
			In Bhogi Lal (supra) Hon&quot;ble Wanchoo J. observed thus:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;Words are generally used in the same sense
			<lb />
			throughout in a Statute unless there is something
			<lb />
			repugnant in the context&quot;
			<lb />
			In the present case if one analysis the words &quot;on the
			<lb />
			market&quot; and &quot;in the market&quot; in the context in which they are
			<lb />
			used, it cannot be said that contextually a departure can be
			<lb />
			made between the section of infringement which defines an act
			<lb />
			of putting the goods on the market as an infringement at one
			<lb />
			place and it cannot be said that same word &quot;on the market&quot;
			<lb />
			when used in Section 30, which is an exception to an
			<lb />
			infringement, can be contextually different to denote it as an
			<lb />
			international market which is so wide than the principal
			<lb />
			provision of infringement.
			<lb />
			Therefore, contextually both the words &quot;on the market&quot; in
			<lb />
			Section 29 and Section 30 are same and likewise the term &quot;in
			<lb />
			the market&quot;. This again leans the interpretation to believe that
			<lb />
			the words &quot;in the market&quot; or &quot;on the market&quot; are concerning
			<lb />
			to the domestic market and not otherwise.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			69.
			<lb />
			For all the above reasons, if one reads Section 30 (3) and its
			<lb />
			sub clauses (a) and (b) contextually, it can be discerned that the
			<lb />
			nowhere it indicates any concept of international exhaustion stemming
			<lb />
			from the said section. Rather, the plain and contextual reading of entire
			<lb />
			section reveals that the said section contemplates a particular situation
			<lb />
			where the goods bearing the registered trade mark are lawfully acquired
			<lb />
			and their consequence thereof which cannot be culminated into
			<lb />
			infringement due to change of ownership or proprietor&quot;s putting himself
			<lb />
			goods in the market. The said section operates within one market where
			<lb />
			the registration of registered trade mark extends. Reading it otherwise
			<lb />
			would be misreading or ignoring the words in the statute like
			<lb />
			&quot;registered trade mark&quot;, &quot;lawful acquisition&quot; and would be rendering
			<lb />
			the words in the statute as dead letters or inoperative.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			70.
			<lb />
			Given the analysis above on the basis of plain and
			<lb />
			contextual reading of Section 30 (3), the matter can also be looked into
			<lb />
			by comparing the similar provision existing under the law of trade
			<lb />
			marks in UK so as to gauge what can be interpretation of the provision
			<lb />
			in that scenario existing in UK.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Comparative Analysis of Indian provisions with that of UK Trade
			<lb />
			Mark Act.
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			71.
			<lb />
			It is, at this stage, relevant to examine the position as it
			<lb />
			exists in the UK Trade Mark law pertaining to the question which falls
			<lb />
			for consideration which is that once the proprietor puts on the goods in
			<lb />
			the market, then he loses the right to object for subsequent sale of
			<lb />
			goods by the said purchaser.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			72.
			<lb />
			For the sake of convenience, relevant provisions relating to
			<lb />
			UK Trademark Act, 1994 are reproduced hereinafter and for the sake
			<lb />
			of comparison, the relevant provisions of Indian Trade Marks Act,
			<lb />
			1999 are also reproduced below:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			UK TRADE MARK ACT, 1994
			<lb />
			Section 9-Rights conferred by registered trade mark -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(1) The proprietor of a registered trade mark has exclusive rights
			<lb />
			in the trade mark which are infringed by use of the trademark in
			<lb />
			the United Kingdom without his consent.
			<lb />
			The acts amount to infringement, if done without the consent of
			<lb />
			the proprietor, are specified in section 10.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) References in this Act to the infringement of a registered
			<lb />
			trade mark are to any such infringement of the rights of the
			<lb />
			proprietor.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(3) The rights of the proprietor have effect from the date of
			<lb />
			registration (which in accordance with section 40(3) is the date
			<lb />
			of filing of the application for registration):
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Provided that -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			a) No infringement proceedings may be begun before the date on
			<lb />
			which the trade mark is in fact registered; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			b) No offence under section 92 (unauthorized use of trade mark,
			<lb />
			&amp; in relation to goods) is committed by anything done before the
			<lb />
			date of publication of the registration.
			<lb />
			Section 10 (4)
			<lb />
			For the purposes of this section a person uses a sign if, in
			<lb />
			particular, he-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			a) affixes it to goods or the packaging thereof;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			b) offers or exposes goods for sale, puts them on the market or
			<lb />
			stocks them for those purposes under the sign, or offers or
			<lb />
			supplies services under the sign;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			c) imports or exports goods under the sign; or
			<lb />
			d) uses the sign on business papers or in advertising.
			<lb />
			Section 12
			<lb />
			Exhaustion of rights conferred by registered trade mark
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(1) A registered trade mark is not infringed by the use of the
			<lb />
			trade mark in relation to goods which have been put on the
			<lb />
			market in the European Economic Area under the trade mark by
			<lb />
			the proprietor or with his consent.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) Sub.-section (1) does not apply where there exist legitimate
			<lb />
			reasons for the proprietor to oppose further dealings in the goods
			<lb />
			(in particular, where the condition of the goods has been changed
			<lb />
			or impaired after they have been put on the market).
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Indian Trade Mark Act, 1999
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			28. Rights conferred by registration -(1) Subject to the other
			<lb />
			provisions of this Act, the registration of a trade mark shall, if
			<lb />
			valid, give to the registered proprietor of the trade mark the
			<lb />
			exclusive right to the user of the trade mark in relation to the
			<lb />
			goods or services in respect of which the trade mark is registered
			<lb />
			and to obtain in respect of infringement of the trade mark in the
			<lb />
			manner provided by this Act.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) The exclusive right to the use of a trade mark given under
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) shall be subject to any conditions and limitations
			<lb />
			to which the registration is subject.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(3) Where two or more persons are registered proprietors of
			<lb />
			trade marks, which are identical with or nearly resemble each
			<lb />
			other, the exclusive right to the use of any of those trade marks
			<lb />
			shall not (except so far as their respective rights are subject to
			<lb />
			any conditions or limitations entered on the register) be deemed
			<lb />
			to have been acquired by any one of those persons as against any
			<lb />
			other of those persons merely by registration of the trade marks
			<lb />
			but each of those persons has otherwise the same rights as
			<lb />
			against other persons (not being registered users using by way of
			<lb />
			permitted use) as he would have if he were the sole registered
			<lb />
			proprietor.
			<lb />
			Section 29(6)(c)-imports or exports goods under the mark; or
			<lb />
			Section 30(3)-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Where the goods bearing a registered trade mark are lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired by a person, the sale of the goods in the market or
			<lb />
			otherwise dealing in those goods by that person or by a person
			<lb />
			claiming under or through him is not infringement of a trade by
			<lb />
			reason only of-
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) the registered trade mark having been assigned by
			<lb />
			registered proprietor to some other person, after the
			<lb />
			acquisition of those goods; or
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) the goods having put on the market under the registered
			<lb />
			trade mark by the proprietor or with his consent.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			73.
			<lb />
			On fair comparison of both the provisions existing in UK
			<lb />
			and Indian law, the following few points are noteworthy and can be
			<lb />
			immediately discerned:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			That the rights conferred on the registered proprietor of trade
			<lb />
			mark in UK is the exclusive right to use the said trademark and
			<lb />
			to prevent infringement in the United Kingdom only.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			The said Trade Mark Act in UK under the Section 12(2) of
			<lb />
			infringement uses identical expression &quot;on the market&quot; just like
			<lb />
			in the Indian Act but when it comes to the question of limitation
			<lb />
			of infringement u/s 12, the wordings of Section are changed and
			<lb />
			the wordings used are &quot;put on the market in the European
			<lb />
			Economic Area&quot;.
			<lb />
			This has been a deliberate/conscious insertion vis-à-vis the
			<lb />
			limitation section/ exception is concerned due to the reason that
			<lb />
			the framers of that section or the law intended to give the wider
			<lb />
			import to the provisions of exhaustion of rights knowingly or
			<lb />
			consciously that if they will confine to the wordings, &quot;on the
			<lb />
			market&quot; then it will only limit the principles of exhaustion in
			<lb />
			United Kingdom only in view of the explicit terms of Section 9
			<lb />
			of the UK Act. Therefore, the framers of UK Act have
			<lb />
			consciously inserted the wordings &quot;in the European economic
			<lb />
			area&quot; in order to confer the wider right so that even if the goods
			<lb />
			are put on the market of European Economic area, the right to
			<lb />
			object for further sale is taken away.
			<lb />
			Although, this I have discerned out of plain reading of the
			<lb />
			section itself which is differently worded with that of Indian Act,
			<lb />
			but this view also finds support from the English authorities
			<lb />
			including treatise on trade mark law namely Modern Law on
			<lb />
			Trade Marks, 3 rd Edition (2008) by Morcom, Roughton &amp;
			<lb />
			Malynicz -LexisNexis wherein the learned author observes that
			<lb />
			the rationale of wordings &quot;European economic area&quot; which have
			<lb />
			been inserted in the Act to give the exhaustion principle a wider
			<lb />
			effect.
			<lb />
			The learned author observes thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;EUROPEAN EXHAUSTION
			<lb />
			Background to the ECJ jurisprudence
			<lb />
			16.6 Under the Trade Marks Act 1938 (TMA 1938), as well as
			<lb />
			the common law, the United Kingdom had developed a doctrine
			<lb />
			of &quot;exhaustion of rights&quot; in cases where a trade mark proprietor
			<lb />
			sought to restrain the importation and sale in t his country of its
			<lb />
			own goods or the goods of an associated company, by means of
			<lb />
			an action for infringement or passing off.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			16.7 As the European Community developed, a doctrine of
			<lb />
			exhaustion of rights also began to take shape under certain
			<lb />
			provisions of the Treaty of Rome that related to free
			<lb />
			movement of goods. After a period in which there was some
			<lb />
			doubt as to how far the ECJ would countenance the
			<lb />
			enforcement of any intellectual property rights to prevent
			<lb />
			imports of goods from one Member State into another, it was
			<lb />
			finally established that trade mark rights would generally be
			<lb />
			enforced in such cases unless the goods in question had been
			<lb />
			placed on the market in a Member State by the proprietor or
			<lb />
			with his consent.
			<lb />
			Other decisions of the ECJ defined
			<lb />
			circumstances, with particular reference to repackaged
			<lb />
			pharmaceutical products, in which a trade mark proprietor might
			<lb />
			object to the imports notwithstanding the fact that the goods had
			<lb />
			been marketed in the Member State of export by him or with his
			<lb />
			consent. Article 7 of the directive made a specific provision for
			<lb />
			exhaustion of trade mark rights within the Community. In
			<lb />
			accordance with the Agreement on the European Economic
			<lb />
			Area (EEA) [The EEA is a slightly wider area than the
			<lb />
			European Union. It was formed because of the wish of three
			<lb />
			countries -Norway, Iceland and Liechtenstein -to participate
			<lb />
			in the internal market, without assuming the full responsibilities
			<lb />
			of EU Membership. The EEA Agreement gives them the right to
			<lb />
			be consulted by the Commission during the formulation of
			<lb />
			Community legislation, but not the right to voice in decision-
			<lb />
			making, which is reserved exclusively for member States…..] of
			<lb />
			2nd may 1992 the doctrine was effectively extended to the
			<lb />
			whole of the EEA by s 12 of the TMA 1994. A similar
			<lb />
			provision can be found in art 13 of the CTMR.&quot;
			<lb />
			Section 12
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Exhaustion of rights conferred by registered trade mark
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(1) A registered trade mark is not infringed by the use of the
			<lb />
			trade mark in relation to goods which have been put on the
			<lb />
			market in the European Economic Area under the trade mark by
			<lb />
			the proprietor or with his consent.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(2) Sub.-section (1) does not apply where there exist legitimate
			<lb />
			reasons for the proprietor to oppose further dealings in the goods
			<lb />
			(in particular, where the condition of the goods has been changed
			<lb />
			or impaired after they have been put on the market).&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			74.
			<lb />
			From the bare reading of aforementioned excerpts quoted
			<lb />
			from Modern Law of Trade Marks, it becomes amply clear that the
			<lb />
			Section 12 as it exists in UK Act has been consciously given a wider
			<lb />
			connotation to the words &quot; on the market&quot; by further adding the words
			<lb />
			in the &quot;European Economic Area&quot; to give them an expansive effect
			<lb />
			beyond the territorial bounds of UK, where the UK registration extends
			<lb />
			so that free market movement can take place within the European
			<lb />
			region/ territories covered in European economic areas. This has been
			<lb />
			indicated by legislative history as mentioned in the excerpts quoted
			<lb />
			above relating to background to framing of Section 12.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			75.
			<lb />
			This insertion is intentionally done to give effect to treaty of
			<lb />
			Rome for free movement of goods as well as EEA agreement wherein
			<lb />
			this was resolved.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			76.
			<lb />
			The above said position also further clarifies the doubt that
			<lb />
			UK law follows the domestic exhaustion of rights. It is not merely
			<lb />
			following any principle of law but rather UK Act has tried to give wider
			<lb />
			effect to the extent permissible under their law and also to give effect to
			<lb />
			the treaties relating to international free movements of goods entered by
			<lb />
			EU countries to extend the said concept of UK market to European
			<lb />
			economic Area.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			77.
			<lb />
			The purpose seems to be that the EU policy framers
			<lb />
			intended to treat Europe or community as one market perhaps due to
			<lb />
			the proximity of areas between the countries and likelihood of
			<lb />
			penetration of goods one country into another which may otherwise
			<lb />
			cause trade barriers if the free movement of goods is not allowed to
			<lb />
			happen or perhaps of the like nature of the economies which are
			<lb />
			operating in neighboring states so that there should be less competition
			<lb />
			between the similar economies within EU. All this have been result of
			<lb />
			common multi partite convention wherein EU Countries are member
			<lb />
			states and have common intention to give effect to treaty of Rome in all
			<lb />
			the EU countries which consequently affected on the national
			<lb />
			legislation in UK in form of Section 12.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			78.
			<lb />
			This view of treating European Community as one market is
			<lb />
			also well analyzed in another leading authority on the subject namely
			<lb />
			Kerly&quot;s Law on Trade Marks and Trade Names [Fifteenth Edition],
			<lb />
			Sweet and Maxwell 2011 wherein the learned author has culled out the
			<lb />
			number of treaties and also the possible impact of the said treaties on
			<lb />
			the UK legislation by observing to the following terms:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;THE PRINCIPLES ENSHRINED IN THE TREATY OF
			<lb />
			ROME
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			16-019 Although the relevant treaties are now (a) the Treaty on
			<lb />
			European Union (TEU) and (b) the Treaty on the functioning of
			<lb />
			the European Union (TFEU), both as amended by the Treaty of
			<lb />
			Lisbon, much of the relevant case law derives from the time
			<lb />
			when the treaty of Rome prevailed. Accordingly, we will set out
			<lb />
			the relevant provisions from the Treaty of Rome (TOR) which
			<lb />
			constitute the first level of legislative provisions.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Article 2 TOR : The community shall have as its task, by
			<lb />
			establishing a common market and an economic and
			<lb />
			monetary union and by implementing common policies or
			<lb />
			activities referred to in Article 3 and 4, to promote throughout
			<lb />
			the community a harmonious and sustainable development of
			<lb />
			economic activities&quot;(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
			Article 3 TOR : &quot; For the purposes set out in Article 2, the
			<lb />
			activities of the community shall include, as provided in this
			<lb />
			treaty and in accordance with the time table set therein:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(a) The prohibition as between Member States, of customs
			<lb />
			duties and quantitative restrictions on the import and
			<lb />
			export of goods, and of all other measures having
			<lb />
			equivalent effect….
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) An internal market characterized by abolition, as
			<lb />
			between Member states, of obstacles to the
			<lb />
			free movement of goods, persons, services and
			<lb />
			capital.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			....
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(g) a system ensuring that competition in the internal
			<lb />
			market is not distorted…. &quot; (Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			79.
			<lb />
			The possible effect of the aforesaid provision relating to
			<lb />
			agreement to establish a common market place on UK legislation has
			<lb />
			also been examined by the learned author in depth. The learned author
			<lb />
			further observes thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot; UNITED KINGDOM LEGISLATION
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			16-022 -First it is necessary to have regard to section 2(1) of
			<lb />
			European Communities Act, 1972 which expressly provides the
			<lb />
			supremacy of the Community Treaties, although the key treaties
			<lb />
			to in the Act is the Treaty Establishing the European Community
			<lb />
			-The &quot;EC Treaty&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot; All such rights, powers, liabilities, obligations and restrictions
			<lb />
			from time to time created or arising by or under the Treaties, and
			<lb />
			all such remedies and procedures from time to time provided for
			<lb />
			by or under the Treaties, as in accordance with the Treaties are
			<lb />
			without further enactment to be given legal effect or used in the
			<lb />
			United Kingdom shall be recognized or available in law and be
			<lb />
			enforced, allowed and followed accordingly&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			In the context of Trade Marks Act 1994, the provision serves
			<lb />
			to reinforce what is already obvious: the relevant provision of
			<lb />
			the 1994 Act implement and are derived from the Trade Marks
			<lb />
			Directive. However, section 12/ article 7 represent the field of
			<lb />
			trade marks just one manifestation of the more general rule
			<lb />
			known as &quot;exhaustion of rights&quot; which applies to the other
			<lb />
			intellectual property rights as well and in order to explain how
			<lb />
			the hierarchy of interests is reconciled, it is necessary to track
			<lb />
			something of the development of the &quot;exhaustion of rights&quot; rule.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			80.
			<lb />
			The discussion relating to the aforementioned provisions of
			<lb />
			treaties became necessary in order to examine the state of affairs
			<lb />
			existing at the time of enactment of UK legislation. The careful reading
			<lb />
			of the afore quoted provisions of the treaties further make it clear that
			<lb />
			the mischief which was sought to be remedied was to create a single
			<lb />
			market concept for European territories and the same has been done by
			<lb />
			way of international covenant entered into by the EU states and
			<lb />
			agreeing to give effect to the same in their respective laws and
			<lb />
			consequently UK Act 1994 incorporated the said concept by way of
			<lb />
			extension of the said concept of market legislatively. In sharp
			<lb />
			contradistinction, these are not the state of affairs which may hold good
			<lb />
			for Indian Act. There is never such an attempt by the law makers which
			<lb />
			has been come to light to bring such a broader concept of world market
			<lb />
			and the contextual reading of the provisions denotes otherwise which
			<lb />
			tilts towards domestic market. Thus, the argument of the defendant of
			<lb />
			free flow of goods may work in Europe context wherein there are
			<lb />
			conventions and legal position giving effect to such a concept by way
			<lb />
			incorporation their respective laws but not here in India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			81.
			<lb />
			In short, the intended purpose, international covenants
			<lb />
			entered by states and state of affairs as existing in Europe warranted
			<lb />
			the extension of the said concept of &quot;on the market&quot; to be extended as
			<lb />
			&quot;on the market in European Economic Area&quot; in UK Act. Thus, the said
			<lb />
			principle of exhaustion has been given a wider effect by widening the
			<lb />
			conception of market. This is done by way of legislative measure by
			<lb />
			adding the words &quot;in European Economic Area&quot; after the words &quot;on
			<lb />
			the market&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			82.
			<lb />
			Now, if one compares, the said provision of law with
			<lb />
			Section 30(3) of Indian Act of 1999, following marked differences can
			<lb />
			be seen:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			That the Indian Act uses the expression &quot;on the market&quot; although
			<lb />
			infringement section as well as limitation Section in 29 and 30
			<lb />
			respectively and it does not distinguish consciously just like UK
			<lb />
			Act to either extend or to amplify the concept of exhaustion of
			<lb />
			rights as done in the case of UK Act.
			<lb />
			Rather, it confines itself by using the expression &quot;on the
			<lb />
			market&quot; and putting the period thereafter without any further
			<lb />
			addition or subtraction of the said expression in the section of
			<lb />
			limitation of rights and there is no differential treatment
			<lb />
			prescribed under 1999 Act of India which can lead to the
			<lb />
			conclusion that both in Section 29 and 30, the expression &quot;on the
			<lb />
			market&quot; is to be treated differently.
			<lb />
			In that view of the matter, it becomes extremely difficult to
			<lb />
			visualize the scenario when UK Act has gone ahead by changing
			<lb />
			the wordings by way of legislative measures by adding the
			<lb />
			wordings &quot;in the European economic area&quot; after the wordings
			<lb />
			&quot;on the market&quot; in the section, how Indian Act which is more
			<lb />
			narrower in terms when it uses the expression &quot;on the market&quot;
			<lb />
			only, can be given even the wider effect than that of UK Act by
			<lb />
			contemplating a situation and by accepting argumentation that
			<lb />
			the Indian provision is made for purposes of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion of rights solely on basis of a theory propounded by
			<lb />
			handful of people including the defendants and some write ups or
			<lb />
			articles written here and there, when the legislative history in UK
			<lb />
			speaks about legislative extension of the concept of market,
			<lb />
			mischief sought to be remedied also speaks to the contrary and
			<lb />
			explicit terms of section in Indian act and their contextual
			<lb />
			readings speak otherwise which limit it to the domestic market.
			<lb />
			It only suggests one thing that it can be done only by way of
			<lb />
			legislative amendments wherein the legislature in its wisdom can
			<lb />
			extend the concept of &quot;on the market&quot; by adding or subtracting
			<lb />
			words on it which is not within the domain of the Court to do so.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			Secondly, if one compares the section carefully u/s 30(3) of the
			<lb />
			Trade Marks Act and Section 12 of the UK Trade Marks Act,
			<lb />
			1994, one can realize that the section which exists in UK states
			<lb />
			that the registered trademark is not infringed by use of trademark
			<lb />
			in relation to the goods which have been put on the market in the
			<lb />
			European Economic Area under that trade mark by the
			<lb />
			proprietor or with his consent.
			<lb />
			However, in sharp
			<lb />
			contradistinction to the same, the Indian Act reads the similar
			<lb />
			provision by stating that the goods having put on the market
			<lb />
			under the registered trademark by the proprietor or with his
			<lb />
			consent under the registered trademark.
			<lb />
			The difference in the words &quot;under the registered
			<lb />
			trademark&quot; used in the Indian Trade Mark Act and the words
			<lb />
			&quot;under that Trade Mark&quot; in UK Act further gains relevance in
			<lb />
			order to analyze what sort of market both the sections
			<lb />
			contemplate. In the case of Indian Act, as it has been analyzed
			<lb />
			above in extenso that it uses the word &quot;on the market&quot; and
			<lb />
			possible impact of the words &quot;under the registered trademark&quot;.
			<lb />
			This is further indicated by the fact that registered proprietor
			<lb />
			cannot object to further sale of goods after the goods having
			<lb />
			been put on the market under the registered trademark by the
			<lb />
			proprietor. The qualification that the goods put by the proprietor
			<lb />
			shall bear registered trademark further clarifies the situation
			<lb />
			that the goods which have been put in the market by the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor is the goods in the same market where the
			<lb />
			mark is registered as that is why it has been consciously used the
			<lb />
			words &quot;goods put on the market under the registered trademark&quot;.
			<lb />
			However, in sharp contradistinction to the same, the UK Act
			<lb />
			consciously omits the word &quot;registered&quot; due to the wider
			<lb />
			expression &quot;on the market&quot; in European economic area as the
			<lb />
			framers of that section were aware that even if the proprietor
			<lb />
			puts the goods under that trade mark in any of the Member State
			<lb />
			of European Economic Area irrespective of the fact as to
			<lb />
			whether it is registered or not, the proprietor will lose its right to
			<lb />
			object and that is why the expression used is &quot;under that
			<lb />
			trademark&quot; so that wider import can be given. But, this is
			<lb />
			conspicuously absent in the Indian Trade Mark Act, 1999 where
			<lb />
			the wordings are goods having been put on the market under
			<lb />
			the registered trademark.
			<lb />
			The wordings &quot;under that trade mark&quot; has aptly examined
			<lb />
			by Kerly&quot;s Law on Trade Marks and Trade Names [Fifteenth
			<lb />
			Edition], Sweet and Maxwell 2011 wherein the learned author
			<lb />
			analyzed the expression &quot;under that trademark&quot; in a very minute
			<lb />
			terms. The learned Author observes thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;16-015 -Article 7 of the TM Directive is virtually
			<lb />
			identical to art. 13 of the CTM Regulation. Despite the
			<lb />
			fact that the CTM Regulation was passed some six years
			<lb />
			after the Directive, the travaux preparatoires make it clear
			<lb />
			that the two provisions were drafted at the same time.
			<lb />
			Both provisions apply to goods put on the market in
			<lb />
			the EEA &quot;under that trade mark&quot;. That expression is
			<lb />
			apt for a CTM Regulation, but is rather clumsy when
			<lb />
			transposed into the TM Directive. In the context of the
			<lb />
			Directive, it must be interpreted as referring not only
			<lb />
			to the particular national registered trade mark but
			<lb />
			also all trade marks which: (10 are owned by the same
			<lb />
			proprietor or by another entity which is economically
			<lb />
			linked (20 are identical or virtually identical, and (3)
			<lb />
			are either registered or unregistered used by the
			<lb />
			proprietor or with his consent for putting goods on the
			<lb />
			market in any state of the EEA. The alternative
			<lb />
			interpretation is untenable, that it refers only to the
			<lb />
			particular national trade mark.&quot;(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			83.
			<lb />
			From the bare reading of said excerpts from Kerly&quot;s
			<lb />
			alongside the wordings of Section 30(3) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999
			<lb />
			the conclusion becomes inescapable that the wordings &quot;on the market&quot;
			<lb />
			&quot;under the registered trade mark&quot; makes the market confined to
			<lb />
			domestic market/ Indian market/ the market which is used in
			<lb />
			consonance with Section 29 and not the international market and the
			<lb />
			wordings &quot;under the registered trademark&quot; further leads to inference
			<lb />
			that the said market is the one wherein the national trademark is
			<lb />
			registered and the wordings of Section 12 of the UK Trade Mark Act
			<lb />
			are widely couched due to these two reasons; first being it uses the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;in the European economic area&quot; which is by virtue of
			<lb />
			effect of treaty of Rome and secondly, by using the expression &quot;under
			<lb />
			that trade mark&quot; as in contradistinction to the &quot;registered trademark&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			84.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the provisions of UK Act although are indicators
			<lb />
			to the effect as to how to interpret the Indian law in the limited context
			<lb />
			but are not in pari materia and therefore cannot be strictly pressed into
			<lb />
			service so as to equate the Indian law with UK law and rather UK law
			<lb />
			is much more at the advance stage when it extends the principle of
			<lb />
			exhaustion in the European economic area by virtue of legislative
			<lb />
			measures which is absent in Indian context.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			85.
			<lb />
			Thus, the comparative analysis between provisions of Indian
			<lb />
			Act of 1999 and UK Act of 1994 further gives the clear indication that
			<lb />
			contextually Indian provisions are intended to operate in domestic
			<lb />
			market wherein the trade mark is registered and cannot be given a
			<lb />
			wider effect as that of UK Act due to change in the wordings of the
			<lb />
			corresponding provisions as existing in UK which is worded widely
			<lb />
			consciously by the framers of the law in UK.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Contextual Reading of Section 30 (4)
			<lb />
			Section 30(4) also needs consideration which reads as under:-
			<lb />
			Section 30(4)
			<lb />
			&quot;Sub-section (3) shall not apply where there exists legitimate
			<lb />
			reasons for the proprietor to oppose further dealings in the
			<lb />
			goods in particular, where the condition of the goods, has
			<lb />
			been changed or impaired after they have been put on the
			<lb />
			market&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			86.
			<lb />
			As it has been seen above that Section 30(3) relates to
			<lb />
			lawful acquisition of the goods under the registered trade mark by a
			<lb />
			person in the market which is the national market with the aid of
			<lb />
			contextual construction. Therefore, the exception which has been
			<lb />
			carved out u/s 30(4) is also applicable to the same provision and cannot
			<lb />
			be said to be given any other interpretation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			87.
			<lb />
			This is necessary to examine as the argument can be taken
			<lb />
			that why there is a need to enact an exception to the rule envisaged in
			<lb />
			Section 30(3) which entitles the proprietor to oppose further dealings if
			<lb />
			the legislative intent was to give a limited interpretation within the
			<lb />
			domestic market itself.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			88.
			<lb />
			However, the said argument is equally unmeritorious and it
			<lb />
			is actually the intent of the legislature and mischief which is sought to
			<lb />
			be remedied that further dealings within the market / domestic market
			<lb />
			can be prohibited if there is a change or impairment of the goods after
			<lb />
			they have been put into the market and there is no reason why it may
			<lb />
			not hold true for domestic markets.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			89.
			<lb />
			If one reads now the provision of Section 30(3) and 30(4)
			<lb />
			contextually, it becomes very clear that the basic purpose was to
			<lb />
			provide for recognition of principle of exhaustion in limited sense by
			<lb />
			curtailing it in relation to the cases where the goods bearing the
			<lb />
			registered trade mark are lawfully acquired by a person and the
			<lb />
			mischief which his sought to be remedied is that the proprietor cannot
			<lb />
			after throwing the goods in the market can turn around and prohibit the
			<lb />
			very same goods on the pretext of change of ownership of the brand
			<lb />
			name or on the pretext that he has himself or with his consent someone
			<lb />
			else has put the goods in the market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			90.
			<lb />
			However, on limited grounds within the market itself he
			<lb />
			realizes that there are some legitimate reasons which make those sales
			<lb />
			unlawful or otherwise the goods are changed or impaired after they
			<lb />
			have been put on the market; then the proprietor is entitled to object the
			<lb />
			said circulation of goods.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			91.
			<lb />
			The introduction of the exception under Section 30 (4)
			<lb />
			further puts embargo on the applicability of the principle of exhaustion
			<lb />
			within the market also which is only in cases where there is no change
			<lb />
			or impairment of goods or where there no legitimate reasons to oppose.
			<lb />
			Thus, It is very limited kind of exhaustion which is permissible under
			<lb />
			the Act of 1999 wherein even the domestic circulation of goods can be
			<lb />
			controlled if there exists legitimate reasons for the proprietor to object
			<lb />
			the said further dealings more specifically the change or impairment of
			<lb />
			the goods after they are put into the market.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			92.
			<lb />
			This clarification also became necessary in order to dispel
			<lb />
			the doubts which exist in some articles and/ or write-ups by the lawyers
			<lb />
			from time to time that India follows the principle of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion when in fact there is not even a whisper of international
			<lb />
			market or international exhaustion either in Section 30(3) or in Section
			<lb />
			30(4).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			93.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, the term &quot;legitimate reasons&quot; are also invited
			<lb />
			in interpretation and the said &quot;legitimate reasons&quot; can be given a
			<lb />
			similar interpretation as given by the European Courts inasmuch as that
			<lb />
			it is only in few context Section 12 is different from Section 30(3) i.e.
			<lb />
			the initial qualification where the goods bearing a registered trade mark
			<lb />
			are lawfully acquired by a person, and the addition of the words in the
			<lb />
			European economic area after the words &quot;on the market&quot; and otherwise
			<lb />
			Section 12 and Section 30 operate in similar sense of term as it takes
			<lb />
			away the right of proprietor to conduct &quot;further dealings&quot; and it is only
			<lb />
			by virtue of conditions of European countries and by virtue of addition
			<lb />
			of wordings &quot;in the European economic area&quot;, the same is extended to
			<lb />
			European region and therefore Section 12(2) which is an exception to
			<lb />
			Section 12(1) where there exists &quot;legitimate reasons&quot;, is akin to Section
			<lb />
			30(4) of the Indian Trade Marks Act. Therefore, there is no reason why
			<lb />
			interpretation accorded by the European Courts with respect to the term
			<lb />
			&quot;legitimate reasons&quot; cannot be pressed into service in a limited sense in
			<lb />
			order to analyze and understand as what sort of legitimate reasons,
			<lb />
			there can be entitling the proprietor to oppose further dealings.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			94.
			<lb />
			Although those judgments may not be relevant for the
			<lb />
			purposes of prohibiting the dealings outside the national region in
			<lb />
			Indian context as widely worded Section 12 in UK Act extending the
			<lb />
			said concept of market as against India where the provision is in
			<lb />
			narrower terms but are certainly relevant for the purposes of gauging as
			<lb />
			to what can be the &quot;legitimate reasons&quot; for the proprietor to oppose
			<lb />
			further dealings of the goods by such persons.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			95.
			<lb />
			Therefore, it follows that the legitimate reasons like loss of
			<lb />
			goodwill, change and impairment of goods and establishing trademark
			<lb />
			connection with that of the proprietor without any authorization or its
			<lb />
			distributor channels, can be said to be all legitimate reasons entitling
			<lb />
			the proprietor to oppose further dealings in the product u/s 30(4). It is
			<lb />
			also to be noticed that sub section 4 of section 30 uses the expression
			<lb />
			&quot;….where there exists legitimate reasons for the proprietor to oppose
			<lb />
			further dealings in the goods in particular, where the condition of
			<lb />
			the goods, has been changed or impaired after they have been put on
			<lb />
			the market&quot; .
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			96.
			<lb />
			From the above discussion, it can be fairly stated that both
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) and Section 30 (4) operate in the domestic market and
			<lb />
			the same cannot be said to be relating or introducing any such concept
			<lb />
			of international exhaustion of rights on the basis of the putting of the
			<lb />
			goods on the market. Rather the conception of market in the context of
			<lb />
			Indian Act is confined to market where the trade mark is registered.
			<lb />
			Statement of Objects &amp; Parliamentary Debates As An Aid To The
			<lb />
			Construction of the Provision.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			97.
			<lb />
			Having discussed the interpretation of the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Trade mark Act and testing the same on the bedrock of contextual
			<lb />
			interpretation, Now, I shall deal with the reliance of parliamentary
			<lb />
			debates and other write ups as relied by the defendants as an aid to
			<lb />
			construction of the provision under the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			98.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the defendants have relied upon the
			<lb />
			following material in order to argue that the said material is emanating
			<lb />
			from parliament and thus required to be considered as aid to
			<lb />
			construction of the provision:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Some Extract from Trade Mark Bill 1999 which is titled as
			<lb />
			&quot;Arrangement of clauses&quot; wherein there notes relating to several
			<lb />
			clauses of Trade Mark Bills wherein the relevant clause 30
			<lb />
			excerpt is reproduced herein after:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;Sub clause (3) and (4) recognize the principle of
			<lb />
			&quot;exhaustion of rights&quot; by preventing the trade mark owner
			<lb />
			from prohibiting on ground of trade mark rights, the
			<lb />
			marketing of goods in any geographical area, once the
			<lb />
			goods under the registered trade mark are lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired by a person. However, when the conditions of
			<lb />
			goods are changed or impaired after they have been put on
			<lb />
			the market, the provision will not apply&quot;.
			<lb />
			This as per the learned counsel for the defendant is a clause
			<lb />
			of statement of objects and reasons appended to the Trade Mark
			<lb />
			Bill, 1999 as stated in the written submissions and thus the same
			<lb />
			must be considered by the court as an aid to construction of the
			<lb />
			provisions which are Section 30 (3) and 30 (4) of the Act.
			<lb />
			Likewise, the Department related Parliamentary standing
			<lb />
			committee on Human Resource Development&quot;s 227 th Report on
			<lb />
			Copyright Amendment Bill, 2010 wherein some incidental
			<lb />
			reference to international exhaustion principle is there with
			<lb />
			reference trade marks which is reproduced herein after:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;7.12 Committee was also given to understand by the
			<lb />
			representative of publishing industry that the scheme of
			<lb />
			copyright law was entirely different from The Trade Marks
			<lb />
			Act and Patents Act 1970. The application of the standards
			<lb />
			and principles of these two laws through the proposed
			<lb />
			amendment of section 2(m) would completely dismantle the
			<lb />
			business model currently employed , rendering several
			<lb />
			industries unviable. On specific query in this regard, the
			<lb />
			department informed that the concept of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion provided under section 107 A of the Patent Act,
			<lb />
			1971 and in section 30 (3) of Trade Marks Act and in section
			<lb />
			2(m) of copyright law were similar. This provision was in
			<lb />
			tune with the national policy on the exhaustion of rights.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			By putting reliance upon the above two references, it has
			<lb />
			been argued that this court should take into consideration the
			<lb />
			aforementioned parliamentary material as an indicators to the
			<lb />
			governing principle of international exhaustion and interpretation
			<lb />
			to the provision must be then accordingly given by the court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			99.
			<lb />
			Let me now discuss the law relating to relevancy of
			<lb />
			parliamentary material including the debates, statement of objects as an
			<lb />
			aid to construction of the provision before examining the
			<lb />
			aforementioned material relied upon by the defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			100.
			<lb />
			It is now well settled that the statement of objects and
			<lb />
			reasons, parliamentary debates and material emanating from parliament
			<lb />
			cannot be used to control the express language of the provision. The
			<lb />
			said materials and debates are not true guide to the interpretation of the
			<lb />
			provision and are only necessary to examine the antecedent state of
			<lb />
			affairs existing at the time when the enactment was passed. The same
			<lb />
			cannot however be used to construe the provisions when the plain and
			<lb />
			contextual reading of the same speaks otherwise.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			101.
			<lb />
			In the case of State of West Bengal v. Union of India,
			<lb />
			AIR 1963 SC 1241, The Supreme Court observed thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;It is however well settled that the Statement of Objects and
			<lb />
			Reasons accompanying a Bill, when introduced in
			<lb />
			Parliament, cannot be used to determine the true meaning
			<lb />
			and effect of the substantive provisions of the statute. They
			<lb />
			cannot be used, except for the limited purpose of
			<lb />
			understanding the background and the antecedent state of
			<lb />
			affairs leading up to the legislation. But we cannot use this
			<lb />
			statement as an aid to the construction
			<lb />
			of the
			<lb />
			enactment....&quot;.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied).
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			102.
			<lb />
			In Aswini Kumar Ghose And Anr. vs Arabinda Bose And
			<lb />
			Anr., AIR 1953 SC 75, Hon&quot;ble Patanjali Shastri J. (as his lordship
			<lb />
			then was) speaking for the majority observed thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;As regards the propriety of the reference to the statement of
			<lb />
			objects and reasons, it must be remembered that it seeks only to
			<lb />
			explain what reasons induced the mover to introduce the Bill in
			<lb />
			the House and what objects he sought to achieve. But those
			<lb />
			objects and reasons may or may not correspond to the objective
			<lb />
			which the majority of members had in view when they passed it
			<lb />
			into law. The Bill may have undergone radical changes during its
			<lb />
			passage through the House or Houses, and there is no guarantee
			<lb />
			that the reasons which led to its introduction and the objects
			<lb />
			thereby sought to be achieved have remained the same
			<lb />
			throughout till the Bill emerges from the House as an Act of the
			<lb />
			Legislature, for they do nor form part of the Bill and are not
			<lb />
			voted upon by the members. We, therefore, consider that the
			<lb />
			statement of objects and reasons appended to the Bill should
			<lb />
			be ruled out as an aid to the construction of
			<lb />
			a statute.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			103.
			<lb />
			Likewise in the case of S.S Bola v. B.D Sardana, AIR
			<lb />
			1997 SC 3126, the Supreme Court again reiterated the same
			<lb />
			proposition by observing:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot; where words used in a statute are clear and unambiguous
			<lb />
			showing the intention of the legislature, it is not
			<lb />
			permissible for the Court to interpret the statute by
			<lb />
			examining the objects and reasons for the statute in
			<lb />
			question&quot;.
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			104.
			<lb />
			From the reading of the aforementioned observations of the
			<lb />
			Apex court, it can be safely said that the statement of objects and
			<lb />
			reasons, parliamentary debates and committee reports are at the best
			<lb />
			looked into examine the antecedent state of affairs and they cannot be
			<lb />
			pressed into service to curtail the plain and contextual meaning of the
			<lb />
			enactment. It is also not correct that they are not relied upon to gauge
			<lb />
			the mischief sought to be remedied but only when the same are guide to
			<lb />
			such mischief sought to be remedied and provision as enacted speaks in
			<lb />
			consonance with the said object and not in cases where there are
			<lb />
			contradictory voices. In the cases of conflict between the language of
			<lb />
			the provisions and parliamentary debates, it cannot be assumed that the
			<lb />
			voice of the few persons in the parliament is the voice of the entire
			<lb />
			legislature or lawmakers as enunciated clearly in Ashwini Kumar
			<lb />
			Ghose (supra).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			105.
			<lb />
			Applying the said principles to the facts of the present case,
			<lb />
			firstly, the statement of objects are not true guide to construction of the
			<lb />
			provision of the statute and cannot be pressed into the service in case
			<lb />
			the provision clearly speaks otherwise. But in the present case, the
			<lb />
			reliance has been placed by the defendant which has been stated to be
			<lb />
			an arrangement of clauses in the Trade Marks Bill, 1999 wherein the
			<lb />
			clause 30 reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot; Sub clause (3) and (4) recognize the principle of &quot;exhaustion of
			<lb />
			rights&quot; by preventing the trade mark owner from prohibiting on
			<lb />
			ground of trade mark rights, the marketing of goods in any
			<lb />
			geographical area, once the goods under the registered trade
			<lb />
			mark are lawfully acquired by a person. However, when the
			<lb />
			conditions of goods are changed or impaired after they have been
			<lb />
			put on the market, the provision will not apply.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			106.
			<lb />
			It is highly doubtful as to how the defendant can call this as
			<lb />
			a statement of objects and reasons of the Trade Marks Act. The source
			<lb />
			of the document is not known, it is not the statement of the object and
			<lb />
			reasons appended to the Trade Marks Act. In fact, the statement of
			<lb />
			objects and reasons appended to the Trade Marks Act, 1999 reads as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot; STATEMENT OF OBJECTS AND REASONS
			<lb />
			The Trade and Merchandise Act, 1958 has served its purpose
			<lb />
			over the last four decades. It was felt that a comprehensive
			<lb />
			review of the existing law be made in view of developments in
			<lb />
			trading and commercial practices, increasing globalization of
			<lb />
			trade and industry, the need to encourage investments flows and
			<lb />
			transfer of technology, need for simplification and harmonization
			<lb />
			of trademark management systems and to give effect to
			<lb />
			important judicial decisions. To achieve these purposes, the
			<lb />
			present Bill proposes to incorporate, inter alia the following
			<lb />
			namely:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a) providing for registration of trademark for services, in
			<lb />
			addition to goods;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) registration of trademarks, which are imitation of well
			<lb />
			known trademarks, not to be permitted, besides enlarging
			<lb />
			the grounds for refusal of registration mentioned in clauses
			<lb />
			9 and 11. Consequently, the provision for defensive
			<lb />
			registration of trademark are proposed to be omitted;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) amplification of factors to be considered for defining a
			<lb />
			well known trademark;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d) doing away with the system of maintaining registration of
			<lb />
			trademark in Part A and Part B with different legal rights,
			<lb />
			and to provide only a single register with simplified
			<lb />
			procedure for registration and with equal rights;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e) simplifying the procedure for registration of registered
			<lb />
			user and enlarging the scope of permitted use;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(f)
			<lb />
			providing for registration of &quot;Collective Marks&quot; owned by
			<lb />
			associations, etc;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(g) providing for an Appellate Board for speedy disposal of
			<lb />
			appeals and rectification applications which at present lie
			<lb />
			before High Courts;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(h) transferring the final authority relating to registration of
			<lb />
			certification trademarks to the Registrar instead of the
			<lb />
			Central Government;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			providing enhanced punishment for offences relating to
			<lb />
			trademark on par with present Copyright Act, 1957, to
			<lb />
			prevent the sale of spurious goods;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(j)
			<lb />
			prohibiting use of someone else&quot; trademarks as part of
			<lb />
			corporate names, or name of business concern;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(k) extension of application of convention country to include
			<lb />
			countries which are members of groups or union of
			<lb />
			countries and Inter-Governmental Organizations;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(l)
			<lb />
			incorporating other provisions, like amending the
			<lb />
			definition of &quot;trademarks&quot;, provisions for filing a single
			<lb />
			application for registration in more than one class,
			<lb />
			increasing the period of registration and renewal from 7 to
			<lb />
			10 years, making trademark offences cognizable,
			<lb />
			enlarging the jurisdiction of courts to bring the law in this
			<lb />
			respect on par with the copyright law, amplifying the
			<lb />
			powers of the court to grant ex parte injunction in certain
			<lb />
			cases and other related amendments to simplify and
			<lb />
			streamline the trademark law and procedure.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			2.
			<lb />
			In view of the extensive amendments necessitated in the
			<lb />
			Trade and Merchandise Act, 1958, it has been though fit
			<lb />
			to repeal and re-enact the said Act incorporating the
			<lb />
			necessary changes.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			3.
			<lb />
			The Bill seeks to achieve the above objects.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			107.
			<lb />
			From the bare reading of the said statement of objects and
			<lb />
			reasons appended to the Act of 1999, no where, the said objects and
			<lb />
			reasons speaks of any such mischief controlling markets by the
			<lb />
			proprietors and also it does not speak at all about the principle of
			<lb />
			international exhaustion of rights introduced in the Trade Marks Act
			<lb />
			1999. Therefore, the statement of objects and reasons appended to the
			<lb />
			Act even if relied in the present case does not aid the case of the
			<lb />
			defendants as they are not indicative of any legislative intent towards
			<lb />
			the principle of international exhaustion as propounded by the
			<lb />
			defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			108.
			<lb />
			The reliance of the Arrangement of clauses by the defendant
			<lb />
			by calling it as a statement of objects and reasons is misplaced as they
			<lb />
			are not statement of objects and reasons in the true sense of term. They
			<lb />
			may be either some parliamentary recommendation or some sort of
			<lb />
			arrangement proposed during the time when bill was about to pass. But
			<lb />
			then again, not all parliamentary material can be said to be true guide to
			<lb />
			construction of the provision. Even the statement of objects and reason
			<lb />
			as an extrinsic aid to the construction is rejected in many cases, then it
			<lb />
			is doubtful as to how any parliamentary material can be relied upon as
			<lb />
			an aid to construction. In any case, applying the principles of Ashwini
			<lb />
			Kumar Ghose (Supra) and S.S. Bhola (supra), the said noting the clause
			<lb />
			30 does not speak of the legislative intent of the entire legislature and
			<lb />
			cannot be used to enlarge or limit the construction of the provision
			<lb />
			when the plain and contextual reading provides for to the contrary.
			<lb />
			Similar is the case with the Copyright committee report which is
			<lb />
			relating to copyright amendment bill where there is a passing reference
			<lb />
			to the Trade marks Act. The said reference is again just the passing
			<lb />
			reference and is not conclusive of the legislative intent. The said
			<lb />
			reference only states that the department answers the said question on
			<lb />
			specific query. The said query must be answered by lawyers or
			<lb />
			informers to the department and not on the basis of the interpretation
			<lb />
			contextually as done above. Thus, it is an indicative of the fact that the
			<lb />
			said principle of exhaustion is much a talked about topic in relation to
			<lb />
			the subject of Intellectual property and the said copyright committee
			<lb />
			report is prepared on the basis of what the lawyers or the lobbies of
			<lb />
			publishers which work or follows such principles internationally
			<lb />
			informs the persons working in such committees in parliament. The said
			<lb />
			excerpts are just reproduced in the said committee reports on basis
			<lb />
			hearsay of those persons and even in the cases where the true import of
			<lb />
			the provision is something different. Thus, the said committee report of
			<lb />
			copyright relating to amendment of the different statute cannot be relied
			<lb />
			upon to amplify the stand that the said report speaks of any such
			<lb />
			legislative intent to re-modify the mischief of market controlling right
			<lb />
			of the proprietor.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			109.
			<lb />
			Thus, the submission of the defendants to the extent, it
			<lb />
			relies the parliamentary material and committee report as an aid to
			<lb />
			construction of Section 30 of the Trade Marks Act is rejected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			110.
			<lb />
			The another connected submission is the reliance on some
			<lb />
			report/ map issued by International Trade Marks Association wherein
			<lb />
			the legal regimes across the globe are mentioned. Again the said report
			<lb />
			is just something what lawyers or lobbies as a member of the
			<lb />
			international organizations inform them. The said organization is a
			<lb />
			brand owners association and takes the aid and assistance of the
			<lb />
			lawyers worldwide for basing their own opinion to publish such data.
			<lb />
			Thus, again the said reports are just hear say material and cannot be
			<lb />
			said to be a guiding force for legislative intent.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			111.
			<lb />
			A similar state of affairs exist with some communication
			<lb />
			issued in from India on 10.07.1989 relating to negotiation of TRIPS
			<lb />
			agreement wherein there is a recommendation that principles of
			<lb />
			international exhaustion should be followed in Trade Mark Laws. The
			<lb />
			said communication or report is again an advise while negotiating an
			<lb />
			agreement and as far as back in 1989 cannot by any stretch of
			<lb />
			imagination be pressed into service to interpret the provisions of 1999
			<lb />
			Act which is passed on 15.09.2003 and no parallel can be drawn from
			<lb />
			such report vis a vis new enactment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			112.
			<lb />
			Likewise is the case with the write ups or articles written by
			<lb />
			the students of the law school or research papers. Most of these write
			<lb />
			ups are written on the basis of what has been talked about in the
			<lb />
			lobbies again and nowhere the said write ups attempt to examine the
			<lb />
			true import of the provision by reading the provision as it stands. The
			<lb />
			conclusions are just drawn on the stray basis that India follows
			<lb />
			international exhaustion without comparison of the wordings of the
			<lb />
			statute in Indian law vis a vis UK Act and other provision of
			<lb />
			commonwealth countries. On the contrary, I have also been able to
			<lb />
			find some internet write ups which speak to the contrary wherein the
			<lb />
			conclusions are deduced that India follows national exhaustion. One
			<lb />
			such article written by Senha Jain from ILS Law College Pune in the
			<lb />
			Journal Of Intellectual Property Rights cited as JIPR Volume 14
			<lb />
			(January 2009) pp 14-27 issued by NISCAIR which recommends as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot; Hence it can conclusively suggested that India Should follow
			<lb />
			national exhaustion. The view seems to have been reinforced
			<lb />
			after passing of the 2007 notification…..&quot;
			<lb />
			In such fluidic state of affairs, it would be unwise to draw
			<lb />
			any inference from such write ups or articles either of Sonia Baldia or
			<lb />
			of Ms. Jain (although seems to be more extensive) as a guiding force
			<lb />
			towards the legislative intent behind enacting Section 30 of the Trade
			<lb />
			Marks Act unless the provision seems to be in consonance with the
			<lb />
			discussion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			113.
			<lb />
			Thus, the write ups, articles and parliamentary material
			<lb />
			relied upon by the defendants as an extrinsic aid to construction of the
			<lb />
			provision is rejected in view of the aforementioned reasons and
			<lb />
			discussions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			114.
			<lb />
			Let me now examine the submission of the defendants that
			<lb />
			this court should follow the judgment passed in the Xerox (supra). I am
			<lb />
			not convinced as to how the Xerox case can at all aid the case of the
			<lb />
			defendants at all and my reasoning for the same can be as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			i) It is settled principle of the law that the judgment is a precedent
			<lb />
			for the legal principle decided therein and not what is logically
			<lb />
			deduced there from. This has been well settled by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in the case of Southern Petrochemicals Co. Limited vs.
			<lb />
			Electricity Inspector, 2007(5) SCC 477 wherein the apex court
			<lb />
			observed thus:
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;A decision, as is well known, is an authority for what it
			<lb />
			decides and not what can logically be deduced therefrom.
			<lb />
			A decision is not an authority on a point which has not
			<lb />
			been considered.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			115.
			<lb />
			A logical corollary to this principle is also that the ratio
			<lb />
			decidendi of the case is the legal principle decided therein and not the
			<lb />
			one what can be inferred there from. In Union Of India &amp; Ors vs.
			<lb />
			Dhanwanti Devi &amp; Ors, (1996) 6 SCC 44 the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			explained what constitutes a binding precedent in the following words:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;It is not everything said by a Judge while giving judgment that
			<lb />
			constitutes a precedent. The only thing in a Judge&apos;s decision
			<lb />
			binding a party is the principle upon which the case is
			<lb />
			decided and for this reason it is important to analyze a
			<lb />
			decision and isolate from it the ratio decidendi. According to
			<lb />
			the well-settled theory of precedents, every decision contains
			<lb />
			three basic postulates --(i) findings of material facts, direct
			<lb />
			and inferential. An inferential finding of facts is the
			<lb />
			inference which the Judge draws from the direct, or
			<lb />
			perceptible facts; (ii) statements of the principles of law
			<lb />
			applicable to the legal problems disclosed by the facts; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(iii) judgment based on the combined effect of the above. A
			<lb />
			decision is only an authority for what it actually decides.
			<lb />
			What is of the essence in a decision is its ratio and not every
			<lb />
			observation found therein nor what logically follows from the
			<lb />
			various observations made in the judgment Every judgment
			<lb />
			must be read as applicable to the particular facts proved, or
			<lb />
			assumed to be proved, since the generality of the expressions
			<lb />
			which may be found there is not intended to be exposition of the
			<lb />
			whole law, but governed and qualified by the particular facts of
			<lb />
			the case in which such expressions are to be found. It would,
			<lb />
			therefore, be not profitable to extract a sentence here and there
			<lb />
			from the judgment and to build upon it because the essence of
			<lb />
			the decision is its ratio and not every observation found therein.
			<lb />
			The enunciation of the reason or principle on which a question
			<lb />
			before a Court has been decided is alone binding as a precedent.
			<lb />
			The concrete decision alone is binding between the parties to it,
			<lb />
			but it is the abstract ratio decidendi, ascertained on a
			<lb />
			consideration of the judgment in relation to the subject matter of
			<lb />
			the decision, which alone has the force of law and which, when it
			<lb />
			is clear what it was, is binding. It is only the principle laid down
			<lb />
			in the judgment that is binding law under Article 141 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution. A deliberate judicial decision arrived at after
			<lb />
			hearing an argument or a question which arises in the case or is
			<lb />
			put in issue may constitute a precedent, no matter for what
			<lb />
			reason, and the precedent by long recognition may mature into
			<lb />
			rule of stare decisis. It is the rule deductible from the application
			<lb />
			of law to the facts and circumstances of the case which
			<lb />
			constitutes its ratio decidendi&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			116.
			<lb />
			Now let me apply the said principles of law relating to ratio
			<lb />
			decidendi or binding precedent to the Xerox case. After due application
			<lb />
			of the aforementioned principles of law to the Xerox (supra), it is clear
			<lb />
			that in Xerox case, while passing the order, learned single judge of this
			<lb />
			court observed thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot; Learned counsel for the parties state that it has not been
			<lb />
			possible to arrive at any agreed interim arrangement. In these
			<lb />
			circumstances , these applications will have to be heard on the
			<lb />
			date fixed….&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot; The only question to be examined today is what is the interim
			<lb />
			arrangement till such time the interim applications are
			<lb />
			heard……..&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;I do not deem it necessary to go into the merits of
			<lb />
			submissions, as it may prejudice either of the parties at the
			<lb />
			hearing of the interlocutory applications. Suffice it to say that
			<lb />
			at this stage, I am of the considered view that it will be
			<lb />
			appropriate to permit import of such Xerox machines, which
			<lb />
			have proper documentation provided there is no change or
			<lb />
			impairment in the machine.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			117.
			<lb />
			From the bare reading of the afore quoted observations of
			<lb />
			the learned single judge of this court, it is clear that the learned single
			<lb />
			judge has made these observation while passing some interim
			<lb />
			arrangement keeping the hearing of the interim applications alive.
			<lb />
			Further, it is clear from the observations of the learned single judge that
			<lb />
			he himself observes that he does not intend to the go into merits of the
			<lb />
			submissions canvassed by both the parties as it may prejudice the
			<lb />
			hearing of injunction applications.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			118.
			<lb />
			Thus, it is wrongful on the part of the defendants to contend
			<lb />
			that there is any legal principle evolved in the Xerox case which has
			<lb />
			been decided after hearing the submissions of both the parties. The
			<lb />
			binding precedents are made when the decision is rendered upon
			<lb />
			examining the submissions of the parties after due application of the
			<lb />
			law on the same.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			119.
			<lb />
			It is another thing that on facts, the learned single judge
			<lb />
			while noting the submissions and remaining it left open to be examined
			<lb />
			later proceeded to pass an order lifting the embargo on importation as a
			<lb />
			matter of interim injunction. But it does not follow from the said order
			<lb />
			that it declares some binding principle of law after applying the tests
			<lb />
			laid down by the Supreme Court so as to carve out the ratio decidendi
			<lb />
			from the case. Rather, the Xerox case leaves the submissions open to
			<lb />
			examined by this court at the later stage.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			120.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the reliance of the defendants of the said decision
			<lb />
			of Xerox (Supra) to articulate that it is binding precedent and thus this
			<lb />
			court should conclude what has been done therein without examining
			<lb />
			the submissions of parties in this case is totally misconceived. The case
			<lb />
			in Xerox is thus an order passed in its own facts and circumstances
			<lb />
			wherein there was already an interim arrangement in place which was
			<lb />
			modified by the court reserving the right of the parties to urge the
			<lb />
			submissions in the interim applications at the later stage and cannot
			<lb />
			come in the way of this court to examine the provisions of the law and
			<lb />
			interpret them as done above.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			121.
			<lb />
			The order in the Xerox (supra) has been passed keeping in
			<lb />
			mind the importation of second hand machines which are being
			<lb />
			imported. The present case does not also relates to second hand goods
			<lb />
			but is a case where the defendants are alleged to have been selling
			<lb />
			genuine products without the permission of the registered proprietor by
			<lb />
			way of importation which is an infringement under Section 29 (1) read
			<lb />
			with Section 29 (6). On that count too, the order of this court in
			<lb />
			Xerox(supra) is clearly distinguishable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			122.
			<lb />
			Thus, the case in Xerox&quot;s case also does not aid the case of
			<lb />
			the defendants in view of my reasoning mentioned above.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			123.
			<lb />
			Let me now examine the impact of an admission of a legal
			<lb />
			position or principle by the plaintiff if any on the case in hand.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			124.
			<lb />
			It has been contention of the defendants that even the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs admits that India follows the principle of international
			<lb />
			exhaustion and therefore this court should hold the same against the
			<lb />
			plaintiff. The defendants in this context rely upon the paragraph 17 in
			<lb />
			the replication which reads that it is not denied that India follows the
			<lb />
			principle of international exhaustion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			125.
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs in response to the same state that the legal
			<lb />
			principle cannot be said to be admitted in as much as in number of
			<lb />
			places the plaintiffs have disputed the same and the main submission of
			<lb />
			the plaintiff has been that the defendants should be restrained from
			<lb />
			importing in view of Section 29 of the Act and thus, there cannot be
			<lb />
			said to be clear or unambiguous admission on the part of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
			This leads me to delve in to question as to whether there can be any
			<lb />
			admission of the legal principle and what can be the possible impact of
			<lb />
			the same in the case in hand.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			126.
			<lb />
			The law of admission has its genesis from the rules of
			<lb />
			evidence wherein it is well settled that the admission is best evidence
			<lb />
			and no further evidence is required once the admission is clear and
			<lb />
			unambiguous. However, the admissions are usually made of some facts
			<lb />
			and not of pure questions of law. Admission is the best piece of
			<lb />
			evidence against the persons making admission. (As was observed by
			<lb />
			this Court in Avadh Kishore Das v. Ram Gopal and Ors.; AIR 1979
			<lb />
			SC 861 in the backdrop of Section 31 of Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (in
			<lb />
			short the `Evidence Act&apos;) it is true that evidentiary admissions are not
			<lb />
			conclusive proof of the facts admitted and may be explained or shown
			<lb />
			to be wrong; but they do raise an estoppel and shift the burden of proof
			<lb />
			placing it on the person making the admission or his representative-in-
			<lb />
			interest. Unless shown or explained to be wrong, they are an
			<lb />
			efficacious proof of the facts admitted).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			127.
			<lb />
			As observed by Phipson in his Law of Evidence (1963
			<lb />
			Edition, Para 678) as the weight of an admission depends on the
			<lb />
			circumstances under which it was made, these circumstances may
			<lb />
			always be proved to impeach or enhance its credibility. The effect of
			<lb />
			admission is that it shifts the onus on the person admitting the fact on
			<lb />
			the principle that what a party himself admits to be true may reasonably
			<lb />
			be presumed to be so, and until the presumption is rebutted, the fact
			<lb />
			admitted must be taken to be established. An admission is the best
			<lb />
			evidence that an opposing party can rely upon, and though not
			<lb />
			conclusive is decisive of matter, unless successfully withdrawn or
			<lb />
			proved erroneous.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			128.
			<lb />
			It needs to reiteration that the interpretation of the provision
			<lb />
			is a pure question of the law and it is only dependent upon the interplay
			<lb />
			of the provisions of the statute.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			129.
			<lb />
			Chief Justice Munir in his Book Law of Evidence, Fifteenth
			<lb />
			Edition, 2010, Universal Publishing House, has observed about the law
			<lb />
			on admission of the purely legal question in the following terms:
			<lb />
			20 Admission on Pure matter of law
			<lb />
			&quot;In England , admissions are receivable to prove matter of law or
			<lb />
			mixed law and fact. But an admission having been defined by the
			<lb />
			Evidence Act as &quot;a statement which suggests any inference as to
			<lb />
			a fact in issue or relevant fact&quot;, it seems that an admission on
			<lb />
			pure matter of law is not within the scope of section 17-31 and
			<lb />
			will be governed by the rules of pleadings&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			130.
			<lb />
			It is thus clear that the admission in the context of Indian
			<lb />
			Evidence Act, 1872 shall always be of facts due to the definition of the
			<lb />
			admission under Section 17 of the Act is confined to statement which
			<lb />
			may suggest inference as to fact or relevant fact. A logical corollary to
			<lb />
			this which follows is that the admissions shall always be of facts or
			<lb />
			relevant facts but cannot be of law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			131.
			<lb />
			Further, if one examines the concept of admissions on the
			<lb />
			basis of law of pleadings as envisaged under the code of civil
			<lb />
			procedure, it is realized that the cardinal rule of pleadings is that the
			<lb />
			pleadings should contain the facts, material facts and not the law. There
			<lb />
			again, it is not practical or feasible to give rise any such admission of
			<lb />
			the law or legal position. Afortiori, it follows that the admission of the
			<lb />
			legal position or legal principle which may or may not be correct is no
			<lb />
			admission in law and it is inconsequential in law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			132.
			<lb />
			In the case of Ram Bharosey versus Ram Bahadur Singh,
			<lb />
			AIR 1948 Oudh 125, the Court has observed that the admission by a
			<lb />
			party on pure question of law is not binding on him. (The same view
			<lb />
			was also taken by the Nagpur Bench in the case of Gulabchand versus
			<lb />
			Bhaiyalal, AIR 1929 Nag 343).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			133.
			<lb />
			It is also well settled that there cannot be an estoppel
			<lb />
			against the law or statutory provisions. When one is concerned with the
			<lb />
			statutory right or constitutional guarantee, there cannot be any estoppel
			<lb />
			against the same. ( Kindly see the judgment passed in A. C. Jose Vs
			<lb />
			Sivan Pillai &amp; Ors, 1984 SCR (3) 74).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			134.
			<lb />
			One of the facet of the proposition that there is no estoppel
			<lb />
			against the statute is that the admissions or concessions made by the
			<lb />
			counsel for the parties under the wrong understanding of law cannot
			<lb />
			operate to the detriment of the party making such admissions and it is
			<lb />
			only on the basis of correct legal position, the rights of the parties are to
			<lb />
			be determined. This proposition has been laid down in the case of
			<lb />
			Union Of India And Ors vs Mohanlal Likumal Punjabi &amp; Ors,
			<lb />
			(2004) 3 SCC 628 wherein the apex court observed thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;In our view the concession, if any, is really of no
			<lb />
			consequence, because the wrong concession made by a
			<lb />
			counsel cannot bind the parties when statutory provisions
			<lb />
			clearly provided otherwise. It was observed by Constitution
			<lb />
			Bench of this court Sanjeev Coke Manufacturing Co v.
			<lb />
			Bharat Coking Coal Ltd (1983 (1) SCC 147) that courts are
			<lb />
			not to act on the basis of concession but with reference to the
			<lb />
			applicable provisions. The view has been reiterated in (1988 (6)
			<lb />
			SCC 538) and Central Council for Research in Ayurveda and
			<lb />
			Sidhha &amp; others versus Dr. K Santhakumari (2001 (5) SCC 60).
			<lb />
			In para 12 of Central Council&apos;s case (supra) it as observed as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;In the instant case, the selection was made by the
			<lb />
			Departmental Promotion Committee. The Committee must
			<lb />
			have considered all relevant facts including the inter se merit
			<lb />
			and ability of the candidates and prepared the select list on
			<lb />
			that basis. The respondent, though senior in comparison to
			<lb />
			other candidates, secured a lower place in the select list,
			<lb />
			evidently because the principle of &quot;merit-cum-seniority&quot; had
			<lb />
			been applied by the Departmental Promotion Committee. The
			<lb />
			respondent has no grievance that there were any mala fides
			<lb />
			on the part of the Departmental Promotion Committee. The
			<lb />
			only contention urged by the respondent is that the
			<lb />
			Departmental Promotion Committee did not follow the
			<lb />
			principle of &quot;seniority-cum-fitness&quot;. In the High Court, the
			<lb />
			appellants herein failed to point out that the promotion is in
			<lb />
			respect of a &quot;selection post&quot; and the principle to be applied is
			<lb />
			&quot;merit-cum-seniority&quot;. Had the appellants pointed out the true
			<lb />
			position, the learned Single Judge would not have granted
			<lb />
			relief in favour of the respondent. If the learned counsel has
			<lb />
			made an admission or concession inadvertently or under a
			<lb />
			mistaken impression of law, it is not binding on his
			<lb />
			client and the same cannot enure to the benefit of any
			<lb />
			party.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			135.
			<lb />
			Again in Uptron India Ltd vs. Shammi Bhan and Another
			<lb />
			(1998 (6) SCC 538), the court also explained the said principle is one
			<lb />
			of species of the principle that there cannot be any estoppel against the
			<lb />
			statute. It was held that a case decided on the basis of wrong
			<lb />
			concession of a counsel has no precedent value. That apart, the
			<lb />
			applicability of the statute or otherwise to a given situation or the
			<lb />
			question of statutory liability of a person/institution under any
			<lb />
			provision of law would invariably depend upon the scope and
			<lb />
			meaning of the provisions concerned and has got to be adjudged
			<lb />
			not on any concession made. Any such concessions would have no
			<lb />
			acceptability or relevance while determining rights and liabilities
			<lb />
			incurred or acquired in view of the axiomatic principle, without
			<lb />
			exception, that there can be no estoppel against statute. (Emphasis
			<lb />
			Supplied).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			136.
			<lb />
			In view of the above discussion, it is clear that the
			<lb />
			admissions made of law or legal provisions are inconsequential, they
			<lb />
			cannot operate as an estoppel against the person making it. The courts
			<lb />
			are not to act upon the admissions of wrong legal principles made by
			<lb />
			the parties. Rather, the court has to adjudicate rights and liabilities of
			<lb />
			parties basing on the true legal position emerging from the interplay of
			<lb />
			the provisions of the statute and not upon any such wrong admissions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			137.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the statements made in the replication by the
			<lb />
			plaintiff if any to the effect that India follows the principle of
			<lb />
			international exhaustion cannot be termed as admission of the legal
			<lb />
			principle and the same cannot operate to the detriment of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
			The said admission whatsoever does not also absolve the court from its
			<lb />
			duty to analyze the legal position as exists on the plain and contextual
			<lb />
			reading of statute merely because the plaintiff mistakenly or otherwise
			<lb />
			has written or made such statement in the replication.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			138.
			<lb />
			Further, Mr. Anand, learned counsel for the plaintiffs has
			<lb />
			informed the court that the same has been inadvertently written by
			<lb />
			some junior advocate which means that the same is an accidental slip
			<lb />
			and confirms the applicability of the afore quoted rule that the rights
			<lb />
			cannot be adjudicated on the basis of the mistaken concessions of law
			<lb />
			given by the parties or their counsel and cannot bind the parties.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the statement made in para 17 or 11 of the replication
			<lb />
			wherein the plaintiffs have not denied that India follows the principle
			<lb />
			of information exhaustion is inconsequential in law and does not aid the
			<lb />
			case of the defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			139.
			<lb />
			Let me now deal with the submissions made by the
			<lb />
			defendants in seriatim:
			<lb />
			a) Firstly, I have already dealt with the submissions of the
			<lb />
			defendants that India follows the principle of international while
			<lb />
			analyzing Section 30 (3) by contextually reading the same and
			<lb />
			arrived at the finding that the said submission is without any
			<lb />
			force.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			b) Secondly, the submissions of the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			defendants that the imports amounts to the goods lawfully
			<lb />
			acquired by a person is also incorrect and the same stands dealt
			<lb />
			with in the discussion relating to Section 30 (3).
			<lb />
			c) Thirdly, I have already discussed the conception of market in my
			<lb />
			discussion on Section 30 (3) in great detail and thus the
			<lb />
			submissions of the defendants that there is a worldwide free
			<lb />
			market and importation is allowed and is not an infringement is
			<lb />
			also rejected. The same does not hold true that Indian Act is
			<lb />
			narrower in terms when it comes to the concept of market.
			<lb />
			d) Fourthly, I have already rejected the parliamentary material
			<lb />
			which is not statement of objects and reasons and even it is
			<lb />
			assumed to be so that they are not true aid of construction of the
			<lb />
			provision where the language speaks otherwise. I have rejected
			<lb />
			the other aids including write ups or maps which cannot be guide
			<lb />
			to the interpretation. Thus, the said argument is again without
			<lb />
			any force and is rejected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			e) Fifthly, I have also dealt with the decision of Xerox (supra)
			<lb />
			reliance of the defendant as per my view is misconceived.
			<lb />
			Similarly, I am also not basing my decision on the basis of ex
			<lb />
			parte order passed in earlier case of Samsung Electronics Co
			<lb />
			Ltd vs. G Chaudhary and thus it does not call for discussion as I
			<lb />
			have independently formed an opinion on the basis of plain and
			<lb />
			contextual reading of the provisions as well as the comparative
			<lb />
			analysis with UK law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			f) Sixthly, the defendants have argued that Section 30 (4) has to
			<lb />
			construed as if it is a proviso to Section 30 (4). Although, there is
			<lb />
			no need to examine the said submission as the case of the
			<lb />
			defendant as per my view does not even come within the
			<lb />
			purview of the Section 30 (3). Still I am examining the said
			<lb />
			submission in following manner:
			<lb />
			The reading of Section 30 (3) and Section 30 (4) reveals
			<lb />
			that although the Section 30 (4) clearly states that the Section 30
			<lb />
			(3) shall not apply in some cases but no where it uses the
			<lb />
			language as &quot;provided&quot; which may make it in as much as that of
			<lb />
			the proviso. The said Section 30 (4) is at the best the exception
			<lb />
			to Section 30 (3) but cannot be assumed to be proviso when it is
			<lb />
			couched in such language.
			<lb />
			It is well settled that the provision which acts as an
			<lb />
			exception cannot necessarily be presumed to be proviso to the
			<lb />
			main section. This has been examine in detail by Supreme Court
			<lb />
			in the case of London Rubber Co. Ltd vs Durex Products, 1964
			<lb />
			SCR (2) 211 wherein Section 10 (1) and (2) of the Trade Marks
			<lb />
			Act, 1940 which are exceptions to each other were contended to
			<lb />
			be proviso to each other. The Supreme Court recorded the
			<lb />
			submission in the following words and thereafter rejected the
			<lb />
			same:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;Mr. Pathak, however, contends that sub-s. (2) is merely a
			<lb />
			proviso to sub-s. (1) and as such it cannot apply to a case
			<lb />
			which squarely falls under s. 8 (a). Being a proviso to sub-s.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(1), the argument proceeds, it must apply to the matter contained
			<lb />
			in the main provision and that since sub-s. (1) applies only to a
			<lb />
			case where a competing trade mark is already on the register it
			<lb />
			cannot apply to a case falling under s. 8 (a) which provision
			<lb />
			deals, according to him, only with cases where there is no mark
			<lb />
			on the register. He contends that the language used in sub-s. (2)
			<lb />
			is in material respects identical with that used in sub-s. (1) and
			<lb />
			thus establishes the mutual connection between the two
			<lb />
			provisions. A similar argument was advanced before the
			<lb />
			High Court and was rejected by it, in our opinion
			<lb />
			rightly.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;The question, however, is whether sub-s. (2) can be regarded
			<lb />
			by itself or it is, as contended by Mr. Pathak, only a proviso to
			<lb />
			sub-s. (1) and being a proviso it must apply only to cases which
			<lb />
			are contemplated by the main enacting provision, that is, sub-s.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(1) of s. 10. He concedes that sub-s. (2) is not described by the
			<lb />
			legislature as a proviso to sub-s. (1) but he wants us to
			<lb />
			construe it as a proviso because it occurs in the same section
			<lb />
			as sub-s. (1) and its language is similar to that of
			<lb />
			sub-s. (1).&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;In support of this contention he has referred us to Ram Narain
			<lb />
			Sons Ltd., v. Assistant Commissioner of Sales Tax(,). That was a
			<lb />
			case where this Court was considering the proviso to Art. 286(2)
			<lb />
			of the Constitution and the Court held that a proviso was meant
			<lb />
			only to lift the ban under Art. 286(2) and nothing more.
			<lb />
			Bhagwati J., who delivered the judgment of the Court has
			<lb />
			observed thus :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;It is a cardinal rule of interpretation that a proviso to a particular
			<lb />
			provision of a statute only embraces the field which is covered
			<lb />
			by the main provision. It carves out an exception to the main
			<lb />
			provision to which it has been enacted as a proviso and to no
			<lb />
			other.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			These observations, however, must be limited in their
			<lb />
			application to a case of a proviso properly so called and
			<lb />
			there is no justification for extending them to a case like the
			<lb />
			present where the legislature has, when it could we I do so if
			<lb />
			that were its intention, not chosen to enact it as a proviso.
			<lb />
			The decision.. therefore, affords no support to the contention.&quot;
			<lb />
			(Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
			Thus, it is clear that in cases where one provision is
			<lb />
			exception to another, the same cannot be called as proviso to the
			<lb />
			same on the basis of the assumption unless the legislature
			<lb />
			expressly enacted the same to be properly so called proviso. In
			<lb />
			the given case, if I apply the said principle, it is clear that the
			<lb />
			terms of Section 30 (4) cannot be cut down by treating it as a
			<lb />
			proviso. The submission of the defendant is thus rejected as
			<lb />
			unmeritorious.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			g) Sixthly, the submission of the defendants that there are other
			<lb />
			entities, who are also doing the importation within the
			<lb />
			knowledge of the plaintiffs and for the same reason, the plaintiff
			<lb />
			are estopped from suing the defendants and seeking injunction.
			<lb />
			In reply, the plaintiffs submit that the defendants have now
			<lb />
			informed about the same and they shall be taking necessary
			<lb />
			action accordingly. I have given due consideration to the
			<lb />
			submission and reject the same as incorrect. I have already
			<lb />
			arrived at the finding that the importation of goods under the
			<lb />
			mark is an infringement envisaged under Section 29 (1) read with
			<lb />
			Section 29 (6) with no exception as to genuine or non genuine
			<lb />
			goods. Therefore, by virtue of the acts of defendants being an
			<lb />
			infringement, the third party misuse cannot be pressed into
			<lb />
			service to escape the liability of infringement which is well
			<lb />
			settled principle in view of dictum of Pankaj Goel Vs. Dabur
			<lb />
			India Limited and Castrol Limited Vs. A.K. Mehta of Division
			<lb />
			Bench of this court. (Pankaj Goel Vs. Dabur India Limited
			<lb />
			2008 (38) PTC 49 (Delhi) held that merely because others are
			<lb />
			carrying on business under similar or deceptively similar
			<lb />
			trademark or have been permitted to do so by the plaintiff,
			<lb />
			cannot offer a licence to the world at large to infringe the
			<lb />
			trademark of the plaintiff. It was further held that even otherwise,
			<lb />
			the use of similar marks by a third party cannot be a defence to
			<lb />
			an illegal act of passing off. In Castrol Limited v. A.K. Mehta
			<lb />
			1997 (17) PTC 408 DB it was held that a concession given in
			<lb />
			one case does not mean that other parties are entitled to use the
			<lb />
			same). In that view of the matter, mere fact that there are other
			<lb />
			traders in the market who are also doing similar acts is
			<lb />
			inconsequential in law when it comes to testing the acts on the
			<lb />
			defendants on thresholds of statutory infringement. Therefore,
			<lb />
			the said submission of the defendant is equally without force.
			<lb />
			h) Seventhly, the submission of the defendants that the concept of
			<lb />
			material alteration is distinct from that of material differences in
			<lb />
			US. The said submission needs no examination as in my view the
			<lb />
			case of defendants does not even fall with Section 30 (3) which
			<lb />
			talks of domestic market where the mark is registered. Thus, the
			<lb />
			question of examining the said concepts and differences in the
			<lb />
			context of the provisions existing in different statutes does not
			<lb />
			arise. The judgments relied upon the defendants to urge this
			<lb />
			point of material differences and material alteration also warrants
			<lb />
			no discussion. The submission is thus not considered as the
			<lb />
			defendants has failed to show how its case falls within section 30
			<lb />
			(3) even.
			<lb />
			i) Eighthly, the submission of defendants that the private
			<lb />
			arrangement between the plaintiff No. 1 and plaintiff No. 2
			<lb />
			cannot contract out the law of the land which is otherwise is also
			<lb />
			rejected. This is due to the reason that the legal position as
			<lb />
			emerging from the analysis done above is to the effect that
			<lb />
			Section 30 (3) operates an exception to an infringement under
			<lb />
			Section 29 within the same market. Therefore, it is only the
			<lb />
			registered proprietor or permitted user who can cause such
			<lb />
			importation. In that view of the matter, there is no reason to
			<lb />
			accuse the plaintiffs to contract out the law as there is no such
			<lb />
			legal position as contemplated by the defendants.
			<lb />
			j) Ninethly, the distinctions between EU directives vis a vis Indian
			<lb />
			statute so far as its comparison with Section 30 (4) with Article 7
			<lb />
			of EU directive is concerned, the same are immaterial as the
			<lb />
			conclusions which I have set out herein are not based on
			<lb />
			legitimate reasons and thus the said discussion is again
			<lb />
			unwarranted.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			k) Tenthly, so far as the other admissions are concerned as alleged
			<lb />
			by the defendant. The one which relates to the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			themselves recognizing the legitimate reasons as an exception to
			<lb />
			international exhaustion falls within the same domain that the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs cannot suffer on the counts of admissions made on the
			<lb />
			basis of mistaken position in law as discussed above and the
			<lb />
			same admissions are inconsequential in law. Further, the other
			<lb />
			admissions as pointed by the defendants do not clinch the issue
			<lb />
			as either they are not clear or ambiguous which do not aid the
			<lb />
			case of the defendants.
			<lb />
			l) Eleventhly, the submissions of the defendants on the aspect of
			<lb />
			guarantees given by the defendants as that of original also do not
			<lb />
			require further consideration as I have arrived at the prima facie
			<lb />
			conclusion that importation by virtue of Section 29 (1) read with
			<lb />
			Section 29 (6) is an infringing act. Thus, the said submissions of
			<lb />
			the defendants do not take the defendant&quot;s case anywhere
			<lb />
			further.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			m) Twelvethly, the submission of the defendants on meta tagging
			<lb />
			being fair use as the same is the only way to describe the article
			<lb />
			which they are selling through importation which according to
			<lb />
			the defendant is permissible under the law. The said contention
			<lb />
			also becomes unmeritorious as the act of importing the products
			<lb />
			without being a registered proprietor or permitted user is
			<lb />
			impermissible, consequently, the promotion of the same on
			<lb />
			website in order to take advantage over and above the market of
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs which the plaintiffs can control cannot in any
			<lb />
			manner categorized as fair use. Once, the plaintiffs object to the
			<lb />
			said use of the mark SAMSUNG and other trade description on
			<lb />
			internet, the same cannot be said to be fair use in order to
			<lb />
			promote infringing act.
			<lb />
			n) Thirteenthly, the submissions of the defendants that there are
			<lb />
			misrepresentation in the suit and thus the injunction application is
			<lb />
			liable to be dismissed is also rejected. The reasons for the
			<lb />
			rejection of the submissions are enlisted as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The defendants&quot; contention that there is a misrepresentation
			<lb />
			due to some past relations between the plaintiffs and
			<lb />
			defendants as the defendants acted as an outlet for the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs product, the same does not aid the case of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff, the same rather shows that the defendants who were
			<lb />
			earlier selling products under the permission of the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			have also started selling parallel imported products later. The
			<lb />
			plaintiff in any case refutes this contention by urging that it is
			<lb />
			only when the defendants started selling such low costs
			<lb />
			printers imported from foreign countries to the detriment of
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs, the suit has been filed and thus the prior relation
			<lb />
			is immaterial. I am convinced with the said submission as the
			<lb />
			case of the plaintiff is confined to the parallel importation of
			<lb />
			the printers and the same cannot be allowed to divert by
			<lb />
			showing past legal relations and rather it reflects upon the
			<lb />
			conduct of the defendants. The agreement dated 1 st January
			<lb />
			2001 relied upon by the defendants to show relation also
			<lb />
			shows that the defendants agreement was relating to PC
			<lb />
			Camera and further in the said agreement also contains the
			<lb />
			clause relating to market channels conflicts and to avoid such
			<lb />
			conflicts. The effect of such an agreement is rather that the
			<lb />
			defendants have subjected to such market conflicting
			<lb />
			restrictions. It is doubtful as to how the defendants if intend
			<lb />
			to use this agreement against the plaintiff can at all raise the
			<lb />
			point of exhaustion against the plaintiff if they want to rely
			<lb />
			this agreement as a past relation as they have by way of
			<lb />
			covenant subjected themselves to such market conflict
			<lb />
			minimization conditions. Thus, the past relation cannot be
			<lb />
			operated against the plaintiffs or in favour of the defendants
			<lb />
			and this has to be examined in trial.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The defendants&quot; contention that there is misrepresentation
			<lb />
			due to the reason that the plaintiffs have not disclosed that the
			<lb />
			defendants were already acting as parallel importers at the
			<lb />
			time when the plaintiff was doing business with them. The
			<lb />
			defendant say this as general statement but does not talk
			<lb />
			about the plaintiffs products in specific along with the
			<lb />
			documents as to the fact that the defendant so called products
			<lb />
			which are subject matter of the proceedings like printers etc
			<lb />
			are also available by way of parallel importation within the
			<lb />
			knowledge of the plaintiff since the time both are engaged
			<lb />
			with the business. If that is not so clearing coming out, then
			<lb />
			the contention of the defendants deserves to be rejected.
			<lb />
			Rather if one sees the document of engagement with the
			<lb />
			defendants, the agreement clearly spells out that there should
			<lb />
			be a market conflict minimization which means that the
			<lb />
			plaintiff has been always been conscious about such parallel
			<lb />
			importation with the defendant. Thus, the knowledge element
			<lb />
			cannot be ascribed to the plaintiffs. In fact, the plaintiff again
			<lb />
			disputes the same which becomes a matter of trial again.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The defendants&quot; contention that there is a misrepresentation
			<lb />
			due to the fact that the plaintiffs themselves are importing
			<lb />
			goods from the other countries. Again, there is no parallel
			<lb />
			which can be drawn with the situation of the plaintiff No. 2
			<lb />
			with that of the defendants. The plaintiff No. 2 is the
			<lb />
			authorized user and rather on affidavit stated to be exclusive
			<lb />
			licencee of the plaintiff No. 1 which can clearly escape the
			<lb />
			case of the plaintiff No. 2 from Section 29 as against the
			<lb />
			defendants who are clearly dealing with the products without
			<lb />
			the consent or authorization and are guilty of infringement
			<lb />
			under Section 29.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 All other submissions of misrepresentation are rejected as
			<lb />
			there is no force in the argument of concealment to the effect
			<lb />
			that there is anything which is being misrepresented by the
			<lb />
			plaintiff. The defendants have failed to substantiate any such
			<lb />
			submission on misrepresentation. There is no counter blast
			<lb />
			litigation which can be inferred at this stage nor is the
			<lb />
			knowledge of the plaintiff in relation to the defendants
			<lb />
			activities clearly shown towards the parallel importation of
			<lb />
			the printers. Thus, the contention of misrepresentation is
			<lb />
			without any force.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			 The contention that the defendants are actually purchasing the
			<lb />
			goods from the legitimate channels is also not correct that
			<lb />
			there is no misrepresentation by the plaintiff. In law, I have
			<lb />
			held that the goods are lawfully acquired by a person has to
			<lb />
			bear a registered trade mark which means that the said
			<lb />
			acquisition has to be from the domestic market. Thus, the
			<lb />
			lawful channels as argued by the defendant does not fit within
			<lb />
			the purview of Section 30(3) of the Act and thus the argument
			<lb />
			is meritless.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			140.
			<lb />
			No further submission of the defendants has remained
			<lb />
			unanswered. The judgments relied upon both the parties in relation to
			<lb />
			material alteration and material differences. Those judgments passed by
			<lb />
			US courts holding in some cases material difference in affirmative and
			<lb />
			in some negative are not relevant for the present discussion as my
			<lb />
			prima facie conclusion is based on the fact that the case of the
			<lb />
			defendants does not fall within Section 30 (3) and I have not based my
			<lb />
			findings on the basis of Section 30 (4), thus all those decisions of US
			<lb />
			and UK court do not warrant discussion. So far as other judgments of
			<lb />
			US courts holding international exhaustion are concerned and EU court
			<lb />
			holding the exhaustion are concerned, the same may hold good in the
			<lb />
			light of their legal position and in the context of the legal provisions
			<lb />
			existing therein. In the Indian context, I have already done the plain and
			<lb />
			contextual reading of the Section 30 (3) and Section 30 (4) whereby I
			<lb />
			have come to the conclusion that the said sections provide for a very
			<lb />
			limited applicability of the said principle of exhaustion within the
			<lb />
			domestic market. Even in those cases, the right to oppose the dealings
			<lb />
			is available. In these circumstances, the discussion relating to US and
			<lb />
			UK decision laying down tests for the purposes of express consent or
			<lb />
			implied consent or when can international/ domestic exhaustion
			<lb />
			principle be invoked do not warrant any detailed discussion. Likewise,
			<lb />
			the detailed discussion on legitimate reasons is not required and suffice
			<lb />
			it to say that aid from the said decisions can be drawn in the limited
			<lb />
			sense as the context in which the provisions exist for opposition of
			<lb />
			dealing in UK is the same as the context in Indian Act although the
			<lb />
			principal provision of exhaustion vary in terms of concept of market.
			<lb />
			The judgments on the point of legitimate reasons also do not further
			<lb />
			warrant discussion as in the present case, I am not invoking the said
			<lb />
			doctrine of legitimate reasons in the present case in the absence of any
			<lb />
			need as the case of the defendants does not fall in Section 30 (3) even.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			141.
			<lb />
			In view of the above discussion, it is for me now to discuss
			<lb />
			the principles relating to grant of temporary injunction which are:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			a) Prima facie case
			<lb />
			b) Balance of convenience
			<lb />
			c) Irreparable loss
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			142.
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs in the present case has been able to show
			<lb />
			prima facie case of infringement of the registered trade mark in view of
			<lb />
			my discussion above wherein Section 29 (1) read with Section 29 (6),
			<lb />
			the imports of the goods under the mark amounts to infringement of the
			<lb />
			trade mark. The defendants have not able to establish any plausible to
			<lb />
			defence to such an infringement. The balance of convenience lies in
			<lb />
			favour of the plaintiffs as the plaintiffs will be more inconvenienced if
			<lb />
			the defendants are allowed to run such market of parallel importation to
			<lb />
			the deteriment of the plaintiffs. The irreparable loss shall also ensure to
			<lb />
			the plaintiff in form of loss of market and depreciation in the goodwill
			<lb />
			under the mark in the event the goods which are not meant for the
			<lb />
			present market are allowed to be continued to be sold by the defendants
			<lb />
			when the statute clearly prohibits so and on the contrary no irreparable
			<lb />
			loss shall occur to the defendants as it is the case of the defendants that
			<lb />
			they are selling the genuine products and capable of selling the same.
			<lb />
			Thus, the defendants can easily switch over to the genuinely purchased
			<lb />
			printers which are emanating from the plaintiffs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			143.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the prayers made in IA No.7774/2011 are
			<lb />
			allowed and the defendants, their agents, servants and all other acting
			<lb />
			for and on their behalf are restrained from importing, exporting and
			<lb />
			dealing in printers and their ink cartridges/toners bearing the trademark
			<lb />
			SAMSUNG and also restrained from using the mark SAMSUNG in
			<lb />
			any manner in respect of promotional activities including on website.
			<lb />
			As far as other products are concerned as prayed in the application, as
			<lb />
			clarified in the order dated 17.11.2011, the plaintiffs are at liberty to
			<lb />
			take an action in accordance with law. The defendants&quot; application
			<lb />
			being I.A. No.10124/2011 under Order XXXIX Rule 4 read with
			<lb />
			Section 151 CPC is dismissed with cost of Rs.30,000/-which shall be
			<lb />
			deposited by the defendants with High Court Advocates Welfare
			<lb />
			Fund within four weeks from today.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			144.
			<lb />
			I.A. No.7774/2011 and I.A. No.10124/2011 are disposed
			<lb />
			of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			MANMOHAN SINGH, J.
			<lb />
			FEBRUARY 17, 2012
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
