<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			(a) A perpetual injunction restraining the defendant by themselves or
			<lb />
			their directors, men, partners, proprietors, stockists, dealers,
			<lb />
			servants, agents, franchises, successors in interest, licensees,
			<lb />
			assignees, representatives or any of them from in any manner
			<lb />
			infringing the plaintiff&apos;s registered Trade and service mark
			<lb />
			&apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos; by use of the Trade and service mark
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA MOBILES WORLD&apos; or POORVIKA/ POORLIYA per se
			<lb />
			with or without any logo/ artwork or any mark deceptively similar
			<lb />
			to that of the plaintiff&apos;s registered Trade Mark or in any other
			<lb />
			manner whatsoever;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(b) A perpetual injunction restraining the defendant by themselves or
			<lb />
			their directors men, partners, proprietors, stockists, dealers,
			<lb />
			servants, agents, franchises, successors in interest, licensees,
			<lb />
			assignees, representatives or any of them from in any manner
			<lb />
			infringing the plaintiff&apos;s copyright in the label &apos;POORVIKA
			<lb />
			MOBILE WORLD&apos; by the use by the defendant of the mark
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA MOBILES WORLD&apos;, POORLIYA per se with or without
			<lb />
			any accompanying logo/artwork or any other deceptively similar
			<lb />
			Trade Mark label or by use of similar/ identical colour scheme, art
			<lb />
			work, lettering style or in any other manner whatsoever;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(c) The defendant be ordered to surrender to plaintiff for destruction
			<lb />
			all name boards, packing materials, visiting cards, letterheads,
			<lb />
			printer bills, cartons, sachets and all the goods bearing the
			<lb />
			Trademark &apos;POORLIYA MOBILES WORLD&apos; or any mark deceptively
			<lb />
			similar to that of the plaintiff&apos;s registered Trade Mark and artistic
			<lb />
			work &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos;;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(d) The defendant be ordered to prepare and submit an account of
			<lb />
			profits made by them by the unlawful use of the Registered Trade
			<lb />
			Mark of the plaintiff and thereafter to pass a final decree upon
			<lb />
			ascertaining the accounts, in favour of the plaintiff and against the
			<lb />
			defendants;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(e) The defendant be ordered to pay punitive damages for the
			<lb />
			unlawful act complained of and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(f) for the costs of the suit.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			For Plaintiffs
			<lb />
			: Mr.K.Sukumaran
			<lb />
			for Mr.K.Rajasekaran
			<lb />
			For Defendant
			<lb />
			: Mr.S.Subbiah, Senior Counsel
			<lb />
			for Mrs.Elizabeth Ravi
			<lb />
			1. The suit is one for perpetual injunction restraining the defendant
			<lb />
			from infringing the plaintiffs trade and service mark &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE
			<lb />
			WORLD&apos;, for a perpetual injunction restraining the defendant from infringing
			<lb />
			the copyright of the plaintiffs in the label &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos;, for
			<lb />
			other consequential reliefs like surrender for destruction of all name boards,
			<lb />
			packing materials, visiting cards, letter heads, printer bills, cartons, sachets
			<lb />
			and other goods bearing the trademark &apos;POORLIYA MOBILE WORLD&apos; or any
			<lb />
			other mark deceptively similar to that of the plaintiffs&apos; registered trademark
			<lb />
			and artistic work &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos;, for accounts and for costs of
			<lb />
			the suit.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			The summary of the case of the plaintiffs is as follows :-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. The plaintiffs are carrying on business in sale of mobile phones and
			<lb />
			accessories for more than 10 years and the plaintiffs trade name
			<lb />
			&apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos; has earned substantial good will and reputation
			<lb />
			in the trade. The 1 st plaintiff applied for registration of its mark and obtained
			<lb />
			registration in Registration No.1706433 in Class 35 on 03.07.2008 claiming
			<lb />
			<lb />
			user since 2004. The 1 st plaintiff licensed the 2 nd plaintiff to use the marks
			<lb />
			&apos;POORVIKA&apos;, &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos;, &apos;Think Mobile Think Poorvika&apos;,
			<lb />
			&apos;UTTHAMAVAATHA MOBILE POORVIKAKE BANNI&apos; etc., under the
			<lb />
			license agreement dated 08.04.2014, in relation to the retail and marketing
			<lb />
			services connected with the sale of mobile phones and its accessories.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. The 1 st plaintiff also filed various trademark applications with the
			<lb />
			name &apos;POORVIKA&apos;. She has also been proactive in restraining infringement
			<lb />
			and trafficking of her intellectual property. The plaintiffs have been issuing
			<lb />
			cease and desist notices to various infringers. The mark &apos;POORVIKA&apos;,
			<lb />
			according to the plaintiffs, has attracted fame and has become well known
			<lb />
			across classes of goods under Section 2(1)(zg) of the Trade Mark Act, 1999
			<lb />
			and it is entitled to statutory protection across territories as well as across
			<lb />
			classes.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4. The 2 nd plaintiff has got various show rooms all over the southern
			<lb />
			states and the 2 nd plaintiff has acquired a right to prevent others from using
			<lb />
			the same or deceptively similar mark. The plaintiffs would also claim that
			<lb />
			the turn over of the 2 nd plaintiff had been on the increase and from a mere
			<lb />
			Rs.3,49,827/-in 2003-04, the turn over has increased to
			<lb />
			Rs.11,02,45,42,740/-in the year 2013-14. The 2 nd plaintiff has also been
			<lb />
			spending huge amounts towards advertisement expenses and the amount
			<lb />
			spent towards advertisement in 2013-14 is Rs.2,01,82,891/-. The plaintiff
			<lb />
			has also been selected as &apos;the number one mobile dealer&apos; in the State of
			<lb />
			Tamil Nadu by The Times of India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. Relying upon Section 2(1)(zg) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999, the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs would contend that the plaintiffs are entitled to seek an injunction
			<lb />
			even in respect of places where the plaintiffs do not have a physical
			<lb />
			presence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6. According to the plaintiffs, the defendant opened an outlet selling
			<lb />
			mobile phones in Vallioor at Tirunelveli District. The defendant used the
			<lb />
			name &apos;POORLIYA&apos; and adopted the style of the plaintiffs in its labels, other
			<lb />
			advertisement and packing materials including the name board. The
			<lb />
			defendant also copied the tag-line of the plaintiffs in english and slightly
			<lb />
			modified the tag-line of the plaintiffs in tamil. Contending that the
			<lb />
			defendant by adopting a trademark with such deceptive similarity is
			<lb />
			attempting to grab the popularity of the plaintiffs and encash upon it, the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs would seek the aforesaid reliefs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7. The suit is resisted by the defendant contending that the word
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA&apos; was coined by the defendant from the words &apos;POORNAM&apos;
			<lb />
			which means perfection and the name of his daughter &apos;VINOLIYA&apos;. It is
			<lb />
			also contended by the defendant that the defendant has been trading in
			<lb />
			mobile phones under the different name called M.M.Mobiles and
			<lb />
			Enterprises in Ervadi in Tirunelveli District from the year 2008, before the
			<lb />
			defendant entered the business at Valliyoor.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8. It is also claimed that the defendant is authorized dealer for various
			<lb />
			leading mobile companies. The defendant would also point out that after the
			<lb />
			filing of the suit, the defendant has changed the style of the letters in its
			<lb />
			name &apos;POORLIYA&apos; which would cure even the slightest resemblance that
			<lb />
			was complained of by the plaintiffs. Therefore, according to the defendant,
			<lb />
			the name as it stands today with the change in the style of writing would
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			efface the so called deception on the part of the defendant. It is also
			<lb />
			contended that the plaintiffs not having any business in Valliyoor cannot
			<lb />
			seek an injunction against the defendant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9. It is the further claim of the defendant that the alleged claim of
			<lb />
			infringement is false and both the plaintiffs and the defendant had started the
			<lb />
			business at about the same time and therefore the defendant cannot be said
			<lb />
			to have infringed the plaintiff&apos;s trademark. On the above contentions, the
			<lb />
			defendant sought for dismissal of the suit.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. On the above pleadings the following issues were framed by this
			<lb />
			Court for determination:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			1. Whether the plaintiffs are entitled for perpetual
			<lb />
			injunction against the infringement of trade marks
			<lb />
			by the defendant?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			2. Whether the plaintiffs are entitled for perpetual
			<lb />
			injunction against the infringement of Copy Right
			<lb />
			by the defendant?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			3. Whether the plaintiffs are entitled for punitive
			<lb />
			damages?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4. Whether the plaintiffs are entitled for cost of the
			<lb />
			suit?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			5. Whether the plaintiffs are eligible for other
			<lb />
			ancillary reliefs?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			6. Other reliefs, if any?
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			11. At trial, one Mr.Uvaraj, Director of the 2 nd plaintiff was examined
			<lb />
			as PW1. On the side of the defendant, one Mr.J.Muthukrishnan, the
			<lb />
			Proprietor of the defendant was examined as DW1. Exs.P1 to P23 were
			<lb />
			marked on the side of the plaintiffs and Exs.D1 to D17 were marked on the
			<lb />
			side of the defendant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. Heard Mr.K.Sukumaran, learned counsel appearing for
			<lb />
			M/s. M.R.Gokul Krishnan and S.Patrick for the plaintiffs and Mr.S.Subbiah,
			<lb />
			learned Senior Counsel for Mr.P.Raja for the defendant.
			<lb />
			Issue Nos.1 and 2:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. The fact that the plaintiff is a registered proprietor of the
			<lb />
			trademark &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos; is not in dispute. The trademark
			<lb />
			registration certificate along with the legal user certificate have been marked
			<lb />
			as Ex.P1. From Ex.P1 it could be gathered that the plaintiff has got a
			<lb />
			registration for the name mark &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos; in class 35 and
			<lb />
			the label registration for the style of writing and the getup. The legal user
			<lb />
			certificate would show that the plaintiff has got a device mark for the design
			<lb />
			in which the letters &apos;POORVIKA MOBILE WORLD&apos; are arranged. These facts
			<lb />
			are not disputed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. It is also seen from Ex.P2, that the design of the plaintiffs is
			<lb />
			published in the trademarks journal dated 16.08.2009 under class 35.
			<lb />
			According to the plaintiffS, it has got branches all over the State of Tamil
			<lb />
			Nadu as well as in the neighboring States and as such, the mark of the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs had obtained a status of a well known trademark under Section
			<lb />
			2(1)(zg) of the Trade Marks Act, 1999.
			<lb />
			adopting the plaintiffs mark with a slight change in the last four letters alone
			<lb />
			replacing the letters &apos;VIKA&apos; by the letters &apos;LIYA&apos; had created a mark which
			<lb />
			is substantially similar to that of the plaintiffs in its get-up and the style of
			<lb />
			writing. The plaintiffs would also add that both the names &apos;POORVIKA&apos;
			<lb />
			and &apos;POORLIYA&apos; are phonetically similar and it would definitely lead to a
			<lb />
			confusion in the minds of the consumers who are men of average
			<lb />
			intelligence with imperfect re-collection.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. It is also the contention of the plaintiffs that the plaintiffs called
			<lb />
			upon the defendant to cease and desist from using the plaintiffs&apos; mark by a
			<lb />
			cease and desist notice dated 17.12.2014. The defendant instead of
			<lb />
			complying with the same, sent a reply claiming that the user is honest and
			<lb />
			bonafide. The defendant also changed the manner of writing of the word
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA&apos; both in english and tamil and claimed that the same would
			<lb />
			meet the demand of the plaintiffs and cure any similarity that was there in
			<lb />
			the marks which were being used by the defendant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. The plaintiffs would also claim that even subsequent to the reply
			<lb />
			to the cease and desist notice that was issued on 06.01.2014 the defendant
			<lb />
			has been adopting the old mark, which is substantially similar to that of the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs. In order to buttress its contention, the plaintiffs would rely upon
			<lb />
			Ex.P16 which is an invoice for purchase of mobile phone issued by the
			<lb />
			defendant on 16.02.2015. It is also contended that the defendant has also
			<lb />
			sought for registration of the mark &apos;POORLIYA&apos; written in a particular
			<lb />
			manner with the Trademark Registry. On the opposition of the plaintiffs,
			<lb />
			the said application has not been granted and the same is said to be pending.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. Mr.K.Sukumaran, learned counsel appearing for the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			would vehemently contend that the words &apos;POORVIKA&apos; and &apos;POORLIYA&apos;
			<lb />
			are phonetically similar and the style of writing of the words by the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs and the defendant is also substantially similar. Drawing my
			<lb />
			attention to Ex.P16, the learned counsel would submit that even after
			<lb />
			sending a reply notice to the cease and desist notice claiming that the style
			<lb />
			of writing has been changed, the defendant had continued to sell mobile
			<lb />
			phones with the same pattern of writing as it existed prior to the reply to the
			<lb />
			cease and desist notice.
			<lb />
			The plaintiffs mark as registered is as follows:-
			<lb />
			The mark &apos;POORLIYA&apos; that was used by the defendant is as follows:-
			<lb />
			Page No.13/34
			<lb />
			The packaging material used by the plaintiffs is as follows:-
			<lb />
			The packaging material used for the defendant was as follows:-
			<lb />
			The tag-lines of the plaintiffs in english and tamil are as follows:-
			<lb />
			The tag-lines of the defendant in english and tamil are as follows:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. Pointing out to the above, the learned counsel for the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			would contend that if this is not deceptive similarity nothing else could be
			<lb />
			termed as deceptive similarity. Drawing my attention to Ex.P16, the sales
			<lb />
			invoice dated 06.01.2015, Mr.K.Sukumaran, would contend that though the
			<lb />
			defendant had claimed that it had changed the style of writing of the word
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA&apos; as follows:-
			<lb />
			it had continued to sell mobile phones under invoices which have the same
			<lb />
			style of writing as found in the cease and desist notice even on 16.01.2015.
			<lb />
			This act of the defendant, according to the learned counsel is nothing but a
			<lb />
			dishonest attempt to continue to infringe the mark of the plaintiffs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20. The learned counsel for the plaintiffs would also further claim that
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs have since started the business in Valliyoor also and therefore
			<lb />
			the defence that the plaintiffs cannot seek injunction without having a
			<lb />
			business establishment at Valliyoor does not also exist any longer.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. Mr.K.Sukumaran, learned counsel for the plaintiff would also
			<lb />
			draw my attention to the judgments of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			➔ Parle Products (P) Ltd. Vs. J.P. and Co.,
			<lb />
			Mysore
			<lb />
			reported in (1972) 1 SCC 618
			<lb />
			➔ Lakshmikant V.Patel Vs. Chetanbhai Shan and another
			<lb />
			reported in (2002) 3 SCC 65
			<lb />
			➔ N.R.Dongre and others Vs. Whirlpool Corporation and another
			<lb />
			reported in (1996) 5 SCC 714
			<lb />
			➔ K.R.Chinna Krishna Chettiar Vs. Shri Ambal &amp; Co.,
			<lb />
			Madras and another reported in (1969) 2 SCC 131.
			<lb />
			Apart from the above the learned counsel would also rely upon the
			<lb />
			judgment of this Court in
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			➔ Gangotree Sweeets and Snacks Pvt. Ltd., Vs. Shree Gangotree
			<lb />
			Sweets, Snacks &amp; Savouries, Trichy reported in 2005 (31) PTC 502.
			<lb />
			and the judgment of mine in
			<lb />
			➔ M/s.Sri Kanishk Collection Vs. M/s. SKC Readymades reported in
			<lb />
			2017 (8) MLJ 163.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. Contending contra Mr.S.Subbiah, learned Senior Counsel
			<lb />
			appearing for the defendant would submit that, no doubt, there was a certain
			<lb />
			similarity between the two marks prior to the issuance of the cease and
			<lb />
			desist notice, but, after the issuance of cease and desist notice, the defendant
			<lb />
			has changed the style of writing and has also applied for a trademark with a
			<lb />
			new style of writing. This according to the learned Senior Counsel, would
			<lb />
			efface the cause of action for infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23. Mr.S.Subbiah, learned Senior Counsel would also point out that
			<lb />
			the defendant has produced Ex.D1 and Ex.D2 which would show the
			<lb />
			substantial change in the style of writing of the letters &apos;POORLIYA&apos;. He
			<lb />
			would also further point out that the name boards of the show rooms of the
			<lb />
			defendant have also been changed. Therefore, the so called deceptive
			<lb />
			similarity even if it had existed, is no longer there. The learned Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel would also point out that Ex.D7 and Ex.D8 would show that the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs have adopted totally different style of exhibiting its name
			<lb />
			&apos;POORVIKA&apos; in its show rooms. However, the learned Senior Counsel
			<lb />
			would concede that he has not made out a case of abandonment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. Mr.S.Subbiah, learned Senior Counsel would also rely upon the
			<lb />
			judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Toyota Jidosha Kabushiki
			<lb />
			Kaisha Vs. Prius Auto Industries Ltd., &amp; others reported in 2018 (3) LW
			<lb />
			452, in order to justify his contention that the plaintiffs without being
			<lb />
			present in Valliyoor cannot seek an injunction restraining the defendant
			<lb />
			from carrying on business at Valliyoor.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. I have considered the submissions of the counsel on either side.
			<lb />
			The fact that the defendant had adopted a similar style of writing and get-up
			<lb />
			which prompted the plaintiffs to issue a cease and desist notice is not
			<lb />
			denied. The very fact that the defendant chose to change its style of writing
			<lb />
			of the word &apos;POORLIYA&apos; would show that the defendant itself saw a
			<lb />
			similarity in the style of writing. The labels, name boards and packing
			<lb />
			materials used by both the parties have been extracted above. It is a fact that
			<lb />
			they had the same colour scheme apart from the style of writing.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. I find considerable similarity, which is capable of deception in the
			<lb />
			marks used by the plaintiffs and the defendant. Though, the defendant had
			<lb />
			claimed that it had changed the style of writing of the word &apos;POORLIYA&apos; in
			<lb />
			tamil and english after issuance of the cease and desist notice and Exs.D1 to
			<lb />
			D6 have been produced to demonstrate that the defendant had in fact
			<lb />
			changed the style of writing the words &apos;POORLIYA&apos;, both in english and
			<lb />
			tamil, it has to be seen as to whether the said change would be sufficient to
			<lb />
			efface the claim of deception by the plaintiffs. While considering the right
			<lb />
			of a registered proprietor of the trademark to prevent others from infringing
			<lb />
			the marks, Courts have consistently held that the entire mark as a whole
			<lb />
			should be looked into. Apart from the visual and the phonetic similarities
			<lb />
			between the two marks should also be weighed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. No doubt, after the change in the style of writing, it cannot be said
			<lb />
			that there is deceptive similarity in the visual representation of the word
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA&apos;, but the phonetic similarity would still exist and the same
			<lb />
			would be a cause for deception.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28. In K.R.Chinna Krishna Chettiar Vs. Shri Ambal &amp; Co., Madras
			<lb />
			and another (supra), the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court dealt with a case of
			<lb />
			phonetic similarity between the words &apos;AMBAL&apos; and &apos;ANDAL&apos;. The
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court while considering the question of deceptive
			<lb />
			similarity, has observed that the ocular comparison is not always the
			<lb />
			decisive test. The resemblance between the two marks must be considered
			<lb />
			with reference to the ear as well as the eye. If there is a close affinity
			<lb />
			between the sound, the same would amount to infringement of trademark.
			<lb />
			After referring to the oft-quoted judgment in Coca-Cola Co. of Canada Vs.
			<lb />
			Pepsi-Cola Co. of Canada Ltd., reported in 1942 (59) RPC 127, the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court quoted with approval the view of this Court and observed as
			<lb />
			follows:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;5. Now the words &quot;Sri Ambal&quot; form part of
			<lb />
			Trade Mark No.126808 and are the whole of Trade
			<lb />
			Mark No.146291. There can be no doubt that the
			<lb />
			word &quot;Ambal&quot; is an essential feature of the trade
			<lb />
			marks. The common &quot;Sri&quot; is the subsidiary part,
			<lb />
			of the two words &quot;Ambal&quot; is the more distinctive
			<lb />
			and fixes itself in the recollection of an average
			<lb />
			buyer with imperfect recollection.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			6. The vital question in issue is whether, if
			<lb />
			the appellant&apos;s mark is used in a normal and fair
			<lb />
			manner in connection with the snuff and if similarly
			<lb />
			fair and normal user is assumed of the existing
			<lb />
			registered marks, will there be such a likelihood of
			<lb />
			deception that the mark ought not to be allowed to
			<lb />
			be registered (see In the matter of Broadhead&apos;s
			<lb />
			Application reported in (1950) 57 PRC 209, 214
			<lb />
			for registration of a trade mark). It is for the Court
			<lb />
			to decide the question on a comparison of the
			<lb />
			competing marks as a whole and their distinctive
			<lb />
			and essential features. We have no doubt in our
			<lb />
			mind that if the proposed mark is used in a normal
			<lb />
			and fair manner the mark would come to be known
			<lb />
			by its distinguishing feature &quot;Andal&quot;. There is a
			<lb />
			striking similarity and affinity of sound between the
			<lb />
			words &quot;Andal&quot; and &quot;Ambal&quot;. Giving due weight
			<lb />
			to the judgment of the Registrar and bearing in
			<lb />
			mind the conclusions of the learned Single Judge
			<lb />
			and the Divisional Bench, we are satisfied that
			<lb />
			there is a real danger of confusion between the two
			<lb />
			marks.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			29. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has held that if there is a phonetic
			<lb />
			similarity between the two names, the same would afford a cause of action
			<lb />
			for an infringement action. While the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court was
			<lb />
			concerned with the names of &apos;SRI AMBAL&apos; and &apos;SRI ANDAL&apos;, we are now
			<lb />
			looking at &apos;POORVIKA&apos; and &apos;POORLIYA&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. As I have already pointed out, while considering the infringement
			<lb />
			action, particularly on deceptive similarity, the Court must look at the entire
			<lb />
			mark and cannot break a mark into various segments and decide on
			<lb />
			similarity or dis-similarity. If the mark is looked in its entirety, despite
			<lb />
			alteration in the style of writing/ visual representation, the phonetic
			<lb />
			similarity still exists and the same would definitely cause confusion among
			<lb />
			the customers.
			<lb />
			Counsel on the territorial applicability, I am afraid that acceptance of such
			<lb />
			contention in the light of globalization would lead to disastrous
			<lb />
			consequences.
			<lb />
			Even in N.R.Dongre and others Vs. Whirlpool
			<lb />
			Corporation and another (supra), the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court pointed out
			<lb />
			that a registered proprietor whose mark is famous, can injunct a person from
			<lb />
			using the said mark even in places where the registered proprietor does not
			<lb />
			have a business. This Court in Gangotree Sweeets and Snacks Pvt. Ltd.,
			<lb />
			Vs. Shree Gangotree Sweets, Snacks &amp; Savouries, Trichy (supra) re-stated
			<lb />
			the law relating to territorial operation of the registered trademark. I have
			<lb />
			followed the judgment in Gangotree Sweeets and Snacks Pvt. Ltd., Vs.
			<lb />
			Shree Gangotree Sweets, Snacks &amp; Savouries, Trichy (supra) in M/s.Sri
			<lb />
			Kanishk Collection Vs. M/s. SKC Readymades (supra). After referring to
			<lb />
			the judgment in Gangotree Sweeets and Snacks Pvt. Ltd., Vs. Shree
			<lb />
			Gangotree Sweets, Snacks &amp; Savouries, Trichy (supra) and the judgment in
			<lb />
			Lakshmikant V.Patel Vs. Chetanbhai Shan and another (supra), I had
			<lb />
			recognized the rights of a registered proprietor to injunct others from
			<lb />
			infringing their trademark even outside the territory.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32. However, it is now admitted by the parties that the plaintiffs have
			<lb />
			also started a branch at Valliyoor and therefore, the contention of the learned
			<lb />
			Senior Counsel that the plaintiffs who have no business in Vallioor cannot
			<lb />
			enforce the right across territories. The judgment in Toyota Jidosha
			<lb />
			Kabushiki Kaisha Vs. Prius Auto Industries Ltd., &amp; others (supra) would
			<lb />
			not be of any help to the plaintiffs since it is a passing off action involving
			<lb />
			overseas territoriality.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			33. The new Act viz., the Trade Marks Act, 1999 recognizes the right
			<lb />
			of a proprietor of a name mark or a device to seek injunction. A trademark
			<lb />
			relating to service is also recognized under the new Act. Going one step
			<lb />
			further, the new Act also recognizes a new concept called &apos;well known
			<lb />
			trademark&apos;, which in effect gives statutory recognition to the existing law of
			<lb />
			Trademarks adopted in N.R.Dongre and others Vs. Whirlpool Corporation
			<lb />
			and another (supra), wherein, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court recognized a
			<lb />
			right of a foreign manufacturer and registered trademark holder to injunct a
			<lb />
			person from infringing his trademark in India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. The evidence on the side of the plaintiffs would establish that it
			<lb />
			has got several branches and it has a huge turn over in sales of mobile
			<lb />
			phones and accessories. The evidence on record would show that the name
			<lb />
			&apos;POORVIKA&apos; has almost become synonymous with mobile phones in all
			<lb />
			these years. The turn over of the plaintiffs has increased to over Rs.1000
			<lb />
			Crores within a span of 10 years from a mere Rs.3,49,000/-in 2003-04.
			<lb />
			This would show the amount of influence the plaintiffs has gained over the
			<lb />
			mobile phone market in Tamil Nadu and out side Tamil Nadu.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. In these circumstances, the defendant by adopting a phonetically
			<lb />
			similar name cannot infringe upon the trademark of the plaintiffs and
			<lb />
			attempt to lure the customers of the plaintiffs. I find that there is a certain
			<lb />
			attempt by the defendant to deceive the customers of the plaintiffs which
			<lb />
			would amount to an infringement of the plaintiffs trademark as well as the
			<lb />
			copyright. Hence, the issue Nos.1 and 2 are answered in favour of the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs.
			<lb />
			Issue No.5:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36. The plaintiff has apart from seeking the injunctive reliefs, also
			<lb />
			sought for the relief of surrender of the packing materials, visiting cards,
			<lb />
			letterheads, printer bills, cartons, sachets, etc., with the mark &apos;POORLIYA&apos;
			<lb />
			or any other deceptively similar mark. Now, that it has been found that the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs are entitled to a decree for injunction on infringement of its mark,
			<lb />
			as a consequence, the plaintiffs would also be entitled to a direction for
			<lb />
			surrender of name boards, packing materials, visiting cards, letterheads,
			<lb />
			printer bills, cartons, sachets and all other goods bearing the trademark
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA MOBILES WORLD&apos; or any other mark deceptively similar to the
			<lb />
			established registered trademark or artistic work &apos;POORLIYA MOBILES
			<lb />
			WORLD&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37. There is also a prayer for accounting. In the light of the findings
			<lb />
			on issue Nos.1 and 2 that the defendant had infringed upon the trademark of
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs, the defendant is definitely liable to accounts for the profits
			<lb />
			made by them by using a deceptively similar mark. In view of the above,
			<lb />
			Issue No.5 is answered in favour of the plaintiffs and it is found that the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs would be entitled to the reliefs of mandatory injunction as well as
			<lb />
			accounting.
			<lb />
			Issue No.3:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. Though a prayer for punitive damages has been made, there is
			<lb />
			total absence of evidence on the quantum of punitive damage and now that
			<lb />
			the relief of accounting has been sought for and granted, it will be open to
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs to seek accounts from the defendant and seek damages after
			<lb />
			accounting on the basis of the final decree that would be passed after the
			<lb />
			accounts are taken.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39. In fine, the suit is decreed granting the reliefs of injunction,
			<lb />
			permanent injunction, mandatory injunction and accounting viz., covered by
			<lb />
			prayers a, b, c and d. The relief of punitive damages is rejected. The
			<lb />
			plaintiffs would be entitled to costs of the suit also.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17.08.2021
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Sl.No
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Exhibits
			<lb />
			Description of documents
			<lb />
			Date
			<lb />
			10 Ex.P10 Photocopy of Certificate of Registration
			<lb />
			-CST
			<lb />
			27.02.2013
			<lb />
			11 Ex.P11 Photocopy
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			VAT
			<lb />
			Registration
			<lb />
			Certificate (Karnataka) of the 2 nd plaintiff
			<lb />
			06.12.2013
			<lb />
			12 Ex.P12 Photocopy of certificate of enrollment
			<lb />
			under Karnataka Tax on Profession,
			<lb />
			Trades, Callings and Employments Act of
			<lb />
			the 2 nd plaintiff
			<lb />
			06.12.2013
			<lb />
			13 Ex.P13 Photocopy of License Deed in favour of
			<lb />
			the 2 nd plaintiff
			<lb />
			08.04.2014
			<lb />
			14 Ex.P14 Photocopy of Notice sent to Poorliya
			<lb />
			Mobiles World and Electronics
			<lb />
			17.12.2014
			<lb />
			15 Ex.P15 Photocopy of Reply sent to plaintiff&apos;s
			<lb />
			notice
			<lb />
			06.01.2015
			<lb />
			16 Ex.P16 Photocopy of Sales Bills of Poorliya
			<lb />
			Mobiles World and Electronics
			<lb />
			16.02.2015
			<lb />
			17 Ex.P17 Photocopy of trademark Application
			<lb />
			POORLIYA (English) No.2909077 in
			<lb />
			Class 35 TM-1
			<lb />
			24.02.2015
			<lb />
			18 Ex.P18 Photocopy of trademark Application
			<lb />
			POORLIYA (Tamil) No.2912586 in Class
			<lb />
			35 TM-1
			<lb />
			27.02.2015
			<lb />
			19 Ex.P19 Photocopy of GSS &amp; Associates
			<lb />
			(Chartered Accountant certificate of
			<lb />
			turnover and expenses)
			<lb />
			16.06.2015
			<lb />
			20 Ex.P20
			<lb />
			(series)
			<lb />
			Photocopies of Brochures, visiting card,
			<lb />
			advertisements and name board of
			<lb />
			POORLIYA Trademark.
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			21 Ex.P21 Photocopy of &quot;Dinamalar&quot; Report
			<lb />
			publishing news of the 2 nd plaintiff
			<lb />
			27.09.2015
			<lb />
			Sl.No
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Exhibits
			<lb />
			Description of documents
			<lb />
			Date
			<lb />
			receiving Certificate from his Excellency,
			<lb />
			the Governor for being selected as No.1
			<lb />
			Mobile Retailer in State of Tamil Nadu.
			<lb />
			22 Ex.P22 Photocopy of depiction of the plaintiff&apos;s
			<lb />
			Trademark
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			23 Ex.P23 Photocopy of Depiction of the defendant&apos;s
			<lb />
			Trademark
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			List of the Witnesses examined on the side of the Defendant:
			<lb />
			DW1 -J.Muthukrishnan
			<lb />
			List of Exhibits marked on the side of the Defendant :
			<lb />
		</table>
		<figure type="table">
			Sl.No
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Exhibits
			<lb />
			Description of documents
			<lb />
			Date
			<lb />
			1 Ex.D1
			<lb />
			Photograph of present lettering style, get-
			<lb />
			up and colour combination of trade name
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA&apos; in tamil version
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			2 Ex.D2
			<lb />
			Photograph of present lettering style, get-
			<lb />
			up and colour combination of trade name
			<lb />
			&apos;POORLIYA&apos; in english version
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			3 Ex.D3
			<lb />
			Photograph of show room at No.58-D/1,
			<lb />
			North Main Road, Vallioor
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			Sl.No
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Exhibits
			<lb />
			Description of documents
			<lb />
			Date
			<lb />
			4 Ex.D4
			<lb />
			Photograph of show room at 292K, North
			<lb />
			Main Road, Near Kalaimagal Paints,
			<lb />
			Vallioor
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			5 Ex.D5
			<lb />
			Photograph of show room at 361, Main
			<lb />
			Road, Near Old Asoka Textiles, Vallioor
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			6 Ex.D6
			<lb />
			Photograph of show room at Kalakad,
			<lb />
			Tirunelveli
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			7 Ex.D7
			<lb />
			Photograph of present trade mark of
			<lb />
			plaintiff
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			8 Ex.D8
			<lb />
			Photograph of plaintiff&apos;s show room at
			<lb />
			No.63A, Thompson Building, North Main
			<lb />
			Road, Vallioor
			<lb />
			--
			<lb />
			9 Ex.D9
			<lb />
			Photocopy of Certificate of Registration
			<lb />
			issued by Commercial Tax Department
			<lb />
			27.08.2015
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			10 Ex.D10 Printout copy of GST Registration
			<lb />
			Certificate
			<lb />
			24.09.2017
			<lb />
			11 Ex.D11 Computer printout copy of Tax Invoice
			<lb />
			issued in show room at No.58-D/1, North
			<lb />
			Main Road, Vallioor
			<lb />
			01.04.2018
			<lb />
			12 Ex.D12 Computer printout copy of Tax Invoice
			<lb />
			issued in show room at 292K, North Main
			<lb />
			Road, Near Kalaimagal Paints, Vallioor
			<lb />
			25.08.2019
			<lb />
			13 Ex.D13 Computer printout copy of Tax Invoice
			<lb />
			issued in show room at 361, Main Road,
			<lb />
			Near Old Asoka Textiles, Vallioor
			<lb />
			25.08.2019
			<lb />
			14 Ex.D14 Computer printout copy of Tax Invoice
			<lb />
			issued in show room at Kalakad,
			<lb />
			Tirunelveli
			<lb />
			25.08.2019
			<lb />
			15 Ex.D15 Computer printout copy of Income tax
			<lb />
			Returns for Assessment year 2017-2018
			<lb />
			19.07.2017
			<lb />
			Sl.No
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Exhibits
			<lb />
			Description of documents
			<lb />
			Date
			<lb />
			16 Ex.D16 Computer printout copy of Income tax
			<lb />
			Returns for Assessment year 2017-2018
			<lb />
			30.03.2018
			<lb />
			17 Ex.D17 Computer printout copy of Income tax
			<lb />
			Returns for Assessment year 2018-2019
			<lb />
			28.01.2019
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			17.08.2021
			<lb />
			dsa
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			To
			<lb />
			The Sub Assistant Registrar,
			<lb />
			Original Side, High Court, Madras.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			R.SUBRAMANIAN,J.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			dsa
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Pre-Delivery Judgment
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17.08.2021
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
